Michael Levin's work on regulating intractable pattern formation in living systems has made
him one of the most compelling biologists of our time. In translation, this means that his team is
sussing out how to develop limbs, regenerate limbs, how to generate minds, and even life extension
by manipulating electric signals rather than genetics or epigenetics. His work is something
that I consider to be worthy of a Nobel Prize, and I don't think I've said that about anyone
on the podcast. Michael Levin's previous podcast, On Toe, is in the description. That's a solo
episode with him where we go into a two-hour deep dive, as well as there's a theolo-cution,
so that is him and another guest, just like today, except between Carl Fursten and Chris
Fields on consciousness. Josje Bach is widely considered to be the pinnacle of an AI researcher
dealing with emotion, modeling, and multi-agent systems. A large focus of Bach's is to build a
model of the mind from strong AI. Speaking of minds, Bach is one of the most inventive minds
in the field of computer science and has appeared several times on Toe prior. Again, there's a solo
episode. There's also a theolo-cution between Josje Bach and Donald Hoffman on consciousness,
and Josje Bach and John Vervecky also on consciousness and reality. Biology has much to
teach us about artificial intelligence and vice versa. This discussion between two brilliant
researchers is something that I'm extremely lucky, blessed, fortunate to be a part of, as well as us
as collective as an audience that are fortunate enough to witness. Thank you and enjoy this
theolo-cution between Josje Bach and Michael Levin. Welcome both Professor Michael Levin
and Josje Bach. It's an honor to have you on the Toe podcast. Again, both of you and then together
right now. Thank you. It's great to be here. Likewise. I enjoy very much being here and look
forward to this conversation. I look forward to it as well. So we'll start off with the question of
what is it that you, Michael, find most interesting about Josje's work? And then
Josje will go for you toward Michael. Yeah, I really enjoy the breadth. So I've been looking,
I think I've probably read almost everything on your website, the short kind of blog pieces
and everything. And yeah, I'm a big fan of the breadth of tackling a lot of the different issues
that you do with respect to computation and cognition and AI and ethics and everything.
I really like that aspect of it. And Josje? Yeah, my apologies. My blog is not up to date. I haven't
done any updates for a few years now on it, I think. So, of course, I'm still
in the process of progressing and having new ideas. And the ideas that I had in recent years,
I have a great overlap with a lot of the things that you are working on.
And when I listened to your Lex podcast last night, there were many thoughts that you had
that I had stumbled on that I've never heard from anybody else. And so I found this very
fascinating and thought, maybe let's look at some of these thoughts first and then go from there
and expand beyond those ideas. What I, for instance, found after thinking about how cells work
kind of obvious but missed by most people in neuroscience or in science in general,
is that every cell has the ability to send multiple message types and receive multiple
message types and do this conditionally and learn under which conditions to do that and to
modulate this. Also, every cell is an individual reinforcement learning agent. Single-celled animal
that tries to survive by cooperating with its environment gets most of its rewards from its
environment. And as a result, this means that every cell can in principle function like a neuron.
It can fulfill the same learning and information processing tasks as a neuron. The only difference
that exists with respect to neurons or the main difference is that they cannot do this over very
long distances because they are mostly connected only to cells that are directly adjacent. Of
course, neurons also only communicate to adjacent cells but the adjacency of neurons is such that
they have excellent parts of the cell that reach very far through the organism. So in some sense,
a neuron is a telegraph cell that uses very specific messages that are encoded in a way
like Morse signals in extremely short high-energy bursts that allow to send messages over very long
distances very quickly to move the muscles of an animal at the limit of what physics allows.
So it can compete with other animals in search for food. And in order to make that happen,
it also needs to have a model of the world that gets updated at this higher rate. So there is
going to be an information processing system that is duplicating basically this cellular brain that
is made from all the other cells in the body of the organism. And at some point, these two systems
get decoupled. They have their own codes, their own language, so to speak. But it still makes
sense, I guess, to see the brain as a telegraphic extension of the community of cells in the body.
And for me, this insight that I stumbled on just because means and motive that evolution would
equip cells with doing that information processing if the organism lives long enough and if the cells
share a common genetic destiny so they can get attuned to each other in an organism,
that basically every organism has the potential to become intelligent. And if it gets old enough to
possess enough data to get to a very high degree of understanding of its environment in principle.
So of course, a normal house plant is not going to get very old compared to us because its
information processing is so much slower. So they're not going to be very smart. But at the
level of ecosystems, it's conceivable that there is quite considerable intelligence. And then
I stumbled on this notion that our ancestors thought that one day in fairyland equals seven
years in human land, which is told in the old myth. And also, at some point, I revised my
notion of what the spirit is. For instance, a spirit is an old word for the operating system
for an autonomous robot. And when this word was invented, the only autonomous robots that were
known were people and plants and animals and nation states and ecosystems. There were no
robots built by people yet. But there was this pattern of control in it that people could observe
that was not directly tied to the hardware that was realized by the hardware but disembodied in
a way. And this notion of spirit is something that we lost after the Enlightenment when we tried to
deal with the wrong Christian metaphysics and superstition that came with it and threw out a
lot of babies with the bathwater. And suddenly, we basically lost a lot of concepts, especially
this concept of software that existed before in a way, this software being a control pattern or a
pattern of causal structure that exists at a certain level of coarse graining as some type of
very, very specific physical law that exists by looking at reality from a certain angle.
And what I liked about your work is that you systematically have focused on this
direction of what a cell can do, that a cell is an agent, and that levels of agency emerge
in the interaction between cells. And you use a very clear language and clear concepts. And you
obviously are driven by questions that you want to answer, which is unusual in science, I found.
Like most of our contemporaries in science get broken, if it doesn't happen earlier during the
PhD, into people who apply methods in teams instead of people who join academia because
they think it's the most valuable thing they can do with their lives to pursue questions that they
are interested in, want to make progress on. All right, Michael, there's plenty to respond to.
Yeah, yeah. Lots of ideas. Yeah, I think your point is very interesting about what really
fundamentally is the difference between neurons and other cells. Of course, evolutionarily,
they're reusing machinery that has been around for a very long time, since the time of bacteria,
basically, right? So our unicellular ancestors had a lot of the same machinery. And even, I mean,
of course, axons can be very long, but there are sort of intermediate structures, right? There are
tunneling nanotubes and things that allow cells to connect to maybe five or 10 cell diameters away,
right? So not terribly long, but also not immediate neighbors necessarily. So that kind
of architecture has been around for a while. And people like Gaurav Sohel look at very brain-like
electrical signaling in bacterial colonies. So I think evolution began to reuse this toolkit
specifically of using this kind of communication to scale up the computational and other kinds of
tricks a really long time ago. And I like to imagine that if somebody had come to
the people who were inventing connectionism and the first sort of perceptrons and neural networks
and so on, if somebody had come to them and said, oh, by the way, sorry, we're the biologists,
we got it wrong. Thinking isn't in the brain, it's in the liver. And so then the question is,
what would they do, right? Would they have changed anything about what they're doing? And then we
said, ah, now we have to rethink our model, or would they have said, fine, who cares? This is
exactly the same model. Everything works just as well. So I often think about that question,
what exactly do we mean by neurons? And isn't it interesting that we are able to steal most of
the tools, the concepts, the frameworks, the math from neuroscience and apply it to problems in
other spaces. So not movement in three-dimensional space with muscles, but for example, movement
through a morphous space, right? Anatomical morphous space. The techniques can't tell the
difference. We use all the same stuff, optogenetics, neurotransmitter signaling, we model active
inference, and we see perceptual by stability, you name it. We take concepts from neuroscience,
and we apply it elsewhere in the body. And generally speaking, everything works exactly
the same. And that shows us, I think, what you were saying, that there's this really interesting
symmetry between these, that a lot of the distinctions that we've been making are in terms
of having different departments and different PhD programs and other things that say,
no, this is neuroscience, this is developmental biology. A lot of these things are just not
as firm distinctions as we used to think. And I suspect that people who insist on strong
disciplinary boundaries do this out of a protective impulse. And what I noticed by
studying many disciplines when I was young, that the different methodologies are so incompatible
across fields, that when I was studying philosophy or psychology, I felt that computer scientists
would be laughing about the methods that each of these fields are using to justify what they're
doing. And this, I think, is indicative of a defect. Because if you take science into the
current regime of regulating it entirely by peer review, there is no external authority. Even the
grand authorities are mostly fields of people who have been trained in the sciences, in existing
paradigms, and then are finding the continuation of those paradigms from the outside. This
meta-paradigmatic thinking does not really exist that much in a peer-reviewed paradigm. And
ultimately, when you do peer review for a couple generations, it also means that if your peers
deteriorate, there is nothing who pulls your science back. And what I missed specifically in
a lot of the way in which neuroscience is done is what you call the engineering stance.
And this engineering sense is very powerful, and you get it automatically when you're a computer
scientist, because you don't really care what language is it written in. What you care in is
what causal pattern is realized. And how can this be realized? And how could I do it? How would I
do it? How can evolution do it? What it means is disposal, and this determines the search space for
the things that I'm looking for. But this requires that I think in causal systems.
And this thinking in causal systems is impossible not to do for a computer scientist,
but it is unusual outside of computer science. And once you realize that, it's very weird.
Suddenly, you have notions that try to replace causal structure with, say, evidence. And then
you notice that, for instance, evidence-based medicine is not about probabilities of how
something is realized and must work. You see people on the cruise ship getting infected over
distances, and you think, oh, this must be airborne. But no, there is no peer-controlled
study, so there is no evidence that it's airborne. And when you look at its disciplines from the
outside, like in this case, the medical profession or the medical messaging and decision-making,
or I get terrified because it directly affects us. And in terms of neuroscience, of course,
there's more theoretical for the most part, but there must be a reason why it's for the most part
a theoretical, why there is no causal model that clinicians can use to explain what is happening
in certain syndromes that people are exhibiting. And I notice this when I go to a doctor and
even at a reputable institution like Stanford, that most of the neuroscientists at some level
there, or most of the neurologists that I'm talking to, at some level dualists, that they
don't have a causal model of the way in which the brain is realizing things. And a lot of studies
which discover that very simple mechanisms like the ability of human beings to use grammatical
structure are actually reflected in the brain. This is so amazing. Who would have thought?
But the developments that existed in computer science have led us on a completely different
track. The perceptron is vaguely inspired by what the brain might be doing, but I think it's really
a toy model or a caricature of what cells are doing. Not in the sense that it's inferior,
it's amazing what you can brute force with the modern perceptron variations. The current
machine learning systems are mind blowing in what they can do, but they don't do it like
biological organisms at all. It's very different. The cells do not form change in which they weight
sums of real numbers. There is something going on that is roughly similar to it, but there's
a self-organizing system that designs itself from the inside out, not by a machine learning
principle that applies to the outside and updates weights after reading and comparing them
and computing gradients to the system. So this perspective of local self-organization by
reinforcement agents that try to trade rewards with each other, that is a perspective that I
find totally fascinating. And I wish this would have come from neuroscience into computer science,
but it hasn't. There are some people which have thought about these ideas to some degree,
but there's been very little cross pollination. And I think all this talk of neuroscience
influencing computer science is mostly visual thinking.
Yeah. It's also, I find this, you know, what you were saying about the different disciplines,
it's kind of amazing how, well, when I give a talk, I can always tell which department I'm in by
which part of the talk makes people uncomfortable and upset. And it's always different depending on
which department it is, right? So there are things you can say in one department that are
completely obvious. And you say this in another group of people and they throw tomatoes. I think
this is just craziness. For instance, I could say in a neuroscience department, I could say
information can be processed without changes in gene expression. You don't need changes in
gene expression to process information because the processing inside a neural network runs on
the physics of action potentials, right? So you can do all kinds of interesting information
processing and you don't need transcriptional or genetic change for that. If I say the same thing
in a molecular genetics department that say, hey, these cells could be processing tons of information
long before the transcriptome ever finds out about it, this is considered just completely wild
because it's thought that most of the hard work or in fact, all of the hard work is done in gene
regulatory circuits and things like that, right? There are other examples. If I say,
here's a collection of cells that communicate electrically to remember a particular spatial
pattern, again, molecular cell biology, what do you mean? How can a collection of cells
remember a spatial pattern? But again, in neuroscience or in an engineering department,
yeah, of course. Of course, they have electrical circuits that remember patterns and can do pattern
completion and things like that. So views of causality, views of just lots of things like
that that are very obvious to one group of people is completely taboo elsewhere. So that distinction,
and yeah, and as Joshua just said, it impacts everything. It impacts education, it impacts
grants, grant reviews, because when these kind of interdisciplinary grants come up,
the study sections have a really hard time finding people that can actually review them
because what often happens is you'll get some kind of computational biology grant and you put a
proposal and you'll have some people on the panel who are biologists and some people who are the
computational folks. And it's very hard to get people that actually can appreciate both sides of
it and understand what's happening together. So they will sort of each critique a certain part
of it. And the other part, they say, I don't know what this is. And as a result, grants like that
don't tend to not have a champion, one person who can say, no, I get the whole thing and I think
it's really good or not. So yeah, even to the point where I'm often asked when people want to
you list me somewhere, they'll say, so what are you? What's your field? And I never know
how to answer that question. To this day, it's been 30 years. I still don't know how to answer
that question. I just can't boil it down to one. It just wouldn't make any sense to say any of the
traditional fields. So what do you say, Joshua, when someone asks you what field you're in?
And it depends on who's asking. So for instance, I found it quite useful to sometimes say,
sorry, I'm not a philosopher, but this or I'm not that interested in machine learning. And I
did publish papers in philosophy and in machine learning, but it's not my specialty in the sense
that I need to identify with it. And in some sense, I guess that these categories are important
when you try to write a grant proposal or when you try to find a job in a particular institution
and they need to fill a position. But for me, it's more, what questions am I interested in?
What is the thing that I want to make progress on or what is the thing that I want to build right
now? And I guess that in terms of the intersection, I'm a cognitive scientist.
So I was asking Michael, prior to you joining Yoshi, why is it Michael that you were doing
podcasts? And if I understand correctly, part of the reason was because you think out loud,
and you'd like to hear the other person's thoughts and take notes and espers your own.
And firstly, like Michael, you can correct me if that's incorrect. And then secondly,
Yoshi, I'm curious for an answer for this, the same question, what is it that you get out of
doing podcasts other than, say, some marketing for if you were promoting something, which I
don't imagine you are currently. No, I'm not marketing anything.
What I like about podcasts is the ability to publish something in a format that is engaging
to interesting to people who actually care about it. I like this informal way of holding on to some
ideas and also like conversations as a medium to develop thought is this space in which we can
reflect on each other, look into each other's minds, interact with the ideas of others in real
time. The production format of a podcast creates a certain focus of the conversation that can be
useful. And it's a pleasant kind of tension that focuses you to stay on task. And I also found that
it's generally useful to some people. The feedback that I get is that people tell me,
I had this really important question and I found this allowed me to make progress on it.
And I feel much better now about these questions. I just clarified something for me that has plagued
me for years and put me on track to solving it, or this has inspired the following work.
So it's a form of publishing ideas and getting them into circulation in our global hive minds
that is very informal in a way, but it's not useless. And also it relieves me in this instance,
at least of the work of cutting, editing, and so on. But anyways, I'm very grateful that you
provide the service of curating our conversation and putting it in a form that is useful to other
people. Yeah, there's something, well, two things I was thinking of. One is that I have conversations
with people all day long about these issues, right? So people in my lab, collaborators,
whatever. And most, of course, the vast majority of those conversations are not recorded and they
just sort of disappear into the ether. And then I take something away from it and the other person
takes something away from it. But I've often thought that, isn't it a shame that all of this
just kind of disappears and it would be amazing to have a record of it? And of course, not every
conversation is gold, but a lot of them are useful and interesting. And there are plenty of
people that could be interested and could benefit from it. So I really like this aspect
that we can have conversations and then they're sort of canned and they're out there for people
who are interested. The other kind of aspect of it, which I don't really understand, but it's kind
of neat, is that when somebody asks me to pre-record a talk, it takes a crazy amount of time
because I keep stopping and realizing, ah, I could have said that better. Let me start from
the beginning. And it's just, it's an incredible ordeal. Whereas something like this that's real
time, I'm sure has as many mistakes and things that I would have rather fixed later, but you
can't do that, right? So you just sort of go with it and that's it. And then it's done and you can
move on. So I like that real time aspect of it because it just helps you to get the ideas out
without getting hung up and trying to redo things 50 times. Yeah, it's a format that allows
tentativity. If we have published, we have a culture in sciences that requires us to
publish the things that we can hope to prove and make the best proof that we can. But when we have
anything complicated, especially when we take our engineering stance, we often cannot prove how
things work. Instead, our answers are in the realm of the possible and we need to discuss the
possibilities. And there is value in understanding these possibilities to direct our future
experiments and the practical work that we do to see what's actually the case. And we don't really
have a publication format for that. We don't get neuroscientists to publish their ideas on how the
mind works because nobody has a theory that they can prove. And as a result, there is basically a
vacuum where theories should be. And the theory building happens informally in conversations
that basically requires personal contact, which is a big issue once conferences been virtual
because that contact diminished. And you get a lot of important ideas by reading the publications
and so on. But this what could be or connecting the dots or possibilities or ideas that might be
proven wrong later that we just exchange as in the status of ideas. That is something that has
a good place in a podcast. Is this podcast, not this TOE podcast, but podcast in general something
new? So for instance, I was thinking about this and I well podcasts go back a while and Brogan
invented this long form format or popularized it. However, on television, there are interviews,
so there's Oprah and those are long one hour, there's 60 minutes. And then back in the 90s,
there was a three and a half hour, it's essentially a podcast, it's like Charlie Rose, three and a
half hour conversation. It's like a Theolocution with Freeman Dyson, Daniel Dennett, Stephen J.
Gould, like the Rupert Sheldrake, all of those on the same one format, it's essentially a podcast
talking about metaphysics. Like, man, oh, man, I can't believe that got published. And then also,
I think about it, well, did Plato have the first podcast? Because he's just publishing these
dialogues and you read them, but it's not as if they're maybe he would have published it in video.
I think Plato was the first podcaster. So is there something new about this format of podcasting
that wasn't there before? Or what's new about it? I think it's like it's like blogging. Blogging
is also not new, right? Being able to write text that you publish, and people can follow what you
are writing and so on, did exist in some sense before, but the internet made it possible to
publish this for everyone. You don't need a publisher anymore. And you don't need a TV
studio anymore. You don't need a broadcast station that is recording your talk show and sends it to
an audience. There is no competition with all the other talk shows because there is no limitations
on how many people can broadcast at the same time. And this allows an enormous diversity of thoughts
and small productions that are done at a very low cost, lowering the threshold for putting
something out there and seeing what happens. So in this sense, it's the ecosystem that emerged is new
because a variable change that changed the cost of producing a talk show.
Right. Michael, you agree?
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, yes, that and all of that. And also just the fact that, as you just said,
these kind of like long form things were fairly rare. So most of the time, if you're going to be
in one of the traditional media, they tell you, okay, you've got three minutes. We're going to
cut all this stuff and we're going to boil it down to three minutes. And this is often incredibly
frustrating. And I understand. I mean, we're drowned in information. And so there is obviously
a place for very short statement on things, but the kind of stuff that we're talking about cannot
be boiled down to TV sound bites or anything. It's just not. And so the ability to have these
long form things so that anybody who wants to really dig in can hear what the actual thought
is as opposed to something that's been just boiled into a very, very, very short statement,
I think is invaluable. Just being able to have it out there for people to find.
What's some stance of yours, some belief that has changed most drastically in the past few years,
let's say three, and it could be anywhere from something abstruse and academic to more colloquial,
like I didn't realize the value of children or overvalued children. Now I'm stuck with them.
Like, geez, that was a mistake. Yeah. So something where I changed
my mind was RNA-based memory transfer. And I think it's a super interesting idea in this context
because it's close to stuff that Michael has been working on and is interested in.
There have been some experiments in the Soviet Union, I think in the 70s, where scientists took
planaria, trained them to learn something. I think they learned how to be afraid of electric
shocks and things like that. And then they put their brains into a blender, extracted the RNA,
injected other planaria with it, and these other planaria had learned it.
And I learned about this as a kid when I, in the 1980s, read Soviet science fiction literature.
I grew up in Eastern Germany. And the evil scientist harvested the brains of geniuses
and injected himself with RNA extracted from these brains and thereby acquired the skills.
And even though I'm pretty sure this probably doesn't work if you do it at this level,
this was inspired by this original research. And I later heard nothing about this anymore.
And so I dismissed it as similar things as I read in Sputnik and other Russian publications,
which create their own mythological universe about ball lightning that is agentic and possibly
sentient and so on. And dismissed this all as basically another universe of another reader's
digest culture that is producing its own ideas that then later on get dissolved once science
advances. Because everybody knows it's synapses, it's connections between neurons that matter.
The RNA is not that important for the information processing. It might change some state, but you
cannot learn something by extracting RNA and re-injecting it into the next organism. Because
how would that work if it's done in the synapses? And then recently there were some papers which
replicated the original research and has been replicated from time to time in different types
of organisms. But to my knowledge, not in, of course, macaques or not even mice. So it's not
clear if their brains work according to the same principles as planaria. But planaria are not
extremely simple organisms, only a handful of neurons. They are something intermediate.
And so their main architecture is different from ours. And the functioning principles of
their neurons might be slightly different, but it's worth following this idea and going down
that rabbit hole. And then I looked from my computer science engineering perspective and
I realized that there are always things about the synaptic story that I find confusing because
they're very difficult to implement. For instance, weight sharing. As a computer scientist, I require
weight sharing. I don't know how to get around this. If I want to entrain myself as computational
primitives in the local area of my brain, for instance, the ability to rotate something,
rotation is some operator that I apply on a pattern that allows this pattern to be represented in a
slightly different way to have this object rotated a few degrees. But an object doesn't
consist of a single point. It consists of many features that all need to get the same rotation
applied to them using the same mathematical primitives. So how do you implement the same
operator across an entire brain area? Do you make many, many copies of the same pattern?
And so computer scientists solved that with so-called convolutional neural networks,
which basically use the same weights again and again in different areas, only
training them once and making them available everywhere. And that would be very difficult
to implement in synapses. Maybe there are ways, but it's not straightforward. Another thing is
if we see how training works in babies, they learn something and then they get rid of the
surplus synapses. Initially, they have much more connectivity than they need. And after they've
trained, they optimize the way in which the wiring works by discarding the things they don't need to
compute what they want to compute. So it's like calling the synapses. It does not freeze or edge
the learning into the brain, but it optimizes the energy usage of the brain. Another issue is that
patterns of activation are not completely stable in the brain. In the cortex, if you look,
you find that they might be moving the next day or even rotate a little bit, which is also difficult
to do with synapses. You cannot read out the weights and copy them somewhere else in an easy,
straightforward fashion. And another issue is defragmentation. If you learn, for instance,
your body map into a brain area and then somebody changes your body map because you have an accident
and lose a finger or somebody gives you an artificial limb and you start to integrate
this into your body map, how do you shift all the representations around? How do you make space for
something else and move it? Or also initially, when you set up your maps via happy and learning,
how do you make sure that the neighborhoods are always correct and you don't need to realign
anything? And I guess you need some kind of realignment. And all these things seem to be
possible when you switch to a different paradigm. And so if you take this RNA base series seriously,
go down this rabbit hole, what you get is the neurons are not learning a local function over
its neighbors, but they are learning how to respond to the shape of an incoming activation front,
like the spatial temporal pattern in their neighborhood. And they are densely enough
connected so the neighborhood is just a space around them. And in this space, they basically
interpret this according to a certain topology to say this is maybe a convolution that gives me
two and a half D or it gives me two D or one D or whatever the type of function is that they want
to compute and they learn how to fire in response to those patterns and thereby modulate the patterns
when they're passed on. So the neurons act something like self-modulating ether,
so which wavefronts propagate that perform the computations. And they store the responses to
the distributions of incoming signals, possibly in RNA. So you have little mixtapes, little tape
fragments that they store in a summa and that it can make more of very cheaply and easily. If
they are successful mixtapes and they're useful computational primitives that they discovered,
they can distribute this to other neurons through the entire cortex. So neurons of the same type
will gain the knowledge to apply the same computational primitives. And that is something
I don't know if the brain is doing that and if the human brain is using these principles
or if it's using them a lot and how important this is and how many other mechanisms exist.
But it's a mechanism that we haven't, to my knowledge, tried very much in AI and computer
science. And it would work. There is something that is a very close analog, that is a neural
cellular automaton. So basically instead of learning weight shifts or weight changes between
adjacent neurons, what you learn is global functions that tell neurons on how to respond
to patterns in the neighborhood. And these functions are the same for every point in your
matrix. And you can learn arbitrary functions in this way. And what's nice about this is that you
only need to learn computational primitives once. Our current neural networks need to learn the same
linear algebra over and over again in many different corners of the neural network
because you need vector algebra for many kinds of operations that we perform.
For instance, operations in space where we shift things around or rotate them.
And if they could exchange these useful operations with each other and just apply
an operator whenever the environment dictates that this would be a good idea to try to apply
this operator right now in this context, that could speed up learning. That could make training
much more sample efficient. So something super interesting to try. And this is one of the rabbit
holes I recently fell down over. I changed my thinking based on some experiment from
neuroscience that doesn't have very big impact for the mainstream of neuroscience,
but that I found reflected in Michael's work with planaria.
Yeah, that's super interesting stuff. I can sprinkle a few details onto this.
So the original finding in planaria was a guy named James McConnell at Michigan, actually,
in the US. And then that was in the 60s, the early 60s. And then there were some really
interesting Russian work that picked it up after that. We reproduced some of it recently
in using modern quantitative automation and things like this. But one of the really cool
aspects of this, and there's a whole community, by the way, with people like Randy Gallistil
and Sam Gershman and, of course, Glantzman, David Glantzman, and people who are... That story of
memory in the precise details of the synapses, that story is really starting to crack actually
for a number of reasons. But one of the cool things that was done in the Russian work,
and it was also done later on by Doug Blackiston, who's in my lab now as a staff scientist and other
people, is this. Certain animals that go through larval stages. So you can take... So the Russians
were using beetle larvae, and Doug and other people used moths and butterflies. So what happens is
you train the larvae. So here you've got a caterpillar. So this caterpillar lives in a
two-dimensional world. It's a soft-bodied robot. It lives in a two-dimensional world. It eats leaves
and so on. And so you train this thing for a particular task. Well, during metamorphosis,
it needs to become a moth or butterfly, which it lives in a three-dimensional world. Plus,
it's a hard-bodied creature. So the controller is completely different for running a caterpillar
versus a butterfly. So during that process, what happens is the brain is basically dissolved.
So most of the connections are broken. Most of the cells are gone. They die. You put together
a brand new brain that self-assembles, and you can ask all sorts of interesting philosophical
questions of what it's like to be a creature whose brain is undergoing this massive change.
But the information remains. And so one can ask, okay, certainly for computer science, it's amazing
to have a memory medium that can survive this radical remodeling and reconstruction.
And there's the RNA story, but also you had mentioned, does this work for mammals?
So there was a guy in the 70s and 80s, there was a guy named George Ungar who did tons of,
he's got tons of papers. He reproduced it in rats. So his was Fear of the Dark. And he actually,
by establishing this assay and then fractionating their brains and extracting this activity,
now he thought it was a peptide, not RNA. So he ended up with a thing called scotophobin,
which turns out to be, I think, an eight mer peptide or something.
And the claim was that you can transfer this scotophobin, you can synthesize it
and then transfer it from brain to brain. And that's what he thought it was. And then I think
David Glansman favors RNA again. But yeah, I agree with you. I think that's a super important
story of how it is that this kind of information can survive just massive remodeling of the
cognitive substrate. In planaria, what we did, and planaria, they have a true centralized brain.
They have all the same neurotransmitters that we have. They're not a simple organism.
What we did was McConnell's first experiments, which is to train them on something. And we
train them to recognize a laser etched kind of bumpy pattern on the bottom of the dish and to
recognize that that's where their food was going to be found. So they made this association between
this pattern and getting food. And then we cut their heads off and we took the tails and the
tails sit there for 10 days doing nothing. And then eventually they grow a new brain.
And what happens is that information is then imprinted onto the new brain and then you can
recover behavioral evidence that they remember the information. So that's pretty cool too,
because it suggests that, well, we don't know if the information is everywhere or if it's in other
places in the peripheral nervous system or in the nerve core that we don't know where it is yet.
But it's clear that it can move around, that the information can move around in the body because
it can be in the posterior half and then imprinted onto the brain, which actually drives all the
behaviors. So thinking about that, I totally agree with you that this is a really important
rabbit hole for asking, but there's an interesting puzzle here, which is this.
It's one thing to remember things that are evolutionarily adaptive, like fear of the dark
and things like this, but imagine, and this hasn't really been done well, but imagine for a moment
if we could train them to something that is completely novel. Let's say we train them,
three yellow life flashes means take a step to your left, otherwise you get shocked, something
like that. And let's say they learn to do it. We haven't done this yet, but let's say this could
work. One of the big puzzles is going to be when you extract whatever it is that you extract,
let's say it's RNA or protein, whatever it is, you stick it into the brain of a recipient host.
And in order for that memory to transfer, one of the things that the host has to be able to do is
has to be able to decode it. And in order to decode it, it's one thing if we share the same
codebook and by evolution, we could have the same codebook for things that come up all the time,
like fear of the dark, things like that. But how would the recipient look at a weird
sort of some kind of crazy hairpin RNA structure and analyze and be like, oh yes,
that's three light flashes and then a step to the left, I see. So you would need to be able to
interpret somehow this structure and convert it back to the behavior. And for behaviors that are
truly arbitrary, that might be, I don't know actually how that would work. And so I think
the frontier of this field is going to be to have a really convincing demonstration of a transfer
of a memory that doesn't have a plausible pre-existing shared evolutionary decoding,
because otherwise you have a real puzzle as to how the decoding is going to work.
So this idea, and then even without the transfer, you can also think of it a different way.
Every memory is like a message, is like basically a transplanted message from your past self to
your future self, meaning that you still have to decode your memories. Whatever your memories are,
in an important sense, you have to, those N-grams, you have to decode them somehow.
So that whole issue of encoding and decoding, whatever the substrate of memory is, is maybe
one of the most important questions there are. One of the ways we can think about these N-grams,
I think that there are priors that condition what kinds of features are being spawned in
which context. For instance, when we see a new scene, the way that perception seems to be working
is that we spawn lots of feature controllers that then organize into objects that are controlled at
the level of the scene. And this is basically a game engine that is forming in our brain,
that is creating a population of interacting objects that are tuned to track our perceptual
data at the lowest level. So all the patterns that we get from our retina and so on are samples,
noisy samples that are difficult to interpret, but we are matching them into these hierarchies
of features that are translated into objects that assign every feature to exactly one object and
every pixel, so to speak, to exactly one, except in the case of transparency, and use this to
interpret the scene that is happening in front of us. And when we are in the dark, what happens is
that we spawn lots of object controllers without being able to disprove them, because there is no
data that forces us to reject them. And if you have a vivid imagination, especially as a child,
you will fill this darkness automatically with lots of objects, many of which will be scary.
And so I think that lots of the fear of the dark doesn't need a lot of encoding in our brain. It
is just an artifact of the fact that there are scary things in the world which we learn to
represent at an early age, and that we cannot disprove them, that they will just spawn.
I remember this vividly as a child, that whenever I had to go into the dark basement to get some
food in our house in the countryside, that this darkness automatically filled with all sorts of
shapes and things and possibilities. And it took me later to learn that you need to be much more
afraid of the ghosts that can hide in the light. So what would be the implications of if you were
able to transfer memory for something that's not trivial, so nothing that's like an archetype of
fear of the dark between a mammal like rats? And when I say transfer memory, I mean, in this way
that you blend up the brain or you, and also, can you explain what's meant by, I think I understand
what it means to blend the brain of a planaria, but I don't think that's the same process that's
going on in rats. Maybe it is. Well, Ungar did exactly the same thing. He would train rats
for particular tasks. He would extract the brain, literally liquefy it to extract the chemical
contents. He would then either inject the whole extract or a filtered extract where you would
divide it up. You'd set fractionate it. So here's the RNAs, here's the proteins, here are other
things. And then he would inject that liquid directly into the brains of recipient rats.
When you do that, you lose spatial structure on the input because you just blended your brain.
Whatever spatial structure there was, you just destroyed it. Also on the recipient,
you just inject it. You're not finding that particular place where you're going to stick
it. You just inject this thing right in the middle of the brain. Who knows where it goes,
where the fluid goes. There's no spatial specificity there whatsoever. So if that works,
what you're counting on is the ability of the brain to take up information via a completely
novel route. So it's not information that's, for example, visual, right? Visual information
that comes in exactly the same place all the time, right? There are optic nerves that connect to
the same place in the brain, and that's where that information arrives. If you bathe the brain in
some sort of informational extract, you're basically asking the cells to take it up almost
as a primitive animal would with taste or touch you, right? That's kind of distributed all over
the body, and you can sort of pick it up anywhere, and then you have to process this information.
So you've got those issues right off the bat, right? That you've destroyed the incoming spatial
structure. You can't really count on where it's going to land in the brain. And then the third
thing, as you just mentioned, is the idea that, especially if we start with information that
especially if we start with information that isn't any, that is so kind of specific and
invented, that three light flashes means move to your left. I mean, there's never been an
evolutionary reason to have that encoded. Like as you just said, having a fear of the dark is
absolutely a natural kind of thing that you can expect. And then there are many other things like
that. But something as contrived as three light flashes, and then you move to your left,
there's no reason to think that we have a built-in way to recognize that. So when you as a recipient
brain are handed this weird molecule with a particular structure or a set of molecules,
being able to analyze that, having the cells in your brain or other parts of the body actually,
that could analyze that and recover that original information would be extremely puzzling. I
actually don't know how that would work. And I'm a big fan of unlikely sounding experiments
that have implications if they would work. So this is something that I think should absolutely
be done. And at some point we'll do it, but we haven't done it yet. So how far did the
research in my school, what is the complexity of things that could be transmitted via this route?
I don't remember everything that he did. The vast majority of, he did not go
far to test all the complexities. What he tried to do was, because as you can imagine,
he faced incredible opposition, right? So everybody sort of wanted to critique this thing.
So he spent all of his time on, he picked one simple assay, which was this fear of the dark
thing. And then he just bashed it for 20 years to just finally try to kind of crack that into the
paradigm. He did not, as far as I know, do lots of different assays to try and make it more complex.
I think it's very ripe for investigation. Did anyone else build upon his work?
Not that I know. I mean, David Glansman is the best modern person who works on this, right? So
he does a plesia and he does RNA. So he favors RNA. There's a little bit of work from Oded Rahavi
in Israel with C. elegans. He's kind of looking into that. There's related work that has to do
with cryogenics, which is this idea that if memories are a particular kind of dynamic electrical
state, then some sort of cryogenic freezing is probably going to disrupt that. Whereas if
it's a stable molecule, then it should survive. So again, I think there are people interested
in that aspect of it, but I'm not sure. I'm not sure they've done anything with it.
There's also Gaurav Venkataraman. I think he's at Berkeley. He told me that
he has been working on this for several years, but he said it's sociologically tricky.
And that's to me fascinating that we should care about that.
What does he mean by that?
What do you care about? What stupid people think? If this possibility exists that this works,
the upside is so big that it's criminal to not research this. I think it's a disaster
that you can read introductory textbooks on neuroscience and never ever hear about any of
these experiments. Everybody who gets the introductory stuff on neuroscience only knows
about information stored in the conic tome. And this leads to, for instance, the Blue Brain
project. If RNA-based memory transfer is a thing, then this entire project is doomed,
because you cannot get the story out of just recording the conic tome. Most of the research
right now is focused on reconstructing the conic tome as it was circuitry and hoping that
we can get the functionality of information processing and deduce the specificity of the
particular brain, what it has learned from the connections between neurons.
But what if it turns out this doesn't matter? You just need connections that are dense enough,
and so basically stochastic lattice that is somewhat randomly wired. What matters is what
the neurons are doing with the information that they're getting through this ether,
through this lattice. It just changes the entire way in which we need to look at things.
And if this possibility exists, and if this possibility is just 1%,
but there are some experimental points in this direction, it is ridiculous to not pursue this
with high pressure and focus on it and support research that goes in this direction. Basically,
what's useful is not so much answering questions in science, it's discovering questions,
it's discovering new uncertainty. Reducing the uncertainty is much easier than discovering new
areas of where you thought that you were certain, but that allow you to get new insights. And it
seems to me that a lot of neuroscience is stuck, that it does not produce results that seem to
accumulate in an obvious way towards a theory on how the brain processes information. So the
neuroscientists don't deliver input to the researchers, and the transformer is not the
result of reading a lot of neuroscience. It's really mostly the result of people's thinking
about statistics of data processing. And it would be great if we would focus on ideas that
are promising and new and that have the power to shake existing paradigms.
Yeah. This is so important, and it's not just neuroscience. In developmental biology,
we have exactly the same thing. And I'll just give you two very simple examples of it where,
and I tell the students, when I give talks to students, I say, isn't it amazing that
in your whole course of biology and your developmental biology textbook, there's not
a mention of any of this because it completely just undermines a lot of the basic assumptions.
So here's a couple of examples. One example is that as of trophic memory in deer,
so there are species of deer that every year they regenerate. So they make this antler
rack on their heads, the whole thing falls off, and then it regrows the next year. So these two
guys, Bobenak, which are a father and son team that did these experiments for 40 years, and I
actually have all these antlers in my lab now because when the younger one retired, he sent me
all these things, all these antlers. The idea is this, what you can do is you take a knife
and somewhere in this branch structure, you make a wound and the bone will heal and you get a
little callus and that's it for that year. Then the whole thing drops off. And then next year,
it starts to grow and it will make an ectopic tine, an ectopic branch at the point where you
injured it last year. And this goes on for five or six years, and then eventually it goes away and
you get a normal rack again. And so the amazing thing about it is that the standard models for
patterning for morphogenesis are these gene regulatory networks and genetic biochemical
gradients and so on. If you try to come up with a model for this, so for encoding an arbitrary point
within a branch structure that your cells at the scalp have to remember for months after the whole
thing is dropped off, and then not only remember it, but then implement it so that when the bone
starts to grow, something says, oh yes, that's the start another tine growing to your left exactly
here. Trying to make a model of this using the standard tools of the field is just incredibly
difficult. And there are other examples of this, but this kind of non-genetic memory that's just
very difficult to explain with standard models. The other thing, which is I think an even bigger
scandal, is the whole situation with planaria. Some species of planaria, the way they reproduce
is they tear themselves in half, each half regenerates the missing piece, and now you've
got two. That's how they reproduce. So if you're going to do that, what you end up avoiding is
Weissman's barrier, this idea that when we get mutations in our body, our children don't inherit
those mutations. So this means that any mutation that doesn't kill the stem cell in the body gets
amplified as that cell contributes to regrowing the worm. So as a result of this, for 400 million
years, these planaria have accumulated mutations. Their genomes are an incredible mess. Their cells
are basically mixoploid, meaning they're like a tumor. Every cell has a different number of
chromosomes potentially. It just looks horrible. As an end result, you've got an animal that is
immortal, incredibly good at regenerating with 100% fidelity and very resistant to cancer.
Now, all of this is the exact opposite of the message you get from a typical course through
biology, which says that, what is the genome for? The genome is for setting your body structure.
If you mess with the genome, that information goes away. You get aging, you get cancer.
Why does the animal with the worst genome have the best anatomical fidelity? I think we actually,
a few months ago, we actually, I think, have some insight into this, but it's been bugging
me for years. And this is the kind of thing that nobody ever talks about because it goes
against the general assumption of what genomes actually do and what they're for. And this complete
lack of correlation between the genome, in fact, an anti-correlation between the genome quality
and the incredible ability of this animal to have a healthy anatomy.
Yeah. What is that insight that you mentioned you acquired a few months ago, preliminary?
Okay. In the name of throwing out kind of new unproven ideas, right? So this is just my
conjecture. We've done some computational modeling of it, which I initially, this was a
very clever student that I work with named Laxwin, who did some models with me. And
I initially thought it was a bug. And then I realized that, no, actually, this is the feature.
The idea is this, imagine... So we've been working for a long time on a concept of
competency among embryonic parts. And what this means is basically the idea that
there are homeostatic feedback loops among various cells and tissues and organs that
attempt to reach specific outcomes in anatomical morphous space, despite various perturbations.
So the idea is that if you have a tadpole and you do something to it, whether by a mutation
or by a drug or something, you do something to it where the eye is a little off kilter,
or the mouth is a little off. All of these organs pretty much know where they're supposed to be.
They will try to minimize distance from other landmarks and they will remodel. And eventually
you get a normal frog so that they will recover the correct anatomy, despite starting off in the
wrong position, or even things like changes in the number of cells or the size of cells.
They're really good at getting their job done despite various changes. So they have these
competencies to optimize specific things like their position and the structure and things like
that. So that's competency. Now, here's the interesting thing. Imagine that you have a
species that has some degree of that competency. And so you've got an individual, if that species
comes up for selection, fitness is high, looks pretty good. But here's the problem.
Selection doesn't know whether the fitness is high because his genome was amazing,
or the fitness is high because the genome was actually so-so, but the competency made up for it
and now everything got back to where it needs to go. So what the competency apparently does
is shield information from evolution about the actual genome. It makes it harder to pick the
best genomes because your individuals that perform well don't necessarily have the best genomes.
What they do have is competency. So what happens in our simulations is that if you start off with
even a little bit of that competency, evolution loses some power in selecting the best genomes,
but where all the work tends to happen is increasing the competency. So then the competency
goes up. So the cells are even better and the tissues are even better at getting the job done
despite the bad genome. That makes it even worse. That makes it even harder for evolution to see
the best genomes, which relieves some of the pressure on having a good genome, but it basically
puts all the pressure on being really competent. So basically what happens is that the genetic
fitness basically levels out at a really suboptimal level. And in fact, the pressure
is off of it. So it's tolerant to all kinds of craziness, but the competency and the mechanisms
of competency get pushed up really high. So in many animals, and there are other factors that
push against this ratchet, but it becomes a positive feedback loop. It becomes a ratchet
for optimal performance despite a suboptimal genome. And so in some animals, this evens out
at a particular point, but I think what happened in planaria is that this whole process ran away
to its ultimate conclusion. The ultimate conclusion is the competency algorithm became so good that
basically whatever the genome is, it's really good at creating and maintaining a proper worm
because it is already being evolved in the presence of a genome whose quality we cannot control.
So in computer science speak, it's kind of like, and Steve Frank put me onto this analogy,
it's kind of like what happens in rate arrays. When you have a nice rate array where the software
makes sure that you don't lose any data, the pressure is off to have really high quality
media. And so now you can tolerate media with lots of mistakes because the software takes care of it
in the rate and the architecture takes care of it. So basically what happens is you've got this
animal where that runaway feedback loop went so far that the algorithm is amazing and it's been
evolved specifically for the ability to do what it needs to do even though the hardware is kind
of crap. And it's incredibly tolerant. So this has a number of implications that to my knowledge
have never been explained before. For example, in every other kind of animal, you can call a stock
center and you can get mutants. So you can get mice with kinky kind of kink tails. You can get
flies with red eyes and you can get chickens without toes and you can get humans come with
albinos and things. There's always mutants that you can get. Planaria, there are no abnormal lines
of planaria anywhere except for the only exception is our two-headed line and that one's not genetic.
That one's bioelectric. So isn't it amazing that nobody has been able, despite 120 years of
experiments with planaria, nobody has isolated a line of planaria that is anything other than
a perfect planaria. And I think this is why. I think it's because they have been actually selected
for being able to do what they need to do despite the fact that the hardware is just very junky.
So that's my current take on it. And really it puts more emphasis on the algorithm and the
decision making among that cellular collective of what are we going to build and what's the
algorithm for making sure that we're all working to build the correct thing.
So if you translate this idea into computer science, a way to look at it is imagine that you
find some computers that have hard disks that are very, very noisy and where the hard disk
basically makes lots and lots of mistakes in encoding things and bits often flip and so on.
And you will find that these computers still work and they work in pretty much the same way
as the other computers that you have. And there is an orthodox sect of computer scientists that
thinks it is necessary that every bit on the hard disk is completely reliable or reliable to
such a degree that you only have a mistake once every 100 trillion copies. And you can
have an error correction code running on the hard disk at the low level that corrects this.
And after some point it doesn't become efficient anymore. So you need to have reliable hard disks
to be able to have computers that work like this. But how would these other computers work?
And it basically means that you create a virtual structure on top of the noisy structure
that is correcting for whatever degree of uncertainty you have or the degree of
randomness that gets injected into your substrate. Dave Eggley has a very nice metaphor for this.
Do you know him, maybe? Yeah, I know him.
Yeah, he's a beautiful artist who explores complexity by tinkering with computational models
and really finds his work very inspiring. And he has this idea of best effort computing. So
in his view, our own nervous system is a best effort computer. It's one that does not rely
on the other neurons around you working perfectly, but make an effort to be better than random.
And then you stack the improbabilities empirically by having a system that evolves to measure in
effect the unreliability of its components. And then stack the probabilities until you get
the system to be deterministic enough to do what you're doing with it. If you have a system that
is, as in the planaria, inherently very noisy, where the genome is an unreliable witness of
what should be done in the body, you just need to interpret it in a way that stacks the probabilities,
that is evaluating things with much more error tolerance. And maybe this is always the case.
Maybe there is a continuum, maybe not. It's also possible that there is some kind of phase shift
where you switch from organisms with reliable genomes to organisms with noisy genomes. And you
basically use a completely different way to construct the organism as a result. But it's
a very interesting hypothesis then to see if this is a radical thing or a gradual thing that happens
in all organisms to some degree. What I also like about this description that you give about
how the organism emerges, it maps in some sense also in how perception works in our own mind.
At the moment, machine learning is mostly focused on recognizing images or individual frames. And
you feed in information frame by frame and the information is totally disconnected.
A system like Dali2 is trained by giving it several hundreds of millions of images.
And they are disconnected. They are not adjacent images in the space of images. And
maybe you could not probably learn from giving 600 million images in a dark room and only looking
at this introduced the structure of the world from this. Whereas Dali can, which gives testament to
the power of our statistical methods and hardware that we have. That far surpasses, I think, the
combined power and reliability of brains, which probably would not be able to integrate so much
information over such a big distance. For us, the world is learnable because its adjacent frames
are correlated. Basically, information gets preserved in the world through time. And we
only need to learn the way in which the information gets transmogrified. And these
transmogrification of information means that we have a dynamic world in which the static image
is an exception. The identity function is a special case of how the universe changes. And
we mostly learn change. I just got visited by my cat. And my cat has difficulty to recognize
static objects compared to moving objects, where it's much, much easier to see a moving ball than
a ball that is lying still. And it's because it's much easier to segment it out the environment
when it moves. So the task of learning on a moving environment, a dynamic environment,
is much easier because it imposes constraints on the world. And so how do we represent a moving
world compared to a static world? The semantics of features changes. And an object is basically
composed of features that can be objects themselves. And the scene is a decomposition
of all the features that we see into a complete set of objects that explain the entirety of the
scene. And the interaction between them and causality is the interaction between objects.
And in a static image, these objects don't do anything. They don't interact with each other.
They just stand in some kind of relationship that you need to infer, which is super difficult
because you only have this static snapshot. And so the features are classifiers that tell you
how to, whether a feature is a hand or a foot or a pen or a sun or a flashlight or whatever,
and how they relate to the larger scene, in which, again, you have a static relationship
in which you need to classify the object based on the features that contribute to them.
And you need to find some kind of description where you interpret features, which are usually
ambiguous and could be many different things, depending on the context in which you interpret
them, into one optimal global configuration, right? But if the scene is moving, this changes
a little bit. What happens now is that the features become operators. They're no longer
classifiers that tell you how your internal state needs to change, how your world needs to change,
how your simulation of the universe in your mind needs to change to track the sensory patterns.
Right, so a feature now is a change operator, a transformation. And the feature is in some sense
a controller that tells you how the bits are moving in your local model of the universe.
And they're organized in a hierarchy of controllers. And these controllers need to
be turned on and off at the level of the scene. And they have a lot of flexibility once you have
them. They can move around in the scene. They're basically now self-organizing,
self-stabilizing entities. In the same way as the mouse is moving around in your organism,
a feature can move around in the organism and shift itself around to communicate with other
features until they negotiate a valid interpretation of reality.
That's incredibly interesting because as soon as you started saying that,
I was starting to think that the virtualization that enables, right, so the earlier part of which
we're saying the virtualization of the information that allows you to deal with unreliable
hardware and everything, the bioelectric circuits that we deal with are a great candidate for that
because actually we see exactly that. We see a bioelectric pattern that is very resistant to
changes in the details and make sure that everybody does the right thing under a wide range of
different defects and so on. But even more than that, the other thing that you were just
emphasizing this, the fact that we learn the delta and that we're looking for change,
very interesting. If you pivot the whole thing from the temporal domain to the spatial domain,
so in development, when we look at these bioelectric patterns, now these patterns
are across space, not across time. So unlike in neuroscience where everything is in the temporal
domain for neurons, these are static voltage patterns across tissue, right, across the whole
thing. So for the longest time, we asked this question, how are these read out? How do cells
actually read these? Because one possibility early, this was a very early hypothesis 20 years ago,
was that maybe the local voltage tells every cell what to be. So it's like a paint by numbers kind
of thing. And each voltage value corresponds to some kind of outcome. That turned out to be false.
What we did find is that, and we have computational models of how this works now,
what is read out is the delta, the difference between regions. It doesn't care, nobody cares
about what the absolute voltage is, what is read out in terms of outcomes for downstream cell
behavior, gene expression, all that. What is actually read out is the voltage difference
between two adjacent domains. So that is exactly actually what it's doing just in the spatial
domain. It only keys off of the delta. And what is learned from that is exactly as you were saying,
it modifies the controller for what's downstream of that. And there may be multiple ones that are
sort of moving around and co-inhabiting. I mean, it's a very compelling picture actually and way
to look at some of the simulations that we've been doing about how the bioelectric data are
interpreted by the rest of the cells. It's very interesting.
So Professor Levin used the word competence earlier, and I'd like you to define that.
Yeah. In order to define it, I want to put out two concepts to this. One idea is that, to me,
and this goes back to what we were talking about before as the engineering stance on things,
I think that useful cognitive claims such as something, when you say this system has whatever
or it can whatever, as far as various types of cognitive capacities, I think those kinds of
claims are really engineering claims. That is, when you tell me that something is competent
at a particular level, so you can think about Wiener and Rosenbluth scale of cognition that
goes from simple passive materials and then reflexes and then all the way up to second
order metacognition and all that. When you tell me that something is on that
ladder and where it is, what you're really telling me is, if I want to predict its behavior or I
want to use it in an engineering context or I want to interact with it or relate to it in some way,
this is what I can expect. That's what you're really telling me. All of these terms,
what they really are, are engineering protocols. If you tell me that something
has the capacity to do associative learning or whatever, what you're telling me is that,
hey, you can do something more with this than you could with a mechanical clock.
You can provide certain types of stimuli or experiences and you can expect it to do this
or that afterwards. Or if you tell me that something is a homeostat, that means that,
hey, I can count on it to keep some variable at a particular range without having to be myself
to control it all the way. It has a certain autonomy now. If you tell me that something
is really intelligent and it can do XYZ, then I know that, okay, you're telling me that it
has even more autonomous behavior in certain contexts. All of these terms, to me, what they
really are, they're not... And that has an important implication. The implication is that
they're observer dependent, that you've picked some kind of problem space, you've picked some
kind of perspective. And from that problem space and that perspective, you're telling me that
given certain goal states, this system has that much competency to pursue those goal states.
And different observers can have different views on this for any given system. So for example,
somebody might look at a brain, let's say a human brain and say, well, I'm pretty sure the only
thing, this is a paperweight. So it's really pretty much just competent in going down gravitational
gradients. So all it can do is hold down paper, that's it. And somebody else will look at it and
say, you missed the whole point. This thing has competencies in behavioral space and
linguistic space. So these are all empirically testable engineering claims about what you can
expect the system to do. So when I say competency, what I mean is we specify a space, a problem
space. And at the time when we were talking about this, the problem space that I was talking about
was the anatomical morphous space. That was the space we were talking about. So the space of
possible anatomical configurations and specifically navigating that morphous space. So you start off
as an egg or you start off as a damaged limb or whatever, and you navigate that morphous space
into the correct structure. So when I say competency, I mean, you have the ability to deploy
certain kinds of tricks to navigate that morphous space with some level of performance that I can
count on. And so the competency might be really low or it might be really high. And I would have to
make specific claims about what I mean. Here's an example of a common, and there are many,
if you just think about the behavioral science of navigation, there are many competencies you
can think about. Does it know ahead of time where it's going? Does it have a memory of where it's
been? Or is it a very simple sort of reflex arc is all it has? Or here's one example of a pretty
cool competency that a lot of biological systems have. If we take some cells that are in the tail
of a tadpole and we modify their ion channels such that they now acquire the goal of navigating to
an eye fate in this morphous space, meaning that they're going to make an eye. These things,
in fact, will create an eye and they'll make an eye in the tail, on the gut, wherever you want.
But one of the cool, and so that's already pretty cool, but one of the amazing aspects is
if I only modify a few cells, not enough to make an actual eye, just a handful of cells,
and we've done this and you can see this work. One of the competencies they have is to recruit
local neighbors that were themselves not in any way manipulated to help them achieve that goal.
It's a little bit like in an ant colony. This idea of recruitment in ants and termites is an
idea of recruitment where individuals can recruit others and talk about a flexible collective
intelligence. This is it. You've re-specified the goal for that set of cells, but one of the
things that they do without us telling them how to do it or having to micromanage it,
they already have the competency to recruit as many cells as they need to get the job done.
For an engineer, that's a very nice competency because it means that I don't need to worry
about taking care of getting exactly the right number of cells. If I'm a little bit over,
that's fine. If I'm way under, also fine. The system has that competency of recruiting
other cells to get the job done. That's what I meant. To make any kind of a cognitive claim,
you have to specify the problem space. You have to specify the goal towards which it's expressing
competencies. Then you can make a claim about, well, how competent is it to get to that goal?
I wish I could remember who it was, but somebody made this really nice analogy about the ends of
that spectrum. They said two magnets try to get together and Romeo and Juliet try to get together,
but the degree of flexible problem solving that you can expect out of those two systems is
incredibly different. Within that range, there are all kinds of in-between systems that may be
better or worse and may deploy different kinds of strategies. Can they avoid local optima? Can they
have a memory of where they've been? Can they look further than their local environment? A
million different things. That's what I meant by competency. It's a claim about
what an engineer can expect the system to do given a particular problem space and a particular
goal that you think it's trying to reach. The way in which you use the word competency
could be treated as the capacity of a system for adaptive control.
One issue that I have with the notion of goals and goal directedness is that sometimes you only
have a tendency in a system to go in a certain direction. It's directed, but the goal is something
that can be emergent. Sometimes it's not. Sometimes there is an explicit representation
in the system of a discrete event that is associated or a class of events with fulfilling
a certain condition that the system has committed itself to. If you don't have that, you don't have
a proper goal. In real systems, it's difficult to say. When do we pursue goals? Sometimes we just
vaguely hungry or moving towards the kitchen because we hope that something will opportunistically
emerge that will deal with this vague tendency in our behavior. We could also say we have the
goal of finding food, but that is a rationalization that is maybe stretching things sometimes.
Sometimes a better distinction for me is going from a simple controller to an agent.
We are very good at discovering agency in the world. What does it actually mean when we discover
agency and when we discover our own agency and start to amplify it by making models of who we
are and how we deal with the world and with others and so on? The minimal definition of agent that I
found is a controller for future states. The thermostat doesn't have a goal by itself. It
just has a target value and a sensor that tells its deviation from the target value and when that
exceeds a certain threshold, the heating is turned on. If it goes below a certain threshold,
the heating is turned off again and this is it. The thermostat is not an agent. It only reacts
to the present frame. It's only a reactive system. Whereas an agent is proactive, which means that
it's trying to not just minimize the current deviation from the target value, but the integral
over the time span, the future deviation. It builds an expectation about how an action is
going to change this trajectory of the universe. Over that trajectory, it tries to figure out some
measure of how big the compound target deviation is going to be. As a result, you get a branching
universe. The branches in this universe, some of these branches depend on actions that are
available to you and that translate into decisions that you can make that move you
into more or less preferable wealth states. Suddenly, you have a system with emergent
beliefs, desires, and intentions. To make that happen, to move from a controller to agency,
agent just being a controller with an integrated set point generator and the ability to control
future states, that requires that you can make models that are counterfactual because the future
universe doesn't exist right now. You need to create a counterfactual model of the future
universe, maybe even a model of the past universe that allows you to reason about possible future
universes and so on. To make these counterfactual causal models of the universe, you need to have a
Turing machine. Without a computer, without something that is Turing complete, that insulates
you from the causal structure of your substrate, that allows you to build representations regardless
of what the universe says right now around you, you need to have that machine. The simplest
system in nature that has a Turing machine integrated is the cell. It's very difficult to
find a system in nature that is an agent, that is not made from cells as a result. Maybe there
are systems in nature that are able to compute things and make models, but I'm not aware of any.
The simplest one that I know that can do this reliably is the cells or arrangement of cells
that can possess agency, which is an interesting thing that explains this coincidence that living
things are agents and vice versa, that the agents that we discover are mostly living things,
or there are robots that have computers built into them, or virtual robots that rely on
computation. The ability to make models of the future is the prerequisite for agency.
To make arbitrary models, which means structures that embody causal simulations of some sort,
that requires computation. Yeah, yeah. I'm on board with that
ladder, that taxonomy of goals and so on. One interesting thing about goals, and as you say,
some are emergent and some are not, there's an interesting planarian version of this,
which is this. We made this hypothesis about, so within planaria, you chop it up into pieces
and every piece regenerates exactly the right rest of the work. If you chop it into pieces,
each piece will have one head, one tail. Then, of course, what happens is it stops when it reaches
a correct planarian, then it stops. We started to think that there are a couple of possibilities.
One possibility is that this is a purely emergent process and that the goal of rebuilding a head is
an emergent thing that comes about as a consequence of other things. Or could there be
an actual explicit representation of what a correct planarian is that serves as a
set point, as an explicitly encoded set point for these cells to follow?
Because it's a cellular collective, we were communicating electrically. We thought, well,
maybe what it's doing is basically storing a memory of what, like you would in a neural
circuit, storing a memory of what it should be. We started looking for this and this is what we
found. This is, I think, one important type of goal in a goal-seeking system is a goal that
you can rewrite without changing the hardware and the system will now pursue that goal instead of
something else. In a purely emergent system, that doesn't work. If you have a cellular automaton or
a fractal or something that does some kind of complex thing, if you want to change what that
complex thing is, you have to figure out how to change the local rules. That's very hard in most
cases. But what we found in planaria is that we can literally, using a voltage reporter die,
we can look at the worm and we can see now the pattern, and it's a distributed pattern,
but we can see the pattern that tells this animal how many heads it's supposed to have.
And what you can do is you can go in and using a brief transient manipulation of the ion channels
with drugs, with ion channel drugs, and we have a computational model that tells you what those
drugs should be, that briefly changes the electrical state of the circuit, but the circuit is amazing.
Once you've changed that state, it holds. So by default, in a standard planaria, it always says
one head, but it's kind of like a flip-flop in that when you temporarily shift it, it holds and
you can push it to a state that says two heads. So now something very interesting happens. Two
interesting things. One is that if you take those worms and you cut those into pieces,
you get two headed worms, even though the hardware is all wild type. There's nothing wrong with the
hardware. All the proteins are the same. All the genetics is the same, but the electric circuit
now says make two heads instead of one. And so this is in an interesting way. It is an explicit
goal because you can rewrite it because much like with your thermostat, there's an interface for
changing what the goal state is, and then you don't even need to know how the rest of the
thermostat works. As long as you know how to modify that interface, the system takes care of
the rest. The other interesting thing is, and I love what you said about the counterfactuals,
what you can do is you can change that electrical pattern in an intact worm and not cut it for a
long time. And if you do that, when you look at that pattern, that is a counterfactual pattern
because that two headed pattern is not a readout of the current state. It says two heads, but the
animal only has one head. It's a normal planarian. So that pattern memory is not a readout of what
the animal is doing right now. It is a representation of what the animal will do in the future if it
happens to get injured. And you may never cut it or you may cut it, but if you do, then the cells
consult the pattern and build a two headed worm, and then it becomes the current state. But until
then, it's this weird like primitive, it's a primitive counterfactual system because it's
able to, a body of a planarian is able to store at least two different representations of what a,
probably many more, but we've found two so far, what a correct planarian should look like. It
can have a memory of a one headed planarian or a memory of a two headed planarian. And both of
those can live in exactly the same hardware and exactly the same body. The other kind of cool
thing about this, and I'll just mention this even though this is disclaimer, this is not published
yet. So take all this with a grain of salt, but the latest thing you can do is you can actually
treat it with some of the same compounds that are used in neuroscience in humans and in rats as
memory blockers. So things that block recall or memory consolidation. And when you do that,
you can make the animal forget how many heads it's supposed to have. And then they basically
turn into a featureless circle when you can just wipe the pattern memory completely.
Were they using exactly the same techniques you would use in a rat or a human? They just forget
what to do when they turn into, they fail to break symmetry and they just become a circle.
So yeah, I think what you were saying is right on with this ability to store counterfactual
states that are not true now, but may represent aspects of the future. I think that's a very
important capacity. Another important notion is a constraint and constraint satisfaction. A
constraint is a rule that tells you whether two things are compatible or not. And the constraint
is satisfied if they're compatible. So you basically have a number of conditions that you
establish by measuring that somehow, for instance, whether you have a head or multiple heads,
and you try to find a solution where you can end up with exactly one head. And if you end up with
exactly one head based on the starting state, then you have managed to find a way to satisfy
your constraints. And so in a sense, what you call a competency is the ability of a system to take
a region of the states of the space of the universe, basically some local region of possible
state that the universe can be in, and move that region to a smaller region that is acceptable.
So there is a region on the universe state space where you have only one head. And there's a larger
region where you don't have any head at all, but the starting state of your organism. And then you
try to get from A to B. So you get from this larger region to the one in which you want to be. Of
course, if you have one head, you want to stay in the region in which you have one head, which,
of course, is usually much easier. But the ability basically to condense the space, to bridge over
many regions into the target region is what comes down to what this competency is. The system
basically has an emergent wanting to go in this region, and it's trying to move there. And so
there are constraints at the level of the substrate that are battling with the functional constraints
that the organism wants to realize to fulfill its function. And sometimes you cannot satisfy this,
and you end up with two heads because you don't know which one you get rid of, or how to digest
one of the heads and so on. And you end up with some Siamese twin. And so this is an interesting
constraint that you have to solve for when you are dealing with reality and how you battle with
the substrate until you get to the functional solution that you evolved for. Yeah, that's
interesting. I mean, we've also found that there are... So we look at exactly this
the navigation, this kind of navigation and morphous space, how you get from here to there
and what paths are possible to get from here to there and so on. One of the things that we found
is that there are regions of that space that belong to other species. And you can push a
planarian with a standard wild type genome into the goal state of a completely different species.
So we can get them to grow a head. So there's a species that normally has a triangular head.
You can make it grow a round head like a different species or a flat head or whatever.
So those are about 100 to 150 million years of evolutionary distance. And you can do it
within a few days just by perturbing that electrical circuit so that it lands in the
wrong space. And then outside of that, there are regions that don't belong to planaria at all.
So planaria are normally nice and flat. We've made planarians that look like they are a cylinder,
like a ski cap. They become like a hemisphere or really weird ones that are spiky. They're
like a ball with spikes on it. There are all kinds of other regions in that space that you can push
them to. And so- Those are new. Those are not species that they diverge from. Those are new.
No one's ever... To my knowledge, yes, there are no such species. It's easier to... And we've
done this in frog too. You can push tadpoles to make it to look like those of other species
or you can make... That's a whole interesting thing for evolution anyway. One species birth
defect is a perfectly reasonable different species. So we can make tadpoles with a rounded tail,
which for a Xenopus tadpole is a terrible tail, but for a zebrafish, that's exactly the right tail.
So you can imagine evolution manipulating the different information processing by electrical
circuits or other machinery that help the system explore that more of a space and start to move
away from whatever that speciation is moving away from your standard attractor that you usually
land on. How does this relate to intelligence? Well, intelligence is the ability to make models
and usually in the service of control, at least that's the way I would explain intelligence.
There are other definitions, but it's the simplest one that I've found.
It also accounts for the fact that many intelligent people are not very good at getting
things done. Basically, intelligence and goal rationality are somewhat orthogonal.
And excessive intelligence is often a prosthesis for bad regulation.
Have you read the intelligence trap? No.
Okay. The author makes a similar case and he's coming on shortly, essentially saying that there
are certain traps that people with high IQs have that are not beneficial for them as biological
beings. They're mainly cognitive biases. So for instance, it's extremely interesting. So let's
just give one of the biases to say you're either liberal biased or you're conservative biased,
and then you were to give a test where there's some data that says that on the surface, it shows
that the data shows that gun control prevents gun violence. Well, the liberals are more likely to
say, yes, this data does show that. But if you're conservative, you're more likely to find, oh,
actually the subtleties in the data show that gun control increases gun violence. And then they
thought, okay, well, let's just switch this to make it such that the superficial data suggests that
gun control increases violence. You need to look at the data carefully to show that it actually
prevents violence. Well, the conservatives in that case would be more quickly to say, oh, look,
the gun control increases violence, and the liberals would find the the loophole. Well,
that's one of the reasons why I don't mind interviewing people who are biased. Because to
me, they're more able to find a justification for something that may be true. But I or and others
are so well, we all have our own biases. We're so inclined in some other direction that we just were
blind to it. But anyway, the point is to affirm what you're saying, Yoshi. Okay, so I know Michael
has a hard cut off at 2pm. So I want to ask the question for a GI that is artificial general
intelligence. It seems as though we're far away or that our current methods of machine learning
and what we learn in neuroscience or or what we learn in computer science is something that we're
missing some paradigm shift or missing some new techniques. Is there something from Michael's
work? Yoshi, I'm asking you this and then Michael, please respond. Is there something from Michael's
work that you think can be applied to the development of a GI if such a creature mind
can exist? Because there are some arguments against it. First of all, I don't know how far
we are for a GI. It could be that the existing paradigms are sufficient to brute force it.
But we don't know that yet. It's a we're going to find out in the next few months.
But it could also be that we need to revive the stack to build systems that work in real time
that are entangled with the environment that can build shared representations with the environment.
And that we need to rewrite the stack. And there are actually a number of questions that I'd like
to ask Michael. What I noticed that Michael is wisely reluctant to use certain words like
consciousness a lot. And it's because a lot of people are very opinionated about what these
concepts mean. And you first have to deal with these opinions before you come down to saying,
oh, here I have the following proposal for implementing reflexive attention
as a tool to form coherence in a representation. And this leads to the same phenomena as what you
call consciousness. So that is a detailed discussion. Maybe you don't want to have
that discussion in every forum. And then having this discussion, you may be looking at how to
create coherence using a reflexive attention process that makes a real time model of what
it's attending to and the fact that it's attending to it so it remains coherent but for itself.
So this is a concrete thing. But I wonder how to implement this in a self-organized fashion
if the substrate that you have are individual agents. And there is a similarity here between
societies and brains and social networks. That is, if you have self-interested agents, in a way,
that try to survive and that get their rewards from other agents that are similar to them
structurally. And they have the capacity to learn to some degree. And that capacity is
sufficient so they can, in the aggregate, learn arbitrary programs, arbitrary computable functions.
And it's sufficient enough so they can converge on the functions that they need to
as a group reap rewards that apply to the whole group because they have a shared
destiny like the poor little cells that are locked in the same skull and they're all going
to die together if they fuck up. So they have to get along, they have to form an organization
that is distributing rewards among each other. And this gives us a search space for possible
systems that can exist. And the search space is mostly given, I think, by the minimal agent
that is able to learn how to distribute rewards efficiently while doing something useful. Using
these rewards to change how you do something useful. So you have an emergent form of governance
in these systems. There's not some centralized control that is imposed on the system from the
outside as an existing machine learning approaches and AI approaches. But this only is an emergent
pattern in the interactions between the individual small units, small reinforcement learning agents.
And this control architecture leads to hierarchical government. It's not fully decentralized in any
way. There are centralized structures that distribute rewards for instance via the dopaminergic
system in a very centralized top-down manner. And that's because every regulation has an optimal
layer where it needs to take place. Some stuff needs to be decided very high up, some stuff needs
to be optimally regulated very low down depending on the incentives. Game theoretically, a government
is an agent that imposes an offset on your payoff metrics to make your Nash equilibrium compatible
with the globally best outcome. To do this you need to have agents that are sensitive to rewards.
It's super interesting to think about these reward infrastructures. Elon Musk has bought Twitter I
think because he has realized that Twitter is the network among all the social networks that is
closest to a global brain. It's totally mind-blowing to realize that he basically trades a bunch of
wealthy stock for the opportunity to become pope. Pope of a religion that has more active participants
than Catholicism even, right? Daily practicing people who enter this church and think together.
And it's a thing that is completely incoherent at this point, almost completely incoherent.
There are bubbles of sentience but for the most part this thing is just screeching at itself.
And now there is the question, can we fix the incentives of Twitter to turn it into a global
brain? And Elon Musk is global brain-pilled. He believes that this is the case and that's the
experiment that he's trying to do which makes me super excited, right? This might fail, there's a
very big chance that it fails but there is also the chance that we get the global brain, that we get
emerging collective intelligence that is working in real time using the internet in a way that
didn't exist before. So super fascinating thing that might happen here. And it's fascinating that
very few people are seeing that Elon Musk is crazy enough to spend 44 billion dollars on that
experiment just because he can and has nothing else to do and thinks it's meaningful to do it,
more meaningful than having so much money in the bank, right? So this makes me interested in
this test bed for rules and this is something that translates into the way in which society
is organized because social media is not different from society, not separate from it.
Problem of governing social media is exactly the same thing as governing a society. You need a
right form of government, you need a legal system, ultimately you need representation and all these
issues, right? It's not just the moderation team and the same thing is also true for the brain.
What is the government of the brain that emerges in what Gary Edelman calls neural Darwinism among
different forms of organization in the mind until you have a model of a self-organizing agent that
discovers that what it's computing is driving the behavior of an agent in the real world and
it covers a first-person perspective and so on. How does that work? How can we get a system that
is looking for the right incentive architecture? And that is basically the main topic where I
think that Michael's research is pointing from my perspective that is super interesting. We have
this overlap between looking at cells and looking at the world of humans and animals and stuff
in general. Yeah, super interesting. Chris Fields and I are working on a framework to understand
where collective agents first come from, right? How do they organize themselves?
And we've got a model already about this idea of rewards and rewarding other cells with
neurotransmitters and things like this to keep copies of themselves nearby because they're the
most predictable. So this idea of reducing surprise, well, what's the least surprising thing?
It's a copy of yourself. And so you can sort of, Chris calls it the imperial model of multicellularity.
But one thing to really think about here is imagine an embryo. This is an amniote embryo,
let's say a human or a bird or something like that. And what you have there is you have a flat disc
of 10,000, 50,000 cells. And when people look at it, you say, what is that? They say it's an embryo,
one embryo. Well, the reason it's one embryo is that under normal conditions, what's going to
happen is that in this disc, one cell is symmetry breaking. One cell is going to decide that it's
the organizer. It's going to do local activation, long range inhibition. It's going to tell all the
other cells, you're not the organizer, I'm the organizer. And as a result, you get one special
point that begins a process that's going to walk through this memorphous space and create a particular
large scale structure with two eyes and four legs and whatever else it's going to have.
But here's the interesting thing. Those cells, that's not really one embryo. That's a weird kind
of Freudian ocean of potentiality. What I mean by that is if you take, and I did this as a grad
student, you can take a needle and you can put a little scratch through that blastoderm, put a
little scratch through it. What will happen is the cells on either side of that scratch don't
feel each other. They don't hear each other's signals. So that symmetry breaking process will
happen twice, once on each end. And then when it heals together, what you end up with is two
conjoined twins because each side organized an embryo and now you've got two conjoined twins.
Now, many interesting things happen there. One is that every cell is some other cell's
external environment. So in order to make an embryo, you have to self-organize a system that
puts an arbitrary boundary between itself and the outside world. You have to decide where do I end
and the world begins. And it's not given to you somehow from outside for a biological system.
Every biological system has to figure this out for itself, unlike modern robotics or whatever,
where it's very clear. Here's where you are. Here's where the world is. These are your
effectors. These are your sensors. Here's the boundary of the outside world. Living things
don't have any of that. They have to figure all of this out from scratch.
The benefit to being able to figure it out from scratch, having to figure it out from scratch,
is that you are then compatible with all kinds of weird initial conditions. For example,
if I separate you in half, you can make twins. You don't have a total failure because now
you have half the number of cells. You can make twins. You can make triplets,
probably many more than that. So if you ask the question, you look at that
blastoderm and you ask how many individuals are there, you actually don't know. It could be zero.
It could be one. It could be some small number of individuals. That process of autopolices has to
happen. And here are a number of things that are uniquely biological that I think relate to
the kind of flexibility plasticity that you need for AGI in whatever space. It doesn't have to be
the same space that we work in, but your boundaries are not set for you by an outside creator.
You have to figure out where your boundaries are. Where is the outside world? So you make
hypotheses about where you end and where the world begins. You don't actually know what your
structure is. Kind of like Vanguard's robots from 2006 where they didn't know their structure and
they had to make hypotheses about, well, do I have wheels? Do I have legs? What do I have? And then
make a model based on basically babbling, right? Like the way that babies babble. So you have to
make a model of where the boundary is. You have to make a model of what your structure is.
You are energy limited, which most AI and robotics nowadays are not. When you're energy and time
limited, it means that you cannot pay attention to everything. You are forced to coarse grain in
some way and lose a lot of information and compress it down. So you have to choose a lens,
a coarse graining lens on the world and figure out how you're going to represent things.
And all of this has to, and there are many more things that we could talk about, but all of these
things are self-constructions from the very beginning. And then you start to act in various
spaces, which again are not predefined for you. You have to solve problems that are metabolic,
physiological, anatomical, maybe behavioral if you have muscles, but nobody's defining the space
for you. For example, if you're a bacterium and Chris Fields points this out, if you're a bacterium
and you're in some sort of chemical gradient, you want to increase the amount of sugar in your
environment, you could act in three-dimensional space by physically swimming up the gradient,
or you can act in transcriptional space by turning on other genes that are better at
converting whatever sugar happens to be around and that solves your metabolic problem instead of,
right? So you have these hybrid problem spaces. So all of this, I think what contributes in
a strong sense to all the things that we were just talking about is the fact that everything
is in biology is self-constructed from the beginning. You can't rely on, you don't know
ahead of time when you're a new creature born into the world. And we have many examples of
this kind of stuff. You don't know how many cells you have, how big your cells are. You can't count
on any of the priors. So you have this weird thing that evolution makes these machines that
don't take the past history too seriously. It doesn't over train on them. It makes
problem-solving machines that use whatever hardware you have. This is why we can make
weird chimeras and cyborgs. And you can mix things and mix and match biology in every way
with other living things or with non-living things because all of this is interoperable,
because it does not make assumptions about what you have to have. It tries to solve whatever
problem is given. It plays the hands that it's dealt. And that results in that assumption that
you cannot trust what you come into the world with. You cannot assume that the hardware is
what it is. It gives rise to a lot of that intelligence, I think, and a lot of that plasticity.
So if you translate this into necessary and sufficient conditions, what seems to be necessary
for the emergence of general intelligence in a bunch of cells or units is that basically each
of them is a small agent, which means it's able to behave with an expectation of minimizing future
target value deviations. It learns that their configuration is environment that signal anticipated
reward. Next thing, these units need to be not just agents, they need to be connected to each other.
And they need to get their rewards or proxy rewards, something that allows them to anticipate
whether the organism is going to feed them in the future from other units that also adaptive.
So you need multiple message types and the ability to recognize and send them with a certain degree
of reliability. What else do you need? You need enough of them, of course. What's not clear to me
is how deterministic do the units need to be? How much memory do they need to be? How much state can
they store? How deep in time does their recollection need to go? And how much forward in time do they
need to be able to form expectations? So we see how large is this activation front that they can
with this shape of the distribution that they can learn and have to learn to make this whole thing
happen. And so basically conditions that are necessary are relatively simple. If you just
wait for long enough and get such a system to percolate, I imagine that the compound agency
will at some level emerge on the system, just in a competition of possibilities in the same way as
emerging agency has emerged on Twitter in a way, with devoked religion in a way that people
were starting to shift around their behavior to maximize likes and retweets. And there was no
external reward that was given on Twitter. So as a result, a local structure emerged a local agency
that was shifting the rewards by itself and emerging causal structure that was in some sense
in downward causation going to organize groups of people into behavioral things. It's really
as interesting to look at Twitter as something like a mind at some level, right? It's working slower,
but it would probably be possible to make a simulation of these dynamics in a more abstract
way and to use this for arbitrary problem solving. And so what would an experiment look like in which
we start with these necessary conditions and narrow down the sufficient conditions?
Yeah, right on. And yeah, we're doing some of that stuff, some of that kind of modeling.
I apologize. I've got to run here. Thank you both for coming out for this. I appreciate it.
Thank you so much. And thank you for bringing us together. So a great conversation. I really
enjoyed it. Likewise. I enjoyed it very much. Thank you, Kurt. Thank you so much, Kurt.
Thanks, Joshua. The podcast is now concluded. Thank you for watching. If you haven't subscribed
or clicked on that like button now would be a great time to do so as each subscribe and like
helps YouTube push this content to more people. Also, I recently found out that external links
count plenty toward the algorithm, which means that when you share on Twitter, on Facebook,
on Reddit, et cetera, it shows YouTube that people are talking about this outside of YouTube,
which in turn greatly aids the distribution on YouTube as well.
If you'd like to support more conversations like this, then do consider visiting theories
of everything.org. Again, it's support from the sponsors and you that allow me to work on
toe full time. You get early access to ad free audio episodes there as well. Every dollar helps
far more than you may think. Either way, your viewership is generosity enough. Thank you.