That's it.
It's a good thing that you're here with us.
I don't know what you're talking about.
Mufasa.
You can't do that.
I don't know if you can hear me, but I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can
't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you,
I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't
hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I
can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear you, I can't hear
I don't know what you're talking about.
I'm going to try to get a little bit of a better understanding of what's going on here.