I don't know what you're talking about.
I don't know if you can hear me, but I can't hear you.
Yeah, dear sir, this is my little lesbian friend.
She sounds very simple.
Oh, and again?
You're cheating!
You are always the most important person in the world.
You are always the most important person in the world...
You're an important person right now, so you are really important...
So you are really important to this world pretiez-
So you're important but you also become really important,
Do you plan to be aItter-
I don't know what you're talking about, but I don't know what you're talking about.
I don't know what you're talking about.
I don't know. I don't know what you're talking about.
I don't know what you're talking about, but I don't know what you're talking about.