I don't know what to do with you.
I really don't know what to do with you.
I really don't know what to do with
you.
I don't know what to do with you.
You know I don't know what to do with you.
and uh
I don't know if you can hear me, but I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can
hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can
I don't know what you're talking about, but I don't know what you're talking about.
I don't know what you're talking about.
So, I'm going to show you how to do it.
So, I'm going to do it.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.