It's a good thing you're here.
It's a big thing you're here.
I don't know if you can hear me, but I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can
hear you, can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can
hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can
I'm going to show you how to do it.
I'm gonna show you how to do it.
It's a good idea to have a little bit of space between the legs.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry
I'm sorry, I'm sorry direction
I pity myself for being like this
I pity myself for being
I want to realize the fact that
I'm a mess
I want to change everything
While helping my friends
Let me know if you see that
and if you care about me
and what you can do
and why you can't
I'm going to show you how to do it.
I'm going to tell you how to do it.
I'm not going to let you get away with this.
I'm going to let you get away with this.