I'm not going to do that.
I'm going to do that.
You can see.
Notice that we're both periods.
I keep you in view of me.
I'm not going to make you fall in love.
You can find a way,
but you decide on me.
And also observe me,
and be objective,
and crap,
and be positive,
and let go of me.
I think that maybe
wherever we're going,
I don't know if you can hear me, but I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can
hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear
you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you,
I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can
So, I'm going to show you how to do it.
I'm going to show you how to do it.