I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry
Okay, okay, okay.
I'm going to show you how to do it.
I don't know if you can hear me, but I can hear you.
I can hear you.
two
four
six
five
two
I don't know what you're talking about.
I don't know what you're talking about, but I think it's a good idea to do that.
I think it's a good idea to do that.
I think it's a great idea to do that.
I'm not sure if this is a good idea or not, but I think it's a good idea.
I'm not sure if this is a good idea, but I think it's a good idea.