Now, I'm going to show you how to do it.
I'm going to show you how to do it.
You put it to the top.
I don't know if you can hear me, but I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can
hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you, I can hear you
I can hear you, you
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry ,I'm sorry, I'm sorry hide
I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't
know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't
It's a good thing that we have a lot of people who are interested in it.
It's a good thing that we have a lot of people who do different
And that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's it, that's
that's it, that's it, that's it,
that's it,
superpower button
Oh, there's a...
I'm going to try to get a little bit closer to the bottom of the pool.