I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm
not sure if you can hear me or not, but I'm not sure if I can hear you.
It's a good idea to have a little bit of space between the two.