I don't know if you can hear me, but I can hear you.
I can hear you.
Nice!
Hi hi hi.
Hi.
x selon
th
the
I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper,
and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I'm going to add a little bit of salt and pepper, and then I can already hear the music...
We're going to turn off the song, sleepy, and then we're off...
You know what, you know what, you know what, you know what, you know what, you know what,
you know what, you know what, you know what, you know what, you know what, you know what,
you know what, you know what, you know what.
You know what, you know what, you know what.
So, I'll explain it to you. I sat at the computer earlier, played a bit, the girls were out
and the woman called and said, should I buy you beer? We are just shopping. I'll bring you
beer. Tell me which beer. And it turned out that we were grilling. So I thought, cool,
we're grilling. But that means I'm drinking beer and that means I won't play after that
because if I'm drunk or just drunk, I can't play anymore. I'm taking it seriously.
I have a delay, then I can't react anymore and that's why I can't do it. So I thought,
I'll look at the debate battle at the competition anyway and I'll drink a beer anyway
because we're grilling. And I did this on the beamer in the living room. That means my wife
pulled it in and so on. Super funny. And then I thought, fuck it, do a live stream.
And I always wanted to do something quick anyway, like a few capitalism films
that are running under the radar that no one knows. First thing, in the video description
you have to find a link to a movie pilot list. If you can't see it, then you have to
make a fun account. Make yourself a fun account or log in with some junk,
with some social media. It should work. Then you can see the list. And I just
clicked them together. That means I will certainly have forgotten films that are super nice.
And if you can think of good films that talk about capitalism, and it's not especially
films like The Big Short that are obvious or Wolf of Wall Street, where that is completely clear,
but films where it may not be completely clear that they talk about capitalism.
These films are especially interesting. And yes, I have now prepared the list
and we'll just go through it. And as I said, if you come up with something, just write it
in the comments. The chat is now there. So, and before it starts, terms like capitalism
are bubbles on a string. The string is the well-known red thread. Such definitions
I see. You're in a good mood today. You have a beer, you have a spade, and that's why
you're making really clever speeches here. I notice that. Okay, no problem. I'll start.
I think I've talked about Killing Them Softly with Brad Pitt before. The film is really
wonderful, because the film is actually the perfect thing, in my opinion, about the films
that I actually want to talk about here. The film was sold back then as a mafia film.
He also only had the actors, for example the guys from the Sopranos. He had these typical
mobster mafia situations. And so was the trailer and so was the poster. So the film was
marketed. And everyone went into the movies and then expected a mafia film. And it was
not a classic mafia film. Everyone was already pissed off and the film also got super
bad reviews because everyone was just disappointed. And I'll tell you, I didn't know
the film and I didn't notice the advertising back then. I only saw it a few months ago.
And I was totally surprised. First of all, the film is also produced by Wood Pitt and
the film is about capitalism. So this setting, this mafia setting that is
embodied there, that's just a make-up artist. That's just a marketing strategy for the
film. But on the other hand, it's an extremely good metaphor. It's about capitalism.
And the nice thing is, Brad Pitt himself plays the main role and he embodies capitalism.
He embodies, in my opinion, all contradictions of capitalism. He has them in him.
So first of all, it's of course Brad Pitt. He looks super cool, he runs around, he's super
clean, he talks all the time and so on. And he just does it as if he were really serious.
And he just wants to, so he's an order killer and he just does his business with killing.
And that's not a problem at all. Morality doesn't play a role in the film at all.
That's really cool. That's what it's about, not at all. But he is constantly
confronted with the fact that his business also leads to things that
piss him off. And that's just funny. And the film is really just elegant and
very nicely done. Especially the first scenes are really dirty and you can see
how it is when you stand in the bottom of the pyramid in the USA. There is no solidarity.
Natural Born Chaos, yes. Very good idea. I'll add it right away.
If my wife was in the chat now, she would have said that a long time ago.
This is my wife's favorite film. In any case, a really good film because he
refers really well to how it is with the media and with the feedback loops.
And above all, he is already so old and yet the film is still completely accurate.
So, Killings in Softly. And that's for example the guy from the Sopranos.
He plays an aging order killer and he should do the job. And he should do the job
only because he wants to kill someone because Brad Pitt doesn't want to do it himself.
He somehow knows the victim so half and he actually didn't want to be pulled in
and that's just too emotional. And he would rather do an alienated business where
he is far away from the content. He doesn't want to argue about content. He just wants
to make a business decision. And then he gets a Sopranos man and he is
already completely over the mountain. So he doesn't want to do his job anymore.
He doesn't want to do anything anymore. He is completely alienated from the world.
He actually just wants to use alcohol. And that is no longer fun for him.
And he meets him in a hotel lobby and he is already badly reprimanded because the guy is
so fat and old and shit and he doesn't want to do it anymore and he is just drunk.
And Brad Pitt tries to get him to do the job and in the end he doesn't do it.
And then Brad Pitt has to do it himself and all that. And that's all totally awesome.
Super nice. And the best thing about the film. So first of all, this whole mess,
how it gets there. The actors are great. The whole excessive violence that is
shown in the film. It is really not fetishizing at all.
It is not like you would expect in a normal gangster movie.
Really masculine, really cool scenes where someone shoots you in the head with a
gun or something. Or where someone beats you up really hard. Yes, there is that.
But they are shown the way they are. Just raw and bloody.
I am actually used to raw violence in films and bloody films.
Nevertheless, I had this feeling when watching the film that this is just not an
aesthetic scene. It is just disgusting. It just resists you because the violence is
shown so realistically. And you really think, oh, does that have to be now?
Do they have to do that now? That's shit. And so on and so on.
And believe me, I have already seen a lot of films. It is not that I am
somehow surrounded by violence and that is why I am not good at it.
And that is wonderful. And of course all the actors are great.
And also all the little characters that are in it.
In my opinion, this is also a metaphor for the hype on the market place.
There are many small actors and that doesn't matter at all.
They will be irrelevant at some point. All the stories of the actors don't matter at some point.
At some point it's just about Brad Pitt and his business and whether he ends the quest
properly or not. And at the end of the film, that is really the best, the end,
the last 2-3 minutes, he is sitting there with the guy with whom he shot the deal
and so on. He was supposed to finish the job.
And somehow he gets less money. He gets beaten up for the money.
And in the background, Obama is running because there is a election campaign.
We are a big nation, we are a community, we all belong together. Come together, people.
And Brad Pitt doesn't have to come out at all and laugh how ridiculous that is.
Because he says, no, wait a minute, the USA is not a country. We are not a community.
Everyone has his own business. And besides, where is my money, you asshole?
And it's just a wonderful situation. I've said that before. The film is really fantastic.
And I think such films are great. He made fun of the people who watch the film,
as it is part of marketing, i.e. with capitalist methods,
to go to the cinema and watch the film about capitalism.
Of course, everyone was pissed off afterwards. I think it's wonderful. I can really imagine
And yes, all these metaphors in the film.
Then these drug addicts at the beginning, the mafia boys with the money and so on.
And then in the end the wrong one is knocked out. And that's just great.
It's a great film. So, next film.
The next film on my list. In German it's called The Black Diamond.
I don't know, I didn't even know that it's called that.
I think I looked it up in German. It's called Uncut Gems in English.
So, unpolished diamonds, one might translate that.
The film is first of all great because it's with Adam Sandler.
And Adam Sandler, you know, that's the guy who always makes these nonsense films.
These normal mainstream comedies, nonsense films.
And in this film, which is a highly serious film, he plays a guy
in the diamond Jewish quarter, where all the other diamond Jews are sitting around
in their weird diamond boots and peeing at each other with the stones and so on.
And I think the film starts with an African from a mine knocking out a fat clunker.
That's how the film starts. So that you can briefly see the misery,
from which misery layer everything is made. And then it's just about how
Adam Sandler tries to tick this fat clunker. And the whole film turns around like this.
And Adam Sandler is just a wheel in the gear. It becomes completely clear in the film
that he is of course not a profiteur of the system. Even if he sells the stone and everything is clean.
He is a profiteur. He has an infinite amount of stress in the film. It makes him completely finished.
He also probably has debts somewhere else. And it's all semi-legal.
Then he has some mafia boys who want to finish him. And he has this diamond shop
and that's so cool. And then he somehow has a wife, then he has an affair and so on.
Then it all goes down the drain. He is always stressed. His phone is constantly ringing.
And the whole setting is so that you as a viewer are permanently really tense.
You really feel the burnout. You feel the burnout of Adam Sandler.
And Adam Sandler in the film is also shown so cool. Because he is already so old.
You can do that really well. He already looks so finished.
And then you have the camera perspectives and close-ups of the faces.
Really intense shots where people are just shown in their ugliness.
That's great. And that's what makes the film so a little bit for me.
This ruckus camera, this stress, the burnout. All that just to somehow earn money.
What the people actually do, at least he, he is also half a player.
He does sports betting and so on. He is of course completely alienated.
What he actually wants is somehow money so that he can buy something with his money.
That's actually the tenor.
The film just completely rots out. It escalates in a certain direction.
And everything is always about this stone.
I would go so far and say this is a typical, this is a real masterpiece.
It's like Killing Them Softly in my opinion. A real masterpiece in terms of a capitalism film.
It's not like The Big Short or other films like Wall Street.
Where it is clear that this is completely clear that this is about capitalism and how stupid it is now.
I think clear films like that are also great. They are just on the list here because they are part of it.
But Uncut Gems is a film that is really really premium.
And I can only recommend it to you if you don't know it.
I have the impression that such films, although they are with such fat actors, do not come into the mainstream.
Because they just treat serious topics and the audience does not want that.
Because of casualization. There are only Avengers and some strange family films.
They are in the mainstream because they create positive vibes.
And that is exactly what people need in times of crisis.
People watch so many films that they break down.
And if you don't have the mental capacity and you just look at something like that all the time, then you go crazy.
Just because you are not aware of your own empathy.
I have the feeling that there must not be a perfect political system.
Because all political currents live from friction and crumbling.
If you think with a perfect political system that it is a system where the debates do not exist.
Or where everyone is always in agreement, where there are no conflicts.
I could imagine that it is a bit like the perfect free market.
Where all information is there and all actors make perfect rational decisions.
Then there is no profit in the system anymore.
I have looked up this article from Investopedia.
The perfect free market, the perfect competition, does not generate any profit anymore.
And maybe that's what you mean, the perfect political system.
As long as it contains people, I don't think it exists.
The inherent human contradictions reflect in our society again.
On a higher level we get them all turned in again.
And be it prejudices and racism, that's enough.
But of course there are many other things that play into it.
That's why I say, because the problem is that there is no perfect political system.
The optimal solution would be the absolute crumbling of all hierarchies.
Maybe not maximum, but extremely strong decentralization.
It could be that there are groups of 50 people who can establish themselves in a kind of debate culture that can function stably.
Because even if one of them goes out with the neighbor's wife and the other husband is angry, they might not give up.
Then you can somehow solve it.
This is also observed in many Swedish films, where people realize that such problems are not so strong if there is enough mental capacity in people.
All these inter-men problems that may also shake up.
If you have hierarchies, if one is the boss of a big company and has hatred for someone,
that he tries to use his power, which he exposes only to destroy someone who has only slept with his wife,
which has nothing to do with the business or the power itself and should actually be irrelevant to the hierarchies.
But that will be done by the fact that our human flaws are transferred to it.
Such a thing would also be possible.
But such a thing is small because of decentralization, because one does not give so much power to individual people.
Then one would automatically solve it.
Yes, people are not perfect, so no systems, I would say.
Yes, that is definitely the case.
You can really compare it with stable systems.
In physics, one talks about stable systems when small deviations do not change the state of balance.
A classic example is cycling.
Cycling only works because of rotation.
Rotation creates, so to speak, the wheels turn, they have a rotation and that is a constant with respect to the fixed star.
Of course, friction takes a little bit away, but that means that when you drive and there is a small deviation,
for example, I steer a little bit like this or I wobble around a bit, then I roll and then I keep tilting back,
then I tilt back, because that is also the case with a circle, in the state of balance.
Against small deviations, it is stable.
If, of course, one of the sides gives you a drop, then you fall off the bike and then the wheel turns, of course.
But for small deviations it is good.
So, and now you have to ask yourself systematically, how do you get the small deviations?
Well, if you do not start a world war, but only once the neighbor's wife has birded, then it is a small deviation.
But that can not make a world war easier.
If you now bird the wife of Putin, then maybe.
But the problem is, only Putin is so powerful.
So if you have small decentralized organs, where, so to speak, the power cannot be organized in big hierarchies,
then you can only generate small deviations with these human errors,
which then, possibly, by the community, which then knows and acts relatively familiarly,
because everyone is connected with everyone, not so alienated and anonymous as now, for example, here,
in a big city, in a normal big city, where you do not even know your neighbors,
then something like that works.
And if you have small hierarchies, with small communities, where everything is somehow debatable,
then it is somehow more conceivable.
And then, so to speak, the question is, how do you solve this with the big problems?
Well, with real networking and transparency.
So you have to strive for a transparent global networking,
in which something similar like a democracy can be nurtured with debate culture.
But that is definitely future music.
The basic requirement would be that you have enough mature citizens.
So not like now, but really many.
Over 50% should already be people who, so to speak, come to terms with it
and at least recognize how the world works.
Social engineering.
Digitalized humanity.
The thing is, I'm doing this video series about digitalization now,
and I don't know what's next, but I'm going to make a video about blockchain at some point.
Because blockchain, so to speak, is an academic aspect,
although very academic, but a relatively positive aspect.
And I think that these things bring all these positive vibes because of what digitalization could do.
It could, for example, pick up all the monopolistic structures.
Because that is exactly what automated, decentralized trust creates, a transparent environment.
Of course, it has many disadvantages, for example, energy consumption.
But the idea is not bad at first, and you can definitely do a lot of things from it.
The thing is, I'm just drawing up a lecture on cryptography,
just because I never really managed to draw it up,
because of how it works in real life, for example with random generators.
I once had a lecture on algorithms in physics or something.
It was mainly about C-programming of such numerical problems.
But something like that was also addressed.
The thing is, when the random generator was made with us,
there are different qualities of random generators.
In essence, they all repeat themselves at some point.
That means you have to sort out the system somehow.
I missed that. I don't know, I was on vacation or something when the lecture was on.
That means, because I didn't understand it in detail,
I'm drawing up a lecture on cryptography now,
and then I want to draw up a lecture on, I don't know, higher data structures,
to really understand how that works.
Of course, I understand schematically how that works with the blockchain.
That's clear. But that's not enough for me.
I want the details so that I know what I'm talking about.
That's always the way it is.
I want to establish this habitus.
Of course, that takes time, but I have the time.
I have the privilege to draw it up.
I like to draw up 13 lectures, 90 minutes each.
Just one every day or something.
At some point I got it. At some point I understood it.
That will definitely come, but I don't know when yet.
But this digitalization series is going to be quite lengthy.
I guess 5, 6, 7, 8 videos will already be published.
But I'm also doing other things on the side, so I don't know exactly when.
Then let's look further into my list.
So, apart from Uncut Gems,
the next film I've seen is the film Good Time.
It's by the same filmmaker.
It's the film before that.
It's also pretty cool.
It has the same thing with the camera and these ugly people in the close-up.
But the story is a bit more brutal.
Uncut Gems has shown the snowball system on the level of the people we would call privileged.
People who have enough income to have a house, an affair, a sports car and so on.
And Good Time shows the difference in the USA.
People who are so poor that they don't know where to get their food next week.
The film is pretty cool because it starts with a guy in a psychological treatment.
Psychotherapy or something like that.
He's talking to someone.
He obviously has a tube test and so on.
And the guy is a bit stupid, you can already see that.
He just looks like that and gives some weird answers.
And suddenly the stupid vampire guy, Robert Pattinson, comes in.
He looks really bad in the film, that's great.
And he says, fuck off you fucking therapist, I'll take my brother with me.
I'll save him from this misery.
I'll take him with me.
And that's how the film starts.
And it turns out that Robert Pattinson, by the way, only makes cool films since he stopped this joke with the vampire.
He made a name for himself with the vampire and now he makes cool films.
And that's the best I've seen so far.
But I've seen a few others that aren't bad either.
And he's the big brother of this guy who's a bit mental.
He's a bit stupid.
And they're both poor pigs.
And what's his plan?
Well, his plan is that he'll transfer a bank with his brother and then he'll fly to Mexico.
That's the plan.
And what do they do?
They somehow have scars and they have masks.
And they dress up as black.
That's funny because it's a bit like the structural racism in the states.
Later he's in a prison cell where only black people are sitting around.
That's funny anyway.
So they transfer a bank.
Then they run away with the money.
Then everything goes wrong.
I think they lose themselves somehow.
How was that?
I think the brother, because he's a bit stupid, gets caught by the bulls.
Robert Pattinson escapes with the money.
And then, I think, he has to wash the money.
And he has a lot of problems.
The funny thing is, Robert Pattinson is the only character in the whole movie who's clever.
You notice that.
He has problems, thinks of something and finds a relatively good solution.
He has the same burnout mentality as Adam Sandler in the other movie.
Or you can compare it with Jack Bauer in 24.
24 starts, then a problem pops up.
Then three more problems pop up.
At some point he has 1,000 tabs open with 1,000 problems.
And he has to solve them all within 24 hours.
That's the way it is.
And there are unpredictable things for Robert Pattinson.
And he gets them somehow.
He tricks people.
He just talks them to death.
So he has found a method.
The people are so stupid.
He just needs to talk to them, talk to them, talk to them.
So really stupid from the side.
Until they just give up and say, yes, you're right or something.
And you notice that.
And the kind of dialogues that are introduced in the movie.
That's how I actually imagine the normal, uneducated difference in the United States.
They really only talk about such idiotic things.
By the way, Idiocacy is actually a great movie, too.
It definitely has to be included here.
And yes, that's definitely the case with the film.
You notice that right away.
And you think all the time, that can't be.
The actions sometimes seem so strange to you.
But that's just because you're completely different.
The situation is evaluated as the people who are represented there.
And to get back to the thing with the racism.
It's super funny.
They're in a amusement park in the meantime.
I think they want to somehow.
What do they actually want?
I think either they want to hide the coal or they want to get the coal.
I don't know anymore.
In any case, they break in there.
And then there are security guys.
And they have to box them over.
And he's black.
And then they steal the clothes and dress themselves as security boys.
And then the real bulls come later.
And they just clearly assume that the black one has to be the criminal.
And that's not being spoken out.
It's like killing in the soft.
It's not being spoken out.
It's just a cool situation.
And you think that's an interesting situation.
Something like that is being watched out for.
Because of course capitalism and inequality and structural exploitation hierarchies,
such as racism or patriarchy or things like that,
they plant themselves very well in almost feudal structures
that we have in capitalism.
And that goes very well with our tradition and where the money is and the snowball system and so on.
And another cool situation is, I think in the film it was like this.
He wants to get his brother out of the hospital.
And he's being watched out for bulls.
Then he has to trick the bulls to get his brother out.
But then he finds out that he's on the wrong bed.
Because his brother was completely crushed by the blacks in the jail.
And he has a face that is completely covered with bandages.
And he doesn't know what he looks like.
And then he seems to be standing in front of the wrong bed
from another guy who was also completely crushed.
He takes him out, throws him in his car,
and then finds out that he's the wrong guy.
With him he runs around.
And the guy tells a story.
He tells a story about how it happened
that he is being watched out for bulls again and has to go to jail again and so on.
And then it's probably like this.
He came out of the jail and of course has no perspective.
Because you have to imagine, if you were in jail in the states,
then you're done for.
Then you can hardly get back into society.
First of all, you're burned.
But on the other hand, you don't have any credibility.
You don't have any credit worth.
You don't get an apartment and things like that.
Of course, you don't get a job if you don't have an apartment.
It all comes down to that.
So when you're poor, it gets more and more difficult in the USA.
Because there are very few solidarity structures at all
to catch these people.
And of course, they slip even further.
Either they become criminals again
or they rot or they are homeless
and then they become criminals again.
With little things and so on.
But that is shown in the film cool.
And the joke is, Robert Pattinson is freeing him now.
Unintentionally from the hospital.
And the guy wakes up and notices that
and says, shit, now I'm fucked.
I can't, I'm as good as in prison.
I'm out on bail.
And that you got me out of here, I can't tell anyone.
I'm fucked.
I can do whatever I want.
So that's his logical conclusion.
And that's why they go to this park.
I have a drug hiding place in the park.
With a bunch of drugs.
We can tick them, then we're rich.
And then we go to Mexico.
That was the logic.
And he helps him to find the treasure.
And that's a super funny quest.
The whole film goes like this.
And it's also from the stress level.
Just like Uncut Gems.
That you're always under stress.
And the film ends with Robert Pattinson.
How he gets arrested.
And sits in a police car.
And he looks into the camera for a minute.
And there's no music anymore.
He just looks.
And as a viewer you let everything go.
What happened in the last few minutes.
In the last hour of the film.
What he just experienced.
What he tried to solve.
What problems he solved.
And how he collapses in the end.
And how unresolvable it is for him.
It seems to him that he can't get out of this.
It's possible for him.
This perspective.
It's portrayed really well in the film.
And that's why I think it's a great film about capitalism.
Because that's how it looks.
Especially for the people who are in these situations.
Who are depicted there.
In my opinion absolutely realistic films.
Which are also portrayed so well.
In between there is also this story.
That a 15 year old is seduced.
Just to stay longer in the apartment.
There is also a lot of borderline stuff.
And it's all so dirty and dirty.
And so shit is depicted.
But just as it is.
I think that's important.
Films that just
The disgusting sides.
Of our civilization.
To the viewer in the face.
And say look at this.
Look at this shit again.
It's so similar.
I really like this film.
This french film.
Cuties.
Or so.
It's called Cuties in english.
I think it's only available in english or french.
But you could also use subtitles.
Maybe it's also available in german in the meantime.
It was a scandal film.
Because minor girls 12 or 13.
Or how old they were.
It doesn't matter.
They twerk and make music video hip-hop.
And do as if they were the biggest whores in the world.
And it's depicted in the film.
And especially the social structures are depicted.
How it is there.
When you live in a banlieue.
And how it is with this whole hip-hop culture.
Which is absolutely
Downright on this
Muslim tradition world.
From which most girls come.
And especially
This mother and so.
And these family structures, this hierarchy.
That the men can do what they want.
He gets himself a new wife.
That's all super interesting.
And the film was
That's why it was a scandal.
Because it's depicted
That the girls dance like in porn.
But first I have to say
The film is made in such a way
That it's not fetishizing.
It's not depicted as erotic.
But it's depicted
Like other little girls see it.
It's always seen
From the eyes.
From the eyes of viewers.
That are in the film.
For example little girls.
Or some erotic pedos
That sit in the audience and turn it with their smartphone.
That's
In my opinion
Not because of this taste.
But because it's a dangerous film.
Because it suggests something wrong.
I think it suggests the right thing.
And it generates this outrage.
Which had to be clear to everyone.
In my opinion for 20 years.
Since I was 14, 15.
And it will be given before.
It will be more and more because of casualization and scandalization.
The sexualization of the youth
Is a business model.
It was already there at TAF.
There was always
At least once a title to see.
Then the titles became younger and younger.
At some point they had
The final class.
Or summer girl 2010.
Or something like that.
Even before Germany's Next Topmodel.
The youngest of the youngest.
The youngest who can still be seen on TV.
Sexualized.
For the quota.
In mainstream.
And of course
It's available in small.
I saw it back then in school.
The young girls watch it.
And then they do it.
It's nothing special.
And of course they bow down to some wankers.
And force them to prostitution.
I already told you that.
Like in the other clip I made.
That's my example.
And as I said
A good time to get back to the film.
He puts it all so well.
And this stupid brother
In the end he comes back
Into this trap.
Into this therapy.
And they just sit there and
He gives himself to this system.
Because Robert Pattinson is in jail.
He doesn't come out anymore.
That's it.
And he gets there for the rest of his life
In this therapy.
And of course his brother
Had a better plan for him.
To live somewhere in freedom.
Not in this cruel capitalist life.
Where he is only gangled.
And where nothing can happen.
A wonderful film.
A 10 out of 10 for me.
I don't know if the list
That the movie gives me
Or if he sorts them
According to rating.
Or if I press F5.
But I can read what's written here.
It's all a snowball system.
Of course it's all a snowball system.
Well paid employee of Antifa GmbH.
Good evening.
Why are leftists so core disabled?
I think the USA
Will be split sooner or later.
What do you mean
With core disabled Dubai?
I have to say.
I have already noticed
That you tend to the right direction.
But to ask the question like that
Is useless.
The USA will be split sooner or later.
In my opinion the USA are already split.
For a very long time.
I wrote in the stream of Wetzelt
Trump is therefore
In my opinion not a good president
For the USA itself.
Just because he made the biggest
Hex cuts of all time.
He really has the record
For the upper 1%
To get more out and pay less taxes.
And everything else he does
Is of course only smoking.
That is not sustainable.
Because he keeps making the pyramids more pointed.
He makes sure that the redistribution
Is getting more and more intense.
And yes.
In my opinion they are already split.
That has now also been shown
In such unrest as back then
In Wetzelt Charlottesville
Where the guy just drove his car through the demo.
Or later of course
With all kinds of Black Lives Matters
Where there was an autonomous zone
Where no police could enter.
Because of course all Americans with their Gatling
Stand all over the place.
And then they made some stress.
There is already a lot going on
In this country.
I said, in my opinion
Can this only end
That the rich people
Pull back their communities
With a fortress wall around them.
And then it runs.
I smell political conditioning
Around childhood.
It definitely sits deep.
Political conditioning
I wouldn't say that.
I think
Of course it is being tried
But it doesn't sit with children.
Children are not political.
Politically
It is a kind of higher structure
Which at some point in time
Comes in as a pattern of thought.
Politics is for us
An extra pattern of thought.
You would do something politically
Which you don't do privately.
These are separated things.
Children are far too honest
And far too grounded.
They are
Very far
Elementary
What you see with children
Is that
After two years
They have a lot of
Stereotypes
In them.
The first one is man and woman.
That is very important to classification.
Their whole brain
Is designed to
In the first three or four years
To only do feature extraction and classification.
And that is where it gets clarified.
I don't know
I can at least see that
With my daughter.
But that depends on what kind of input comes in.
And you can see that
That these typical men and women
Roll.
The girls should rather
Sit in a corner and read a good book
And the boys should go out.
That is measured
At different kindergartens and schools.
That the staff likes it that way.
And that they don't want to force it.
For example the classic gender roles.
That girls are bad at math.
And boys are the genius engineers.
That is measured
In the kindergarten by themselves.
That is done subconsciously.
And of course many parents do it that way.
That is an indoctrination.
And the political
Has mostly something to do
With the social environment
Where you come from.
Of course in the long run
But especially at the beginning
Kindergarten, early childhood
That is not the case with politics.
I would agree
That later
With 14 to 18
That there is something
That goes in.
Whereby
With 14 to 18
You are mostly
If everything goes wrong
Relatively independent.
I would imagine
I thought about it myself.
I was disappointed
By the left for a long time.
And then I was out.
With 18 to 25
I was
Not interested
In politics at all.
But also
For left, right and so on.
Of course I was always a lefty.
But I felt alienated
By the left scene.
I had green dreadlocks
When I was a teenager.
I was a real disgusting punk.
But later
I politicized myself
By sitting too often in front of the computer.
That is essential.
That's how it came about.
And that's how it came about with my channel.
So
Something happens
In the sense of anyone.
And if it does not happen for profit
But for reasons
For the existence of humanity
As a pattern of thought
A pattern of thought is formed
So that the sexual intercourse decreases or so.
I would say
12 to 15-year puberty phase.
Yes, possible.
So it is definitely so
If I had to conclude from my observation
I also know
Many where I would say
Yes, that has to happen at some point
In this time
That the parents
Their ideology
The children
I would see that too.
But the most important thing
That happens much earlier.
I am convinced of that.
This thing with the ideology
You can then choose yourself at some point.
If you are 15
Then you are able to see the contradictions
Of the ideology of the parents.
That's what most people identify with puberty.
They just see the contradictions of the parents.
And they hold them in the face
And say
That's why I have always kept you.
They recognize that first
They have a mental crisis in puberty.
They realize that they have lived a lie for 10-14 years.
I thought my parents are gods.
And suddenly it doesn't work anymore.
You could also see that with puberty.
It's just a awakening.
That's where the brain
Has reached this stage of development.
To reflect on oneself
And to reflect on others
And to move into others
Where this stage is completely closed.
That's the first result.
What's going on with the world?
It's totally contradicting itself.
There are a thousand contradictions.
It's not clear at all.
That's probably called puberty.
And then it has something to do with farting and farting.
But that's another thing.
That's also coming.
I'm thinking right now
I have to pee.
I've already had too much beer before.
Before we continue with the next film
I'll turn on the music first.
I'm thinking about what to do.
Write in the chat
If you want something hard
Or if you want something relaxed.
And I'll think about it.
What's hard?
Yes, that you say that.
Death row.
I could have thought of that.
Okay, but because you want death row
You definitely want some black metal.
And I don't like that.
Hard, relaxed.
Difficult.
It works, of course.
But I'll do it first.
A little bit of death metal.
And then I'm going to pee
And then I'll be right there.
And then I'm going to pee and then I'll be right there.
We'll do it here.
There, that's good.
That's good.
Are you ready?
Does he think that the coal soup was bad?
While he spits them out?
or does it only look like a bandwagon?
Well, that's a stylistic tool that doesn't appeal to the common listener at all.
That's anti-casualization.
And when I was young, I listened to Korn and Rammstein.
The first Korn album and the first Rammstein album.
I listened to them in the first and second grade.
That was the shit back then. I thought that was crazy.
And then I was in a fan camp.
Maybe I've already told you the story.
In a fan camp there was a buddy of a teacher.
An awful metalhead. It's clear to me now that he was a metalhead.
He said, here boy, you can already hear the crazy music.
Come to my car. I have a great facility in the car.
No homo, no pedo.
And then he played me Morbid Angel or Cannibal Corpse or something like that.
And it was just exactly that.
What is the man doing there? Why does it sound so stupid? What is that? What is he supposed to do?
And then he said, if you listen to something like that now, you'll hear something like that later.
And I said, no, that doesn't make any sense at all. It's shit.
And it's actually like that. You have to develop a ear for it.
It's like for a good wine or for a whiskey or something.
You have to develop a taste for it.
You have to have a sense of sensibility.
And with that kind of music, I've had the craziest thing with black metal.
For ten years, after I've already heard super extreme music,
I've still dedicated myself to black metal for its rudeness.
And it's only been a few years since I've been able to hear black metal.
And yes, that's how it is for the...
So if you've never heard that before, then it's not for you.
You're thinking, what's the point of that?
First of all, it sounds super stupid. You're thinking, what kind of stupid thing is that?
But that's always the case with art.
And the most obviously stupid thing is, of course, hip-hop.
And that attracts everyone, of course, because it's very easy to understand.
That's full, no casualization.
Because that's all about how you become a pimp.
And the boys think that with 12, 13, 14, 15, of course, that's great.
Anyway, another topic.
So, hard, relaxed comes next.
And then comes relaxed electromove.
That's all I have.
Ah.
A Mindener?
No, he didn't come from Minden.
He came here directly from my city.
I sometimes see him on the Christmas market.
And I tell him that he shaped me.
As a little child.
Of course, he can't remember it, but I can't remember him.
I always tell him that.
Yes, of course.
So, let's move on to the list.
Let's move on to the list.
So, the next thing on my list is the film.
Which is also completely unknown.
Black 47.
I don't even know what it's called.
No, it's also called Black 47 in German.
And the film takes place in Ireland.
At the time when the British Empire was still big at the start.
And since then, the Iranians have had the worst hatred of Great Britain.
Because they were the colonial powers.
They were occupiers.
They just went through imperialism.
With the Iranians.
With the Gaelic people, who just wanted to wander around.
And the film begins.
There comes a soldier from the war again.
Who swore for the British.
He is a traitor for the Iranians.
And he just wants to go home to his family.
And he arrives and sees that the house is destroyed.
The family is no longer really there.
And he is then first of all taken into this paper logic.
Who are you? Why don't you have ID papers?
And so on and so forth.
Then he smashes them all away.
And so it really rots out.
And the scene that made capitalism critical for me.
Is the situation.
That there are the remains of his family.
I believe his sister.
His little sister has a child.
She lives with her husband.
In an abandoned house.
In the middle of nowhere.
In the middle of Pampa there is nothing.
Except such a tram and a stone house.
With a straw roof around it.
And it's cold as hell. It's winter.
The people die out there just because it's so cold.
His old original house.
So where she comes from, it's bombed away.
There is nothing left.
And they live in this house where nothing is.
Where nobody bothers.
And suddenly the British militia arrives.
And ensures justice and order.
Because they don't even own this property.
They don't own this property at all.
It's written on a piece of paper.
That it belongs to someone else.
And nobody bothers.
But they just bother.
Because they are the colonial power.
And they want to suppress them.
And with that the film starts.
That's the 14th or 15th minute.
Or maybe half an hour.
There is this scene.
And it's so absurd.
Because it shows exactly how it is with the property.
It's cold as hell.
And they get shot.
That means they die.
Because it's minus 10 degrees.
The man thinks it's shit.
And he gets shot by the soldiers.
Who only do their duty.
And in the film it's shown very well.
If you talk to some of the irons.
At best old irons.
They have the story in their pockets.
How it is with the British.
With the great power of Great Britain.
Why they are so powerful.
And how they have
in the smallest
already
built out their power structures.
And just suppressed people.
Just for fun.
The film is a bit dystopian.
The film seems to me
so dark and so disgusting.
And everything is hopeless.
And so really disgusting.
It reminds me of The Road.
Just because of the climate.
Because it's so shit and so dystopian.
It's just really shit.
And that's why
the film plays in the past.
But he sees
in front of my inner eye
he felt
as if it was a representation
for a future version.
As if it was a dystopian film.
As if we could go back
in such a situation.
That's how the film affects me.
I can't really describe it.
Because nobody would think
that this is a capitalism film.
But somehow for me
it's probably because of my selection bias.
Because I make so many
YouTube videos.
And I have this English channel
one year longer than the German one.
I'm more active with the Snow Wall system.
With all these ideas.
To criticize that.
I think that's the reason.
It's always like that.
When you have tunnel vision
you only have the nail
and the hammer.
That's about it.
The next film is The Big Short.
I don't need to talk about it.
It's clear.
The best part of the film is Brad Pitt.
Like with Killings and Softly.
He's a really cool guy.
But I don't need to talk about it.
The film is well known.
It's 2008, financial crisis,
perfectly explained.
In a really cool movie.
All around.
Hollywood.
Nice people are shown.
They tell you something.
The film tells
a nice story.
Around this whole situation.
And how criminal
the banks and the rating agencies are.
How criminal they are.
That's shown really well.
And of course it's fantastic.
Every single aspect,
every level of the Snow Wall system
is shown.
I just missed the context.
You're the one with the hot air balloon, right?
I don't get it.
Kvairz wrote a Minden-Thunder.
I thought he meant someone from Minden.
Then Felix Fuchs-Hase
felt like he was talking.
Because he's from Minden.
Now Kvairz says at least.
And then he says something about the hot air balloon.
That's too hard for me.
In Hip-Hop
there are underground styles.
Psycho-Core for example.
Where you think WTF.
The majority is categorization
up to 10. But another topic.
Sure, in Hip-Hop
actually
I never really thought about it.
But I always had the feeling that
Hip-Hop is about class struggle.
About how you can
as a little man
fight your life in the worst way
in the USA, where there is no solidarity.
And if you grow up in a block
somewhere in a new settlement
in the East it's nothing different.
You can do Hip-Hop about it.
Because the stories of the streets
happen there. The whole country.
You see it.
And you have something to tell.
And that's being transported in Hip-Hop.
It's being transported very well.
Because you don't need musical skills for it.
To make a beat is trivial.
Or you always find someone who can do it.
And the rest is alienation.
Then you can rap about it.
Of course you don't need the skills.
It's all art.
Because you have to do it with the rhyme.
And really cool boys can do it live.
You give them a theme about what they should rap about
and then they do it.
That's a lot of art. I don't want to deny that.
But mainstream rap is of course ridiculous.
In Germany it's even more ridiculous.
Because everything that happens in Germany
in mainstream is really the funniest.
It's always copied from the USA.
They just copy the trends from there.
And then they make it worse.
You see that everywhere.
With Joko and Klaas.
With the men's world.
It's just a copy of Me Too.
Things like that.
Even that. It's super ridiculous.
And you see it even crazier with the German influencers.
They just copy content directly.
And the one who puts it on the top
is of course Mani Boy.
Mani Boy is just a funny guy.
With all his nonsense.
100% is basically every video
of any other American influencer
who makes Hip-Hop.
100%. Just copied.
It's just funny.
What's the next movie?
The next movie.
The big crash margin call.
It's at least as awesome
as The Big Short.
But it's a bit more unknown.
First with Kevin Spacey.
It's great.
But mostly
from a different perspective.
The movie is also about
the 2008 financial crisis.
But from the perspective
of The Big Short
the decision-making levels
the banks, the politics
the rating agencies
the big companies
From this perspective
The Big Short is not represented.
It's a middle class.
With the big crash
at margin call
it's about the top level
of some kind of
I assume
some financial advisory company
or something like that.
Could be another
snowball system. Doesn't matter.
It's so awesome.
It's just like
a piece of paper.
The audience doesn't know
what's on the paper.
They panic.
They want to know what's on the paper.
But the audience doesn't know
what's on the paper.
The paper goes all the way
up in the snowball system.
At some point Kevin Spacey comes
by. Kevin Spacey is
one of the last
in this pyramid.
And that's super awesome.
Because on the paper
our system collabs.
Our mathematical models
have results.
And everyone sees the crash
and has to limit the damage.
And in the movie
it's shown pretty well.
The smallest wankers
die from their job.
They tank the damage.
In the end.
People like Kevin Spacey
The absolute
king is a famous actor.
I can't remember his name.
He plays a great role.
Because he's the absolute
top mafia mob.
Everyone has respect for him.
And the best scene
in the movie
is where
a small
middleman
explains how the business works.
That's so awesome.
I laughed my ass off.
I was so happy.
That was super serious.
In the cabrio he explains how the business works.
And in the end
the little wanker went to the toilet
and puked.
And that sucked.
Just because he explained
how messy capitalism really is.
And that he lived a lie when he
made the propaganda fairy
to be successful
and to be a great businessman.
That's super shown in the movie.
A great movie.
And much less known than The Big Short.
But totally wrong.
He has to be known.
Everyone should know him in the movie.
He's like The Big Short.
He tells about capitalism.
He talks about it.
You don't have to talk in metaphors.
It's not a hidden story
like in Good Time or Killing Them Softly
where you have to think about it.
It hits you right in the face.
How it is with the alienation.
And with the Wall Street.
That's super.
That's a really awesome movie.
And he has so many details.
So many details.
Like I said, it starts with the note.
And then all these dialogues.
And Kevin Spacey is also
and that's always the nice thing.
You want to think that they are all winners of the system.
But you can see very clearly that they are not.
They all have a terrible life.
Kevin Spacey is the main character.
And he is also
depicted a little bit
of his private life.
How toxic it all is.
He's separated from his wife.
The only flaw I have
with The Big Crash is that
the smart-spirited geek-nerd-2-type
is an engineer.
It's always depicted
as if the engineers
are the cool guys with the math
and the crazy knowledge.
But in reality it's more
IT-ers,
mathematicians or physicists
who do this shit.
Because they are the ones with the math skills.
You have to imagine that in a pyramid.
You have math, that's the shit.
That's the real shit.
But it's often too abstract.
Only if you're up for it before, you go after the math
in something else.
Otherwise people just stay there in the math
and prove that some 74-dimensional rings
create some crazy algebras
and structures
and that's why they form a group.
That's what they do.
But there are two kinds of math.
One is computer science,
so IT.
It's basically applied math.
Theoretical Informatics 1 and 2
are only about
formal
proofability and decision-making
and things like that.
And in the end Goedel's Inconvenience.
And the other thing is physics.
That's the description of what we see out here
with the language of mathematics.
Those are the two adults.
And everything below that,
biology,
geology,
economics,
I don't even want to start with that.
It doesn't count at all.
That's a bastard.
The priest once
accidentally
fucked a boy's ass, but a girl's
and she got pregnant.
That's the motto.
And other than that
chemistry, engineering,
engineers,
those are craftsmen,
those are people with a screwdriver in their hands.
The real nerds
are math, physics
and computer science.
But computer science is difficult
because you have a lot of computer scientists
who do something far from mathematics.
In the end they only become web designers
or admins in some
different structures and so on.
But real computer science,
the really crazy shit,
that's super sexy.
And I would go a little bit in that direction
with cryptography, for example.
That's what I'm working on right now.
But also a lot of other things.
Decisiveness problems, NP,
completeness, stuff like that,
Turing machine, everything that has to do with it.
That's mathematics.
That's completely clear.
That's just a concrete application
of the language.
Because predictability is
a question of mathematics.
But it is occupied by computer science
and there are
extra lectures about it and so on.
But in my opinion it all comes together.
If you are a real physicist,
you also include IT and math.
If you are a real mathematician, you also include math and computer science.
If you are a real mathematician, you also include math.
Physics mostly not because
it is an application
that most IT people are not interested in.
They want to understand how a quantum computer works.
But that's a different story.
I'm a little disappointed
because of the engineer.
But otherwise the movie is great.
Except for the engineer, the movie is absolutely great.
Where am I?
I'll read a little more.
Yes, enough awesome hip-hop.
Honestly, I've already heard
from Alligator that it should be nice.
I can't say anything about the others.
Yandilay, Semidilux, Dendemann.
It all sounds like nonsense to me.
Who do I like the most?
The one over there.
The one hanging on the wall over there.
Captain Peng.
He is great.
Captain Peng, can you
take a look at it?
There are a few things on YouTube.
Super awesome, of course very poetic.
Deep-seated philosophical texts.
Super packed.
Super packed, I think it's great.
I'm a fan, I've seen it live.
Captain Peng and the tetake from Delphi.
The woman was already pregnant.
We pulled ourselves in, that was great.
I like him for example.
I'm also really into Romano.
Just because of the middleman.
Because the guy represents this ambivalence.
He has so much because
he grew up in the 90s.
He ate it all up.
You can tell by the way he talks
that he has all these cultural influences.
And that's great.
I drove to Osnabrck
and saw him live and showed him
my metal cut and we did a high five.
That was great. I like him.
He's just nice.
And he does funny stuff.
He also does capitalism criticism.
If he wants to.
I'm sure there's good hip-hop.
Especially because
it's a grassroots thing.
From the streets.
With attitudes.
It's the struggle.
Against the hierarchy and the shit.
Against our expansion system.
You have to say how shitty it is.
I just remembered another movie.
I have to play it before I continue.
Or I'll forget it.
It's called
The one with Jennifer Lopez.
Don't be surprised.
It's great.
It's called Hustlers.
Hustlers.
I'll talk about it later.
Then we'll have it.
It's a great movie.
Hustlers.
Where do I have it?
Imagine.
Jennifer Lopez
is a stripper
in the USA.
She has to get around
and she has a kid.
She has to pay the rent.
Like all Americans.
It's always the complete alienation.
They only do the job because of the money.
She finds out
that you can get bigger money
when you do private parties
with the fat punks.
You only need
a few girls.
She knows enough girls
that you can get around.
The great thing is
we do private parties
with their wives.
They don't like their wives.
They are managers.
They all have a wife.
So they do this.
They do a party with their wives.
They give them drugs.
They steal their credit cards
and take the money.
They pull the money
out of the hierarchy
like Robin Hood.
That's the business model.
It works well.
In the movie
you can see certain aspects
of how it works.
With the strip-shops
and the logic of use.
If you are too bad
you have to piss yourself off.
You have to do casualization
and marketing.
It looks great.
Not with academic words.
Not like in a lecture.
Just like it looks
on the street.
That's awesome.
It's not academic.
It's easy for everyone
why the problems
are for this person
and why they act like that.
That's great.
Jennifer Lopez
does a great business out of it.
She modifies it
and expands it.
She gets more girls
who can take more orders.
Who expand more
and maybe to other cities.
That's great.
I haven't seen the movie
for a long time.
It's not that long
but I don't know how it ends.
The movie was
a great criticism of capitalism.
It's a perfect movie
because it shows
a certain aspect
of capitalism
that you can't kill.
It's about
the business aspects
of capitalism.
Jennifer Lopez has to calculate
and clear her business.
She has to stay clean
and have a clear mind.
I've seen
another movie
where a woman
is hosting
poker tournaments.
She's crazy.
What was the name of the movie?
If my wife
would watch it,
she would have
drunk too much alcohol
after the barbecue.
I think she's drunk already.
If she would watch it,
she would know the movie.
It's a movie
where a woman
is hosting
poker tournaments.
This nerd
also participates.
Who participates?
Kevin Costner.
I just need to go through
the movie list with Kevin Costner.
Kevin Costner.
I click on it.
Filmography.
Then I scroll down.
This has to happen.
The movie is called Molly's Game.
Great.
Molly's Game.
Not bad.
I'll put it in the list.
Great movie about capitalism.
It's like this.
Kevin Costner
has, I think,
three children.
And Kevin Costner is a great guy.
The woman is still awake.
I already took over the job.
I found out the movie.
But it's funny.
You can talk to the boys
if you write funny things.
He has three children.
They are all elite children.
He promotes and demands
endlessly.
He makes real professionals out of him.
Everything they do is to the max.
Only pro-gamer-wise.
High level, upper point, one percent.
If you bring performance,
you have to get the gold medal in the Olympics.
For example, at the ski jump.
Molly,
the main character,
she does ski jumping.
She pulls something in here
and gets something crazy everywhere.
A finish here and there.
Super cool.
The movie is so funny
because it shows
exactly this scaling
and the business model.
It's off-secret
because
luck in this scale
is forbidden in the USA
as soon as you take something from the pot.
As soon as you take a profit.
It's well represented.
She has a lawyer
and then there's a trial.
It's about honor
and now
it's about
patriarchy
and how women
in this world
can achieve more
if they want to.
They have to push through.
The fight, the struggle,
it's so well represented.
And she's a crazy troll.
She can do everything.
She's very intellectual
and she looks good
and she could achieve everything.
But she wants to do
these half-illegal business.
That's her thing.
She just wanted to get her daddy
out of it.
But the movie is great
and it's about capitalism.
Mully's Game
I can only recommend it.
It's not direct.
It's not like Margin Call
or The Big Shot where you say
capitalism is going to blow your face.
You look at it from the perspective
with the glasses
that I want to show you.
It's all a snowball system.
Look where the snowball system is.
Then you see the snowball systems everywhere.
It's no wonder.
The next movie
that I want to talk about
is the first movie
with Robert Pattinson
that I saw
where I thought,
maybe this guy has potential.
Cosmopolis
The movie itself is not great.
It's almost an art movie.
I don't want to say David Lynch
but it seems
like an art movie
because it has
absurd actions.
Robert Pattinson seems
to be an extremely rich guy
who drives around in a limousine.
And outside the limousine
the whole world collapses.
Probably after 2008
in a financial crash.
That's the setting.
That's what I think.
It's not really named.
He does his rounds
with his limousine,
goes to stores, has quests.
And in the end
it culminates
because he's hanging around
in a limousine.
I don't know if the woman will listen.
There's a guy
who was once released
by his father
and since then
his existence sucks
and he feels really bad.
And the whole movie
has this obvious touch.
Take a look at the elite
how disgusting they are on the road.
That's shown really well.
And Robert Pattinson
is the perfect actor for it
because he's a boy.
He's a slippery boy.
He's a Christian Bale
American Psycho-like
but without muckies.
A really slippery boy.
You look at him when he's wearing a suit
and you think, is he unsympathetic?
That's a rich,
shabby wessie footsie
who grew up with a golden spoon
and is a really disgusting wessie.
He got everything in shit
and doesn't need to do anything
and says, I earned it,
I got my status, I got it.
That's the movie.
That's the feeling you get
when you see this movie.
And when you see Robert Pattinson
when he shaved his ass.
That's my suggestion
because I like to think in these stereotypes.
And that's
definitely an interesting movie
because, as I said, that was the first movie
I think that was the movie after
this Twilight shit.
He already decided
to make serious movies that are kind of crazy.
And you have to expect that from him.
Sure, this shit with the vampires
he had to do
I mean, it's not bad.
You make a name, you earn money
that's mainstream.
But then the question is,
do you continue in the snowball system?
Or do you want to get even crazier
and make even more shit movies?
Or do you want to make interesting movies?
And I would expect that from him.
And as I said, all the movies
I've seen with him
made me think that he's a serious guy
who actually wants
real movie content.
I think that's great.
Cosmopolis.
And as I said,
you have to go
in the video description
and click on the link
so you can see the list,
the movie pilot list.
So, what does it say here?
Moneyboy is not satirical?
Yes, Moneyboy.
Like in the office.
When it started with the swag
and that's already a copy of another original.
There's a hip-hopper who thinks it's serious.
We also thought that it's a satire.
But he's also touring with it
and he's serious.
He goes on stage and he does it.
And there's the hip-hop crowd and they like it.
And he likes it too. He's a hip-hop person.
That's what I'm really talking about.
He also does interviews with hip-hop channels
and he lives this style.
He also wrote a bachelor or master's
about this topic with hip-hop
and how to market it.
I think that's an ambivalence.
He finds it interesting,
but he also focuses on the music.
I really think that
he's
in this respect
not a pure satire project
like Akan and Stefan, for example.
In case that tells you something.
I'm a kid from the 90s
so I know something like that.
Yes, Moneyboy. Of course he's from Switzerland.
No, Austria. I don't know.
Wait. Wien City.
He's from Wien City.
That's right. Hip-hop against the original class struggle.
The other two-packed songs are
disaster,
mainstream,
class struggle. There's still enough hip-hop.
I'm not an expert.
But apart from hip-hop,
Techno is a product made in Germany.
Yes, it can be.
I don't know them. I think they're super lame.
Mhmnner hren Techno.
I know enough people who aren't Mhmnner
who also listen to Techno.
In my opinion, this is the real musical
milestone of Germany
worldwide.
The real musical milestone
of Germany
worldwide.
First of all,
all the classical composers.
Sure, we don't need to talk about that.
Germany, super sick.
But then, Rammstein.
Lol.
Rammstein.
If someone is an exporter here,
then it's Rammstein.
And then, of course, there are
Scorpions.
Just from the scale of success,
Scorpions. And there are
a few other creators, for example.
In thrash metal, they're huge.
Or...
There are a few other really sick
German bands. Necrophagous
is, in my opinion, a purely German band.
But they're only in
tech desks, so to speak, legends.
But they have a legend status for that.
There are a lot of German bands
that are really sick. And techno.
I don't know much about that.
But I would have thought,
techno is identical all over the world.
And there is no
belonging to any artist
or so. I thought, you can't
distinguish that. That's such an
indistinguishable, analogue mass.
Whether you now take the techno song
that takes one and a half hours
from one, or party
on the other track
that takes one and a half hours or so.
I don't know. You'd have to tell me
which sick boys in techno
are really hard.
Kraftwerk or something. It could be.
But they're just...
They're actually pioneers.
I don't know if they're counted
as techno. I really don't know
much about that.
I, as an incoming engineer,
feel very offended by that.
Yes, well paid employee of
Antifa GmbH. I'm sorry.
But that's my
elitist pissbubble in which
I find myself. Because I just
have too much experience
with engineers. I'm
an incoming doctor engineer.
I'm myself. I'm also an engineer
on paper. And in my
last seven years I've only had to do
with engineers.
And that's my experience
that I have there.
Many of them can only blackbox.
What they can't do very much is
really apply mathematics.
Most of them can't even understand
what a Fourier transformation is.
They don't understand that. They have
mostly a symbolism. They can do that,
but they can't interpret it. And in my
exercises I see the inflation rate
really brutal. I do exercises for
engineers. Medical technology.
That's essentially electrical engineering.
And for a while I've only had the
electrical engineer and medical engineer.
They come from a school and
two weeks before the school starts
they do math preparation.
But that's essentially
what the Abitur doesn't do anymore.
But what you need to get to the university.
And there you can see how brutal
that is.
And it continues.
It doesn't get any better.
Then master students come out
who are sitting in an exam
with me. Electrical engineering.
They don't write down the Roman law.
That's super ridiculous. But classical
is just Fourier analysis.
Normal...
I don't know. Normal
functional theory I don't want to say.
But algebra, so to speak.
The nearest algebra.
I only see deficits everywhere.
And that's
for some reason
the problem is huge for engineers.
And for physicists
And the mathematicians
I had to deal with until now,
didn't.
But that's a very personal
view of me.
Of course that can be different
on the big scale.
But that's what I see.
That the engineer
is more of a low-level
flat wanker.
And of course it can be that you're a
crazy boy and a crazy dude and just want to use it
and that's why you're an engineer.
But that's not a thing.
Nothing wrong with it.
I only say what I see
that I don't like about the nerds.
But I think that's just alienation
and inflation. They can't do anything for the people.
So.
Geology.
No. Philosophers are so sexy
that the will to profit against them
stinks like rotten eggs.
Yes, definitely. Philosophy is really nice.
But...
It's just...
You can't earn your bread
with philosophy.
Unless you're a really awesome...
David Garrett I almost said
Richard David Precht or something like that.
Who sells books and always
holds himself in a camera because he's such a cool boy
and has a bunch of groups and can do marketing.
People like that can live well with it.
So a few freaks who live in the media
can live well with their philosophy
or a few thinkers who
really
stick out with their thoughts.
Otherwise you can do almost nothing with philosophy.
Those are the ones who arrived at the top
in the hierarchy. They can't grow higher
in their local snowball system
as a philosopher. You could
at most become a Habeck-type.
He's also a philosopher. Then you'll become a chancellor.
Or...
You just go around in some local
universities and you're lucky and get a job.
But it's clear that it doesn't work with
everyone because there are way too many
graduates and way too few
applications for people like that.
You just have to do something else.
Of course you can say, I'm a writer
and a web designer and a philosopher
academically. You've got a paper on it
and I've studied something and I'm doing something completely different.
That works. I'm also a physicist and I could
apply for everything. I could
become a consultant
or I could do something.
I could become a software representative.
I could write offers
or sell something
or something like that. You could do
everything. But as a
philosopher
it's difficult to do something like that.
Hatred on money-elite
phyre KIZ
I eat rich.
A Christmas story
and the chocolate factory.
Is a Christmas story
some kind of family story
with these weird shit amis?
Could be.
Corona, however,
holds the record of the most
devoured brain areas.
I don't know. I would say
alcohol is quite good.
And of course the normal
Infotainment mainstream.
But it also destroys a lot of brain areas.
Especially with the children
that are growing up now.
If you grow up with two years
with a screen in front of your face
then you are too much
in your head with ten.
Nothing can develop cognitively.
Techno comes from Germany.
Sven Wett.
The engineer
is not so difficult.
Okay, I'll write that down for later.
Then I have it somewhere else.
You never know.
Marosha Blmchen
Okay, yes, I remember.
Blmchen was hardcore techno, right?
It was really upda upda.
Like a boom boom boom boom boom
boom boom boom boom boom boom boom boom boom boom boom boom boom
Yes, that's right. That was funny.
But rather Gawa. Yes, definitely
I am fully involved. If already, then already.
What comes to my mind
is Rotterdamer Terror Corpse.
Does anyone know that?
That was really hardcore in my opinion.
But that has to be like that
in the direction, right?
The university generation
Student course.
Which generation do you mean?
This university generation.
Well, he obviously means those who are currently studying.
Right now, at this moment.
So all those who were
matriculated at the latest
five years ago
or are currently matriculated.
Function theory for every analysis
I'm doing right now and I find it mega exciting.
I also want to apply
and wanted to be an inventor since my childhood.
Yes, that's definitely a cool setting.
Then I wish you
that you find a good professor
with whom you can write
real final work.
I have the impression that this is a huge problem.
Due to this massive alienation, people
no longer want to go out on serious topics
and struggle with teaching.
But if you find something cool there
maybe in a company with an application
that is often possible with engineers
that you go to a company for which you work
they benefit from it.
You write a work about it. The professor is happy.
It has something to do with applications.
It is something unique. It is a real project
because it is unique and can not be repeated.
If you have fun with it, it is great.
The gain of knowledge is maximum
because you can apply your mathematical knowledge.
Morph. What does it look like
with group talking?
That is brown and knocks against
what is brown and knocks against the glass?
I do not know.
When I shit on your mother's face
she then knocks against my glass
and asks herself
why did you do that?
Techno is not mine at all.
I do not know anything about it.
This is a rich man with the three ghosts.
This is Ebenezer Scrooge.
Ebenezer Scrooge.
Then I arrived down here.
Then we can continue in the list.
Next film.
I just saw it. It is called Eye for Eye.
Christian Bale main role
and a lot of other great actors.
The film is full of great actors
such as Woody Harrelson
aka natural born killers
or
Forest Whitaker
and super cool film.
The film is so cool
because he
tells the story
a bit like Good Times
on this lower income layer.
Christian Bale is a worker
in a steel factory.
His father is just dying
because of the impacts
that he has had on the dams
during his life in the steel factory.
This is the context.
He has to work
to get over the rounds.
The metal factory
that he works in is going to be closed.
It is like a robot.
There was prosperity
but it is gone now.
Everywhere everything is dirty.
Everything is shit and dirty.
I also stand on it.
I stand on it when everything is dirty.
When I was in Istanbul
it was great.
I stood on it because everything was dirty.
I walked around with my wife in Peking.
Everything was dirty.
I stand on the big cities that are dirty.
When it is dirty and shit
you feel that there are still people
who have a struggle
and know how shitty life is.
I feel much better
when you sit in a bar
and eat the rotten fries
and see how people live there.
I think that is much more authentic
and you still feel life.
It is not like in Singapore
or Dubai where everything is clean
and clean.
We are in the upper 10%
of the pyramid.
Everything is fine here.
You notice this difference
when you are somewhere.
This difference is clear
in this movie.
Everything is dirty.
Christian Bale is a nice boy.
He is being sold.
He is being portrayed as a nice protagonist.
He is an honorable man.
He doesn't let himself be blamed.
He works honestly for his money.
He has this attitude.
He goes hunting.
But he doesn't kill the deer
because he doesn't like it.
He did that with the rifle.
But then he thinks he doesn't need to shoot.
He doesn't care.
You notice that Christian Bale
is a nice character.
He is being portrayed.
You have to think about
what kind of a dude he is.
He is not an aggro guy.
But he knows how to defend himself
against the fun he has.
Everything is great.
Then something happens.
He drives
along a street
and there is a bad exit.
Someone hits a car.
He kills a child
or a mother, I don't know.
He kills two people.
That's why he goes to jail.
Then his life breaks.
In the USA it is always on fire.
If you can't work for a month
everything goes bad.
No money, your wife disappears.
He goes to jail.
His wife disappears.
His father dies by accident.
His brother
goes on the wrong track.
His brother has a similar problem.
He is poor, but he doesn't want to work in the steelworks.
What does he do?
He goes to the army.
That's the American dream.
Sell your life.
He goes to the army.
He is four times in Iraq.
He is traumatized.
He has post-traumatic stress disorder.
He is really bad.
The only thing he can do
when he comes back
is to call himself a prostitute.
But you don't call it that.
You call it that.
You do cage fights.
You fight with other boys.
Then you go to sports.
There are fighters who beat you to death.
It doesn't matter.
Illegal fights.
Same thing as prostitution
on the male-male level.
The nice thing about the movie
is that it is there again.
It is presented as it is.
Everyone in this movie
no matter if they are
at the top of the hierarchy
they all have an unhappy life.
They all lead an unhappy life.
None of them can claim
that he is good at it.
Even Woody Harrelson
who is the craziest boy
of all these motherfuckers
who leads the freest life of all.
Even he is permanently
dissatisfied and pisses.
He has to take drugs all the time
because everything around him
is disgusting and disgusting.
And he himself is disgusting and disgusting.
And that's just great.
The movie is there again.
That's a movie where I say
yes, wonderful.
He puts his finger right in the wound.
How shitty the world is
especially over there in the American dream.
I don't even know where it is.
I think it's said Michigan or something.
There must be exactly the situation
when the baby boomers were there
and you could work hard for your
life and so on.
And now all the factories are closing
and he also says in between
because it's cheaper in China to buy steel
than to produce it here.
And what always strikes me
when I see a movie like this
that is now on the topic
is this debate
that is currently being led here
with the windmills because
they pollute our landscape.
That's super ridiculous.
Fuck the landscape.
There's a windmill.
Do you have a problem that you can't
draw a picture because it doesn't
look like it was 100 years ago?
Our world is changing
and we as humans are changing our world.
That's nothing new.
And to put windmills there
is a weakness because of aesthetics.
I never understood that.
But the normal industrialization
makes it out of itself anyway.
In the middle of nature, there's a
super cool valley, there are mountains,
everything could be super nice, but everywhere
are some rails laid, some
cobblestones, everything is super
dirty, everything is some kind of fleece bands,
everything looks shit, there's some metal
scrap lying around everywhere, some shitty
cars that are no longer driven and so on.
And that is the normal degree
of pollution that capitalism
favors with our environment and our
nature. So talking about aesthetics
doesn't take place anyway and
that's a good point.
And of course,
it's a revenge movie and I'm
totally against revenge movies because
it takes away my lowest instincts.
Just because, of course,
Christian Bale's brother
is being killed
by Woody Harrelson because he's a
stupid mafia wanker who says
you owe me and I'll kill you all.
And Woody Harrelson is generally
a crazy dude who kills everyone
he doesn't want to kill anymore.
Well, and Christian Bale
is a calm guy all the time
but he has
enough of it and
now he has to go through it
and he just makes him cold.
And that's a nice
story. It's just a nice
story about the
situation that you actually ask yourself
what kind of choice do people have
who are still living there?
In what kind of world were they born
there? And that's the first world.
There you should actually say
okay, there should actually be a
solidarity community that makes sure
that people can become something else
apart from steel workers and drug dealers.
But that's being shown there
because the other option, the alternative
is to become a policeman and the drug
dealers and other spas just chase them.
What is not shown
is, so to speak, you could go to a
university or something, but that just doesn't exist because
it's somewhere in the province. And of course
everyone has this rotten idea
of homeland love and patriotism
and work honestly
for your money and all this
work fetish that is being
poured into these Americans.
All these contradictions
are well represented in the film.
Even if the film doesn't directly
address it. And that's why
I would say it's a good film about capitalism.
Hmm...
Yes, his beard already has a beard.
You're talking about some insiders, aren't you?
I can't start anything with them.
I'm still in elementary school,
so I still have a little bit
ahead of me, but I
will remember your words
and will look after a
good professional or a good
business. Yes, that
definitely has to be the case.
For the engineers, this is very important.
I would even say that
this is the most important thing.
That's where you make the most experience.
Because
especially in engineering studies
I've always had the impression that
the teaching...
Okay,
that can also be different from
university to university.
It's probably better if you're at
Humboldt University or Erlangen than
if you're at a provincial university.
But still, especially because the
engineering studies are
related to their practice,
this is of course important.
And
among us, you learn the most.
That's the only
time that you're really
self-reliant and have to solve problems.
At least that would be the best.
That's the ideal case. You get a problem
that is so moderated that you can
create it yourself and then
solve it with mathematics.
For example,
I had a friend who was
in the university for a long time and
then studied electrical engineering.
He's in the same situation now.
He's just doing that now
at companies.
And he's really getting into it.
I have the impression that
it's definitely much better than
studying 08.15 and then
writing a good bachelor's degree.
Because I've seen that too.
I see a lot of engineers
who are of course completely alienated.
And I can't tell anyone that they're doing a good job afterwards.
They will only do a good job somewhere later.
You know, they will do this experience
at most, if they're lucky,
after graduation. But you should actually
do that in your studies. You should experience it in your studies
alone to know
if that's actually something for you.
That's a kind of fireball.
And that's what belongs in an education.
So that afterwards someone comes out
who can really
go into a room
and say, hey,
I'm the crazy boy.
I can solve these problems.
You're the management guys.
You're the guy with the PR.
You're the one who's the operator
and calculates the numbers.
But I'm doing the content here.
I'm taking care of the content.
That's what the engineer should be able to do.
And I have the impression that
there are far too few people
who can still do that
after graduation.
But that's the way it is. And now in my
support I see that quite often.
I have about 50-50 students,
50% students and 50% people
who are at the university.
And what can I say?
They're almost all engineers, of course.
I don't do math
because I can't do that
with the proofs and the words
and the vocabulary, because I'm not a mathematician myself.
Only very rarely can I help with that.
But otherwise
they're almost all engineers.
I also have some financial problems,
but I don't want to talk about them to the engineers.
Where did we end up?
Next movie.
The Drop Bargeld.
That's what it's called in German.
And I also saw the movie last time.
First of all, it's with Tom Hardy.
That's great.
He's with the guy from
Sopranos.
I think that's the same guy.
The movie is also
almost a
horror thriller, but
very different.
Tom Hardy
is the main character
and he lives in a city
and he works as a waiter.
He does a very
simple job.
And he doesn't want to have anything to do
with the mafia,
which is everywhere.
And you notice all the time
that he is
someone who
doesn't want to have anything to do with them,
but doesn't have a problem
with it
if he gets pissed,
that he could
somehow finish the people.
But he doesn't do it.
He leaves it all behind.
He doesn't try to have any interaction
with this parallel world,
he just wants to earn money
and live, and he doesn't know
what he wants to do.
You have this feeling that he's up to something,
but it's not said if he's up to something
or if he doesn't know what he wants to do,
but you are thrown into this setting.
And then one day
a dog in a trash can
which wasn't meant for him
turns out to be
a complicated method
of making a psycho into a troller.
But he gets involved
in the story of a psycho
who wants to become a troller
and he falls in love with the troller
or the troller falls in love with him
and then there is an interaction
and the guy is a psycho
and a criminal and he
threatens everyone with death.
And it's like this,
the guy who owns the bar
in which he works,
he has weird things going on
and the bar is always used
as a drop.
That means the mafia boys
somehow store money
between them in the evening
and then get it a few hours later.
So that some of the suppliers
drop the money they made
through their drug sales
and then someone else comes
and takes it away.
That's the model.
I don't know if he gets some profit
or if it's just money.
Anyway, this film lives in this world
and it's a side-effect
an interesting side-effect
because it changes things a little bit.
The guy tries
to trick the mafia
and you know it's a bad idea
and they really kick you out.
The boy gets really pissed
and it's a little bit Romanian
and it's also represented a little bit
and a little bit of everyday racism
is also put in there, that's all funny.
My cat is barking, I'll get her in.
The nice thing about this film is
Tom Hardy is,
we all know him,
he's the coolest Pumperboy
who could destroy everyone in the world
if he wanted to.
And you think all the time,
but that's Tom Hardy, why doesn't he destroy him?
But he doesn't.
He's a very chill, very chill boy.
At the end of the film
there's a conflict
over a
masculine
boy-legend story
that represents
a big lie
and he knows it all the time
but he plays along
because he really doesn't want
to have anything to do with it.
And the story comes out
that if he has to
and is forced to,
he pulls it through and makes people cold.
But you're not playing with the shit
that's lying on the floor, are you?
The cat gets annoyed,
comes in
and then gets annoyed on the floor.
I like that.
Anyway, Tom Hardy
turns out to be a really cool motherfucker
at the end of the film,
makes him cold, takes the princess with him
and happy end.
That's basically the story.
And the cool thing is,
all the time there's a bully
that he knows from church
and he also has a funny role
but he can't do anything.
He can only look at these mafia structures
and somehow
don't really intervene
because it's clear, the bullies are powerless.
And in the end, the bully
also gives him the props
because you're a really cool boy.
And Tom Hardy of course doesn't say anything about it.
And it's just
all these structures
and also how the business runs
because mafia is of course also just a business.
It shows how these two parallel worlds work
and that's often the case
in these gangster films.
That you have these parallel worlds
where you have this bully world
that somehow does the legal way
and there are also business models
included and there's corruption too.
And then there's the complete
illegality where
mafia structures work exactly
according to the same scheme.
The snowball system is always the same,
you always have the same hierarchies,
they're just called differently,
and then it's corrupt and
there's something going on and so on.
It's always like that.
It's always done like that.
And that's why I think this film
is so cool and that's why it talks about
capitalism because
with the existence
of these people
it shows them,
it shows how they live there
under what conditions they live there
and also
people like
Tom Hardy
can develop their own morals
or a codex
according to which they can live.
Life has made them tough, but they still have
a moral codex. And many don't have that.
You have to imagine
Tom Hardy is absolutely
unique in how he's
portrayed because a normal person
wouldn't behave like that. A normal person
would have given up much earlier and would have been
crushed. Tom Hardy is
portrayed as someone who has
a very high resilience,
a very high character strength
compared to this external
influence and
influence, so to speak, that
influence him.
And that shows how difficult it is,
how difficult it is to grow up there and to act like that
and to become an upright citizen or
to do something great.
What's going on with the cat? It's completely
rusting out here, isn't it? It can't be crazy.
What's going on?
Emmy?
Where are you?
Do you want to get out?
Yes, Departed is also a movie, of course.
By the way, Departed is
a remake. You should all know that.
The original
movie is called Internal Fias
and has more than one part.
And we all
got into it really well.
And Departed is really
copied one by one. It's a real,
real remake for the American market.
Because of casualization.
The people in the mainstream can't take
these Asian faces off. They can't.
Asian movies can't watch them,
can they? They have a different
gestic, they have a different habitus.
You can't sell that to people.
And that's what Bo Jin Ho did
really well with Snowpiercer, that he
bought some Americans for it. Because
otherwise he could never have such a success
with the movie. With Snowpiercer.
Because of this wickedness.
People can't do that.
I mean, people can't watch
German or French or Spanish
productions in peace. They get
a scratch somehow. And for the American market
it's not even there. They have to
remake everything again.
And Departed is one of these remakes
where everyone says, this is such a cool movie.
But fuck you, dude. It's just a Korean movie.
I think it's Korean.
Infernal Envy, definitely.
And as I said, not even that bad.
Not even that bad.
You know.
And where we're already at, Asian movies.
I Saw the Devil. Super movie.
Then of course
Oldboy. Of course it also has an American
remake by now.
Oldboy. Super strong movie.
And what did we see last time?
A really cool movie. I think
The Audition.
Or
Gestndnisse. I still find that out.
I still find that out.
I quickly check
the movie pilots.
I quickly find that out.
I just have to look at the first page.
They are all very well rated by me.
So, and
So, what did I have already?
I Saw the Devil
I Saw the Devil already.
Then
Oldboy, I already said that.
Infernal Enviers
Infernal Enviers has a 9.5
Departed also has a 9.5
I see that Departed is
USA and Hong Kong.
That means the Chinese
added Hitler.
They added some money to it.
Adaption? No, that's not it.
What does the movie
Confessions
Confessions mean?
So
Confessions
Oh no
What is it?
I think it's called Audition.
The movie was
really nice.
This is an Asian movie from Japan.
I really liked it.
Is that the one
where the
movie
nice but it's not the one
I mean
Woman, tell me if you are still
online. What was the name
of the movie where the teacher
claims she infected everyone with AIDS?
What was the name?
I thought it was called Confession.
I have to search again.
I think it was from Japan.
No, that's not what it's called. I can't remember.
I can't see it in my history.
The problem is, it's not compatible.
Sometimes I didn't rate the movies.
And then they're just gone.
Then they disappeared in the Nirvana of Bits and Bytes.
The movies.
What was it called? It can't be.
It was a Japanese movie.
I'm just going to google it now.
Japanese movie.
Woman puts on AIDS.
And then somehow confessions.
Right.
Japanese. The movie is called German title. Confessions from 2010.
And then I just searched for it. Confessions or what?
It can't be or what?
So.
It comes right into the list.
Confessions.
No, no, it's not called Confessions. It's called...
Fuck.
It's called Confessions. Original title. Koku Haku.
This movie is really awesome.
I liked it. I gave it a new one. I just didn't find it.
Confessions.
No, it doesn't belong in the list.
Because it's not a film about capitalism.
I just wanted to show Asian movies.
This movie is awesome. You can give it a try.
So.
And now...
Where did we stop? White Drop.
Okay, I told you Tom Hardy.
Next movie. Sorry to Bother You. I already told you about it.
It's basically...
Yeah.
You have to watch it.
It's a must-see like The Big Short and The Big Crash.
It's a little bit funnier.
But it has a lot more parts of the snowball system and capitalism than the others.
It starts with Call Center and ends with the absolute creation of life.
I think I talked about it in my video about mass animal husbandry and the exploitation of life through capitalism.
I think that's what I'm talking about because it's exactly in this direction. Human capital and so on.
So what else do I have here? The shaft.
Well, I made an English video about the shaft.
For me, the nice thing about the shaft is that this thing with the Monte Carlo simulation
and the markets or, let's say, with the solution, with the spontaneous solidarity, is well represented.
You could still discuss whether it's about capitalism or socialism.
But that doesn't matter. It's about hierarchies.
And of course I would like to say that it's essentially about capitalism.
The film is critical of capitalism.
But you don't have to...
It's basically about hierarchy criticism and how a society is built up in a world
in which you can only imagine that there must be hierarchies.
And whether you call it capitalism or socialism doesn't matter.
I think that's well represented in the film.
And of course it has a lot of funny aspects.
I made a long English video about it, about 20 minutes or so.
If you can stand my English, you can give it to me because it's really disgusting.
But I don't want to talk about it anymore.
It's completely clear that this is a film that belongs in such a list.
The next film.
Rampage 2.
Capital punishment.
I think all Rampage parts are great.
They are by Uwe Boll and they are fantastic.
The films are really just wonderful.
I totally agree.
And Rampage 2 is just super awesome because it's really about capitalism
and how he wants to really destroy the establishment.
And it's just awesome.
And I think Uwe Boll also plays himself.
Or he plays some other film maker.
And it's just ...
Ah yes.
So of course you can guess Uwe Boll and hate him as you want.
But I think this film is really awesome.
I'm just on it.
The next film.
Good bless America.
Super awesome film.
It's not directly about capitalism or something.
But it's about ...
... about media and about this fucked up American culture
that at the end, after a hundred years, comes out of the people.
A lot is being said about it.
There is also this fetish that everyone always has to become younger.
And that actually all are pedophiles because of their sexual ideals.
Everyone wants to fuck a 14-year-old and so on.
Everything is shown super well.
That this whole cult and this whole beauty ideal is based on it.
And ...
I think in the end, they are in a talk show or in some evening show
and ...
... they bang their heads a little bit.
That reminds a little bit of the end of Joker.
But the film is also made a little funny at the beginning.
But it's just ... it's just wonderful.
It's for people who are latent,
what they have against this capitalist use of logic
and this stupid culture of stupidity.
It's wonderful.
So everyone who likes idiocacy
has to see God Bless America.
These films are not the same,
but I have the impression that they belong together.
So God Bless America.
Super cool film. I can only recommend it.
The next film on the list is known.
The Wolf of Wall Street.
I don't need to say anything about it.
It's a great film.
It's just fantastic.
Especially the end.
The end is really premium.
The whole film is premium.
Don't get me wrong.
The film is super cool.
But the end.
How he holds these workshops, these lectures
with the pen.
How do I sell the pen to people and so on.
And the camera perspective.
How the audience is filmed, so to speak.
And how everyone actually goes down on these guys
with the success and so on.
That's great.
The film has several layers of interpretation
and they are all fantastic.
Super cool film.
I don't need to say anything more.
Next film.
Falling Down.
A normal day.
Now you ask yourself, what does it have to do with capitalism?
The film is only about capitalism.
Michael Douglas comes to a few stations of his life
in the film.
And again and again he asks questions.
Why is it like this?
Why is it so shitty here?
Why don't you do it like this?
And the answer is always capitalism.
But he doesn't see it.
Because for a while he himself in this cold war
in this ideology that the Americans are the best.
And that he is a patriot.
And that he would do everything for his country and so on.
I think he also worked at the CIA as an engineer
or something like that.
And he sacrificed himself for his country.
But no one gives a fuck about it.
And in the end it's all a big joke.
And of course he also has a huge psychosis.
He beats his wife and everything is shit.
And he is not understood.
He doesn't feel valued.
And there is this super cool scene
also with the Nazi in this store.
Where he says to the Nazi
we are not friends and you are not an American.
You are just an asshole.
And that is a wonderful scene.
Because he doesn't see himself that way.
He doesn't see that he also behaves racistically.
Or even better, that capitalism
strengthens these racist tendencies.
Whereas he himself is not racist.
He also tells this Asian in the store
that he is just a fucking faggot
and that the coke is so expensive.
And so he completely rages.
And I don't even know how it was.
But of course he throws some racist words at his head.
But he just does that because
he doesn't want to be in his culture
because he is a racist.
And the other guy is a real racist.
And he also has something against whores.
And he sits in his leather shop
with the military stuff and the tank fist and so on.
And all this nonsense.
And then he clearly limits himself.
And says, no, wait a minute, that's me.
But I'm not. I'm a real American
and we are really crazy here.
We are the Americans, we don't need that.
This whole film actually shows everyone
all these contradictions of capitalism
and above all this western culture
which was highly stylized there.
Especially at the time, the film is already 20, 30 years old.
It is shown super cool.
And above all it is shown
why the conservatives and the AFD
why they are so to speak strong.
Because people like Michael Douglas
they don't see the problem.
They only see symptoms.
And Michael Douglas is not able
to do a system analysis.
He goes over this golf course,
he completely rubs off
that these damn yuppie wankers
No, they are not yuppies.
No, they are some old rich sacks.
It doesn't matter. He rubs off completely
that this is not a public park.
You think, what is this supposed to be?
Why is there a fence around here?
What kind of wankers are you?
This fence should be accessible to the public,
this park should be accessible.
And you are pissing yourselves off with your golf.
This can't be true. Shit.
And he just doesn't see that capitalism is the problem.
Oh, and by the way,
now I remember another movie,
which definitely has to be on the list.
I, Daniel Blake, also has to be on the list.
It's also an awful movie,
we'll talk about that in a moment.
Yes, and Michael Douglas.
It's just great.
First of all, of course, great actor.
And he fits in really well.
And then the end with his daughter and so on.
The bully.
The bully who is always behind him.
He is one day before the pension.
He could just lie back and say
fuck it, but no.
He is an honest man.
And his wife at home
only makes him stress and he doesn't want to go home at all.
That's why he would rather work.
But he only has colleagues who piss him off
and who don't follow him.
He is the only one who takes his job seriously.
And he is a really nice boy.
Who just wants the best for everyone.
And he gets really pissed off by the system.
You notice that too.
And that's so funny, because
both protagonists, this old cracker,
the bully and Michael Douglas,
the old cracker
could also have a bad day
and completely freak out.
And he is really just being fucked up
on his job and he is also doing great shit.
But he has the resilience
and this goodwill.
And Michael Douglas doesn't have that anymore.
This is the dualism
of these two people.
How they meet at the end and talk about
things they can't do.
And then of course he beats him up.
I think he beats him up at the end.
And then the movie is over.
And it's all super tragic.
The movie is lovely.
And in my opinion it's all about
capitalism in the movie.
So...
What are the boys writing here?
The question is, how do I recognize
a good prof, what is a good topic
for the final work. Yes, that is difficult of course.
So you should first
go after whether the topic
sounds interesting to you.
Intuitively. Whether you think that is an interesting topic.
That is the most important thing.
If you, after the pitch meeting,
after the first three minutes,
think that is an interesting topic.
Or that is an important topic
for the industry,
for the society.
Or just an academically interesting topic.
One that challenges you mentally.
Where you think, oh that is a cool problem.
And I can already imagine how to solve that.
I am interested in
solving that. Because usually
it becomes much more difficult in detail
and then turns out to be completely different.
But that doesn't matter. You then have this motivation
to fight through it.
That is always the case.
That would be a good occasion.
That you say, that is a cool topic.
I don't know how it works at your university,
but typically it was like that.
You go to a prof and say, what topics do you have?
Then he has a catalog of topics there.
And then you look at them.
Or you have a friend
or you know an engineering company
that would do something like that.
And then you can go to the prof and say,
I have someone here who would do that with me.
And then you can build a connection in that direction as well.
That is actually all relatively chill at the university.
If you find something like that.
The worst are the 0815 topics.
Like, measure here
and write a protocol about it.
And that is your job.
That is a well-earned note.
And that is how they lure people.
Well-earned notes. But you learn almost nothing.
That is alien.
Nobody cares about your results.
And sometimes
it is like that
that these quests are
a real dead-end in my opinion.
That does not lead to anything.
You miss something
and then nobody cares
and then it is just shit.
Much better is that you have a concrete problem
and you have to solve it.
Let's say you have a machine
that has an output
and you have another machine
and they have to be connected
and you have to automate something.
You have to optimize a process
or you have to understand
that the interface works
and that the machines can communicate with each other.
Something like that.
A typical engineer's topic.
That is actually cool.
And you learn a lot.
You learn something for practice.
Bus systems,
you have other protocols.
In general, you learn something about IT.
That comes next.
That is an engineer
who is the most general
of those people who are in practice
can think outside of the box.
I do not want to force you to become a programmer
but I want to make it clear
that if you have something like that
where machines have protocols
where you have to think about
how that works
how signals are processed
then you have to think about
how the world works.
That is much better and that brings a lot more.
What is written on your paper
that is completely irrelevant
because the heart attack is so strong
that everyone already knows that.
The companies of today see that everywhere.
If you can say in a meeting
I have clarified this and that
because I am crazy and I put it on me
and besides, lol
then it brings a lot more
because you then go in with your
inflated young man's breast
and say I'm the crazy boy.
That is the elegance that you have to have.
As a physicist, for example, I always have it.
That is the Jedi sword
that I got with my diploma
that I imagine myself
I am so crazy.
With such an elegance
if you go somewhere like that
and say you are the crazy boy
of course people can also think
what kind of a fucking asshole is that
but of course you have to pack it like that
that you are just self-confident.
That is the most important thing.
That's how it is with the wedding show too.
If you make it clear to the woman
that you are a crazy boy
and that you are just self-confident
you get the ices.
You have to shine it out.
And that only works if you really understand
and stand behind it.
If you stand on a piece of paper
that you are a great engineer
but you know that what you did there is not worth anything
then it is difficult
to act authentically.
At least that's my impression.
That people can't do that.
The worst are the guys who think they are the best
but they can't do anything.
Because those are the guys
you ask yourself a question.
I already had conversations with such people.
You ask yourself a very simple question.
What does the Fourier transformation
of Cosinus look like?
And then they can't do that.
And I can only laugh at them
how ridiculous that is.
People like that can go to hell.
I stopped doing Mechatronics
and then I worked as a car mechanic.
Yes, of course.
Why not?
It could be.
It always depends on the personality.
For some it would be better to do it later.
For some it is good
if they do a few years of training.
First training, then studies
or going to the club or whatever.
That would be a classic thing
like what my buddy did.
He was in the club for 6, 7 or 8 years.
But he didn't want to go to the juice shop anymore.
And then he got out
of the good job he had.
He was safe.
He went out and decided for a happy student life
with little money.
Just because he found it so disgusting.
And now he is still in his job
and has to do a lot more.
He decided to do it
just because he found it better.
Because it is something that
makes him feel closer to himself.
Less alienation.
But looking back
you could
start studying again.
You just have to find
a way to do it in parallel
with the university.
Or to take an education credit
and do it again.
I don't know how it is with BAfG.
If you are 25 now, you will still get BAfG.
I think BAfG goes up to 30.
Or does it go up to 25?
I don't know.
You have to work on it.
Why not study now?
Unfortunately, Titanic
scared me so much. Blood diamond was the first film
that I wanted to watch.
But that is funny because
Leonardo DiCaprio
except for Titanic
only made good movies.
He is also a kind of Robert Pattinson.
He was crazy before.
He made many good movies before.
He has the Streets of New York
or something like that.
I don't remember his name.
He was very young.
Then also films like The Beach.
Super cool film.
DiCaprio made a lot of
really good movies.
And Titanic was...
I grew up with it too.
That is the Titanic.
What kind of shit movie is that?
According to the motto.
He makes a love-homo movie.
He should fuck with his dick stuff.
Sure, that is the mainstream
attitude you get.
But as soon as you have seen The Beach
or James Carroll
was his name.
Jim Carroll?
Streets of New York or something like that?
One of the first movies.
Only good movies.
Leonardo DiCaprio made almost only good movies.
Yes, that is good
if it is valued on programming
and signal processing.
Because that is actually
an engineer who does not do that.
Or who does not develop
any interest for development.
He is a boomer.
He lives on a dying branch.
That is clear.
Especially because the engineer
represents the interface between
a real, normal mechanic
and an academic physicist.
That is someone who has the practical
relationship but still understands
the theoretical basics.
At least as far as he needs it
for his problem solving.
It is clear that you cannot
say that the L2-norm
of the function
is smaller than infinite.
That is not expected from you.
You are expected to understand
these things with mathematics
so far as to correctly
classify and solve the problems.
By the way, you can write me an email.
I like to help people
who are in such a situation.
Because I know myself quite well.
Especially with mathematics.
And if someone is a well-paid
employee of Antifa GmbH
then I already have
a kind of house-sympathy.
To be honest, I did not know
what an in-study
should bring me.
Well, if you say
what did you do?
You worked at a car dealer.
That means you have a lot of practice.
Practice, I assume.
The nice thing about
an academic career is
the academic
elegance that comes with it.
And I do not mean
that an elitist pisser
comes out of it
and raises you
to another level.
Because you see
certain things
from a different perspective.
You cannot underestimate
what that brings.
It brings a lot.
Studying, if you do it
because you feel like it.
I am not talking about all those
weirdos who make inflation
and just want a piece of paper
so that they are hired at a bank
or get a boss position in a
bureaucratic office.
I am talking about
people who are interested in content.
And if you say you worked at a car dealer
then I assume you have
a lot of experience.
You know the numbers.
You know the mechanics.
But first of all
I would say that the car
with the combustion engine
is a story
that is on the dying branch.
But on the other hand
there is much more to discover.
The engineering studio is
a window into a different world.
You have this application
in your head.
That is mostly the case.
As an engineer you want
to install a milling machine
or you want to become a sports technician
and build fitness equipment.
It does not matter.
You have an idea of what you want to do.
And that is not a problem.
The nice thing is that
through the academic input
that you get
I would say
you see
how it is with modular thinking
and abstract thinking.
That is
an awesome intellectual
level up.
And nobody can steal it from you.
That is super powerful.
You feel much better afterwards.
It is just
I do not get it wrong.
I want the activity
of normal people
who did not go to university
and did something right.
I do not want to talk about that.
As a physicist
I did computer-oriented
theoretical physics
in my graduate school.
I am far away from the practice.
But I still see that
in engineers.
I know engineers
who are teaching
or doing engineering activities
and they are crying
how terrible it is
to deal with students
who are only affected by inflation
and so on.
If you want
to do something like that
then do it.
If you do not want to do it
If you are interested
in the content
and you learn a lot
even in the inflation
you can learn a lot.
It is not used anymore.
You have to do
30-25%
of the content.
But you can do 80%.
Nobody can forbid that.
And nobody can forbid
you to do
secondary literature
if you are interested.
Maybe not statistical physics
but only theoretical mechanics.
It is a nice excursion
if you have the luxury
to do something like that.
I can only recommend it to everyone.
I think it is a real enrichment.
It really helps
to create something.
You can find my e-mail address
on the channel.
In the YouTube interface.
Channel info.
I am going to get a beer
and turn on the music.
We said
hard and relaxed.
Hard and relaxed.
I am thinking about
what would be good.
Let me think.
Hard and relaxed.
No.
Maybe.
I have a good idea.
Hard and relaxed.
See you soon.
Thank you.
Music
.