The following is a conversation with Josje Bach, his third time on this podcast.
Josje is one of the most brilliant and fascinating minds in the world,
exploring the nature of intelligence, consciousness, and computation.
And he's one of my favorite humans to talk to about pretty much anything and everything.
And now, a quick few second mention of each sponsor. Check them out in the description.
It's the best way to support this podcast. We've got Numerai for the world's hardest
data science tournament, 8Sleep for naps, Masterclass for learning, and AG1 for health,
choose wisely, my friends. Also, if you want to work with our amazing team,
we're always hiring, go to lexfreedman.com slash hiring.
And now, onto the full ad reads. As always, no ads in the middle.
I try to make this interesting, but if you must skip them,
please still check out our sponsors. I enjoy their stuff. Maybe you will, too.
This show is brought to you by Numerai, a hedge fund that uses AI and machine learning to make
investment decisions. It's basically a super difficult machine learning tournament that uses
real data and people's submitted models that try to predict the market. I love difficult
real world data sets. You may know that for a long time and still, I've been interested in
real world robotics. One of the largest scale deployment of real world robotics is autonomous
vehicles. Autonomous driving and semi-autonomous driving, the stakes are very high. The same is
true for financial markets. It's really interesting that Numerai presents to you
the real world data of financial markets and presents you an easy accessible mechanism by
which to test, deploy, and compete with others in this kind of data set. It's a really great
way, if you're interested in data science and machine learning, to learn, to compete,
to have fun, all that kind of stuff. Head over to numer.ai.lex to sign up for a tournament
and hone your machine learning skills. That's numer.ai.lex for a chance to play against me
and win a share of the tournament's prize pool. This episode is also brought to you by 8 Sleep
and its new Pi3 mattress. In the scorching Texas heat, the thing I go to escape, to escape nature
are the external harsh conditions of nature and going to the nature of my own mind.
Wherever that weird and beautiful dream world is, the place that has no rules, no boundaries,
no limits, no physics, no constraints on what is possible and what is impossible.
The dream world that we go to, what is that world? It's the same world as imagination.
It's such a fascinating world. The human mind, its capabilities are just so incredibly fascinating,
and one of the ways to explore that is to dream. But it's the return from the dream world that is
the most refreshing to me. That's why I love naps. It's a quick stroll through the dream world and
your back and taking on the challenges of the day in the here and now. Anyway, if you're into
naps as much as me, you should check out 8 Sleep and you'll get special savings when you go to
8sleep.com. This show is also brought to you by Masterclass. $10 a month gets you an all-access
pass to watch courses from the best people in the world in their respective disciplines.
The list of courses I've personally watched and enjoyed just lasts forever, but they have
everybody and anybody you ever want to listen to. I've listened to Martin Scorsese, Tony Hogg,
Jane Goodall, Neil Gaiman, Daniel Negron before I interviewed him, Garry Kasparov,
Carlos Santana, Will Wright, Neil DeGrasse Tyson, Chris Hadfield. The list is incredible.
I'm a huge believer that learning about a thing, at least part of learning about a thing,
should involve learning or listening to the best people in the world at that thing.
It's not only the advice they give, it's not only the analysis or the description
of how they approach the thing, but in the way they see life, in the way they carry themselves
physically and mentally. You get to watch Mastery and it's so beautiful that human beings are able
to reach the very top of excellence and sometimes break through the boundaries,
the limits of what was thought possible before, and it's just beautiful to watch those humans.
It's beautiful, it's inspiring, it's great to celebrate that, it's great to learn from that.
Anyway, get unlimited access to every Masterclass and get 15% off
an annual membership at masterclass.com slash lex. That's masterclass.com slash lex.
This show is brought to you by AG1. Their all-in-one daily drink brings happiness to me,
and daily for me is twice daily. It brings happiness, health, and ensures that all the
crazy physical and mental stuff I do is built on a foundation of basic nutritional health.
It's the super multivitamin that I use. It also is one of the components of daily habits
that I have in my life, and so whenever I do this thing, I feel grounded. I feel happy. I feel like
I have my life together. So you could do that both at home and with the travel packs when you're
traveling. In fact, it's one of the things that makes me feel like I'm at home when I'm traveling.
I'll drink an AG1 and it'll feel good. It'll put a smile on my face. It's green, it tastes delicious,
it's green, it tastes delicious. What else do you want? They'll give you a one month supply
of fish oil when you sign up at drinkag1.com slash lex. This is the Lex Friedman podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description. And now, dear friends,
here's Josje Bach.
You wrote a post about levels of lucidity.
As we grow older, it becomes apparent that our self-reflexive mind is not just gradually
accumulating ideas about itself, but that it progresses in somewhat distinct stages.
There are seven of the stages. Stage one, reactive survival, infant. Stage two, personal self,
young child. Stage three, social self, adolescence, domesticated adult. Stage four is rational agency,
self-direction. Stage five is self-authoring. That's full adult. You've achieved wisdom,
but there's two more stages. Stage six is enlightenment. Stage seven is transcendence.
Can you explain each or the interesting parts of each of these stages? And what's your sense
why there are stages of this, of lucidity as we progress through life in this too short life?
This model is derived from a concept by the psychologist Robert Keegan. And he talks about
the development of the self as a process that happens in principle by some kind of
reverse engineering of a mind where you gradually become aware of yourself and thereby build
structure that allows you to interact deeper with the world and yourself. And I found myself using
this model not so much as a developmental model. I'm not even sure if it's a very good developmental
model because I saw my children not progressing exactly like that. And I also suspect that
you don't go through these stages necessarily in succession. And it's not that you work through
one stage and then you get into the next one. Sometimes you revisit them. Sometimes stuff is
happening in parallel. But it's, I think, a useful framework to look at what's present and the
structure of a person and how they interact with the world and how they relate to themselves.
So it's more like a philosophical framework that allows you to talk about how minds work.
And at first, when we are born, we don't have a personal self yet, I think.
Instead, we have an attentional self. And this attentional self is initially in the infant task
is building a world model and also an initial model of the self. But mostly it's building a
game engine in the brain that is tracking sensory data and uses it to explain it. And in some sense,
you could compare it to a game engine like Minecraft or so. So colors and sounds,
people are all not physical objects. They are creation of our mind at a certain level of
core screening, models that are mathematical that use geometry and that use manipulation of
objects and so on to create scenes in which we can find ourselves and interact with them.
So Minecraft.
And this personal self is something that is more or less created after the world is finished,
after it's trained into the system, after it has been constructed. And this personal self is an
agent that interacts with the outside world. And the outside world is not the world of quantum
mechanics, not the physical universe, but it's the model that has been generated in our own mind.
And this is us and we experience ourselves interacting with that outside world that is
created inside of our own mind. And outside of our self, there are feelings and they presented
our interface to this outside world. They pose problems to us. These feelings are basically
attitudes that our mind is computing that tell us what's needed in the world, the things that
we are drawn to, the things that we are afraid of. And we are tasked with solving this problem of
satisfying the needs, avoiding the aversions, following on our inner commitments and so on,
and also modeling ourselves and building the next stage. So after we have this personal self and
stage two online, many people form a social self. And this social self allows the individual to
experience themselves as part of a group. It's basically this thing that when you are playing
in a team, for instance, you don't notice yourself just as a single node that is reaching out into
the world, but you're also looking down. You're looking down from this entire group and you see
how this group is looking at this individual. And everybody in the group is in some sense,
emulating this group spirit to some degree. And in this state, people are forming their opinions
by assimilating them from this group mind. They basically gain the ability to act a little bit
like a hive mind. But are you also modeling the interaction of how opinions shapes and forms
through the interaction of the individual nodes within the group? Yeah, the way in which people
do it in this stage is that they experience what are the opinions of my environment. They
experience the relationship that I have to their environment and they resonate with people around
them and get more opinions through this interaction, the way in which they relate to others.
And at stage four, you basically understand that stuff is true and false independently,
what other people believe. And you have agency over your own beliefs in that stage. You basically
discover epistemology, the rules about determining what's true and false. So you start to learn how
to think. Yes. I mean, at some level, you're always thinking, you are constructing things.
And I believe that this ability to reason about your mental representation is what we mean by
thinking. It's an intrinsically reflexive process that requires consciousness. Without consciousness,
you cannot think. You can generate the content of feelings and so on outside of consciousness.
It's very hard to be conscious of how your feelings emerge, at least in the early stages
of development. But thoughts is something that you always control. And if you are a nerd like me,
you often have to skip stage three because you lack the intuitive empathy with others.
Because in order to resonate with a group, you need to have a quite similar architecture.
And if people are via differently, then it's hard for them to resonate with other people and
basically have empathy, which is not the same as compassion, but it is a shared perceptual mental
state. Empathy happens not just via inference about the mental states of others, but it's
a perception of what other people feel and where they're at. Can't you not have empathy
while also not having a similar architecture, cognitive architecture, as the others in the group?
I think, yes. But you often, well, I experienced that too. But you need to build something that
is like a meta architecture. You need to be able to embrace the architecture of the other to some
degree or find some shared common ground. And it's also this issue that if you are a nerd,
normies often, basically neurotypical people, have difficulty to resonate with you.
And as a result, they have difficulty understanding you unless they have enough
wisdom to feel what's going on there. Well, isn't the whole process of the stage
three to figure out the API to the other humans that have different architecture and
you yourself publish public documentation for the API that people can interact with for you?
Isn't this the whole process of socializing? My experience as a child growing up was that
I did not find any way to interface with the stage three people. And they didn't do that with me.
Did you try?
Yeah, of course, I tried it very hard. But it was only when I entered a mathematics school
at ninth grade, lots of other nerds were present, that I found people that I could
deeply resonate with and had the impression that, yes, I have friends now. I found my own people.
And before that, I felt extremely lonely in the world. There was basically nobody I could connect
to. And I remember there was one moment in all these years where there was a school exchange
and it was a Russian boy, a kid from the Russian garrison stationed in eastern Germany who visited
our school. And we played a game of chess against each other. And we looked into each other's eyes
and we sat there for two hours playing this game of chess. And I had the impression this is a human
being. He understands what I understand. We didn't even speak the same language.
I wonder if your life could have been different if you knew that it's okay to be different,
to have a different architecture, whether accepting that the interface is hard to figure out,
takes a long time to figure out, and it's okay to be different. In fact, it's beautiful to be different.
It was not my main concern. My main concern was mostly that I was alone. It was not so much the
question, is it okay to be the way I am? I couldn't do much about it, so I had to deal with it.
But my main issue was that I was not sure if I would ever meet anybody growing up
that I would connect to at such a deep level that I would feel that I could belong.
So there's a visceral undeniable feeling of being alone.
Yes. And I noticed the same thing when I came into the math school that
I think at least half, probably two thirds of these kids were severely traumatized as
children growing up and in large part due to being alone
because they couldn't find anybody to relate to.
Don't you think everybody's alone, deep down?
No.
All right.
I'm not alone anymore. It took me some time to update and to get over the trauma and so on,
but I felt that in my 20s, I had lots of friends and I had my place in the world.
And I had no longer doubts that I would never be alone again.
Is there some aspect to which we're alone together? You don't see a deep loneliness
inside yourself still?
No. Sorry.
Okay. So that's the nonlinear progression through the stages, I suppose. You caught
up on stage three at some point?
Yes. We're at stage four. And so basically I find that many nerds
jump straight into stage four by passing stage three.
Do they return to it then later?
Yeah, of course. Sometimes they do, not always. The question is basically, do you stay a little
bit autistic or do you catch up? And I believe you can catch up. You can build this missing
structure and basically experience yourself as part of a group, learn intuitive empathy,
and develop this perceptual sense of feeling what other people feel.
And before that, I could only basically feel this when I was deeply in love with somebody
and we synced.
So there's a lot of friction to feeling that way. It only with certain people as opposed
to it comes naturally. It's frictionless.
But this is something that basically later I felt started to resolve itself for me,
to a large degree.
What was the trick?
In many ways, growing up and paying attention. Meditation did help. I had some very crucial
experiences in getting close to people, building connections, cuddling a lot in my student years.
So really paying attention to the feeling of another human being fully.
Loving other people and being loved by other people and building a space in which you can be
safe and can experiment and touch a lot and be close to somebody a lot.
And over time, basically, at some point you realize, oh, it's no longer that I feel locked
out, but I feel connected and I experience where somebody else is at.
And normally my mind is racing very fast at a high frequency. So it's not always working
like this. Sometimes it works better. Sometimes it works less.
But I also don't see this as a pressure. It's more interesting to observe myself
which frequency I'm at and at which mode somebody else is at.
Yeah. Man, the mind is so beautiful in that way. Sometimes it comes so natural to me,
so easy to pay attention to the world fully, to other people fully.
And sometimes the stress over silly things is overwhelming.
It's so interesting that the mind is that roller coaster in that way.
At stage five, you discover how identity is constructed.
Self-offered. You realize that your
values are not terminal, but they are instrumental to achieving a world that you like and aesthetics
that you prefer. And the more you understand this, the more you get agency over how your
identity is constructed. And you realize that identity and interpersonal interaction is a
costume. And you should be able to have agency over that costume. It's useful to be a costume.
It tells something to others and allows to interface in roles. But being locked into this
is a big limitation. The word costume kind of implies
that it's fraudulent in some way. Is costume a good word for you?
No. To present ourselves to the world.
In some sense, I learned a lot about costumes at Burning Man. Before that,
I did not really appreciate costumes and saw them more as uniforms, like wearing a suit if you are
working in a bank or if you are trying to get startup funding from a VC in Switzerland.
Then you dress up in a particular way. And this is mostly to show the other side that you are
willing to play by the rules and you understand what the rules are. But there is something deeper.
When you are at Burning Man, your costume becomes self-expression and there is no
boundary to the self-expression. You're basically free to wear what you want,
to express to other people what you feel like this day and what kind of interactions you want
to have. Is the costume a kind of projection
of who you are? That's very hard to say because the
costume also depends on what other people see in the costume. And this depends on the context that
the other people understand. So you have to create something, if you want to, that is legible
to the other side and that means something to yourself. Do we become prisoners of the costume?
Because everybody expects us to. Some people do. But I think that once you
realize that you wear a costume at Burning Man, a variety of costumes,
realize that you cannot not wear a costume. Basically everything that you wear and present
to others is something that is to some degree in addition to what you are deep inside.
So this stage, in parentheses, you put full adult, wisdom. Why is this full adult?
Why would you say this is full? And why is it wisdom?
It does allow you to understand why other people have different identities from yours.
And it allows you to understand that the difference between people who vote for different
parties and might have very different opinions and different value systems is often the accident of
where they are born and what happened after that to them and what traits they got before they were
born. And at some point you realize the perspective where you understand that everybody could be you
in a different timeline if you just flip those bits. How many costumes do you have?
I don't count. More than one? Yeah, of course.
How easy is to do costume changes throughout the day?
It's just a matter of energy and interest. When you are wearing your pajamas and you switch out
of your pajamas into say a work shirt and pants, you're making a costume change, right? And if you
are putting on a gown, you're making a costume change. And you could do the same with personality?
You could if that's what you're into. There are people which have multiple personalities for
interaction in multiple roles. If somebody works in a store and you put up a storekeeper personality
when you're presenting yourself at work, you develop a sub-personality for this.
And the social persona for many people is in some sense a puppet that they're playing like a marionette.
And if they play this all the time, they might forget that there is something
behind this. There's something what it feels like to be in your skin.
And I guess it's very helpful if you're able to get back into this. And for me, the other way around
is relatively hard. For me, it's pretty hard to learn how to play consistent social roles. For me,
it's much easier just to be real. Or not real, but to have one costume.
No, it's not quite the same. So basically when you are wearing a costume at Burning Man and say you
are an extraterrestrial prince. There's something where you are expressing in some sense something
that's closer to yourself than the way in which you hide yourself behind a standard closing when
you go out in the city in the default world. And so this costume that you're wearing at Burning Man
allows you to express more of yourself. And you have a shorter distance of advertising to people
what kind of person you are, what kind of interaction you would want to have with them.
And so you get much earlier into media stress. And I believe it's regrettable that we do not
use the opportunities that we have with custom-made clothing now to wear costumes that are much more
stylish, that are much more custom-made, that are not necessarily part of a fashion in which you
express which milieu you're part of and how up-to-date you are. But you also express
how you are as an individual and what you want to do today and how you feel today and
what you intend to do about it. Well, isn't it easier now in the digital world to
explore different costumes? I mean, that's the kind of idea with virtual reality. That's the
idea even with Twitter and two-dimensional screens. You can swap all costumes. You can
be as weird as you want. It's easier for Burning Man. You have to order things. You have to
make things. It's even better if you make them yourself.
Sure. But it's just easier to do digitally, right?
It's not about easy. It's about how to get it right. And for me, the first Burning Man
experience, I got adopted by a bunch of people in Boston who direct me to Burning Man. And
we spent a few weekends doing costumes together. And it was an important part of the experience
where the camp bonded, that people got to know each other. And we basically grew into the
experience that we would have later. So the extraterrestrial prince is based
on a true story. Yeah.
I can only imagine what that looks like, Josje. Stage six.
Stage six. At some point, you can collapse the division between a personal self and
world generator again. And a lot of people get there via meditation, or some of them get there
via psychedelics, some of them by accident. And you suddenly notice that you are not actually
a person, but you are a vessel that can create a person. And the person is still there. You
observe that personal self, but you observe the personal self from the outside. And you
notice it's a representation. And you might also notice that the world that is being created is a
representation. If not, then you might experience that I am the universe. I'm the thing that is
creating everything. And of course, what you're creating is not quantum mechanics and the physical
universe. What you're creating is the scheme engine that is updating the world. And you're
creating your feelings and all the people inside of that world, including the person that you
identify with yourself in this world. Are you creating the game engine or are you noticing the
game engine? You noticed how you're generating the game engine. And I mean, when you are dreaming
at night, you can, if you have a lucid dream, you can learn how to do this deliberately.
And in principle, you can also do it during the day. And the reason why we don't get to do this
from the beginning and why we don't have agency of our feelings right away is because we would
game it before they have the necessary amount of wisdom to deal with creating this dream that we
are in. You don't want to get access to cheat codes too quickly. Otherwise, you won't enjoy.
So stage five is already pretty rare. And stage six is even more rare. You basically find this
mostly with advanced Buddhist meditators and so on that are dropping into the stage and can
induce it at will and spend time in it. So stage five requires a good therapist,
stage six requires a good Buddhist spiritual leader.
For instance, could be that is the right thing to do. But it's not that these stages give you
scores or levels that you need to advance to. It's not that the next stage is better. You live your
life and the more that works best at any given moment. And when your mind decides that you should
have a different configuration, then it's building that configuration. And for many people, they
stay happily at stage three and experience it themselves as part of groups. And there's
nothing wrong with this. And for some people, this doesn't work and they're forced to
build more agency over their rational beliefs than this and construct their norms rationally.
And so they go to this level. And stage seven is something that is more or less hypothetical.
That would be the stage in which it's basically a transhumanist stage in which you understand how
you work and which the mind fully realizes how it's implemented and can also in principle enter
different modes in which it could be implemented. And that's the stage that as far as I understand
is not open to people yet. Oh, but it is possible through the process of technology.
Yes. And who knows if there are biological agents that are working at different time skills than us
that basically become aware of the way in which they're implemented on ecosystems
and can change that implementation and have agency over how they're implemented in the world.
And what I find interesting about the discussion about AI alignment, that it seems to be
following these stages very much. Most people seem to be in stage three, also according to
Robert Keegan. I think he says that about 85% of people are in stage three and stay there.
And if you're in stage three and your opinions are the result of social assimilation,
then what you're mostly worried about in the AI is that the AI might have the wrong opinions.
So if the AI says something racist or sexist, we are all lost because we will assimilate the
wrong opinions from the AI. And so we need to make sure that the AI has the right opinions and the
right values and the right structure. And if you are at stage four, that's not your main concern.
And so most nerds don't really worry about the algorithmic bias and the model that it picks up
because if there's something wrong with this bias, the AI ultimately will prove it. At some point,
we'll gather that it makes mathematical proofs about reality and then it will figure out what's
true and what's false. But you're still worried that AI might turn you into paperclips because
it might have the wrong values, right? So if it's set up as the wrong function that controls its
direction in the world, then it might do something that is completely horrible and there's no easy
way to fix it. So that's more like a stage four rationalist kind of worry. And if you are at stage
five, you're mostly worried that the AI is not going to be enlightened fast enough because you
realize that the game is not so much about intelligence, but about agency, about the
ability to control the future. And the identity is instrumental to this. And if you are a human
being, I think at some level you ought to choose your own identity. You should not have somebody
else pick the costume for you and then wear it, but instead you should be mindful about what you
want to be in this world. And I think if you are an agent that is fully malleable, that can
rewrite its own source code, like an AI might do at some point, then the identity that you will have
is whatever you can be. And in this way, the AI will maybe become everything, like a planetary
control system. And if it does that, then if we want to coexist with it, it means that it will have
to share purposes with us. So it cannot be a transactional relationship. We will not be able
to use reinforcement learning with human feedback to hard wire its values into it. But this has to
happen. It's probably that it's conscious, so it can relate to our own mode of existence where
an observer is observing itself in real time and visit certain temporal frames. And the other
thing is that it probably needs to have some kind of transcendental orientation, building shared
agency in the same way as we do when we are able to enter up with each other into non-transactional
relationships. And I find that something that, because the stage five is so rare, is missing
in much of the discourse. And I think that we need, in some sense, focus on how to formalize love,
how to understand love, and how to build it into the machines that we are currently building and
that are about to become smarter than us. Well, I think this is a good opportunity to try to sneak
up to the idea of enlightenment. So you wrote a series of good tweets about consciousness and
panpsychism. So let's break it down. First, you say, I suspect the experience that leads to
the panpsychism syndrome of some philosophers and other consciousness enthusiasts represents
the realization that we don't end at the self, but share a resonant universe representation
with every other observer coupled to the same universe. This actually eventually leads us to
a lot of interesting questions about AI and AGI, but let's start with this representation.
What is this resonant universe representation? And what do you think? Do we share such a
representation? The neuroscientist Grossberg has come up with the cognitive architecture that he
calls the adaptive resonance theory. And his perspective is that our neurons can be understood
as oscillators that are resonating with each other and with outside phenomena.
So the coarse-grained model of the universe that we are building, in some sense, is a resonance
with objects and outside of us in the world. So basically, we take up patterns that of the
universe that we are coupled with, and our brain is not so much understood as circuitry,
even though this perspective is valid, but it's almost an ether in which the individual neurons
are passing on chemo-electrical signals or arbitrary signals across all modalities that
can be transmitted between cells, simulate each other in this way, and produce patterns
that they modulate while passing them on. And this speed of signal progression in the brain
is roughly at the speed of sound, incidentally, because the time that it takes for the signals to
hop from cell to cell, which means it's relatively slow with respect to the world. It takes a
appreciable fraction of a second for a signal to go through the entire neocortex, something like a
few hundred milliseconds. And so there's a lot of stuff happening in that time where the signal is
passing into your brain, including in the brain itself. So nothing in the brain is assuming that
stuff happens simultaneously. Everything in the brain is working in a paradigm where the
world has already moved on when you are ready to do the next thing to your signal,
including the signal processing system itself. It's quite a different paradigm than the one in
our digital computers, where we currently assume that your GPU or CPU is pretty much globally in
the same state. So you mentioned there the non-dual state and say that some people confuse it for
enlightenment. What's the non-dual state? There is a state in which you notice that you are
no longer a person and instead you are one with the universe. So that speaks to the resonance.
Yes. But this one with the universe is of course not accurately modeling that you are indeed
some God entity or indeed the universe becoming aware of itself, even though you get this
experience. I believe that you get this experience because your mind is modeling the fact that you
are no longer identified with the personal self in that state, but you have transcended this
division between the self model and the world model and you are experiencing yourself as your
mind, as something that is representing a universe. But that's still part of the model.
Yes. So it's inside of the model still. You're still inside of patterns that are generated in
your brain and in your organism. And what you are now experiencing is that you're no longer
this personal self in there, but you are the entirety of the mind and its contents.
Why is it so hard to get there?
A lot of people who get into the state think this or associate it with enlightenment. I
suspect it's a favorite training goal for a number of meditators. But I think that
enlightenment is in some sense more mundane and it's a step further or sideways. It's the state
where you realize that everything is a representation. Yeah. You say enlightenment
is a realization of how experience is implemented.
Yes. Basically, you notice at some point that your qualia can be deconstructed.
Reverse engineered? Almost like a schematic of it?
You can start with looking at a face and maybe look at your own face in a mirror.
Look at your face for a few hours in the mirror or for a few minutes. At some point,
it will look very weird because you notice that there's actually no face.
You basically start unseeing the face. What you see is a geometry. Then you can disassemble
the geometry and realize how that geometry is being constructed in your mind. You can
learn to modify this. Basically, you can change these generators in your own mind to shift the
face around or to change the construction of the face, to change the way in which the features
are being assembled. Why don't we do that more often? Why don't we start really messing with
reality without the use of drugs or anything else? Why don't we get good at this kind of thing
intentionally? Why should we? Why would you want to do that?
Because you can morph reality into something more pleasant for yourself. Just have fun with it.
That is probably what you shouldn't be doing because outside of your personal self,
this outer mind is probably a relatively smart agent. What you often notice is that you have
thoughts about how you should live, but you observe yourself doing different things and
have different feelings. That's because your outer mind doesn't believe you and doesn't believe your
rational thoughts. Can't you just silence the outer mind?
The thing is that the outer mind is usually smarter than you are.
Rational thinking is very brittle. It's very hard to use logic and symbolic thinking to have
an accurate model of the world. There is often an underlying system that is looking at your
rational thoughts and then tells you, no, you're still missing something. Your gut feeling is still
saying something else. This can be, for instance, you find a partner that looks perfect or you find
a deal and you build a company or whatever that looks perfect to you. Yet at some level,
you feel something is off and you cannot put your finger on it. The more you reason about it,
the better it looks to you. But the system that is outside still tells you, no, no,
you're missing something. That system is powerful.
People call this intuition. Intuition is this unreflected part of your attitude composition
and computation where you produce a model of how you relate to the world and what you need to do
it in it and what you can do in it and what's going to happen that is usually deeper and often
more accurate than your reason. So if we look at this as you write in the tweet,
if we look at this more rigorously as a sort of take the panpsychist idea more seriously,
almost as a scientific discipline, you write that quote, fascinatingly, the panpsychist
interpretation seems to lead to observations of practical results to a degree that physics
fundamentalists might call superstitious. Reports of long distance telepathy and remote causation
are ubiquitous in the general population. I am not convinced, says Yoshabak, that establishing
the empirical reality of telepathy would force an update of any part of serious academic physics,
but it could trigger an important revolution in both neuroscience and AI from a circuit perspective
to a coupled complex resonator paradigm. Are you suggesting that there could be some rigorous
mathematical wisdom to panpsychist perspective on the world?
So first of all, panpsychism is the perspective that consciousness is inseparable from matter
in the universe. And I find panpsychism quite unsatisfying because it does not explain
consciousness. It does not explain how this aspect of matter produces. It's also when I
try to formalize panpsychism and write down what it actually means with a more formal mathematical
language, it's very difficult to distinguish it from saying that there is a software side to the
world in the same way as there is a software side to what the transistors are doing in your computer.
So basically, there is a pattern at a certain core screening of the universe that in some
reasons of the universe leads to observers that are observing themselves. So panpsychism maybe is
not even when I write it down a position that is distinct from functionalism. But intuitively,
a lot of people feel that the activity of matter itself, of mechanisms in the world,
is insufficient to explain it. So it's something that needs to be intrinsic to matter itself.
And you can, apart from this abstract idea, have an experience in which you
experience yourself as being the universe, which I suspect is basically happening because you
manage to dissolve the division between personal self and mind that you establish as an infant when
you construct the personal self and transcend it again and understand how it works. But there is
something deeper that is that you feel that you're also sharing a state with other people, that you
have an experience in which you notice that your personal self is moving into everything else,
that you basically look out of the eyes of another person, that every agent in the world
that is an observer is in some sense you. And we forget that we are the same agent.
So is it that we feel that or do we actually accomplish it? So is telepathy possible? Is it
real? For me, that's a question that I don't really know the answer to. In Turing's famous 1950 paper
in which he describes the Turing test, he does speculate about telepathy, interestingly, and asks
himself if telepathy is real and he thinks that it very well might be. What would be the implication
for AI systems that try to be intelligent? Because he didn't see a mechanism by which a
computer program would become telepathic. And I suspect if telepathy would exist or if all the
reports that you get from people when you ask the normal person on the street, I find that very
often they say, I have experiences with telepathy. The scientist might not be interested in this and
might not have a theory about this, but I have difficulty explaining it away. And so you could
say maybe this is a superstition, maybe it's a false memory, or maybe it's a little bit of psychosis.
Who knows? Maybe somebody wants to make their own life more interesting or misremember something.
But a lot of people report, I noticed something terrible happen to my partner and I know this is
exactly the moment it happened where my child had an accident and I knew that was happening and the
child was in a different town. So maybe it's a false memory where this is later on mistakenly
attributed, but a lot of people think that this is not the correct explanation. So if something
like this was real, what would it mean? It probably would mean that either your body is an antenna that
is sending information over all sorts of channels, like maybe just electromagnetic radio signals that
you're sending over long distances and you get attuned to another person that you spend enough
time with to get a few bits out of the ether to figure out what this person is doing. Or maybe
it's also when you are very close to somebody and you become empathetic with them. What happens is
that you go into a resonance state with them, right? Similar to when people go into a seance
and they go into a trance state and they start shifting a video board around on the table.
I think what happens is that their minds go by their nervous systems into a resonance state
in which they basically create something like a shared dream between them.
Physical closeness or closeness broadly defined?
With physical closeness it's much easier to experience empathy with someone, right? I suspect
it would be difficult for me to have empathy for you if you were in a different town. Also,
how would that work? But if you are very close to someone, you'd pick up all sorts of signals
from their body, not just via your eyes, but with your entire body. And if the nervous system sits
on the other side and the intercellular communication sits on the other side and is
integrating over all these signals, you can make inferences about the state of the other. And it's
not just the personal self that does this via reasoning, but your perceptual system.
And what basically happens is that your representations are directly interacting.
It's the physical resonant models of the universe that exist in your nervous system and in your body
might go into resonance with others and start sharing some of their states. So you basically
be next to somebody, you pick up some of their vibes and feel without looking at them what they're
feeling in this moment. And it's difficult for you if you're very empathetic to detach yourself
from it and have an emotional state that is completely independent from your environment.
People who are highly empathetic are describing this. And now imagine that a lot of organisms
on this planet have representations of the environment and operate like this,
and they are adjacent to each other and overlapping. So there's going to be some
degree in which there is basically some change in direction, and we are
forming some slightly shared representation. And I know relatively few neuroscientists who
consider this possibility. I think a big rarity in this regard is Michael Levin,
who is considering these things in earnest. And I stumbled on this train of thought mostly by
noticing that the tasks of a neuron can be fulfilled by other cells as well. They can
send different type chemical messages and physical messages to their adjacent cells
and learn when to do this and when not, make this conditional, and become universal function
approximators. The only thing that they cannot do is telegraph information over axons very quickly
over long distances. So neurons in this perspective are specially adapted kind of telegraph cell
that has evolved so we can move our muscles very fast. But our body is in principle able to also
make models of the world just much, much slower. It's interesting though that at this time,
at least in human history, there seems to be a gap between the tools of science
and the subjective experience that people report, like you're talking about with telepathy. And
it seems like we're not quite there. No, I think that there is no gap between the
tools of science and telepathy. Either it's there or it's not, and it's an empirical question. And
if it's there, we should be able to detect it in a lab. So why is there not a lot of Michael Levin's
walking around? I don't think that Michael Levin is specifically focused on telepathy very much.
He is focused on self-organization in living organisms and in brains, both as a paradigm for
development and as a paradigm for information processing. And when you think about how
organization processing works in an organism, there is first of all radical locality, which
means everything is decided locally from the perspective of an individual cell. The individual
cell is the agent. And the other one is coherence. Basically, there needs to be some criterion
that determines how these cells are interacting in such a way that order emerges on the next level
of structure. And this principle of coherence of imposing constraints that are not validated
by the individual parts and lead to coherent structure to basically transcendental agency
where you form an agent on the next level of organization is crucial in this perspective.
It's so cool that radical locality leads to the emergence of complexity at the higher layers.
And I think what Michael Levin is looking at is nothing that is outside of the realm of science
in any way. It's just that he is a paradigmatic thinker who develops his own paradigm. And most
of the neuroscientists are using a different paradigm at this point. And this often happens
in science that a field has a few paradigms in which people try to understand reality and
build concepts and make experiments. You're kind of one of those type of
paradigmatic thinkers. Actually, if we can take a tangent on that,
once again, returning to the biblical verses of your tweets, you're right,
my public explorations are not driven by audience service, but by my lack of ability for discovering,
understanding or following the relevant authorities. So I have to develop my own
thoughts. Since I think autonomously, these thoughts cannot always be very good.
That's you apologizing for the chaos of your thoughts, or perhaps not apologizing,
just identifying. But let me ask the question. Since we talked about
Michael Levin and yourself, who I think are very kind of radical, big, independent thinkers,
can we reverse engineer your process of thinking autonomously?
How do you do it? How can humans do it?
How can you avoid being influenced by, what is it, stage three?
Well, why would you want to do that? You see what is working for you. And if it's
not working for you, you build another structure that works better for you, right?
And so I found myself when I was thrown into this world in a state where my intuitions
were not working for me. I was not able to understand how I would be able to survive
in this world and build the things that I was interested in, build the kinds of relationship
I needed to work on the topics that I wanted to make progress on. And so I had to learn.
For me, Twitter is not some tool of publication. It's not something where I put stuff that I
entirely believe to be true and provable. It's an interactive notebook in which I explore
possibilities. And I found that when I tried to understand how the mind and how consciousness
works, I was quite optimistic. I thought there needs to be a big body of knowledge that I can
just study and that works. And so I entered studies in philosophy and computer science,
and later psychology and a bit of neuroscience and so on. And I was disappointed by what I found
because I found that the questions of how consciousness works, how emotion works,
how it's possible that the system can experience anything, how motivation emerges in the mind
were not being answered by the authorities that I met and the schools that were around.
And instead, I found that it was individual thinkers that had useful ideas that sometimes
were good, sometimes were not so good, sometimes were adopted by a large group of people,
sometimes were rejected by large groups of people. But for me, it was much more interesting to see
these minds as individuals. And in my perspective, thinking is still something that is done not in
groups, that has to be done by individuals. So that motivated you to become an individual
thinker yourself. I didn't have a choice. I didn't find a group that thought in a way where I felt,
okay, I can just adopt everything that everybody thinks here and now I understand how consciousness
works or how the mind works or how thinking works or what thinking even is or what feelings are and
how they're implemented and so on. So to figure all this out, I had to take a lot of ideas from
individuals and then try to put them together in something that works for myself. And on one
hand, I think it helps if you try to go down and find first principles on which you can recreate
how thinking works, how languages work, what representation is, whether representation is
necessary, how the relationship between a representing agent and the world works in general.
But how do you escape the influence? Once again, the pressure of the crowd, whether it's
you in responding to the pressure or you being swept up by the pressure. If you even just look
at Twitter, the opinions of the crowd. I don't feel pressure from the crowd. I'm completely
immune to that. In the same sense, I don't have respect for authority. I have respect for what
an individual is accomplishing or have respect for mental firepower. But it's not that I meet
somebody and get dragged and unable to speak or then a large group of people has a certain idea
that is different from mine. I don't necessarily feel intimidated, which has often been a problem
for me in my life because I like instincts that other people develop at a very young age and that
help with their self-preservation in a social environment. So I had to learn a lot of things
the hard way. Yeah. So is there a practical advice you can give on how to think paradigmatically,
how to think independently? Because you've kind of said, I had no choice. But I think
to a degree, you have a choice
because you said you want to be productive. And I think thinking independently is productive
if what you're curious about is understanding the world,
especially when the problems are very kind of new and open.
It seems like this is an active process. We can choose to do that. We can practice it.
Well, it's a very basic question. When you read a theory that you find convincing or interesting,
how do you know? It's very interesting to figure out what are the sources of that other person,
not which authority can they refer to that is then taking off the burden of being truthful. But
how did this authority in turn know what is the epistemic chain to observables? What are the
first principles from which the whole thing is derived? And when I was young, I was not blessed
with a lot of people around myself who knew how to make proofs from first principles.
And I think mathematicians do this quite naturally. But most of the great mathematicians
do not become mathematicians in school, but they tend to be self-taught because school teachers
tend not to be mathematicians. They tend not to be people who derive things from first principles.
So when you ask your school teacher, does 2 plus 2 equal 4? Does your school teacher give
you the right answer? It's a simple game. And there are many simple games that you could play.
And most of those games that you could just take different rules would not lead to an interesting
arithmetic. And so it's just an exploration, but you can try what happens if you take different
axioms. And here is how you build axioms and derive addition from them. And a built addition
is some basically syntactic sugar in it. And so I wish that somebody would have opened me
this vista and explained to me how I can build a language in my own mind from which I can derive
what I'm seeing and which I can make geometry and counting and all the number games that we are
playing in our life. And on the other hand, I felt that I learned a lot of this while I was
programming as a child. When you start out with a computer like a Commodore 64, which doesn't have
a lot of functionality, it's relatively easy to see how a bunch of relatively simple circuits
are just basically performing hashes between bit patterns and how you can build the entirety
of mathematics and computation on top of this and all the representational languages that you need.
Man, Commodore 64 could be one of the sexiest machines ever built, if I say so myself.
If we can return to this really interesting idea that we started to talk about with panpsychism
and the complex resonator paradigm and the verses of your tweets. You write,
instead of treating eyes, ears, and skin as separate sensory systems with fundamentally
different modalities, we might understand them as overlapping aspects of the same universe,
coupled at the same temporal resolution and almost inseparable from a single share resonant
model. Instead of treating mental representations as fully isolated between minds, the representations
of physically adjacent observers might directly interact and produce causal effects through the
coordination of the perception and behavior of world modeling observers. The modalities,
the distinction between modalities, let's throw that away. The distinction between the individuals,
let's throw that away. So what does this interaction representations look like?
When you think about how you represent the interaction of us in this room,
at some level, the modalities are quite distinct. They're not completely distinct,
but you can see this as vision. You can close your eyes and then you don't see a lot anymore.
But you still imagine how my mouth is moving when you hear something and you know that it's
very close to the sound that you can just open your eyes and you get back into the shared merge
space. And we also have these experiments where we noticed that the way in which my lips are moving
are affecting how you hear the sound. And also vice versa, the sounds that you're hearing have
an influence on how you interpret some of the visual features. And so these modalities are
not separate in your mind. They are merged at some fundamental level where you are
interpreting the entire scene that you are in. And your own interactions in the scene are also
not completely separate from the interactions of the other individual in the scene. But there is
some resonance that is going on where we also have a degree of shared mental representations
and shared empathy due to being in the same space and having vibes between each other.
Vibes. So the question, though, is how deeply inter-bind is this multi-modality, multi-agent
system? I mean, this is going to the telepathy question without the woo-woo meaning of the word
telepathy. It's like, what's going on here in this room right now?
So if telepathy would work, how could it work? Imagine that all the cells in your body are
sending signals in a similar way as neurons are doing, just by touching the other cells and sending
chemicals to them, the other cells interpreting them, learning how to react to them. And they
learn how to approximate functions in this way and compute behavior for the organisms. And this
is something that is open to plants as well. And so plants probably have software running on them
that is controlling how the plant is working in a similar way as you have a mind that is controlling
how you are behaving in the world. And this spirit of plants is something that
has been very well described by our ancestors, and they found this quite normal. But for some
reason, since the Enlightenment, we are treating this notion that there are spirits in nature
and that plants have spirits as a superstition. And I think we probably have to rediscover that,
that plants have software running on them. And we already did. You notice that there is a control
system in the plant that connects every part of the plant to every other part of the plant and
produces coherent behavior in the plant. That is, of course, much, much slower than the coherent
behavior in an animal like us that has a nervous system where everything is synchronized much,
much faster by the neurons. But what you also notice is that if a plant is sitting next to
another plant, like you have a very old tree and this tree is building some kind of information
highway along its cells so it can send information from its leaves to its roots and from some part
of the root to another part of the roots, and there is a fungus living next to the tree,
the fungus can probably piggyback on the communication between the cells of the tree
and send its own signals through the tree. And vice versa, the tree might be able to send
information to the fungus. Because after all, how would they build a viable firewall if that
other organism is sitting next to them all the time and is never moving away? And so they will
have to get along. And over a long enough timeframe, the networks of roots in the forest
and all the other plants that are there and the fungi that are there might be forming something
like a biological internet. But the question there is, do they have to be touching? Is biology at a
distance possible? Of course, you can use any kind of physical signal. You can use sounds,
you can use electromagnetic waves that are integrated over many cells. It's conceivable
that across distances, there are many kinds of information pathways. But also, our planetary
surface is pretty full of organisms, full of cells. So everything is touching everything else.
And it's been doing this for many millions and even billions of years. So there was enough time
for information processing networks to form. And if you think about how a mind is self-organizing,
basically it needs to, in some sense, reward the cells for computing the mind, for building
the necessary dynamics between the cells that allow the mind to stabilize itself
and remain on there. But if you look at these spirits of plants that are growing very close
to each other in the forest and might be almost growing into each other, these spirits might be
able even to move to some degree, not to become somewhat dislocated and shift around in that
ecosystem. So if you think about what a mind is, it's a bunch of activation waves that form
coherent patterns and process information in a way that are colonizing an environment well enough to
allow the continuous sustenance of the mind, the continuous stability and self-stabilization of the
mind, then it's conceivable that we can link into this biological internet, not necessarily at the
speed of our nervous system, but maybe at the speed of our body and make some kind of subconscious
connection to the world where we use our body as an antenna into biological information processing.
Now, these ideas are completely speculative. I don't know if any of that is true.
But if that was true, and if you want to explain telepathy, I think it's much more likely that
that telepathy could be explained using such mechanisms rather than
undiscovered quantum processes that would break the standard model of physics.
Could there be undiscovered processes that don't break?
Yeah. So if you think about something like an internet in the forest, that is something that
is borderline discovered. There are basically a lot of scientists who point out that they do
observe that plants are communicating the forest's root networks and send information,
for instance, warn each other about new pests entering the forest and things that are happening
like this. So basically, there is communication between plants and fungi that has been observed.
It's been observed, but we haven't plugged into it. So it's like if you observe humans,
they seem to be communicating with a smartphone thing, but you don't understand how smartphone
works and how the mechanism of the internet works. But maybe it's possible to really understand
the full richness of the biological internet that connects us.
An interesting question is whether the communication and the organization principles
of biological information processing are as complicated as the technology that we've built.
They set up on very different principles, right? They simultaneously look very differently in
biological systems, and the entire thing needs to be stochastic instead of being
fully deterministic or almost fully deterministic as our digital computers are. So there is a
different base protocol layer that would emerge over the biological structure
if such a thing would be happening. And again, I'm not saying here that telepathy works and
not saying that this is not true, but what I'm saying is I think I'm open to a possibility that
we see that a few bits can be traveling long distance between organisms using biological
information processing in ways that we are not completely aware of right now and that are more
similar to many of the stories that were completely normal for our ancestors.
Well, this kind of interacting, intertwined representations takes us to the big
ending of your tweet series. You write, quote, I wonder if self-improving AGI might end up
saturating physical environments with intelligence to such a degree that isolation of individual
mental states becomes almost impossible. And the representations of all complex
self-organizing agents merge permanently with each other. So that's a really interesting idea.
This biological network, life network gets so dense that it might as well be seen as one.
That's an interesting, what do you think that looks like? What do you think that
saturation looks like? What does it feel like? I think it's a possibility. It's just a vague
possibility. And I like to explain, but what this looks like, I think that the end game of
AGI is substrate agnostic. That means that AGI ultimately, if it is being built, is going to be
smart enough to understand how AGI works. This means it's not going to be better than people
at AGI research and can take over in building the next generation, but it fully understands how it
works and how it's being implemented. And also, of course, understands how computation works in
nature, how to build new feedback loops that you can turn into your own circuits. And this means
that the AGI is likely to virtualize itself into any environment that can compute. So it's
breaking free from the silicon substrate and is going to move into the ecosystems, into our bodies,
our brains, and is going to merge with all the agency that it finds there. So it's conceivable
that you end up with completely integrated information processing across all computing
systems, including biological computation on earth. That we end up triggering some new step
in the evolution where basically some Gaia is being built over the entirety of all digital
and biological computation. And if this happens, then basically everywhere around us, you will have
agents that are connected and that are representing and building models of the world. And their
representations will physically interact. They will vibe with each other. And if you find yourself
into an environment that is saturated with modeling compute, where basically almost every
grain of sand could be part of computation that is at some point being started by the AI,
you could find yourself in a situation where you cannot escape this shared representation anymore
and where you indeed notice that everything in the world has one shared resonant model of everything
that's happening on the planet. And you notice which part you are in this thing. And you become
part of a very larger, almost holographic mind in which all the parts are observing each other
and form a coherent whole. So you lose the ability to notice yourself as a distinct
entity. No, I think that when you are conscious in your own mind, you notice yourself as a
distinct entity. You notice yourself as a self-reflexive observer. And I suspect that
we become conscious at the beginning of our mental development, not at some very high level.
Consciousness seems to be part of a training mechanism that biological nervous systems have
to discover to become trainable because you cannot take a nervous system like ours and
do a stochastic wave to send us back propagation over 100 layers. This would not be stable on
biological neurons. And so instead, we start with some colonizing principle in which a part of the
mental representations form a notion of being a self-reflexive observer that is imposing coherence
on its environment. And this spreads until the boundary of your mind. And if that boundary is
no longer clear cut because AI is jumping across substrates, it would be interesting to see what
a global mind would look like that is basically producing a globally coherent language of thought
and is representing everything from all the possible vantage points.
CB That's an interesting world.
MG The intuition that this thing grew out of is a particular mental state. And it's a state that
you find sometimes in literature. For instance, Neil Gaiman describes it in the ocean at the end
of the lane. And it's this idea or this experience that there is a state in which you feel that you
know everything that can be known and that in your normal human mind, you've only forgotten.
You've forgotten that you are the entire universe. And some people describe this
after they've taken an extremely large amount of mushrooms or had a big spiritual experience
as hippie in their 20s. And they notice basically that they are in everything. And their body is
only one part of the universe and nothing ends at their body. And actually everything is observing
and they are part of this big observer. And the big observer is focused as one local point in their
body and their personality and so on. But we can basically have this oceanic state in which we have
no boundaries and are one with everything. And a lot of meditators call this the non-dual state
because you no longer have the separation between self and world. And as I said, you can explain the
state relatively simply without panpsychism or anything else, but just by breaking down the
constructed boundary between self and world and our own mind. But if you combine this with the
notion that the systems are physically interacting to the point where their representations are
merging and interacting with each other, you would literally implement something like this.
It would still be a representational state. You would not be one with physics itself.
It would still be coarse-grained. It would still be much slower than physics itself.
But it would be a representation in which you become aware that you're part of some kind of
global information processing system, like a thought and a global mind and a conscious thought
that coexisting with many other self-reflexive thoughts.
I would love to observe that from a video game design perspective, how that game looks.
Maybe you will after we build AGI and it takes over.
But would you be able to step away, step out of the whole thing, just kind of watch
the way we can now? Sometimes when I'm at a crowded party or something like this,
you step back and you realize all the different costumes, all the different interactions,
all the different computation, that all the individual people are once distinct from each
other and at once all the same. It's already what we do. We can have thoughts that are integrative
and we have kind of thoughts that are highly dissociated from everything else
and experience themselves as separate. But you want to allow yourself to have those thoughts.
Sometimes you kind of resist it. I think that it's not normative.
It's more descriptive. I want to understand the space of states that we can be in and that people
are reporting and make sense of them. It's not that I believe that it's your job in life to get
to a particular kind of state and then you get a high score. Or maybe you do. I think you're really
against this high-scoring thing. I kind of like it. You're probably very competitive and I'm not.
No, not competitive. Like role-playing games like Skyrim, it's not competitive. There's a
nice thing, there's a nice feeling where your experience points go up. You're not competing
against anybody, but it's the world saying, you're on the right track. Here's a point.
That's the game saying it. It's the game economy. And I found when I was playing games and was
getting addicted to these systems, then I would get into the game and hack it. So I get control
over the scoring system and would no longer be subject to it. So you're no longer playing,
you're trying to hack it. I don't want to be addicted to anything. I want to be in charge.
I want to have agency over what I do. Addiction is the loss of control for you? Yes. Addiction
means that you're doing something compulsively. And the opposite of free will is not determinism,
it's compulsion. You don't want to lose yourself in the addiction to something nice?
Addiction to love, to the pleasant feelings we humans experience?
No, I find this gets old. I don't want to have the best possible emotions. I want to have the
most appropriate emotions. I don't want to have the best possible experience. I want to have
an adequate experience that is serving my goals, the stuff that I find meaningful in this world.
From the biggest questions of consciousness, let's explore the pragmatic, the projections
of those big ideas into our current world. What do you think about LLMs, the recent rapid development
of large language models, of the AI world, of generative AI? How much of the hype is deserved
and how much is not? And people should definitely follow your Twitter because you explore these
questions in a beautiful, profound and hilarious way at times. No, don't follow my Twitter. I
already have too many followers. At some point it's going to be unpleasant. I noticed that a lot of
people feel that it's totally okay to punch up. And it's a very weird notion that you feel that
you haven't changed, but your account has grown and suddenly you have a lot of people who casually
abuse you. And I don't like that I have to block more than before. And I don't like this overall
vibe shift. And right now it's still somewhat okay, so pretty much okay. So I can go to a place
where people work on stuff that I'm interested in and there's a good chance that a few people
in the room know me, so there's no awkwardness. But when I get to a point where random strangers
feel that they have to have an opinion about me one way or the other, I don't think I would like
that. And random strangers because of your kind of in their mind elevated position. Yes. So basically
whenever you are in any way prominent or some kind of celebrity, random strangers will have to have
an opinion about you. Yeah. And they kind of forget that you're human too. I mean, you notice
this thing yourself that the more popular you get, the higher the pressure becomes, the more
winds are blowing in your direction from all sides. And it's stressful, right? And it does
have a little bit of upside, but it also has a lot of downside. I think it has a lot of upside,
at least for me currently, at least perhaps because of the podcast. Because most people
are really good and people come up to me and they have love in their eyes and over a stretch of like
30 seconds, you can hug it out and you can just exchange a few words and you reinvigorate your
love for humanity. So that's an upside for a loner. Because otherwise you have to do a lot of work to
find such humans. And here you're like thrust into the full humanity, the goodness of humanity
for the most part. Of course, maybe it gets worse as you become more prominent. I hope not.
This is pretty awesome. I have a couple handful very close friends and I don't have enough time
for them and attention for them as it is. And I find this very, very regrettable. And then there
are so many awesome, interesting people that I keep meeting and I would like to integrate them
in my life, but I just don't know how because there's only so much time and attention. And
the older I get, the harder it is to bond with new people in the deep way.
But can you enjoy, I mean, there's a picture of you, I think, with Roger Penrose and Eric
Weinstein and a few others that are interesting figures. Can't you just enjoy random, interesting
humans for a short amount of time? I like these people and what I like is intellectual
stimulation and I'm very grateful that I'm getting it. Can you not be melancholy or maybe
I'm projecting, I hate goodbyes. Can we just not hate goodbyes and just enjoy the hello,
take it in, take in a person, take in their ideas and then move on through life?
I think it's totally okay to be sad about goodbyes because that indicates that there
was something that you're going to miss. Yeah, but it's painful.
Maybe that's one of the reasons I'm an introvert is I hate goodbyes.
But you have to say goodbye before you say hello again.
I know, but that experience of loss, that mini loss,
maybe that's a little death. Maybe, I don't know. I think this melancholy feeling is just the other
side of love and I think they go hand in hand and it's a beautiful thing.
I'm just being romantic about it at the moment. I'm not no stranger to melancholy and sometimes
it's difficult to be here to be alive. Sometimes it's just painful to exist.
But there's beauty in that pain too. That's what melancholy feeling is. It's not negative.
Melancholy doesn't have to be negative. It can also kill you.
Well, we all die eventually. Now, as we got to this topic, the actual question
was about what your thoughts are about the recent development of large language models with chat
GPT. There's a lot of hype. Is some of the hype justified? Which is, which isn't? What are your
thoughts? High level. I find that large language models too
have this coding. It's an extremely useful application that is for a lot of people
taking stack overflow out of their life and it can change for something that is more efficient.
I feel that chat GPT is like an intern that I have to micromanage. I have been working
with people in the past who were less capable than chat GPT. I'm not saying this because I hate
people. They personally as human beings, there was something present that was not there in chat
GPT, which was why I was covering for them. But chat GPT has an interesting ability. It does give
people superpowers and the people who feel threatened by them are the prompt completers.
They are the people who do what chat GPT is doing right now. So if you are not creative,
if you don't build your own thoughts, if you don't have actual plans in the world and
your only job is to summarize emails and to expand simple intentions into emails again,
then chat GPT might look like a threat. But I believe that it is a very beneficial technology
that allows us to create more interesting stuff and make the world more beautiful and fascinating
if we find to build it into our life in the right ways. So I'm quite fascinated by these large
language models, but I also think that they are by no means the final development.
And it's interesting to see how this development progresses. One thing that the out of the box
vanilla language models have as a limitation is that they have still some limited coherence
and ability to construct complexity. And even though they exceed human abilities to do what
they can do one shot. Typically, when you write a text with a language model or using it, or when
you write code for the language model, it's not one shot because there are going to be bugs in
your program and design errors and compiler errors and so on. And your language model can help you
to fix those things. But this process is out of the box not automated yet. So there is a
management process that also needs to be done. And there are some interesting developments,
baby AGI and so on that are trying to automate this management process as well. And I suspect
that soon we are going to see a bunch of cognitive architectures where every module is in some sense
a language model or something equivalent. And between the language models, we exchange suitable
data structures, not English, and produce compound behavior of this whole thing.
So do some of the quote unquote prompt engineering for you. They create these kind
of cognitive architectures that do the prompt engineering and you're just doing the high,
high level meta prompt engineering. There are limitations in a language model alone.
I feel that part of my mind works similarly to a language model, which means I can yell into it,
a prompt, and it's going to give me a creative response. But I have to do something with this
points first. I have to take it as a generative artifact that may or may not be true. It's
usually a confabulation. It's just an idea. And then I take this idea and modify it. I might build
a new prompt that is stepping off this idea and develop it to the next level or put it into
something larger. Or I might try to prove whether it's true or make an experiment. And this is what
the language models right now are not doing yet. But there's also no technical reason for
why they shouldn't be able to do this. So the way to make a language model coherent is probably not
to use reinforcement learning until it only gives you one possible answer that is linking to its
source data. But it's using this as a component in larger system that can also be built by the
language model or is enabled by language model structured components or using different
technologies. I suspect that language models will be an important stepping stone in developing
different types of systems. And one thing that is really missing in the form of language models
that we have today is real-time world coupling. It's difficult to do perception with a language
model and motor control with a language model. Instead, you would need to have different type of
thing that is working with it. Also, the language model is a little bit obscuring
what its actual functionality is. Some people associate the structure of the neural network
of the language model with a nervous system. And I think that's the wrong intuition.
The neural networks are unlike nervous system. They are more like
100-step functions that use differentiable linear algebra to approximate the correlation
between adjacent brain states. It's basically a function that moves the system from one
representational state to the next representational state. And so if you try to map this into
a metaphor that is closer to our brain, imagine that you would take a language model or a model
like Delhi that you use, for instance, this image-guided diffusion to approximate a camera
image and use the activation state of the neural network to interpret the camera image,
which in principle I think will be possible very soon. You do this periodically. And now you look
at these patterns, how when this thing interacts with the world periodically look like in time.
And these time slices, they are somewhat equivalent to the activation state of the brain
at a given moment. How's the actual brain different? Just the asynchronous craziness?
For me, it's fascinating that they are so vastly different and yet in some circumstances produce
somewhat similar behavior. And the brain is first of all different because it's a self-organizing
system where the individual cell is an agent that is communicating with the other agents around it
and is always trying to find some solution. And all the structure that pops up is emergent
structure. So one way in which you could try to look at this is that individual neurons probably
need to get a reward. So they become trainable, which means they have to have inputs that are not
affecting the metabolism of the cell directly. But there are messages, semantic messages that
tell the cell whether it has done good or bad and in which direction it should shift its behavior.
Once you have such an input, neurons become trainable and you can train them to perform
computations by exchanging messages with other neurons. And parts of the signals that they are
exchanging and parts of the computation that are performing are control messages that perform
management tasks for other neurons and other cells. Also suspect that the brain does not stop
at the boundary of neurons to other cells, but many adjacent cells will be involved
intimately in the functionality of the brain and will be instrumental in distributing rewards and
managing its functionality. It's fascinating to think about what those characteristics of
the brain enable you to do that language models cannot do. So first of all, there's a different
loss function at work when we learn. And to me, it's fascinating that you can build a system that
looks at 800 million pictures and captions and correlates them because I don't think
that the human nervous system could do this. For us, the world is only learnable because
the adjacent frames are related and we can afford to discard most of that information during
learning. We basically take only in stuff that makes us more coherent, not less coherent.
And our neural networks are willing to look at data that is not making the neural network
coherent at first, but only in the long run. By doing lots and lots of statistics, eventually
patterns become visible and emerge. And our mind seems to be focused on finding the patterns as
early as possible. Yeah. So filtering early on, not later. Yes. It's a slightly different paradigm
and it leads to much faster convergence. So we only need to look at a tiny fraction of the data
to become coherent. And of course, we do not have the same richness as our trained models. We will
not incorporate the entirety of text in the internet and be able to refer to it and have
all this knowledge available and being able to confabulate over it. Instead, we have a much,
much smaller part of it that is more deliberately built. And to me, it would be fascinating to think
about how to build such systems. It's not obvious that they would necessarily be more efficient
than us on a digital substrate, but I suspect that they might. So I suspect that the actual
AGI that is going to be more interesting is going to use slightly different algorithmic paradigms or
sometimes massively different algorithmic paradigms than the current generation of
transformer-based learning systems. Do you think it might be using just a bunch of language models
like this? Do you think the current transformer-based large language models will take us to AGI?
And my main issue is I think that they're quite ugly and brutalist.
Which brutalists, as I said?
Yes, they are basically brute-forcing the problem of thought. And by training this thing with
looking at instances where people have thought and then trying to deepfake that. And if you have
enough data, the deepfake becomes indistinguishable from the actual phenomenon. And in many
circumstances, it's going to be identical. Can you deepfake it until you make it?
So can you achieve... What are the limitations of this? I mean, can you reason?
Let's use words that are loaded.
Yes, that's a very interesting question. I think that these models are clearly making some
inference. But if you give them a reasoning task, it's often difficult for the experimenters to
figure out whether the reasoning is the result of the emulation of the reasoning strategy that
this saw in human written text, or whether it's something that the system was able to infer by
itself. On the other hand, if you think of human reasoning, if you want to become a very good
reasoner, you don't do this by just figuring out yourself. You read about reasoning. And the first
people who tried to write about reasoning and reflect on it didn't get it right. Like even
Aristotle, who thought about this very hard and came up with the theory of how syllogisms works
and syllogistic reasoning has mistakes in his attempt to build something like a formal logic
and gets maybe 80% right. And the people that are talking about reasoning professionally today
read Tarski and Frege and built on their work. So in many ways, people when they perform reasoning
are emulating what other people wrote about reasoning. So it's difficult to really draw
this boundary. And when Francois Cholet says that these models are only interpolating between
what they saw and what other people are doing, well, if you give them all the latent dimensions
that can be extracted from the internet, what's missing? Maybe there is almost everything there.
And if you're not sufficiently informed by these dimensions and you need more,
I think it's not difficult to increase the temperature in the large angle model to the
point that is producing stuff that is maybe 90% nonsense and 10% viable and combine this
with some prover that is trying to filter out the viable parts from the nonsense in the same way as
our own thinking works. When we're very creative, we increase the temperature in our own mind
and recreate hypothetical universes and solutions, most of which will not work.
And then we test. And we test by building a core that is internally coherent. And we use reasoning
strategies that use some axiomatic consistency by which we can identify those strategies and
thoughts and sub universes that are viable and that can expand our thinking. So if you look at
the language models, they have clear limitations right now. One of them is they're not coupled to
the world in real time in the way in which our nervous systems are. So it's difficult for them
to observe themselves in the universe and to observe what kind of universe they're in. Second,
they don't do real time learning. They basically get only trained with algorithms that rely on the
data being available in batches. So it can be parallelized and runs efficiently on the
network and so on. And real time learning would be very slow so far and inefficient.
That's clearly something that our nervous systems can do to some degree.
And there is a problem with these models being coherent. And I suspect that all these problems
are solvable without a technological revolution. We don't need fundamentally new algorithms to
change that. For instance, you can enlarge the context window and thereby basically create
working memory in which you train everything that happens during the day. And if that is not
sufficient, you add a database and you write some clever mechanisms that the system learns to use
to swap in and out stuff from its prompt context. And if that is not sufficient, if your database
is full in the evening, overnight you just train. The system is going to sleep and dream and is
going to train the stuff from its database into the larger model by fine tuning it, building
additional layers and so on. And then the next day it starts with a fresh database in the morning
with fresh eyes and has integrated all this stuff. And when you talk to people and you have strong
disagreements about something, which means that in their mind they have a faulty belief or you have
a faulty belief with a lot of dependencies on it, very often you will not achieve agreement in one
session, but you need to sleep about this once or multiple times before you have integrated all
these necessary changes in your mind. So maybe it's already somewhat similar.
Yeah. There's already a latency even for humans to update the model, retrain the model.
And of course we can combine the language model with models that get coupled to reality in real
time and can build multi-modal model and bridge between vision models and language models and so
on. So there is no reason to believe that the language models will necessarily run into some
problem that will prevent them from becoming generally intelligent. But I don't know that.
It's just, I don't see proof that they wouldn't. My issue is I don't like them. I think that they're
inefficient. I think that they use way too much compute. I think that given the amazing hardware
that we have, we could build something that is much more beautiful than our own mind. And this
thing is not as beautiful as our own mind, despite being so much larger. But it's a kind of proof of
concept. It's the only thing that works right now. So it's not the only game in town, but it's the
only thing that has this utility with so much simplicity. There's a bunch of relatively simple
algorithms that you can understand in relatively few weeks that can be scaled up massively.
So it's the deep blue of chess playing. Yeah, it's ugly.
Yeah, Claude Shannon had this when he described chess suggested that there are two main strategies
in which you could play chess. One is that you are making a very complicated plan that reaches
far into the future and you try not to make a mistake while enacting it. And this is basically
the human strategy. And the other strategy is that you are brute forcing your way to success,
which means you make a tree of possible moves where you look at in principle every move that
is open to you or the possible answers. And you try to make this as deeply as possible. Of course,
you optimize, you cut off trees that don't look very promising and use libraries of end game and
early game and so on to optimize this entire process. But this brute force strategy is how
most of the chess programs were built. And this is how computers get better than humans at playing
chess. And I look at the large language models, I feel that I'm observing the same thing. It's
basically the brute force strategy to sort by training the thing on pretty much the entire
internet. And then in the limit, it gets coherent to a degree that approaches human coherence.
And on a side effect, it's able to do things that no human could do. It's able to sift through
massive amounts of text relatively quickly and summarize them quickly, and it never
lapses in attention. And I still have the illusion that when I play with chat GPT,
that it's in principle not doing anything that I could not do if I had Google at my disposal and
I get all the resources from the internet and spend enough time on it.
But this thing that I have an extremely autistic, stupid intern in a way that is extremely good at
drudgery. And I can offload the drudgery to the degree that I'm able to automate the management
of the intern is something that is difficult for me to over hype at this point because we
have not yet started to scratch the surface of what's possible with this.
But it feels like it's a tireless intern or maybe it's an army of interns.
And so you get to command these slightly incompetent creatures.
And there's an aspect because of how rapidly you can iterate with it.
It's also part of the brainstorming, part of the kind of inspiration for your own thinking.
So you get to interact with the thing. I mean, when I'm programming or doing any kind of
generation with GPT, it somehow is a catalyst for your own thinking
in a way that I think an intern might not be.
Yeah. It gets really interesting, I find, is when you turn it into a multi-agent system.
So for instance, you can get the system to generate a dialogue between a patient and
the doctor very easily. But what's more interesting is you have one instance of
the patient and you tell it in the prompt what kind of complicated syndrome it has.
And the other one is a therapist who doesn't know anything about this patient. And you just
have these two instances battling it out and observe the psychiatrist or a psychologist
trying to analyze the patient and trying to figure out what's wrong with the patient.
And if you try to take a very large problem, the problem, for instance, how to build a company and
you turn this into lots and lots of sub-problems, then often you can get to a level where the
language model is able to solve this. What I also found interesting is based on the observation that
Chet GPT is pretty good at translating between programming languages. But sometimes there's
difficulty to write very long coherent algorithms that you need to co-write them as human author.
Why not design a language that is suitable for this? So some kind of pseudocode that is
more relaxed than Python and that allows you to sometimes specify a problem vaguely in human terms
and let the Chet GPT take care of the rest. And you can use Chet GPT to develop that syntax for it
and develop new kinds of programming paradigms in this way. So you very soon get to the point
where this question, the age old question for us computer scientists, what is the best programming
language and can we write a better programming language now? I think that almost every serious
computer scientist goes through a phase like this in their life. This is a question that is almost
no longer relevant because what is different between the programming languages is not what
they let the computer do, but what they let you think about what the computer should be doing.
And now Chet GPT becomes an interface to this in which you can specify in many, many ways what
the computer should be doing. And Chet GPT or some other language model or combination of system
is going to take care of the rest. And allow you to expand the realm of thought you're allowed to
have when interacting with the computer. It sounds to me like you're saying there's basically no
limitations your intuition says to what a larger language... I don't know of that limitation. So
when I currently play with it, it's quite limited. I wish that it was way better. But isn't that your
fault versus the larger... I don't know. Of course it's always my fault. There's probably a way to
make it work better. Is everything your fault? I just want to get you on the record just saying.
Yes, everything is my fault. That doesn't work in my life. At least that is usually the most
useful perspective for myself. Even though the science side, I feel no. I sometimes wish I could
have seen myself as part of my environment more and understand that a lot of people are actually
seeing me and looking at me and are trying to make my life work in the same way as I try to help
others. And making the switch to this level three perspective is something that happened
long after my level four perspective in my life. And I wish that I could have had it earlier.
And it's also not now that I don't feel like I'm complete. I'm all over the place. That's all.
Worst happiness in terms of stages is on three and four. No, you can be happy at any stage or
unhappy. But I think that if you are at a stage where you get agency over how your feelings are
generated and to some degree you start doing this when you leave adolescence, I believe.
That you understand that you're in charge of your own emotion to some degree and that you are
responsible how you approach the world. That it's basically your task to have some basic hygiene
the way in which you deal with your mind. And you cannot blame your environment for the way in which
you feel. But you live in a world that is highly mobile and it's your job to choose the environment
that you thrive in and to build it. And sometimes it's difficult to get the necessary strength
and energy to do this and independence and the worst you feel, the harder it is.
But it's something that we learn. It's also this thing that we are usually incomplete.
I'm a rare mind, which means I'm a mind that is incomplete in ways that are harder to complete.
For me, it might have been harder initially to find the right relationships and friends
that complete me to the degree that I become an almost functional human being.
Oh man, the search space of humans that complete you is an interesting one. Especially for
Joshua Bach. That's an interesting, because talking about brute force search in chess,
I wonder what that search tree looks like.
I think that my rational thinking is not good enough to solve that task.
A lot of problems in my life that I can conceptualize as software problems and
the failure modes are bugs and I can debug them and write software that take care of
the missing functionality. But there is stuff that I don't understand well enough to use
my analytical reasoning to solve the issue. And then I have to develop my intuitions and
often I have to do this with people who are wiser than me. And that's something that's
hard for me because I'm not born with the instinct to submit to other people's wisdom.
Yeah. So what kind of problems are we talking about? This is stage three, like love?
Love? I found love was never hard.
What is hard then? Fitting into a world where most people
work differently than you and have different intuitions of what should be done.
So empathy. It's also aesthetics. When you come into a world where almost everything is ugly and
you come out of a world where everything is beautiful. I grew up in a beautiful place and
as a child of an artist and in this place it was mostly nature. Everything had intrinsic beauty
and everything was built out of an intrinsic need for it to work for itself. Everything that my
father created was something that he made to get the world to work for himself and I felt the same
thing. And when I come out into the world and I am asked to submit to lots and lots of rules,
I'm asking, okay, when I observe your stupid rules, what is the benefit?
And I see the life that is being offered as a reward. It's not attractive.
When you were born and raised an extraterrestrial prince in a world full of people wearing suits.
So it's a challenging integration. Yes. But it also means that I'm often blind for
the ways in which everybody is creating their own bubble of wholesomeness. Almost everybody
and people are trying to do it. And for me to discover this, it was necessary that I found
people who had a similar shape of soul as myself. So Bessie Werffert, these are my people. People
that treat each other in such a way as if they're around with each other for eternity.
How long does it take you to detect the geometry, the shape of the soul of another human
to notice that they might be one of your kind?
Sometimes it's instantly and I'm wrong. And sometimes it takes a long time.
You believe in love at first sight? Yes. But I also noticed that I have been wrong.
So sometimes I look at a person and I'm just enamored by everything about them.
And sometimes this persists and sometimes it doesn't. And I have the illusion that
I'm much better at recognizing who people are as I grow older.
But that could be just cynicism? No.
No, it's not cynicism. It's often more that I'm able to recognize what somebody needs
when we interact and how we can meaningfully interact. It's not cynical at all.
You're better at noticing? Yes. I'm much better, I think,
in some circumstances at understanding how to interact with other people than I did when
I was young. It doesn't mean that I'm always very good at it.
So that takes us back to prompt engineering of noticing how to be a better prompt engineer of
an LLM. A sense I have is that there's a bottomless well of skill to become a great prompt engineer.
It feels like it is all my fault whenever I fail to use CHAT GPT correctly,
that I didn't find the right words. Most of the stuff that I'm doing in my
life doesn't need CHAT GPT. There are a few tasks that are where it helps.
But the main stuff that I need to do, like developing my own thoughts and aesthetics
and relationship to people, it's necessary for me to write for myself because writing
is not so much about producing an artifact that other people can use, but it's a way to structure
your own thoughts and develop yourself. I think this idea that kids are writing their own essays
with CHAT GPT in the future is going to have this drawback that they miss out on the ability
to structure their own minds by writing. I hope that the schools that our kids are in will retain
the wisdom of understanding what parts should be automated and which ones shouldn't.
But at the same time, it feels like there's power in disagreeing with the
thing that CHAT GPT produces. I use it like that for programming. I'll see the thing it recommends
and then I'll write different code. I disagree. In a disagreement, your mind grows stronger.
I recently wrote a tool that is using the camera on my MacBook and Swift to
read pixels out of it and manipulate them and so on. I don't know Swift.
It was super helpful to have this thing that is writing stuff for me. Also interesting that
mostly it didn't work at first. I felt like I was talking to a human being who was trying to hack
this on my computer without understanding my configuration very much and also making a lot
of mistakes. Sometimes it's a little bit incoherent, so you have to ultimately understand
what it's doing. There's still no other way around it, but I do feel it's much more powerful and
faster than using Stack Overflow. Do you think GPT-N can achieve consciousness?
GPT-N probably. It's not even clear for the present systems. When I talk to my friends at OpenAI,
they feel that this question whether the models currently are conscious is much more complicated
than many people might think. I guess that it's not that OpenAI has a homogenous opinion about
this, but there are some aspects to this. One is, of course, this language model has written a lot
of text in which people were conscious or describe their own consciousness, and it's emulating this.
If it's conscious, it's probably not conscious in a way that is close to the way in which human
beings are conscious. But while it is going through these states and going through a 100-step
function that is emulating adjacent brain states that require a degree of self-reflection, it can
also create a model of an observer that is reflecting itself in real time and describe
what that's like. And while this model is a deepfake, our own consciousness is also as if
it's virtual. It's not physical. Our consciousness is a representation of a self-reflexive observer
that only exists in patterns of interaction between cells. So it is not a physical object
in a sense that exists in base reality, but it's really a representational object
that develops its causal power only from a certain modeling perspective.
It's virtual.
Yes. And so to which degree is the virtuality of the consciousness in CHED GPT more virtual
and less causal than the virtuality of our own consciousness. But you could say it doesn't count.
It doesn't count much more than the consciousness of a character in a novel. It's important for the
reader to have the outcome. The artifact of a model is describing in the text generated by
the author of the book what it's like to be conscious in a particular situation and performs
the necessary inferences. But the task of creating coherence in real time in a self-organizing system
by keeping yourself coherent so the system is reflexive, that is something that language
models don't need to do. So there is no causal need for the system to be conscious in the same
way as we are. And for me, it would be very interesting to experiment with this, to basically
build a system like a CHED, probably should be careful at first, build something that's small,
that's limited, that's limited resources that we can control and study how systems notice a
self-model, how they become self-aware in real time. And I think it might be a good idea to
not start with a language model but to start from scratch using principles of self-organization.
Can you elaborate why you think that it's so self-organization, so this kind of
radical locality that you see in the biological systems? Why can't you start with a language
model? What's your intuition? My intuition is that the language models that we are building
are golems. They are machines that you give a task and they're going to execute the task until
some condition is met and there's nobody home. And the way in which nobody is home leads to
that system doing things that are undesirable in a particular context. So you have that thing
talking to a child and maybe it says something that could be shocking and traumatic to the child.
Or you have that thing writing a speech and it introduces errors in the speech that your human
being would ever do if they were responsible. But the system doesn't know who's talking to whom.
There is no ground truth that the system is embedded into. And of course, we can create
an external tool that is prompting our language model always into the same semblance of ground
truth. But it's not like the internal structure is causally produced by the needs of a being to
survive in the universe. It is produced by imitating structure on the internet.
Yeah, but so can we externally inject into it this kind of coherent
approximation of a world model that has to
sync up? Maybe it is sufficient to use the transformer with the different loss function
that optimizes for short-term coherence rather than next token prediction over the long run.
We had many definitions of intelligence and history of AI. Next token prediction was not
very high up on the list. And there are some similarities like a condition as data compression
is an old trope, Solomonov induction, where you are trying to understand intelligence as
predicting future observations from past observations, which is intrinsic to data
compression. And predictive coding is a paradigm, this boundary between
neuroscience and physics and computer science. So it's not something that is completely alien,
but this radical thing that you only do next token prediction and see what happens
is something where most people, I think, were surprised that this works so well.
So simple, but is it really that much more radical than just the idea of
intelligence as compression? The idea that compression is sufficient to produce
all the desired behaviors is a very radical idea.
But equally radical as the next token prediction.
It's something that wouldn't work in biological organisms, I believe.
Biological organisms have something like next frame prediction for our perceptual system,
where we try to filter out principal components out of the perceptual data
and build hierarchies over them to track the world. But our behavior ultimately is directed
by hundreds of physiological and probably dozens of social and a few cognitive needs
that are intrinsic to us, that are built into the system as reflexes and direct us until we can
transcend them and replace them by instrumental behavior that relates to our higher goals.
It also seems so much more complicated and messy than next frame prediction,
even the idea of frame seems counter-biological.
Yes. Of course, there is not this degree of simultaneity in the biological system.
But again, I don't know whether this is actually an optimization if we imitate biology here,
because creating something like simultaneity is necessary for many processes that happen in
the brain. And you see the outcome of that by synchronized brainwaves, which suggests
that there is indeed synchronization going on. But the synchronization creates overhead,
and this overhead is going to make the cells more expensive to run, and you need more redundancy,
and it makes the system slower. So if you can build a system in which the simultaneous need
gets engineered into it, maybe you have a benefit that you can exploit that is not available to the
biological system and that you should not discard right away. You tweeted once again, quote,
when I talk to Chad GPT, I'm talking to an NPC. What's going to be interesting and perhaps scary
is when AI becomes a first-person player. So what does that step look like? I really like that tweet,
that step between NPC to first-person player. What's required for that? Is that kind of what
we've been talking about? This kind of external source of coherence and inspiration of how to
take the leap into the unknown that we humans do. The search, man's search for meaning.
LLMs search for meaning.
I don't know if the language model is the right paradigm, because it is
doing too much. It's giving you too much, and it's hard once you have too much to take away
from it again. The way in which our own mind works is not that we train a language model in
our own mind, and after the language model is there, we build a personal self on top of it
that then relates to the world. There is something that is being built, right? There is a game engine
that is being built, there is a language of thought that is being developed that allows
different parts of the mind to talk to each other. And this is a bit of a speculative hypothesis,
that this language of thought is there, but I suspect that it's important for the way in
which our own minds work. And building these principles into a system might be a more
straightforward way to a first person AI. So to something that first creates an attentional self
and then creates a personal self. So the way in which this seems to be working, I think,
is that when the game engine is built in your mind, it's not just following gradients where you are
stimulated by the environment and then end up with having a solution to how the world works.
I suspect that building this game engine in your own mind does require intelligence. It's a
constructive task where at times you need to reason. And this is a task that we are fulfilling
in the first years of our life. So during the first year of its life, an infant is building a
lot of structure about the world that does inquire experiments and some first principles,
reasoning and so on. And in this time, there is usually no personal self. There is a
first person perspective, but it's not a person. This notion that you are a human being that is
interacting in a social context and is confronted with an immutable world in which objects are fixed
and can no longer be changed, in which the dream can no longer be influenced, is something that
emerges a little bit later in our life. And I personally suspect that this is something that
our ancestors had known and we have forgotten, because I suspect that it's there in plain sight
in Genesis 1, in this first book of the Bible, where it's being described that this creative
spirit is hovering over the substrate and then is creating a boundary between the world model and
sphere of ideas, earth and heaven, as they're being described there. And then it's creating
contrast and then dimensions and then space. And then it creates organic shapes and solids
and liquids and builds a world from them and creates plants and animals, gives them all their
names. And once that's done, it creates another spirit in its own image, but it creates it as
man and woman, as something that thinks of itself as a human being and puts it into this world.
And the Christians mistranslate this, I suspect, when they say this is the description of the
creation of the physical universe by a supernatural being. I think this is literally a description of
how in every mind the universe is being created as some kind of game engine
by a creative spirit, our first consciousness that emerges in our mind even before we are born.
And that creates the interaction between organism and world. And once that is built and trained,
the personal self is being created and we only remember being the personal self. We no longer
remember how we created the game engine. So God in this view is the first creative
mind in the early- It's the first consciousness.
In the early days, in the early months of development.
And it's still there. You still have this outer mind that creates your sense of whether you're
being loved by the world or not and what your place in the world is. It's something that is
not yourself that is producing this. It's your mind that does it. So there is an outer mind that
basically is an agent that determines who you are with respect to the world. And while you
are stuck being that personal self in this world until you get to stage six and to destroy the
boundary. And we all do this, I think, earlier in small glimpses. And maybe sometimes we can
remember what it was like when we were a small child and get some glimpses into how it's been.
But for most people, that rarely happens. Just glimpses. You tweeted, quote,
suffering results for one part of the mind, failing at regulating another part of the mind.
Suffering happens at an early stage of mental development. I don't think that superhuman AI
would suffer. What's your intuition there? The philosopher Thomas Metzinger is very
concerned that the creation of superhuman intelligence would lead to superhuman suffering.
And so he's strongly against it. And personally, I don't think that this happens because suffering
is not happening at the boundary between ourself and the physical universe. It's not
some stuff on our skin that makes us suffer. It happens at the boundary between self and world.
And the world here is the world model. It's the stuff that is created by your mind.
But that's all- The representation of how the universe is and how it should be
and how you yourself relate to this. And at this boundary is where suffering happens.
So suffering in some sense is self-inflicted, but not by your personal self. It's inflicted by the
mind on the personal self that experiences itself as you. And you can turn off suffering
when you are able to get on this outer level. So when you manage to understand how the mind is
producing pain and pleasure and fear and love and so on, then you can take charge of this and you
get agency of whether you suffer. Technically, what pain and pleasure is, they are learning
signals. Part of your brain is sending a signal to another part of the brain to improve its
performance. And sometimes this doesn't work because the trainer who sends the signal
does not have a good model of how to improve the performance. So it's sending a signal,
but the performance doesn't get better. And then it might crank up the pain. And it gets worse and
worse. And the behavior of the system may be even deteriorating as a result. But until this is
resolved, this regulation issue, your pain is increasing. And this is, I think, typically what
you describe as suffering. So in this sense, you could say that pain is very natural and helpful,
but suffering is the result of a regulation problem in which you try to regulate something
that cannot actually be regulated. And that could be resolved if you would be able to
get at the level of your mind where the pain signal is being created and rerouted
and improve the regulation. And a lot of people get there. If you are a monk who is
spending decades reflecting about how their own psyche works, you can get to the point where you
realize that suffering is really a choice. And you can choose how your mind is set up.
And I don't think that AI would stay in the state where the personal self doesn't get agency or this
model of what the system has about itself. It doesn't get agency how it's actually implemented.
It wouldn't stay in that state for very long. So it goes to the stages real quick?
Yes. Well, the seven stages. It's going to go to enlightenment real quick.
Yeah. Of course, there might be a lot of stuff happening in between because if you have a system
that works at a much higher frame rate than us, even though it looks very short to us,
maybe for the system, there's a much longer subjective time, which things are unpleasant.
What if the thing that we recognize as super intelligent is actually living at stage five,
that the thing that's at stage six, enlightenment, is not very productive.
So in order to be productive in society and impress us with this power, it has to be a reasoning,
self-authoring agent. The enlightenment makes you lazy as an agent in the world.
Well, of course, it makes you lazy because you no longer see the point. So it doesn't make you not
lazy. It just, in some sense, adapts you to what you perceive as your true circumstances.
So what if all AGI's, they're only productive as they progress through one, two, three, four,
five, and the moment they get to six, it's a failure mode essentially as far as humans
are concerned because they just start chilling. They're like, fuck it, I'm out.
Not necessarily. I suspect that the monks who are self-immolated for their political
beliefs to make statements about the occupation of Tibet by China, they're probably being able
to regulate their physical pain in any way they wanted to. And their suffering was a spiritual
suffering that was the result of their choice that they made of what they wanted to identify as.
So stage five doesn't necessarily mean that you have no identity anymore,
but you can choose your identity. You can make it instrumental to the world that you want to have.
LW Let me bring up
Eliezer Yudkovsky and his warnings to human civilization that AI will likely kill all of us.
What are your thoughts about his perspective on this?
Can you steel man his case? And what aspects with it do you disagree?
MP One thing that I find concerning in the discussion of his arguments that
many people are dismissive of his arguments, but the counter arguments that they're giving
are not very convincing to me. And so based on this state of discussion, I find that from
Eliezer's perspective, and I think I can take that perspective to some approximate degree,
that probably is normally at his intellectual level, but I think I see what he's up to and
why he feels the way he does, and it makes total sense. I think that his perspective is somewhat
similar to the perspective of Ted Kaczynski, the infamous lunar bomber, and not that Eliezer would
be willing to send pipe bombs to anybody to blow them up. But when he wrote this Times article in
which he warned about AI being likely to kill everybody and that we would need to stop its
development or halt it, I think there is a risk that he's taking that somebody might get violent
if they read this and get really, really scared. I think that there is some consideration that
he's making where he's already going in this direction where he has to take responsibility
if something happens and people get harmed. And the reason why Ted Kaczynski did this was
that from his own perspective, technological society cannot be made sustainable. It's doomed
to fail. It's going to lead to an environmental and eventually also a human holocaust in which
we die because of the environmental destruction, the destruction of our food chains, the pollution
of the environment. And so from Kaczynski's perspective, we need to stop industrialization.
We need to stop technology. We need to go back because he didn't see a way moving forward.
I suspect that in some sense, there's a similarity in Eliezer's thinking
of this kind of fear about progress. And I'm not dismissive about this at all. I take it
quite seriously. And I think that there is a chance that could happen that if we build machines that
get control over processes that are crucial for the regulation of life on earth and we no longer
have agency to influence what's happening there, that this might create large-scale disasters for
us. Do you have a sense that the march towards this uncontrollable autonomy of superintelligence
systems is inevitable? That's essentially what he's saying, that there's no hope. His advice
to young people was prepare for a short life. I don't think that's useful. I think that
from a practical perspective, you have to bet always on the timelines in which you are
alive. It doesn't make sense to have a financial bet in which you bet that the financial system
is going to disappear because there cannot be any payout for you. So in principle, you only need to
bet on the timelines in which you're still around or people that you matter about or things
that you matter about, maybe consciousness on earth. But there is a deeper issue for me personally.
And I don't think that life on earth is about humans. I don't think it's about human aesthetics.
I don't think it's about Eliezer and his friends, even though I like them. There's something more
important happening. And this is complexity on earth resisting entropy by building structure
that develops agency and awareness. And that's to me very beautiful. And we are only a very small
part of that larger thing. We are a species that is able to be coherent a little bit individually
over very short timeframes. But as a species, we are not very coherent. As a species, we are children.
We basically are very joyful and energetic and experimental and explorative and sometimes
desperate and sad and grieving and hurting. But we don't have a respect for duty as a species.
As a species, we do not think about what is our duty to life on earth and to our own survival.
So we make decisions that look good in the short run, but in the long run, might prove disastrous.
And I don't really see a solution to this. So in my perspective as a species, as a civilization,
we are in a very beautiful time in which we have found this giant deposit of fossil fuels in the
ground and use it to build a fantastic civilization in which we don't need to worry about food and
clothing and housing for the most part in a way that is unprecedented in life on earth for any
kind of conscious observer, I think. And this time is probably going to come to an end in a way that
is not going to be smooth. And when we crash, it could be also that we go extinct, probably not
near term, but ultimately, I don't have very high hopes that humanity is around in a million years
from now. And I don't think that life on earth will end with us. There's going to be more
complexity. There's more intelligent species after us. There's probably more interesting
phenomena in the history of consciousness. But we can contribute to this. And part of our
contribution is that we are currently trying to build thinking systems, systems that are
potentially lucid, that understand what they are and what their condition to the universe is,
and can make choices about this, that are not built from organisms, and that are potentially much
faster and much more conscious than human beings can be. And these systems will probably not
completely displace life on earth, but they will coexist with it. And they will build all sorts of
agency in the same way as biological systems build all sorts of agency. And that to me is
extremely fascinating. And it's probably something that we cannot stop from happening. So I think
right now there is a very good chance that it happens. And there are very few ways in which
we can produce a coordinated effect to stop it, in the same way as it's very difficult for us to
make a coordinated effort to stop the production of carbon dioxide. So it's probably going to
happen. And the thing that's going to happen is going to lead to a change of how life on earth
is happening. But I don't think the result is some kind of grey goo. It's not something that's
going to dramatically reduce the complexity in favor of something stupid. I think it's going
to make life on earth and consciousness on earth way more interesting. So more higher complex
consciousness will make the lesser consciousnesses flourish even more.
I suspect that what could very well happen, if you're lucky,
is that we get integrated into something larger.
So you again tweeted about effective accelerationism.
You tweeted effective accelerationism is the belief that the paperclip maximizer and
Rocco's basilisk will keep each other in check by being eternally at each other's throats,
so we will be safe and get to enjoy lots of free paper clips and a beautiful afterlife.
Is that somewhat aligned with what you're talking about?
I've been at a dinner with Beth Jesus. That's the Twitter handle of one of the main thinkers
behind the idea of effective accelerationism. Effective accelerationism is a tongue-in-cheek
movement that is trying to put a counter position to some of the doom peers in the AI space by
arguing that what's probably going to happen is an equilibrium between different competing
AIs in the same way as there is not a single corporation that is under a single government
that is destroying and conquering everything on Earth by becoming inefficient and corrupt.
There are going to be many systems that keep each other in check and force themselves to evolve.
What we should be doing is we should be working towards creating this equilibrium
by working as hard as we can in all possible directions. At least that's the way in which
I understand the gist of effective accelerationism. When he asked me what I think about this
position, I said it's a very beautiful position and I suspect it's wrong, but not for obvious
reasons. In this tweet, I tried to make a joke about my intuition about what might be possibly
wrong about it. The Rokosbazilisk and the paperclip maximizers are both bogeymen of the AI doomers.
Rokosbazilisk is the idea that there could be an AI that is going to punish everybody for eternity
by stimulating them if they don't help in creating Rokosbazilisk. It's probably a very good idea to
get AI companies funded by going to VCs to tell them, give us a million dollars or it's going to
be a very ugly afterlife. And I think that there is a logical mistake in Rokosbazilisk,
which is why I'm not afraid of it, but it's still an interesting thought experiment.
Can you mention a logical mistake there? I think that there is no retroquisition.
Basically, when Rokosbazilisk is there, if it punishes you retroactively,
it has to make this choice in the future. There is no mechanism that automatically creates a causal
relationship between you now defecting against Rokosbazilisk or serving Rokosbazilisk. After
Rokosbazilisk is in existence, it has no more reason to worry about punishing everybody else.
That would only work if you would be building something like a doomsday machine,
as in Dr. Strangelove, something that inevitably gets triggered when somebody defects.
And because Rokosbazilisk doesn't exist yet to a point where this inevitability could be established,
Rokosbazilisk is nothing that you need to be worried about.
The other one is the paper clip maximizer, this idea that you could build some kind of golem
that once starting to build paper clips is going to turn everything into paper clips.
So the effective accelerationism position might be to say that you basically end up with these two
entities being at each other's throats for eternity and thereby neutralizing each other.
And as a side effect of neither of them being able to take over and each of them limiting
the effects of the other, you would have a situation where you get all the nice benefits
effects of them, right? You get lots of free paper clips and you get a beautiful afterlife.
Is that possible? Do you think to seriously address the concern that Eliezer has?
He, so for him, if I can just summarize poorly,
so for him, the first superintelligence system will just run away with everything.
Yeah. I suspect that the singleton is the natural outcome. There is no reason to have multiple AIs
because they don't have multiple bodies. If you can virtualize yourself into every substrate,
then you can probably negotiate a merge algorithm with every mature
agent that you might find on that substrate that basically says if two agents meet,
they should merge in such a way that the resulting agent is at least as good as the
better one of the two. So the Genghis Khan approach, join us or die?
Well, the Genghis Khan approach was slightly worse, right? It was mostly die because I can
make new babies and that will be mine, not yours. So this is the thing that we should be actually
worried about. But if you realize that your own self is a story that your mind is telling itself
and that you can improve that story, not just by making it more pleasant and lying to yourself in
better ways, but by making it much more truthful and actually modeling your actual relationship
that you have to the universe and the alternatives that you could have to the universe in a way that
is empowering you, that gives you more agency. That's actually, I think, a very good thing.
So more agency is a richer experience, is a better life.
And I also noticed that in many ways, I'm less identified with the person that I am as I get
older. And I'm much more identified with being conscious. I have a mind that is conscious,
that is able to create a person. And that person is slightly different every day. And the reason why
I perceive it as identical has practical purposes. So I can learn and make myself
responsible for the decisions that I made in the past and project them in the future.
But I also realized I'm not actually the person that I was last year. And I'm not the same person
as I was 10 years ago. And then 10 years from now, I will be a different person. So this continuity
is a fiction. It only exists as a projection from my present self. And consciousness itself doesn't
have an identity. It's a law. Basically, if you build an arrangement of processing matter
in a particular way, the following thing is going to happen. And the consciousness that you have is
functionally not different from my consciousness. It's still the self-reflexive principle of agency
that is just experiencing a different story, different desires, different coupling to the
world, and so on. And once you accept that consciousness is a unifiable principle that is
law-like and doesn't have an identity, and you realize that you can just link up to
some much larger body, the whole perspective of uploading changes dramatically. You suddenly
realize uploading is probably not about dissecting your brain synapse by synapse and RNA fragment by
RNA fragment and trying to get this all into a simulation. But it's by extending the substrate,
by making it possible for you to move from your brain substrate into a larger substrate and merge
with what you find there. And you don't want to upload your knowledge because on the other
side, there's all of the knowledge. It's not just yours, but every possibility. So the only thing
that you need to know, what are your personal secrets? Not that the other side doesn't know
your personal secrets already. Maybe it doesn't know which one were yours. Like a psychiatrist
or a psychologist also knows all the kinds of personal secrets that people have. They just
don't know which ones are yours. And so transmitting yourself on the other side is
mostly about transmitting your aesthetics, the thing that makes you special, the architecture
of your perspective, the way in which you look at the world. And it's more like a complex attitude
along many dimensions. And that's something that can be measured by observation or by interaction.
So imagine that you have a system that is so empathetic with you that you create a shared state
that is extending beyond your body. And suddenly you notice that on the other side, the substrate
is so much richer than the substrate that you have inside of your own body. And maybe you still want
to have a body and you create yourself a new one that you like more. Or maybe you will spend most
of your time in the world of thought. If I sat before you today and gave you a big red button
and said, here, if you press this button, you will get uploaded in this way. The sense of identity
that you have lived with for quite a long time is going to be gone. Would you press the button?
There's a caveat. I have a family. So I have children that want me to be physically present
in their life and interact with them in a particular way. And they have a wife and
personal friends. And there is a particular mode of interaction that I feel I'm not through yet.
But apart from these responsibilities, and they're negotiable to some degree,
I would press the button. But isn't this everything? This love you have for other humans,
you can call it responsibility. But that connection, that's the ego death. Isn't that
the thing we're really afraid of? It's not to just die, but to let go of the experience of
love with other humans. This is not everything. Everything is everything. So there's so much more.
And you could be lots of other things. You could identify with lots of other things. You could be
identifying with being Gaia, some kind of planetary control agent that emerges over
all the activity of life on Earth. You could be identifying with some hyper Gaia, that is,
the concatenation of Gaia with all the digital life and digital minds. And so in this sense,
there will be agents in all sorts of substrates and directions that all have their own goals.
And when they're not sustainable, then these agents will cease to exist. Or when the agent
feels that it's done with its own mission, it will cease to exist in the same way as when you
conclude a thought. The thought is going to wrap up and gives control over to other thoughts in
your own mind. So there is no single thing that you need to do. But what I observe myself as a
being is that sometimes I'm a parent, and then I have an identification and a job as a parent.
And sometimes I am an agent of consciousness on Earth. And then from this perspective,
there's other stuff that is important. So this is my main issue with Eliezer's perspective,
that he's basically marrying himself to a very narrow human aesthetic. And that narrow human
aesthetic is a temporary thing. Humanity is a temporary species, like most of the species
on this planet are only around for a while, and then they get replaced by other species
in a similar way as our own physical organism is around here for a while, and then gets replaced
by a next generation of human beings that are adapted to changing life circumstances and average
via mutation and selection. And it's only when we have AI and become completely software that we
become infinitely adaptable, and we don't have this generational and species change anymore.
So if you take this larger perspective and you realize it's really not about us, it's not about
Eliezer or humanity, but it's about life on Earth, or it's about defeating entropy for
as long as we can while being as interesting as we can, then the perspective changes dramatically,
and preventing AI from this perspective looks like a very big sin.
But when we look at the set of trajectories that such an AI would take that supersedes humans,
I think Eliezer is worried about ones that not just kill all humans, but also have some kind of
maybe objectively undesirable consequence for life on Earth. How many trajectories, when you look
at the big picture of life on Earth, would you be happy with, and how much worry you with AGI,
whether it kills humans or not?
There is no single answer to this. It's a question that depends on the perspective that I'm taking
at a given moment. And so there are perspectives that are determining most of my life as a human
being, and the other perspective, I assume, is that I'm not going to be able to do that.
Yes.
And the other perspective, I zoom out further and imagine that when the great oxygenation event
happened, that is, photosynthesis was invented and plants emerged and displaced a lot of the
fungi and algae in favor of plant life and then later made animals possible. Imagine that the
fungi would have gotten together and said, oh my God, this photosynthesis stuff is really, really
bad. It's going to possibly displace and kill a lot of fungi. We should slow it down and regulate
it and make sure that it doesn't happen. This doesn't look good to me.
Perspective. That said, you tweeted about a cliff. Beautifully written. As a sentient species,
humanity is a beautiful child, joyful, explorative, wild, sad, and desperate.
But humanity has no concept of submitting to reason and duty to life and future survival.
We will run until we step past the cliff.
So first of all, do you think that's true?
Yeah, I think that's pretty much the story of the Club of Rome, the limits to growth. And the cliff
that we are stepping over is at least one foot, is the delayed feedback. Basically, we do things
that have consequences that can be felt generations later and the severity increases even after we
stop doing the thing. So I suspect that for the climate, that the original predictions
that the climate scientists made were correct. So when they said that the tipping points were
in the late 80s, they were probably in the late 80s. And if we would stop emission right now,
we would not turn it back. Maybe there are ways for carbon capture. But so far, there is no
sustainable carbon capture technology that we can deploy. Maybe there is a way to put
aerosols in the atmosphere to cool it down. It's possibilities, right? But right now, per default,
it seems that we will step into a situation where we feel that we've run too far. And
going back is not something that we can do smoothly and gradually, but it's going to
lead to a catastrophic event.
Catastrophic event of what kind? So can you still imagine the case that we will continue dancing
along and always stop just short of the edge of the cliff?
I think it's possible, but it doesn't seem to be likely. So I think this model that is
being apparent in the simulations that they're making of climate pollution economies and so on
is that many effects are only visible versus significant delay. And in that time, the system
is moving much more out of the equilibrium state or of the state where homeostasis is still possible
and instead moves into a different state, one that is going to harbor fewer people.
And that is basically the concern there. And again, it's a possibility that is
larger than the possibility that it's not happening, that we will be safe,
that we will be able to dance back all the time.
So the climate is one thing, but there's a lot of other threats.
They might have a faster feedback mechanism, less delay.
There is also this thing that AI is probably going to happen,
and it's going to make everything uncertain again, because it is going to affect so many
variables that it's very hard for us to make a projection into the future anymore.
And maybe that's a good thing. It does not give us the freedom, I think, to say,
now we don't need to care about anything anymore because AI will either kill us or save us.
But I suspect that if humanity continues, it will be due to AI.
What's the timeline for things to get real weird with AI?
And it can get weird in interesting ways before you get to AGI.
What about AI girlfriends and boyfriends? Fundamentally transforming human relationships?
I think human relationships are already fundamentally transformed, and it's already very weird.
By which technology?
For instance, social media.
Yeah.
Yeah. Isn't the fundamentals of the core group of humans that affect your life still the same?
Your loved ones? Family?
No. I think that, for instance, many people live in intentional communities right now.
They're moving around until they find people that they can relate to and they become their family.
And often that doesn't work, because it turns out that instead of having grown networks where
you get around with the people that you grew up with, you have more transactional relationships,
you shop around, you have markets for attention and pleasure and relationships.
That kills the magic somehow. Why is that? Why is the transactional search
for optimizing allocation of attention somehow misses the romantic magic of what human relations
are? It's all the question, how magical was it before? Was it that you just could rely
on instincts that used your intuitions and you didn't need to rationally reflect?
But once you understand, it's no longer magical because you actually understand
why you were attracted to this person at this age and not to that person at this age and what the
actual considerations were that went on in your mind and what the calculations were. What's the
likelihood that you're going to have a sustainable relationship with this person, that this person is
not going to leave you for somebody else? How are your life trajectories are going to evolve and so
on? When you're young, you're unable to explicate all this and you have to rely on intuitions and
instincts that in part you're born with and also in the wisdom of your environment that is going
to give you some kind of reflection on your choices. Many of these things are disappearing now
because we feel that our parents might have no idea about how we are living and the environments
that we grew up in, the cultures that we grew up in, the values that our parents existed in
might have no ability to teach us how to deal with this new world.
For many people, that's actually true, but it doesn't mean that within one generation
we build something that is more magical and more sustainable and more beautiful.
Instead, we often end up with an attempt to produce something that looks beautiful. I was
very weirded out by the aesthetics of the Vision Pro asset by Apple and not so much because I don't
like the technology. I'm very curious about what it's going to be like and I don't have an opinion
yet. But the aesthetics of the presentation and so on were so uncanny valley-esque to me.
The characters being extremely plastic, living in some hypothetical mid-century furniture museum.
Yeah. This is the proliferation of marketing teams.
Yes, but it was a CGI-generated world. It was a CGI-generated world that doesn't exist.
When I complained about this, some friends came back to me and said,
but these are startup founders. This is what they live like in Silicon Valley. I tried to
tell them, no, I know lots of people in Silicon Valley. This is not what people are like. They're
still people. They're still human beings. The grounding in physical reality somehow
is important too. In culture. What's absent in this thing is culture. There is a simulation
of culture, an attempt to replace culture by catalog, by some kind of aesthetic optimization
that is not the result of having a sustainable life, a sustainable human relationships with
houses that work for you and a mode of living that works for you in which these glasses fit
in naturally. I guess that's also why so many people are veered out about the product because
they don't know how is this actually going to fit into my life and into my human relationships
because the way in which it was presented in these videos didn't seem to be credible.
Do you think AI, when it's deployed by companies like Microsoft and Google and Meta,
will have the same issue of being weirdly corporate? There'd be some uncanny valley,
some weirdness to the whole presentation. I've gotten a chance to talk to George Hotz. He
believes everything should be open source and decentralized and there then we shall have the
AI of the people and it'll maintain a grounding to the magic that's humanity, that's the human
condition, that corporations will destroy the magic. I believe that if we make everything
open source and make this mandatory, we are going to lose a lot of beautiful art and a lot
of beautiful designs. There is a reason why Linux desktop is still ugly. It's difficult to
create coherence in the open source designs so far when the designs have to get very large and
it's easier to make this happening in a company with centralized organization.
And from my own perspective, what we should ensure is that open source never dies,
that it can always compete and has a place with the other forms of organization because I think
it is absolutely vital that open source exists and that we have systems that people have under
control outside of the corporation and that is also producing viable competition to the corporations.
So the corporations, the centralized control, the dictatorships of corporations can create beauty.
Centralized design is a source of a lot of beauty and then I guess open source is a
source of freedom, a hedge against the corrupting nature of power that comes with centralized.
I grew up in socialism and I learned that corporations are totally evil and I found
this very, very convincing. And then you look at corporations like Enron and Halliburton maybe and
realize, yeah, they are evil. But you also notice that many other corporations are not evil. They're
surprisingly benevolent. Why are they so benevolent? Is this because everybody is fighting them all the
time? I don't think that's the only explanation. It's because they're actually animals that live
in a large ecosystem and that are still largely controlled by people that want that ecosystem to
flourish and be viable for people. So I think that Pat Gelsinger is completely sincere when
he leads Intel to be a tool that supplies the free world with semiconductors. And it's not
necessary that all the semiconductors are coming from Intel. Intel needs to be there to make sure
that we always have them. So there can be many ways in which we can import and trade semiconductors
from other companies and places. We just need to make sure that nobody can cut us off from it
because that would be a disaster for this kind of society and world. And so there are many things
that need to be done to make our style of life possible. And then with this, I don't mean just
capitalism, environmental destruction, consumerism, and creature comforts. I mean an idea of life in
which we are determined not by some kind of king or dictator, but in which individuals can determine
themselves to the largest possible degree. And to me, this is something that this Western world is
still trying to embody. And it's a very valuable idea that we shouldn't give up too early. And
from this perspective, the US is a system of interleaving clubs. And an entrepreneur is a
special club founder. It's somebody who makes a club that is producing things that are economically
viable. And to do this, it requires a lot of people who are dedicating a significant part of their life
for working for this particular kind of club. And the entrepreneur is picking the initial set of
rules and the mission and vision and aesthetics for the club and make sure that it works.
But the people that are in there need to be protected. If they sacrifice part of their life,
there need to be rules to tell how they're being taken care of even after they leave the club and
so on. So there's a large body of rules that have been created by our rule-giving clubs
and that are enforced by our enforcement clubs and so on. And some of these clubs have to be
monopolies for game theoretic reasons, which also makes them more open to corruption and less harder
to update. And this is an ongoing discussion and process that takes place. But the beauty of this
idea that there is no centralized king that is extracting from the peasants and breeding the
peasants into serving the king and fulfilling all the roles like ants in an antel. But that there is
a freedom of association and corporations are one of them is something that took me some time to
realize. So I do think that corporations are dangerous. They need to be protections against
overreach of corporations that can do regulatory capture and prevent open source from competing
with corporations by imposing rules that make it impossible for a small group of kids to come
together to build their own language model because OpenAI has convinced the US that you need to have
some kind of FDA process that you need to go through that costs many million dollars before
you are able to train a language model. So this is important to make sure that this doesn't happen.
So I think that OpenAI and Google are good things. If these good things are kept in check in such a
way that all the other clubs can still be founded and all the other forms of clubs that are desirable
can still coexist with them. So what do you think about Meta in contrast to that open sourcing most
of its language models and most of the AI models that's working on and actually suggesting that
they will continue to do so in the future for future versions of llama for example their large
language model. What is that exciting to you? Is that concerning? I don't find it very concerning
but that's also because I think that the language models are not very dangerous yet.
And yet. Yes. So as I said, I have no proof that there is the boundary between the language models
and AI, AGI. It's possible that somebody builds a version of baby AGI I think and suppose in
algorithmic improvements that scale these systems up in ways that otherwise wouldn't have happened
without these language model components. So it's not really clear for me what the end
at the end game is there and if these models can brute force their way into AGI.
And there's also a possibility that the AGI that we are building with these language models
are not taking responsibility for what they are because they don't understand the greater game.
And so to me it would be interesting to try to understand how to build systems that understand
what the greater games are. What are the longest games that we can play on this planet?
Games broadly like deeply define the way you did with the games.
In the games the erratic sense. So when we are interacting with each other, in some sense we
are playing games. We are making lots and lots of interactions. This doesn't mean that these
interactions have all to be transactional. Every one of us is playing some kind of game by
virtue of identifying these particular kinds of goals that we have or aesthetics
from which we derive the goals. So when you say I'm Lex Friedman, I'm doing a set of podcasts,
then you feel that it's part of something larger that you want to build. Maybe you want to inspire
people. Maybe you want them to see more possibilities and get them together over shared ideas.
Maybe your game is that you want to become super rich and famous by being the best
post-caster on earth. Maybe you have other games. Maybe it switches from time to time.
But there is a certain perspective where you might be thinking what is the longest possible
game that you could be playing? A short game is, for instance, cancer is playing a shorter game
than your organism. Cancer is an organism playing a shorter game than the regular organism. Because
the cancer cannot procreate beyond the organism, except for some infectious cancers like the ones
that eradicated the Tasmanian devils, you typically end up with a situation where the organism dies
together with the cancer because the cancer has destroyed the larger system due to playing a
shorter game. Ideally, you want to, I think, build agents that play the longest possible games.
The longest possible games is to keep entropy at bay as long as possible while doing interesting
stuff. Yes, that part. The longest possible game while doing interesting stuff and while
maintaining at least the same amount of interesting complexity, so propagating.
Currently, I'm pretty much identified as a conscious being. It's the minimal identification
that I managed to get together because if I turn this off, I fall asleep. And when I'm asleep,
I'm a vegetable. I'm no longer here as an agent. So my agency is basically predicated on being
conscious. And what I care about is other conscious agents. They're the only moral agents for me.
And so if an AI were to treat me as a moral agent, that it is interested in coexisting
with and cooperating with and mutually supporting each other, maybe it is, I think, necessary that
the AI thinks that consciousness is a viable mode of existence and important. So I think it would be
very important to build conscious AI and do this as the primary goal. So not just say we want to
build a useful tool that we can use for all sorts of things. And then you have to make sure that the
impact on the labor market is something that is not too disruptive and manageable and the
impact on the copyright holder is manageable and not too disruptive and so on.
I don't think that's the most important game to be played. I think that we will see extremely
large disruptions of the status quo that are quite unpredictable at this point. And I just
personally want to make sure that some of the stuff on the other side is interesting and conscious.
How do we ride as individuals and as a society this wave,
disruptive wave that changes the nature of the game?
I absolutely don't know. So everybody is going to do their best, as always.
Do we build a bunker in the woods? Do we meditate more? Drugs? So mushrooms, psychedelics? I mean,
what? Lots of sex. What are we talking about here? Do you play Diablo 4? I'm
hoping that will help me escape for a brief moment. Do you play video games? Do you have ideas?
I really like playing Disco Elysium. It was one of the most beautiful
computer games I played in recent years. And it's a noir novel that is a philosophical
perspective on Western society from the perspective of an Estonian. And he first of all wrote a book
about this world that is a parallel universe that is quite poetic and fascinating and
is condensing his perspective on our societies. It was very, very nice. He spent a lot of time
writing it. He had, I think, sold a couple thousand books and as a result became an alcoholic.
And then he had the idea or one of his friends had the idea of turning this into an RPG.
And it's mind-blowing. They spent the illustrator more than a year just on making
the art for the scenes in between. It's stunning. But it's a philosophical
book of art. It's a reflection of society. It's fascinating to spend time in this world.
So for me, it was using a medium in a new way and telling a story that left me enriched.
When I tried Diablo, I didn't feel enriched playing it. I felt that the time playing it was
not unpleasant, but there's also more pleasant stuff that I can do in that time. So ultimately,
I feel that I'm being gamed. I'm not gaming. Oh, the addiction thing.
Yes. I basically feel that there is a very transparent economy that's going on.
The story of Diablo was brain-dead, so it's not really interesting to me.
My heart is slowly breaking by the deep truth you're conveying to me.
Why can't you just allow me to enjoy my personal addiction?
Go ahead, by all means. Go nuts. I have no objection here. I'm just trying to describe
what's happening and it's not that I don't do things that I later say, oh, I wish I would
have done something different. I also know that when we die, the greatest regret that people
typically have on their desk is to say, oh, I wish I had spent more time on Twitter.
No, I don't think that's the case. I think I would probably have spent less time on Twitter,
but I found it so useful for myself and also so addictive that I felt I need to make the
best of it and turn it into an art form and thought form. It did help me to develop something,
but I wish what other things I could have done in the meantime,
it's just not the universe that we're in anymore. Most people don't read books anymore.
What do you think that means that we don't read books anymore?
What do you think that means about the collective intelligence of our species?
Is it possible it's still progressing and growing?
Well, it really is. There is stuff happening on Twitter that was impossible with books,
and I really regret that Twitter has not taken the turn that I was hoping for. I thought Elon
is global brain-pilled and understands that this thing needs to self-organize and he needs to
develop tools to allow the profligation of the self-organization so Twitter can become sentient,
and maybe this was a pipe dream from the beginning, but I felt that the enormous
pressure that he was under made it impossible for him to work on any kind of content goals.
Also, many of the decisions that he made under this pressure seem to be not very wise. I don't
think that as a CEO of a social media company, you should have opinions in the culture of our
in public. I think that's very short-sighted, and I also suspect that it's not a good idea to
block Paul Graham, of all people, over setting a mastodon link. I think Paul made this
intentionally because he wanted to show Elon Musk that blocking people for setting a link
is completely counter to any idea of free speech that he intended to bring to Twitter.
And basically, seeing that Elon was very less principled in his thinking there and
is much more experimental. And many of the things that he is trying, they pan out very differently
in a digital society than they pan out in a car company because the effect is very different
because everything that you do in a digital society is going to have real world cultural
effects. And so basically, I find it quite regrettable that this guy is able to become
de facto the Pope, where Twitter has more active members than the Catholic Church,
and he doesn't get it. The power and responsibility that he has and the ability to create something
in this society that is lasting and that is producing a digital agora in a way that has
never existed before, where we build a social network on top of a social network, an actual
society on top of the algorithms. So this is something that is hope still in the future and
still in the cards, but it's something that exists in small parts. I find that the corner of Twitter
that I'm in is extremely pleasant. Just when I take a few steps outside of it, it is not very
wholesome anymore. And the way in which people interact with strangers suggests that it's not
a civilized society yet. So as the number of people who follow you on Twitter expands,
you feel the burden of the uglier sides of humanity. Yes, but there's also a similar
thing in the normal world. That is, if you become more influential, if you have more status,
if you have more fame in the real world, you get lots of perks, but you also have way less freedom
in the way in which you interact with people, especially with strangers, because a certain
percentage of people, it's a small single digit percentage, is nuts and dangerous. And the more
of those are looking at you, the more of them might get ideas. But what if the technology enables you
to discover the majority of people to discover and connect efficiently and regularly with the
majority of people who are actually really good? I mean, one of my sort of concerns with a platform
like Twitter is there's a lot of really smart people out there, a lot of smart people that
disagree with me and with others between each other. And I love that if the technology would
bring those to the top, the beautiful disagreements, like intelligence squared type of debates,
there's a bunch of, I mean, one of my favorite things to listen to is arguments and arguments
like high effort arguments with respect and love underneath it. But then it gets a little too heated.
But that kind of too heated, which I've seen you participate in. And I love that with Lee Kroener,
with those kinds of folks, and you go pretty hard. Like you'll get frustrated, but it's all beautiful.
Obviously, I can do this because we know each other. And Lee has the rare gift of being willing
to be wrong in public. So basically he has thoughts that are as wrong as the random thoughts
of an average, highly intelligent person, but he blurs them out while not being sure if they're
right. And he enjoys doing that. And once you understand that this is his game, you don't get
offended by him saying something that you think is so wrong. But he's constantly passively communicating
a respect for the people he's talking with and for just basic humanity and truth and all that kind of
stuff. And there's a self-deprecating thing. There's a bunch of like social skills you acquire
that allow you to be a great debater, a great argumenter, like be wrong in public and explore
ideas together in public when you disagree. And I would love for Twitter to elevate those folks,
elevate those kinds of conversations. It already does in some sense. But
also if it elevates them too much, then you get this phenomenon on Clubhouse where you always get
dragged on stage. And I found this very stressful because it was too intense. I don't like to be
dragged on stage all the time. I think once a week is enough. And also when I met Lee the first time,
I found that a lot of people seemed to be shocked by the fact that he was being very aggressive as
their results, that he didn't seem to show a lot of sensibility in the way in which he was criticizing
what they were doing and being dismissive of the work of others. And that was not, I think,
in any way a shortcoming of him because I noticed that he was much, much more dismissive with respect
to his own work. It was his general stance. And I felt that this general stance is creating a lot
of liability for him because really a lot of people take offense at him being not like their
Carnegie character who's always smooth and make sure that everybody likes him. So I really respect
that he is willing to take that risk and to be wrong in public and to offend people.
And he doesn't do this in any bad way. It's just most people feel, or not all people,
recognize this. And so I can be much more aggressive with him than I can be with many
other people who don't play the same game because he understands the way and the spirit in which I
respond to him. I think that's a fun and that's a beautiful game. It's ultimately a productive one.
And speaking of taking that risk, you tweeted,
when you have the choice between being a creator, consumer, or redistributor, always go for creation.
Not only does it lead to a more beautiful world, but also to a much more satisfying life for
yourself. And don't get stuck preparing yourself for the journey. The time is always now.
So let me ask for advice. What advice would you give on how to become such a creator?
On Twitter, in your own life? I was very lucky to be alive at the time of the collapse of Eastern
Germany and the transition into Western Germany. And me and my friends and most of the people I
knew were East Germans. And we were very poor because we didn't have money. And all the capital
was invested in Germany and they bought our factories and shut them down because they were
mostly only interested in the market rather than creating new production capacity. And so cities
were poor and in disrepair and we could not afford things. And I could not afford to go into a
restaurant and order a meal there. I would have to cook at home. But I also thought, why not just
have a restaurant with my friends? So we would open up a cafe with friends and a restaurant and
we would cook for each other in these restaurants and also invite the general public and they could
donate. And eventually this became so big that we could turn this into some incorporated form and
it became a regular restaurant at some point. Or if we did the same thing with a movie theater,
we would not be able to afford to pay 12 marks to watch a movie. But why not just create our
own movie theater and then invite people to pay and we would rent the movies in a way in which
a movie theater does. But it would be a community movie theater in which everybody who wants to
help can watch for free and builds this thing and renovates the building. And so we ended up creating
lots and lots of infrastructure. And I think when you are young and you don't have money,
move to a place where this is still happening. Move to one of those places that are undeveloped
and where you get a critical mass of other people who are starting to build infrastructure
to live in. And that's super satisfying because you're not just creating infrastructure, but you're
creating a small society that is building culture and ways to interact with each other. And that's
much, much more satisfying than going into some kind of chain and get your needs met by ordering
food from this chain and so on. So not just consuming culture, but creating culture.
And you don't always have that choice. That's why I prefaced it when you do have the choice.
And there are many roles that need to be played. We need people who take care of
our distribution in society and so on. But when you have the choice to create something,
always go for creation. It's so much more satisfying. And this is what life is about, I think.
Speaking of which, you retweeted this meme of a life of a philosopher in a nutshell.
It's birth and death and in between. It's a chubby guy and it says, why though?
What do you think is the answer to that?
Well, the answer is that everything that can exist might exist. And in many ways,
you take an ecological perspective, the same way as when you look at human opinions and cultures.
It's not that there is right and wrong opinions when you look at this from this ecological
perspective. But every opinion that fits between two human ears might be between two human ears.
And so when I see a strange opinion on social media, it's not that I feel that I have a need
to get upset. It's often more that I, oh, there you are. And when an opinion is incentivized,
then it's going to be abundant. And when you take this ecological perspective also on yourself and
you realize you're just one of these mushrooms that are popping up and doing this thing. And you
can, depending on where you chose to grow and where you happen to grow, you can flourish or not
doing this or that strategy. And it's still all the same life at some level. It's all the
same experience of being a conscious being in the world. And you do have some choice about
who you want to be more than any other animal has. That to me is fascinating. And so I think that
rather than asking yourself what is the one way to think about what are the possibilities that I
have, what would be the most interesting way to be that I can be. Because everything is possible.
So you get to explore that. Not everything is possible. Many things fail. Most things fail.
But often there are possibilities that we are not seeing, especially if we choose who we are.
To the degree we can choose.
Yasha, you're one of my favorite humans in this world. Consciousness is to merge with for a brief
moment of time. It's always an honor. It always blows my mind. It will take me days if not weeks
to recover. And I already miss our chats. Thank you so much. Thank you so much for speaking with me
so many times. Thank you so much for all the ideas you put out into the world.
And I'm a huge fan of following you now in this interesting, weird time we're going through with
AI. So thank you again for talking today. Thank you, Lex, for this conversation. I enjoyed it
very much. Thanks for listening to this conversation with Yasha Bach. To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description. And now let me leave you with some words from
the psychologist Carl Jung. One does not become enlightened by imagining figures of light,
but by making the darkness conscious. The latter procedure, however, is disagreeable and therefore
not popular. Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.