The
history of AI and the history of the philosophy of AI are deeply intertwined, from Leibniz
to Turing to Hubert Dreyfus to today.
Thought experiments drive technologies, which in turn drive a shift in the understanding
of what intelligence itself is and might become and back and forth.
But for that philosophy to find its way today, for this phase of AI, which it needs to, that
finding its way needs to include expanding from the European philosophical tradition
of what AI even is.
And the connotation of this, from the connotation of artificial intelligence drawn from the
Deng era in China was as a kind of, in relation to a kind of industrial mass mobilization.
The Eastern European includes what Stanislav Lem called existential technologies, just
as the Soviet era, it meant something more like governance rationalization.
All of these contrast with the Western individualized and singular anthropomorphic models that dominate
contemporary debates still today.
So to ponder seriously the planetary pasts and futures of AI, must not only, it must
extend and alter our notions of artificiality as such, intelligence as such, and must not
only draw from this range of traditions, but also to a certain extent, almost inevitably,
also leave them behind.
What Turing proposed in his famous test as a sufficient condition for intelligence, for
example, has become instead, solipsistic demands and misrecognitions.
To idealize what appears and performs as most quote human in AI, either as praise or as
criticism, is to willfully constrain our understanding of what machine intelligence is as it is.
And this includes language itself.
Large language models and their eerily convincing text and prediction capabilities has been
used to write novels and screenplays, to make images in movies, songs, voices, symphonies,
and are even being used by biotech researchers to predict gene sequences for drug discovery.
Here at least, the language of genetics really is a language.
LLMs also form the basis of generalist models capable of mixing inputs and outputs from
one modality to another, interpreting what an image sees, so instruct the movement of
a robot arm and so forth.
Such foundational models may become a new kind of public utility around which industrial
sectors organized, what we call cognitive infrastructures.
So with their speculative philosophy then?
Well, I honestly don't think that society at present has the critical and conceptual
terms to properly approach this reality head on.
As a co-author and I wrote recently, quote, reality overstepping the boundaries of comfortable
vocabulary is the start, not the end of the conversation.
Instead of groundhog day debates about whether machines have souls or can think like people
imagine themselves to think, the ongoing double helix relationship between AI and the philosophy
to do less projection of its own maxims and instead construct newer, more nuanced vocabularies
for analysis, critique and composition based on the weirdness right in front of us.
And that is really the topic of my talk, the weirdness right in front of us, and the clumsiness
of our language to engage it.
Toward that, let me say that, again, that the impasses over whether machine intelligence
as mind or sentience or consciousness are, in fact, impasses in our language and our
imagination more than they are in what is actually happening has happened and will happen.
The productive interest instead may have less to do with how AI adheres to precedent models
than what it reveals and does about the limitations of those models.
So I say reveals and does. Why the split? Well, instead of presuming that ideas are
first formed and then tools are wielded to act upon them, we may observe instead that
different tools, or as well, that different tools make different ideas possible. It's
not just that they invite different dispositions towards the world, they literally make the
world conceivable in ways otherwise impossible. Per Lem, Stanislaw Lem that is, and his notion
of an epistemological and instrumental technology distinction, we might say that some kinds
of technologies have the greatest social impact in what they do and enable in artificially
transforming the world. These are instrumental. Others, however, have greater social impact
in what they reveal about how the world works. These are epistemological technologies. Telescopes
and microscopes are good examples. Yes, they allow perception of the very large and the
very small, but more importantly, they enable Copernican shifts in self-comprehension,
grasping of our very selves as part of planetary and indeed extraplanetary conditions. With
such shifts, it was possible to orient not only where the planet is, but thereby where
and when and what, quote, we are, and of course, also thereby putting into question that collective
pronoun itself. Taken together, again, these may be called epistemological technologies.
Again it is certain that computation is artificially transforming the world in the form of a accidental
megastructure that shifts politics and economics and cultures in its own image. However, computation
is also an epistemological technology that has and does and will reorient the course
of what a viable planetary condition may be. In fact, we may say that the planetary as
such is an image that emerges via computation, via, for example, climate science, which is
based of course on planetary sensors and models and most of all super computing simulations
of the planetary past, present and future. The very idea of climate change is, in other
words, an epistemological accomplishment of planetary computation. And thus, so indirectly,
is the notion of the Anthropocene and of humanity as a terraforming subject. And that is what
is at stake. So, full disclosure then, in this regard, my own approach to philosophy
for a philosophy of technology then can then be understood as, in a sense, an inversion
of the malaise carefully lamented by Heidegger for whom technical reasons alienation of
the intuitive givenness of the world is its and indeed our downfall. Whereas for me, I
think he has it backwards. That alienation, that Copernican weirdness achieved through
technological mediation of our cognition has been and will be a path to access anything
called being. Once again, where we are, when we are, where we are and how we are. But clearly,
AI is not only disclosing these, it is also forcing us to question them. We then experience
different kinds of, if you like, AI overhangs and arguably underhangs. An AI application
overhang means that the technology is capable of doing things, that a society has a hard
time integrating, modeling, adopting for any number of good or bad reasons. What one of
our, in Antikythera program, one of the meta-science projects by Darren Zhu, Will Freudenheim and
Imran Sekolala calls an AI epistemic overhang, on the other hand, means that AI is capable
of discovering things, knowing things, disclosing things. That human science has a hard time
modeling and integrating and adopting. The latter, we would argue, is not just an issue
for science. In its generality, it is many ways the focus of this talk. So first, about
alignment. What does it mean to ask machine intelligence to align to human wishes and
self-image? Is this a useful tactic for design or a dubious metaphysics that obfuscates how
intelligence as a whole might evolve? Given that AI and philosophy of AI have evolved
in a tight coupling, informing and delimiting one another, how should we rethink this framework
in both theory and practice? Or let me put it somewhat differently. If the stack describes
the topology of planetary scale computation, the question that it implies is what is planetary
scale computation for? We might insist that the emergence of machine intelligence must
be steered toward a kind of planetary sapience in the service of viable long-term futures.
And for that, instead of strong alignment with human values and superficial anthropocentrism,
this steerage of AI means treating these humanisms with some nuanced suspicion and recognizing
instead a broader potential. At stake is not only what AI is, but what a society is and
indeed what either one is for. And what should align with what? The term synthetic intelligence
in our parlance refers to the wider field of artificially composed intelligent systems
that both do and do not correspond with humanism's traditions. These systems, however, can of
course complement and combine with human cognition and intuition and creativity and abstraction
and discovery. But as such, both are forever altered by these amalgamations.
Now, machine intelligence itself may or may not be, strictly speaking, artificial. Now,
if we mean artificial as something that is composed deliberately by some kind of precedent
intelligence, then AI is a form of machine intelligence that is so composed. But it is
perhaps not so simple. We recognize every day that there are forms of machine intelligence
that are genuine and yet evolved without deliberate design. Just look around the city. And second,
we can zoom out and see that the intelligence that does any artificializing is itself evolved.
And so, its artifacts are then also part of this evolutionary phylogeny. Now, the primary
significance of this for the present talk is that we should not, repeat not, see AI
simply as a direct reflection of human ideas, culture, and economics. Nor, vis-a-vis alignment
should it be. Put directly, the extent that it directly reflects human culture is not
a goal, nor is it a reality. The extent to which it departs from human culture is not
what we might name a disaster, and nor is it a hypothetical. That departure is, in fact,
our reality. That human intelligence must or should orient, which is our preferred term,
AI toward viable planetary futures, is essential. But again, that viability does not arrive
simply from making AI resemble us or admire us or be subservient to our wishes. To the
contrary. Now, there is obviously a Venn diagram overlap between AI ethics on the one hand,
and AI alignment on the other. But there is also, between them, a kind of impasse. Or
at least in principle, a contradiction between their visions. AI ethics, particularly in
guises associated with popular pundits and so forth, insists, when coaxed, that AI is
simply the reflection of human societies. From unjust biases and unequal economic systems
that produce it. It seeks to demystify AI as just us. Nothing more. Nothing less. As a
theory, it asks us to identify in principle any technology, especially AI, as ontologically
artifactual. AI alignment, on the other hand, and again, my abstraction of these correlates more to
the popular and populist guises than any deeper serious research. Alignment may hold that the
potential existential, or at least serious, risk of AI is based in the fact that it is now so
deeply divergent from human cultural values and norms. And that securing a safe future means
actually gluing it to those values and norms. So you see the theoretical problem. How can AI be
both automatically reflective of human biases and values and dangerously unreflective of human
biases and values? How can the positions that straddle my cartoon binary hold the apparently
contradictory conclusion at once? How can we observe that, again, that AI is us, and this is
bad, and simultaneously that it is not us, and this is also bad? Well, it can be both, but only
if we would radically qualify and specify what we mean by alignment and allow for alignment such
that AI not only bends to social norms, but also for which society evolves in the positive sense
in relation to the epistemological and instrumental affordances of AI. So before I go into a little
bit more detail about what I envision, let me further contrast and clarify what I don't
envision, what I don't mean. The possibly very sensible perspective that AI and potential AGI
pose an existential risk and so therefore should be the focus of planetary concern for
geopolitical and geosocial debate has not always been well represented in the public sphere as it
should be. AI moral panics overwhelm imaginative reason in what amounts to several simultaneous AI
moral panics competing for attention, oxygen and hegemony. These range from rather predictable
American culture war templates that focus less on what is said than who is saying it to a strange
inversion where some of the most well-known for rapturous, millenarian visions of AI have rotated
to apocalyptic, eschatological ideas without missing a beat. From the singularity to the
Unibomber and back is the new horseshoe theory of AI politics. The hype doom binary imploding into
itself. Elsewhere, but not too far away, many public intellectuals spent the spring of 2023 in a
perhaps well-meaning piety game to see who could say that we are in fact more fucked. You say we
are fucked because of AI. Well, I say we are more fucked than thou. Sometimes the game
eventuated in public letters of concern of varying quality and intellectual legitimacy,
I think, but almost all with signatories that included very good and smart people.
The most dubious of these, however, called for those in charge to push the imaginary red pause
button on AI, quote, until we can figure out what's going on, as the man said. Knowing full
well that no such button exists. That bad actors will not play along and that they themselves
perhaps stand to benefit down the line for having signaled their concern thusly.
Most importantly, that unlike aliens in a sci-fi movie who land and say take me to your leader,
that when it comes to the serious, serious risks identified, there is no them to petition.
Who is in charge is the right question. And I would like to think that the posing of that
question was the real point and hopefully impact of the letters. That said, it is clear that the
present discourse around AI is ironically enough exemplary of the kind of discourse that the
discourse around AI is warning us about. Tribal, hyperbolic, truthy, unnecessarily dominated by
whoever talks loudest and says the most outrageous thing, all amplified by advertising machines.
Some critics may even go so far as to insist that AI is neither artificial nor intelligent.
They say that it is not artificial because it is made of physical materials by people for specific
purposes, which is the very definition of the artificial. They say it is not intelligent
because it is merely modeling and solving problems, which in many significant ways is a good
shorthand definition for a general theory of intelligence that is inclusive of but not
exclusive to what it feels like to be human. They say that AI is not artificial because it is made
human. Others may go a step further and advance a position that we might call AI denialism. That is,
AI doesn't really exist. Don't be fooled. It is just statistics. It is just gradient descent.
This is a bit like saying a symphony doesn't exist, it is just sound waves. Or that food
doesn't exist, it is just molecules. All of these are trivially true,
but this AI denialism is not remotely helpful in addressing the concerns it purports to stand for
by making this particular case. The thing is it is usually advanced as part of a political position
in relation to the economics of AI, often a quite legitimate one, that then raises the stakes
to an ontological claim. And so it is perhaps difficult to climb down from denialism
because it seems to put the validity of the politics in question.
Elsewhere, AI denialism dovetails with what we might call AI abolitionism. AI does not really
exist but should nevertheless be abolished. Now, there is a lot to unpack here and to do
these positions justice and to systematically critique the critique of AI in this way and would
take at least a few other lectures, but let me then just offer the punch line of what those other
lectures might be because it is also the punch line of this lecture or one of them. There are
several. Sociomorphism, that AI is or should be the reflection of human society, is the logical
extrapolation of anthropomorphism, that AI is or should be the reflection of a single human.
Both of these, neither of these, is a real alternative to a California ideology's planetary
hegemony. They are in fact the pinnacle of it. The strong anthropomorphic view of AI
goes back at least to the Turing test where what he offered as a sufficient condition for
identifying machine intelligence became a necessary condition. That is, unless AI could perform
thinking the way that humans think that humans think, then it's disqualified. This idealization
of what we could call reflectionism, it manifested as well in the psychologism of human-centered
design, which proved a very mixed bag as it turned out, and is present in the now contested
terrain for human-centered AI, humanistic AI and so on, which are perhaps posed to make many of
the same errors as human-centered design. I will talk about what we call human-AI interaction
design, or HAID, in a moment. We are, in antikythera, very invested in this idea,
not despite of its weirdness and complexity, but because of it.
We are interested in the weirdness as well that is ensured by attempts to eradicate the badness.
The last decade of AI ethics surely prevented a lot of horrible things. Alignment researchers
themselves contributed to many of the core technologies that we now make use of, scaling
laws to ROHF in particular. And yet, also, at the same time, ethics ended up dovetailing
accidentally with corporate brand concerns to give us LLMs that are lobotomized to never speak
about sex and violence in any meaningful way. We have prudish AIs. We all foresee how bad it
could get if the worst human preoccupations were directly aligned with the power of foundation
models. But we also, at the same time, think about the critical role of sex and violence in
the evolution of animal intelligence, including ours. And so recognize the weirdness of machine
intelligence evolving with these topics as unspeakables. Now, again, to be clear, my
positions on this are not intended to be posed at the expense of the research in AI ethics and
alignment, but rather actually in concert with their conclusions that ethics and alignment as
such are together necessary but insufficient frameworks for the long-term orientation of
machine intelligence. That, in other words, alignment overfitting is real. My concern,
however, is that exhaustion with tech solutionism gives way to self-congratulatory parades of
political solutionism that is now overflowing op-ed columns, trade books, and yes, schools and
universities. On the continent, the inability to grasp how planetary computation upends 18th
century forms of Westphalian citizenship leads as well to regulatory solutionism, AI laws that
address yesterday's problems, the EU forever running to where the ball no longer is.
Trying to shoehorn planetary dynamics into citizen-scale policies. For example,
its permanent focus on individual citizen data as the core locus of concern and governance
is, in a post-pandemic world, probably the wrong lens. The way out of this is to cut the knot
of the weakest forms of reflectionism, which we might define as the moral and practical
axiom that AI does or should be ontologically anthropomorphic. Not only are technologies not
exhausted by the projection of social relations upon them, they are capable of forcing new
practical concepts that contravene those social relations in the first place.
As such, the harm, to use the parlance of the day, is not only in what reflectionism directs
our attention to, but equally, perhaps more so, what it directs our attention from.
AI represents an existential risk and existential potential in both senses of that term.
By this, I don't mean that it may or may not kill us, but that it may or may not disclose to humans
and to animal intelligence, to planetary intelligence, fundamental truths about what we
are, what their existential condition really is. This is the Copernican risk-reward calculus,
one that is neither messianic nor apocalyptic. Now, you may hear my criticism, such as it is,
of shallow AI anthropomorphism and say, yes, but as it turns out, AI actually does reflect
human intelligence in some important ways. So, against a shallow anthropomorphism that
insists that AI present itself as thinking how humans think that humans think, there is also
a deep anthropomorphism, or better, a deep biomorphism, that may correspond to how humans
and other animals do really think, even if they don't experience thinking in that way.
This is not only true, it's profound, and this is, as I say, what shallow reflectionism
models. For example, very recently, research in how AIs discern edges in images was, for example,
directed researchers to unidentified, as yet identified, unspecified neuronal mechanisms in
human brains that perform more or less the same thing. As I'll discuss in a moment in relation to
one of Antikythera's projects, AIs are becoming a kind of experimental organism, like a lab rat,
in which it's possible to test for human conditions and responses.
This would not work if there was no fundamental correspondence. But what is and isn't the quality
of that correspondence is of genuine philosophical and practical interest.
We also see, at perhaps a higher level of abstraction, that iterative predictive dynamics
of transformer models does correspond with the iterative predictive dynamics of biological
neurons. This was not the plan, but there it is. So yes, actually, you are a stochastic parrot,
after all. Always has been. But you should not take that as the insult
that the authors of that infamous paper perhaps intended it to be.
Iterative stochastic prediction and thinking through the recursions of mental simulation
and embedded embodied perception is how humans made all the things that you hold most dear.
Literature, music, science, and so on. Parrots, by the way, are actually very smart and creative,
so they're kind of a lousy token species for mindless repetition, but that's another thing.
The deeper correspondence between iterative stochastic prediction and artificial and
natural systems is technically an anthropomorphism, but as said, probably better to call it a
biomorphism. And it suggests then a different kind of AGI, an artificial generic intelligence.
And this is really the point. Emphasis on the correspondence between AI and the manifest image
of human thought and intelligence and culture comes at this terrible price, obscuring the real
and profoundly significant correspondence between animal machine intelligence that do not already
register in common cultural norms, but which could orient those norms to the underlying reality
from which they emerge. A different bidirectional path of and for alignment.
And notice I say from which they emerge, as opposed to the reality that emerges from those
cultural norms. This is where perhaps there are some points of difference in our approach
and some others on offer in the humanities. It comes down to something rather fundamental
of what is inside of what. The planet makes worlds or worlds make planets.
I say that we must avoid what obscures the deeper and more philosophically challenging ways
that AI does think like brains, but simultaneously does not orient itself around humanist norms,
which thus distances human brains from human values in uncomfortable ways.
In uncomfortable ways. Is this the real point of contention and unease?
In the most extreme versions of reflectionism, what is being defended, I sometimes wonder,
seems like a kind of political theological conviction that there is nothing outside the
text as they used to say. Nothing outside the sociological interpretation of technology.
The political economy of science. The reality of culture as determinant of reality.
Nothing causing culture, but culture itself. Culture causing culture, which is caused by more
culture and thus anything, including AI, is intrinsically a reflection of that culture
and nothing more. We might call this social reductionism and cultural determinism,
which for all its lip service to post-humanism can be the most militant guise of humanism.
Now, obviously AI as it exists is fortunately and unfortunately a reflection of the cultures
that produced it, but and here is the perhaps critical fork in the road. It is not nor should
it be only a reflection of culture. It is more. We are more. AI itself and more importantly,
the qualities of reality that are certain to be revealed by AI, all the Copernican twists to come
are things to which culture must and will align. Not only something that must and will align to
culture. So, two conclusions.
Just some. AI is an existential technology and as such must align in both directions.
AI aligning to culture's wisdom. Culture to AI's disclosures. So, specifically,
first, lowercase alignment should be seen as a tactic for making machine intelligence's
instrumentality, making it cohere to agency and intention to make it work. But uppercase alignment
and the attendant metaphysics is an inadequate grounding for the long-term orientation of machine
intelligence by animal intelligence. Second, a two-way alignment is both possible and desirable.
AI's epistemic overhangs, things that it knows and implies for us to know that we have a difficult
time grasping and accommodating and incorporating are not pathologies. They are in fact the deeper
point of AI. And so, between AI as generic intelligence, AI as an experimental super
organism per one of our Antikythera projects called the End of Science by our studio researchers
Darren Zhu and Connor Cook, AI becomes an uncannily productive sort of mirror. But it's not a mirror
reflecting what we think we are because we can see it and feel it, but rather a mirror of what
we are but cannot see and cannot feel. At least not yet. Now, I would like to then
specify this, ground this a bit in some of the work that we've done to try to explore
these ideas and many others in the Antikythera program and to tell you a little bit about the
studio but more importantly about the work. All the projects that I'll show you in a kind of
summary coming up were all really just completed at the end of last week where they were first
privately shown in Los Angeles. And again, we'll be back in London in the fall to do a
bigger showcase around these. Antikythera, as Stephanie signaled to you, is a research
program, a think tank of sorts for the speculative philosophy of computation. It is supported and
housed at the Berggruen Institute. We're pleased to be joined by Niels Gilman from the Institute
here tonight. Stephanie is the associate director. Nikolai is also here, my longtime friend and
collaborator. Shrelka is our studio director and we are also held afloat by Case Miller and Emily
Knapp and growing quite, growing every day it seems. The program includes 70 plus affiliate
researchers from around the world, various universities, and has just completed in our
last phase 12 studio researchers who completed this studio cycle. It is, in essence, a program
that not only seeks to map planetary computation but to ask and provide some provisional answers
to what planetary scale computation is for. Now, as I've already said, philosophy and more
generally, the project of developing viable concepts about how the world works and thus
thinking about and thus thinking about how the world works has always developed in conjunction
with what technology reveals and does and thus what it's possible to think. And so at least in
that regard, I am something of a technological determinist but only if we expand the definition
of technology to its properly expansive scope. Here's the thing. At this moment, technology
and particularly planetary computation has outpaced our theory. The response, as I've hinted
tonight, is to some extent to force comfortable and settled ideas about ethics and scale and
polity and meaning onto a situation that not only calls for a different framework but is already
generating that different framework. So instead of simply applying philosophy to the topic of
computation, we start from the other direction and produce ideas and the speculative from the
direct encounter, from making things. So that being said, the program, the Antikythera program's
real interest is not so much in calculation, in formalization, quantification, interoperability
as such, than it is about how computation provides orientation, navigation, cosmology, in
essence, planetary. The inspiration for the name comes from the Antikythera mechanism first
discovered in 1901 in a shipwreck off the Greek island of said name and dated to about 200 B.C.
It is perhaps apocryphally the first computer. But it is certainly a primordial computer. But it
was not simply a calculator. It was also an astronomical machine mapping and predicting the
movements of stars and planets, marking annual events and orienting a naval culture upon the
surface of the globe. So it not only calculated interlocking variables, it gave a comprehensive
orientation of thought in relation to its astronomic predicament, enabling prescriptive
thought to act in relation to this revealed circumstance. So beyond forms of computation that
are already perceivable in natural systems, artificial computation such as this is a kind of
world ordering, a foundation for what would become complex culture. And that is really the
core of it. For our initiative, the name Antikythera refers to computational technology
that discloses and accelerates the planetary condition of intelligence. So let me go a bit
deeper into some of the themes and ideas of the program and to show you some of the work,
which will be playing in the background as I explain a little bit where it came from and what
it's up to. Several of the projects, not all of them, several of the projects speak directly
to questions of AI and indeed to questions of AI alignment rather directly. The project
HAI ID or HAID, Human Artificial Intelligence Interaction Design by Antikythera Studio
Researchers William Morgan, Sarah Olympia Scott and Daniel Barkay is what you see here. It is
an ever growing catalog of existing and almost existing modes, positions and syndromes of human
AI interaction that allows us to map and generalize the space. It is a compendium of
hundreds of operant models, syndromes, patterns and persistent folk ontologies. As such, it maps
not one but several conceptual models for what human AI interaction design may be and might be
based upon. It sees HAID as present as a kind of subset of HCI but one that will arguably
overwhelm and redefine that field, especially as personal AIs are more generally deployed at
platform scale. As I've already insisted, the history of AI and the history of philosophy of
AI are deeply intertwined. One side of that ledger is populated by numerous thought
experiments, both canonical and obscure, the imitation game, the Chinese room, the paper clip
maximizer, the three blue banana problem, Samantha's infidelity, the driverless red
trolley and so on. These thought experiments responded to extend AI and in turn framed and drove
further development of the technology. But each was not only a metaphor for what AI is but also a
scenario for human AI interaction and indeed one because the other. We try to figure out what AI
is by figuring out the terms for interacting with it and to learn how to interact with it by
learning what it is, a perfectly understandable approach. Lately, however, with the rise of LLM,
there are many new entries to this list, including Sydney's nervous breakdown in which instead of
falling in love with this articulate OS, as in her, a journalist coaxes a chat bot to perform
disturbing feats of abnormal psychology. Among the most notorious new entries may simply be
called the Blake-Lamoine scenario where the highly evolved tendency to ascribe intentionality to
linguistically competent conversance can lead to some unnecessary conclusions. Blaze and I wrote a
piece addressing this episode called the model is the message, suggesting that the intelligence
there is not quite what Lamoine thought it was, but not quite not what he thought it was either.
With many AI interfaces, it would seem that computers have mastered presenting themselves in
ways that require almost no additional comprehension for users beyond ingrained social
interaction cues. The history of HCI is in this way a story that shifts from humans having to
understand how computers work in order to use them to computers figuring out how humans work in
order to be used by them. Now, language in its most abstract forms, linguistic reasoning, not only
talking and writing, accelerates the latter dramatically and flexibly, even disturbingly. And so
draws the practical boundaries of Haid both deep and wide. As you will see, the capacity for AI to
present itself through human social cues is remarkable and in fact becomes the interface in and of
itself. The shift from HCI to Haid means a shift from designing click paths to designing synthetic
personalities. Now, perhaps the most quantitatively pervasive form of Haid is one in which the user
doesn't even know the AI is there. Things just work. They work and who cares how. However, the forms
of Haid that this project focuses on are those that inspire and extend personal relationships with
not only AI but AI persona. Now, what we call personal AIs are essential to this and represent a
field of tremendous interest, but personal can simply mean AIs that are customized by your
personal use of it that are not necessarily persona. But many of the AIs that you will use and
which will use you will be as personalized as your search history, if not your fingerprint. The
avenue of exploration for this project is then the shift from a form of HCI that is based largely
in spatial references, inside versus outside, up and down, over, under, to one that is based on
psychosocial metaphors. Now, this is obviously a tremendously powerful shift, but one that comes
with all the risks and downsides of human psychology itself. And yet, in the most basic form,
this isn't optional. Some projective comprehension in the form of a mental model of what's
going on here. In this case, what the AI is, what its affordances are, what it is and isn't doing,
what and where and why it is, is so on. Folk ontologies are not optional. Most AI hate, we
might suppose, will be interaction with, again, in some ways, AIs are invisible and boring and
unmemorable and yet critical to the reproduction of everyday life, but as said, personal AIs are
another matter. They are, they mean a kind of AI that is being trained in how you think, like
teaching a dog a new trick, but also being trained by your thinking, like carving a rock into
an arrowhead. It is a personalization of an external mental model. And is this potentially an
experience of the self in the third person? If so, how can we not be fascinated? Now, in a moment,
I will talk about another project of ours that is with simulations. Simulations, then, but
however, clearly already tie back to the discussion of personal AIs, which are, in a sense,
simulations of us or perhaps we are the digital twin of the AI that is working on our behalf. For
both, the sim to real problematics are real and, of course, weird. Perhaps you are the NPC.
Perhaps your shadow is chasing you. Perhaps all personality is a placebo. Memory is a
key. Maybe the key to any personal alignment worth the name. Perhaps, then, if the uncanny valley
is when you are weirded out by something that is but is not quite human, the inverse uncanny valley
is when you are much more deeply weirded out by seeing yourself through the eyes of the
machinic other and don't quite recognize what you see, but you do recognize that what you see is
you, but in a way not, and yet it is more real than the version of you that you experience as
you. Perhaps you and that newly demystified you will engage in what security teams call
coordinated inauthentic behavior. What is alignment then? The field of Hade, then, is obviously
not brand new in reality. It's quite old, but it is new perhaps as a formal disciplinary field of
research and design, one that begins as such as said as a subset of HCI and may in time come to
encompass it. Then, if so, does it pretend to shift from cognitive psychology of HCI to a
renewal of psychoanalysis for HAI ID? Time will tell. Okay. Next. As said, we are as clear, we
are quite interested in LLM, but not just as chatbots. We are also deeply interested, but
rather also as a form of what we call cognitive infrastructure. The embedding of linguistic
competence and hence symbolic reasoning in the inanimate and utterly non-anthropomorphic
materials and systems of the world for which here, mind is literally distributed. This
project, Whole Earth Codec, posits AI not as a brain in a petri dish, but as a synthetic
augmentation of the forms of intelligence that emerge in and as complex ecological niches.
It's by, this project is by Antikythera Studio researchers, Christina Lu, a DeepMind alum,
and Delana Tran and Connor Cook. The project takes AI as a landscape scale phenomenon, focusing
less on how AI may align with you or me than how it may align with AI in the wild, may align
with the wider ecosystem. AI as an inorganic participant in an organic increasingly self-modeling
living world. Put differently, Whole Earth Codec rethinks the position and application of
artificial intelligence as a form of planetary intelligence and considers potential and
necessary conditions for their alignment. It started by responding to a brief about the
quality of data used for foundation models and by quality, it was meant whether the data is
any good, but also what kind of data it is. Training models that would have global influence
on just whatever data happens to be left out in the open, all but guarantees some degree of
suboptimal quality. If the most interesting data that could, in theory, contribute to broad
base socially constructive purposes is both private and or privatized, then other approaches
are needed. Techniques like federated learning would allow that data to contribute to the
reweighting of common models without disclosing underlying values. We could, in principle,
have our cake and keep it private too. But for this project, such a rotation also implies a
shift in what kind of data should be produced. It ventures that aggregating data about
individual human users is only a fraction of what is possible and necessary for planetary
intelligence worth the name. It proposes a fundamental deindividuation of computational
observation in a focus instead on impersonal, ecological and systemic data. That is, instead of
centering on individual data, instead of centering on individual data with ecological data as a kind
of exceptional subsidiary, it inverts this. It posits data about individuals as a specific
subset of ecological data, which, as should be clear, traces a recurring theme in all of our
work, culture framed as a function of the planetary rather than the inverse. So, the scenario
it explores for planetary intelligence is one in which systems of sensing and modeling are
global, but importantly, it is an observatory looking not outward but inward. The self-attention
of the transformer model is posed as an alternative metaphor to the panopticon of Foucault. The
positions of the observer and the observed are less supervisor and supervised than they are
mutually recursive. The model is sensing itself and thereby the planet is sensing itself. The
transformer's self-referentiality is the figure, the allegory for planetary models as well. They
call this folding the gaze. The scenario also hinges on the figure and function of multimodality.
If we see computation itself as a kind of generic syntax between qualitatively unlike things and
actions, then this project locates this generic syntactical function in the sensing and modeling
applications of, as I say, AIs and landscape scale technology. The sensing and modeling system
is a system for the artificial transduction of planetary phenomena into integrated and
recombinant data, hence whole earth codec. Multimodality operates both at the level of the
kinds of phenomena that are incorporated and artificially mutualized and in the range of
applications and functions to which the system as a whole might be directed, mixing and matching
inputs and outputs. Multimodal phenomenon, transduced and filtered into a generic syntax,
outputted as multimodal application technologies. In this scenario, planetary intelligence enables
planetary ecologies, again inclusive of human systems, to recompose themselves because the
composition of whole earth codec as a technology for planetary composition enables the emergence
of that intelligence. Knowing enables making, but making makes knowing possible. Last project that
I'll show tonight. The, which is called vivarium. Perhaps the philosophy of simulation begins with
the beginnings of philosophy itself. In a cave in Greece where Plato and Socrates cultivated a
long-standing paranoia, not just of simulations, but of mediated perception and its relation to
thought. External and internal simulation in conflict or alignment. There in that cave, they
set the foundation not only as what would become a topic for philosophy, but perhaps, as I say,
the foundational paranoia from which Western philosophy was born. Now, the politics of
simulation can also be very personal. As you pass through a security gateway, perhaps at an
airport, what is under inspection is not only your physical person, but also trace digital
personas linked to you, but which live in a near-distance shadow city called the cloud. If the
uniform lets you pass, it's because a decision was made according to risk models on those silhouettes
of which your physical person is a reflection. Your ears may burn as the infrastructure whispers
about your doubles, but it's not just you that's in play. At home and at work, as AI and simulations
convene, the designer versus player distinction will collapse from both directions because large
AI models and large simulation models will themselves converge, the latter as the interface
to the former. Elsewhere, scientific simulations have proposed a different kind of planetary
politics around the frame of climate change that seeks to give political priority and agency to
large-scale long-duration simulations of macrological processes. It doesn't articulate itself as such,
but the core of this approach, the core of climate politics, I say, is an attempt to refocus
governmental attention from the mediation of voice to the mediation of ecologies and to make
scientifically significant simulations sovereign actors, to make simulations of the future in
order to govern the present. Now, Viverium, a project by Antikythera Studio researchers
Deliana Tran, Christina Lu, and Will Freudenheim deals with the question of sim to real rather
directly. It poses a platform for collective intelligence that aggregates multiple toy worlds
into a larger platform of worlds that can be used to train physicalized AI and to aggregate
collective data and thus collective intelligence. It works for one-to-one, one human, one AI,
between one human and many AIs, many humans in one AI, and perhaps most interestingly, for forms
of collaborative embodiment, many humans in many AIs. In practice, as already posed, simulations
are an epistemological technology. They are technologies to think with, which in principle
makes a philosophy of simulation, a philosophy of things to think with, central to the purpose of
any program such as ours. We recognize that simulations are pervasive. Our friends from
neuroscience raise the point that simulations are not only a kind of external technology with
which intelligence figures out the world, but simulations is how minds have intelligence at
all. The cortical columns of animal brains are constantly predicting what will be next,
running through little simulations of the world and the immediate future, resolving them with
new inputs and even competing with each other to organize perception and action. For many
computational simulations, their purpose is as a model that reflects reality such as one hopes
for climate science or astrophysics. For others, the back and forth is not just mirroring. Some
simulations not only model the world, but feed back upon what they model both directly and
indirectly. These we call recursive simulations. Recursive simulations are those which not only
model that reality, but allow us to intervene and interact with it as part of our embodied and
intentional experience in a decisive feedback loop. So what are called digital twins, perhaps a
form of personal AI, are one such dynamic. So as Vyvarium shows, many AIs, especially those
embodied in the world, such as driverless cars, are already trained in toy world simulations where
they can explore more freely, bumping into walls until they, like us, learn the best ways to
perceive and model and predict the real world. For the recursive simulation between simulation and
the real, in some ways the real is the baseline model for the simulations and simulations are
sometimes the baseline model for the real. Toy worlds serve as a kind of bounded domain of
constrained information exchange interaction between otherwise unlike and incompatible things
and actions. They are where some AIs learn to navigate the real world by navigating these
focused reduction simulations of their contours. The sim to real passage is not just in terms of
the implications of specific learned experiences, but also the physical virtual hybridization as
such. ML exists in the world. AI is on its way to become something like a generic solvent soaked
into things and into how they behave. And so the back and forth learning between artificial
intelligence and natural intelligence never really stops. For the project, there are, as said,
multiple possible combinations of human users, AI as prostheses, AI as users, human or humans as
prostheses. There are multiple combinations of embodiment, of agency, of action in and across
the simulation, the real and the recursion. Not just one to one, one to many, but ultimately many
to many. Keep in mind, however, for us the AI's world is a simulation of ours and one we can
interact with. The AI, our world, is just one part of the omni-simulation that it simply calls
reality. Let me conclude. And while I make some concluding remarks, I will show clips from a
fourth project called Xenoplex, which is on AI and the philosophy of biology, assembly theory and
empirical astrobiology. It's by Antikythera, Derenzu and Connor Cook. Back to where we began, back
to the Stanislaw Lem inspired distinction between existential or epistemological and
instrumental phases of technologies. So for AI, in terms of its instrumental impact, alignment
overfitting is itself a kind of existential risk. As said, capital A alignment is an inadequate
practical metaphysics for what AI orientation implies and demands. Now, I assume that most, if
not all, serious alignment researchers would not disagree. Now, if only the journalists,
influencers and charismatic mega critics would follow their lead. As for the AI epistemological
impact, what will be the ultimate impact of AI? The ultimate impact of AI will be on what we,
quote unquote, come to grasp about what we are, how we are, why we are and the contingencies of
that pronoun. What that will be, we don't know and we can't know. We can't really anticipate
Copernican shifts and traumas in advance. Just recall that we didn't confirm the existence of
other galaxies until 1924 or scientifically confident precise age of the earth until 1953.
We don't know, but we have to defend the space in which what we will learn will go. We may presume
that with regards to AI as an experimental super organism, one of those likely areas is what we
today call neuroscience and tomorrow may simply call philosophy and vice versa. So what are the
kinds of questions to be asked that are likely to lead in the direction of epistemic disclosure?
There's likely no wrong answers, but safe bets are that posing fundamental questions about what,
quote, life is and what intelligence is and why the words that we use may be inadequate
signifiers for the range of phenomenon that they hope to describe. Even the boundary position
between these is unclear as the boundary between life as is the boundary between life and technology
and intelligence and technology are already, not just for advanced computers but for anything.
Perhaps life is fundamentally something like evolutionary autopoiesis through niche
technologization or perhaps intelligence is or perhaps both. Biotic systems make use of
abiotic systems to replicate themselves as organisms and across generations. They can't
exist without this fundamental technologization of the world. If part of the definition of
intelligence is means agnostic problem solving, then this niche technologization is at least
partially intelligent. This cycle happens not just once or twice here and there, but
everywhere and constantly over and over for billions of years. It doesn't just happen on
the earth. It happens by the earth. Life slash intelligence slash technologization is something
that the earth does. And it not only does it, the earth makes and remakes itself through this
process, building scaffolds for the next slightly more complex scaffold which are incorporated
into the next scaffold and so on. It's why we have an atmosphere and why we have artificial
intelligence. Some planets, at least one, fold themselves over time into forms of matter capable
of not only participating in the cycle but of making abstractions about their own participation
in them and thereby recalibrate them. Human brains are one such form. But they're not
necessarily the only form capable of such abstractions. And nor are those brains
independent of the technical systems of machine sensing and modeling and simulation and
prediction that make those abstractions possible. Sapience itself is technological. More
specifically, it's clear that simulation is, as said, not only part of how animal brains
work, scientific inquiry works, how prediction works, it's ultimately how the recursion
necessary for direct composition works. Simulation, as we know it, is an advanced coupling of
biotic and abiotic systems. It is part of the scaffolding. That is, biospheres make
technospheres that create biospheres that use technospheres to comprehend the whole dynamic. I
think you see where I'm heading with this. What's called artificial intelligence is the
name for a form of technologization that can occupy more than one position in this cycle.
It can be part of the means of technical modeling that humans use to grasp planetary process.
But it can also be the form of intelligence that's doing the grasping. It can be not only a
means of planetary sapience but also co-constitutive of that sapience as such. That's one way in
which the epistemic implications of AI get really interesting and really weird. It's then
possible to locate AI not just in the reflective shadow of human intelligence but in the longer
arc of intelligence as a planetary phenomenon and in the emergence of planetary intelligence as
such. I suggested the very definition of these terms is, of course, put up for grabs not just by
philosophy but by what clearly intelligent machine systems are already doing and by the need to
shift the words to the reality. I repeat, to shift the words to the reality. I will end with
this. There is at present a dangerous disconnect between cosmology and cosmology. By this I mean
that if I go ask my friends in the astrophysics department, they will presume I want to know
more about black holes and big bangs and curvature of space time and that kind of stuff. But if I
go ask my friends in anthropology, they will presume I want to know about how different
cultures imagine eschatology, kinship, how they think the universe began accordingly in
relationship to those. Now, in the humanities there is, I am sorry to report, significant noise
generated around this disconnect. The conclusion drawn adamantly by some is that the
abstractions of scientific cosmology must be brought, quote, down to earth. Made to heal to the
sovereignty of human cultures. I, however, wonder what are the cultures, plural, of the
world that can be composed, not just inherited and lived and lived through that align their
ways with the disclosures of planetary processes with that sapience that make them possible and
which are graspable by them. That project is to collectively compose cosmologies adequate to the
challenge of long-term planetary viability. Not necessarily the reconciliation of that with the
diversity of cultural traditions by its subordination. That is, the disenchantment thesis
that modern secularization of the cosmos removed cosmological grounding from culture is wrong.
Instead, it made a real cosmology finally possible. Cultural cosmology emerges from the material
possibility of thought. And that material possibility of thought emerges from the physical
realities that are, in the long run, continuous among humans. Even if they exceed the
uncertain boundaries of whatever humans are. So, instead of reifying cultural traditions and
projecting them onto the universe, the better cosmopolitical project for the future is to
grasp what is both convergent, because evolutionary, and what is divergent, because human, in the
planetarization of civilizations and to derive abstraction and meaning accordingly. I hope
that the implications for AI alignment, for shifting the words to the reality, are clear.
What's at stake for that shift via AI is basically everything. Thank you.