Welcome to Future Histories, my name is Jan Gross and it is my great pleasure to welcome
Yevgeny Matosov in today's episode.
He is a researcher and writer as well as founder of the knowledge curation platform The Syllabus.
Regular listeners will know that I highly appreciate his work.
Time and time again, Yevgeny succeeds in pushing our thoughts further through his very thorough
research and sharp thinking.
So you can imagine that I was and still am quite excited to have the chance to welcome
him as a guest in Future Histories.
In many ways, this couldn't be more fitting.
And there is an exciting announcement to make related to me and Yevgeny recording this episode
because a transcript of this episode will be featured in an upcoming book I co-edit
together with Christoph Sorg.
It's an edited volume called Creative Construction, Plant Economies in the 21st Century and Beyond
and it will be published with Bristol University Press.
I am absolutely thrilled about the fantastic group of people that are coming together for
this edited volume.
There are contributions by Laura Horn, Jakob Heyer, Samia Mohamed, Nick Dyer-Witherford,
There will be a chapter by Elena Hoferbeth, Matthias Schmelzer and Cedric Durand.
Christoph Sorg will of course provide the chapter as will I myself.
And there will be transcripts of two conversations, one between Nancy Fraser and Christoph Sorg
and one, you guessed it, between Yevgeny Morozov and myself.
I can promise you that this is not the last time you'll hear me be absolutely excited
about this book.
Right now the release is scheduled for May 2024 and be assured I'll keep you updated
on that.
Now that I have so shamelessly indulged in self-promotion for the last few minutes,
let me be equally excited about an upcoming project by Yevgeny.
It's a podcast series written and presented by Yevgeny himself and it's called The Santiago
Boys and it's described as a wild tale of how Salvador Allende's engineers dared to
challenge corporations and spy agencies and almost won a battle for the very soul of
information technology.
You'll find a link to the very stylish website of the Santiago Boys podcast in the show notes.
On the website you'll find a trailer and in order to stay updated until it's released
this summer, you can subscribe to newsletter.
Yevgeny has worked on this podcast series for quite a while now and has already been
an expert on the topic before that so we can all look forward to a surely exciting approach
to the topic.
I for once am thrilled and looking forward to listening to this podcast this summer.
Before we finally start, I would like to welcome Saskia as a patron of future histories and
I'd like to thank Urs, Lukas, Wilfried, Fabian, Georg and Karl for their kind donations.
And now please enjoy today's episode with Yevgeny Matosov on Discovery Beyond Competition.
Welcome Yevgeny.
Glad to be here.
There's a lecture you gave at Berkeley titled Beyond Competition, Alternative Discovery
Procedures and the Post-Capitalist Public Sphere and you start the lecture by hinting
towards the, and I quote you here, inability of the left to make sense of digital technologies
and what to do with them and then you continue that in your view the left has a problem with
making sense of its own project and related to that you ask, and I quote you again, what
should their future be other than just defending the welfare state and insisting that they
can humanize capitalism, end quote.
So I'm of course very much interested in both of these tasks, making sense of a possible
broader project of the left as well as making sense of the role of digital technologies
for such a project.
What are the main challenges surrounding both of these tasks and how are they related to
each other?
Well, it's a lot to bite, so I'm not sure how we're going to tackle it.
So probably these issues will pop up as we speak, but so that lecture I think was almost
two years ago that I gave it.
So I think, you know, my thinking always evolves and it probably has evolved since then.
I haven't gotten back to celebrating the left as the kind of the source of forward progressive
thinking on matters of technology, so that hasn't changed.
But to answer your question, I think let's try to tackle them separately.
Let's first tackle some of the problems of the left and then we can talk about technology
because I think ultimately the reason why the left has not been able to come up with
a more exciting plan for how to use technology and technologies is because it kind of got
stuck in a certain intellectual, political trap, if you will.
So before we get it out of that trap, I don't think that any forward thinking about technology
would emerge.
So do you want me to, I mean, like I can go on.
Yes, of course.
You know, like do you really want me to try to lay it out?
That's why I'm asking.
No, no, because it's a huge question.
I mean, it's a question about which you can borrow the right 10 books and you can have
an entire book imprint of Verso books dedicated just to that question.
So fine, let me start because it's so abstract that I feel like I might not land if I jump
off that plane.
You can try.
Fine.
So let me try to outline it.
So traditionally, I think the left has inherited this idea, or at least the radical left that's
liberal Keynesian left has inherited this idea that somehow its task is to figure out
how to deploy the tools of planning and all the associated knowledge techniques and repertoires
in order to show that the market does a suboptimal job at allocating resources.
Right.
So the project of the left has been essentially, and again, I'm not talking about Keynesians.
I'm talking about kind of hardcore left.
The project has been to show that you can build alternative rationalities of allocating
goods and resources that would beat the rationality of the market.
And to some extent, you know, it has been done with various success in places like the
Soviet Union, partially, of course, by relying on all sorts of techniques like input output
methods and whatnot.
The temptation within that tradition, of course, is to think that now that we have more tools
and techniques of organizing knowledge, including those of big data and artificial intelligence,
we should essentially try to recover that focus on allocating goods and resources and
turbocharge it essentially with these new techniques and to show and prove to the liberal,
to the neoliberals, if you will, who have shifted this debate into this knowledge-intensive
dimension thanks to people like Hayek and before he meets us.
And the objective is to show them that essentially they got it wrong, that market is suboptimal
and that there is a better way to do it.
And we can have a better allocative rationality if you want to put it that way.
This is what I think is what some of the most tech-friendly leftists imagine the task of
the left to be.
I, for one, remain skeptical that this task should retain the focus that it has retained
within that cohort.
I don't even think that it's a mainstream focus of the left, to be honest.
I think that the left that has not opted for Keynesianism has opted for some kind of Hayekian
view that markets are better at organizing knowledge and that maybe we should just focus
on somehow cleaning up afterwards.
And the left that is still thinking about something that goes beyond the market or some
kind of Keynesian multiplier is trying to recover and improve and turbocharge the toolkit
of Soviet planning.
Me, I've been thinking about these issues for quite a few years now and the conclusion
I've reached, which I don't think I'm going to lay out in full in this conversation because
I'm still working on finishing a book, I've started on this, so it's kind of thinking
in progress.
Even though I know the answer, I will keep the suspense and not give you what I really
think about all of these issues.
Ultimately, the conclusion I've reached is that there is so much more for the left to
do with this technologist if only it slightly tweaks the initial question with which it
starts this operation.
And the question with which it starts this operation now, I think, is still primarily
focused on how do we satisfy human needs and the needs that are basic.
How do we make sure that people get fat?
How do we make sure that people get enough adequate housing?
How do we make sure that all of these basic needs are satisfied?
There is, of course, a huge debate on the left.
How do you count needs?
How do you quantify them?
How do you qualify them?
Are they trans-historical?
Are they permanent?
Do they change?
That's a whole debate of its own and I don't want to take any position in that debate in
this conversation.
But ultimately, I think as long as you retain your focus within this needs paradigm, if
you will, you are not going to ask truly exciting questions that will allow you as a leftist
to win over the neoliberal camp and their vision of the market.
Because their vision of the market is no longer about allocation of goods as it was at the
beginning of this debate, which some of us and people on your podcast would know it probably
already fairly well, which is the big event that starts it as the so-called socialist
calculation debate, where the discussion is primarily about which of the two systems does
a better job of satisfying the needs of the populace, whether it's the market or whether
it's the plan.
I don't think that the neoliberals are still arguing about needs, even though the leftists
still are arguing about needs.
For neoliberals of the most sophisticated kind, the market became something else entirely.
It's a way of organizing the journey into the unknown, as Hayek writes about competition
in one instance.
It's a way of assuming and allowing more complexity into our social affairs.
For someone like James Buchanan, it's even an instrument of becoming and allowing people
to discover who they really are and who they want to be.
It's no longer about satisfying basic needs.
This I would argue is what accounts for the buy-in and legitimacy of the market as a tool
of organizing society.
Because for the more sophisticated end of the neoliberal debate, markets are not tools
of organizing economies.
They are infrastructures of organizing civilization.
As long as the left doesn't present an equally powerful vision of its infrastructure for
organizing civilization and not just allocating raincoats and beds, it will never be able
to defeat neoliberalism, at least ideationally.
This is the background.
We can jump into any of these points, but this is sort of how I see it.
I didn't yet give you any hint, at least in these remarks, as to what this alternative
project of the left might be.
But I do think that the fight that the left is fighting, it has no opponent because the
neoliberals have moved on and so has probably the general public.
Much of this discussion about how you can satisfy basic needs using AI and Walmart and
Amazon-like planning, it's a debate that I'm not sure anybody on the right, of the sophisticated
neoliberals who have engaged with socialist calculation debate, even needs to hear.
Because these people, if you read them, if you read even somebody like Buchanan writing
about computers in the early 1990s, he will tell you point blank, yeah, sure, computers
can maybe arrive at a perfectly planned economy, but computers will still not give you the
possibility of exploring who you truly are and of unearthing this becoming and discovery
element that the market does.
And this is why socialism will never win.
I mean, this is their argument.
But what I'm saying is that the answer of the left with regards to big tech and AI and
cloud computing and infrastructures has to provide an answer to that critique and not
just to the critique of, well, we can allocate rain codes better by using Amazon-like warehouses
methods.
That to me, it's not that relevant.
Okay, maybe let's try to pick this apart a bit because I'm wondering to what degree we're
talking about a successful myth, so to speak, a narrative on the part of the neoliberals
and to what degree we're talking about an actual ability to bring about something new.
Because depending on what we're talking about, we have to address or we might have to bring
up different alternative solutions.
Because I'm to a certain degree wondering why we should accept this Hayekian myth as
a starting point in the first place, since it's so extremely narrow and somewhat kind
of easy to disprove, I would say, by pointing to the many inventions that are not really
based on monetary incentives and market competition, et cetera.
And when it comes to the public imaginary, for example, it seems that non-market based
discovery is somewhat firmly being recognized within a broader public imagination as well,
I would say.
The stereotype inventor in novels, films, and comics, et cetera, used to be more of
a intrinsically motivated nerd figure and not the business type who primarily seeks
profit.
And I would say that this business type in the liberal version of things only comes into
the picture afterwards when the invention kind of has to be brought to the market, so
to speak.
But if this is the case, but if discovery is not really the problem because we have
these intrinsically motivated nerd types, then this would mean that what we need most
is not so much a new mechanism for the discovery of things, but an alternative mode or alternative
modes of allocating funds and democratizing investment, et cetera, in order to then bring
about effectively the huge potential for the new, so to speak, that seems to be a somewhat
inherent feature of human potential.
And on a worldwide scale, for example, this potential is extremely untapped since, for
example, venture capital has a extreme bias with regard to flowing money to their own
kind regardless of actual ability.
So I would be interested.
Is it a narrative that we are combating in this case, or is it an actual ability of market
competition to really bring about the new?
I mean, you're framing it in a certain way, and I'm not sure that these are the only
options in this debate, meaning that I understand what you're saying, but I don't think that
the focus on invention is necessarily the correct one, because the whole point of linking
it and lumping it with becoming is that you can also account for the consumer side of
things and not just for the inventor side of things.
So on the consumer side of things, the argument that neoliberals would make is that having
the market as the infrastructure of modernity is what precisely allows you to discover what
you really want, to express your needs and to eventually have them satisfied in a way
that has not been done before, because these needs were not even in your head.
So you can, of course, argue that there are all sorts of ways to do it differently.
And of course, there are.
I'm just saying that it's not just the story of the Schumpeterian entrepreneur
inventing something in the garage.
I mean, there are bigger things at stake here.
I think with regards to the story told by neoliberals, if you account for both the consumption
side and the production side, and if you account also for a very important element of it, which
is scale, because ultimately the story that somebody like Hayek would tell you is that,
sure, you can have solidarity and altruism in a small community in a village where everybody
knows each other, but as you start scaling things up and you have urbanization and
modernization, it becomes very hard to scale this stuff.
So the additional factor in the neoliberal story, of course, is the process of modernization
that, yes, you have what Hayek would say the cash nexus that now penetrates and intermediates
everything in a way that wasn't there before.
But it brings with it certain benefits of which this ability to live in a modern world
where things are discovered and where there is new that's produced by the behavior of
both consumers and entrepreneurs, it's there.
Do I think this story is partly accurate?
Yes.
Do I think that's the only way in which you can account for different alternatives to
different possibilities of becoming and discovery and scaling up the process of modernization
in a way that bypasses the market?
Of course, I think it's possible.
But the way I think to go about it is not to dismiss the story told by the neoliberals,
is to instead to historicize it and to say that, look, guys, you have a story that emerges
from the Cold War.
You set up your two punching bags or your punch one punching bag in this case, which
was the state or the central state and sort of Keynesian liberals play the supporting
Castro every now and then because you could always pick them, pick on them and say, look,
these guys are almost communists, so you can let them play with their monetary policy.
And if you let them play with government spending, eventually we'll all be like the Soviet Union.
So it's kind of one and a half punching bags, if you really want to be accurate.
But why are they the only options?
And this is where you really start understanding that you can have a more sophisticated type
of society, so you can have more complexity, you can have more social coordination among
people and actors and institutions that were not in touch before.
That doesn't at all require any mediation by the price mechanism and the price system,
because if the argument made by the neoliberals is that essentially you need the price system
so that people can come together and start coordinating things and coordinating their
needs and understanding what's available, what's not available.
Why not just do it directly?
And if you can do it directly, and we do that actually all the time, we do that actually
in families, you know, when you need to coordinate with your spouse or partner about picking
up kids from a kindergarten, you don't organize an auction and you don't appeal to intellectual
property rights and you don't create a market and that behavior, you just send a message
over WhatsApp or any other type of infrastructure and you basically coordinate how to make something
happen that before that was just a virtuality or was just a hypothetical possibility and
with some basic information exchange, it becomes a reality and an actuality, right?
It happens all the time and that should prompt some questions in our mind as to what are
the prerequisites and possibilities for scaling this up and making them richer and making
sure that the types of social coordination that are possible in the market are also possible
in other domains of life and maybe they need the funding and the infrastructures and the
kind of risk-free environments in which to develop.
But this is what I think needs to be essentially, this is the argument that needs to be used
against neoliberals.
It's not to say that the market doesn't do it, but what I think we should do is to essentially
accept it and say, yes, the market does it, but it does it with huge costs, first of all,
and these costs are not fully accounted for by the neoliberals themselves, very often,
and it's not the only way to do it.
And the organizing religious myth at the core of neoliberalism is that you only have two
options, the market and the state, and there is nothing else in the twin, and if you don't
do the market, you'll eventually end up in Gulag, and that's just not the story, right?
And then, of course, you have all sorts of perversions, yes, you can have Elon Musk taking
a lot of money from the government and blah, blah, blah, but ultimately, you're never going
to win that rhetorical fight, because I think broadly, the story, with a few bad exceptions
that receive a lot of bad press, the story told by neoliberals, to some extent, is partially
correct.
Yes, you can have a bunch of small entrepreneurs who essentially don't really, who can treat
everything as a black box, because the market system and the price system allows them to,
they don't need to know why there is an earthquake in Sri Lanka or why there is suddenly a bunch
of refugees landing and driving up the prices of shelter accommodation, they don't care
why, they just need to know where the price will be moving, and since the price will be
moving, they can take action and other counterparts can take other action, and yes, you can run
society as a black box, and by running it as a black box, you can essentially coordinate
effectively with all sorts of, to use in your classical economics, externalities, and do
we really need them, and maybe we don't, and if we don't need them, then the question
becomes what other alternatives and possibilities and infrastructures of social coordination,
discovery and becoming do we need?
Once you pose the question that way, then you really need to have a good answer as to
why that program should be a priority and not the program of satisfying basic needs
by giving everybody a coat and a bad bank.
Okay, so I guess now the obvious question is what are the mechanisms, Elkeny?
What are the mechanisms, the infrastructures, etc., that we need to bring about in order
to provide for this type of coordination that is able to also be attractive as an alternative
and also, of course, function at this level of abstraction that you are describing?
The question should be why, like why do you want to do that?
Because I think it's a big question, because if, what is the goal?
The goal, one goal might be because you want to generate alternative ways of,
you want to create alternative ways of generating value, right?
Or kind of socialist value that's not capitalist, and you think that you would be able to somehow
have people who engage in social coordination with each other, whose social being, if you will,
is productive, but in a non-capitalist way of something that can then be valorized by
society as such, and that be used for satisfying the very basic human needs
that they're now satisfying through the market, right?
So that would point towards a more, I don't want to say,
economistic, but a very, let's say, social reproduction-like rationale, right?
So you want to, because unless you pose the question why,
I think you're not going to get a very solid answer.
That alternative might be because we think that by facilitating all these
ways of engagement, collaboration, coordination, and so forth, we are advancing society forward,
and we believe in progress because we are progressive, so some of us are,
and we think that it will result in a society that will be many steps
above where it was before because you would be able to cure cancer or avoid the next COVID,
and so forth. This is a somewhat different argument for why that needs to be done,
and you can have even other arguments by saying that, well, we think that people should have
the capacity to form whatever groups and communities they want and pursue whatever
styles of life they want, and we should facilitate that, and part of facilitating that would be
providing them with the infrastructure and some kind of opportunities to engage in those different
life forms and lifestyles and to pursue them at scale, which to me would be yet a different
reason, which would require a somewhat different set of interventions, and to some extent,
in neoliberal thought, even though they don't do it a very thorough job of explicating that,
the market serves all these functions. It's an allocative device because it allocates goods,
however imperfectly. It's a device and an infrastructure of seeking and allowing for
greater complexity of social interaction, and it's a device which, for better or worse,
allows people to withdraw, if you will, and form their own communities and live as they will,
with all sorts of constraints and restraints. There are probably many other functions,
and I think that when people on the left are posing this question,
they need to understand what part of it they are trying to address. Maybe they want to address
all three or four, but I'm not going to give you an answer that from the get-go is going to
solve all these problems. All I can tell you is that it seems obvious to me that the basic
story accepted by the neoliberals, but also by many people on the left, that the choice between
more market or more state is incorrect. There are plenty of ways we coordinate,
and you don't even need to look at the examples I gave with parents and spouses coordinating over
WhatsApp. If you look at a basic school, there is a lot of complexity because there are a lot of
pupils and students and teachers and rooms, and that problem of complexity is solved with a very
simple device called the timetable, which, as far as I'm concerned, is neither an example of the
market nor an example of the state. It's essentially a part of tech infrastructure
that greatly reduces complexity and allows for social coordination when none was possible before.
We have hundreds of such devices in everyday life, and we have maybe even thousands of them,
and the question then is can we have more? Yes. Can we be more advanced? Yes. Would our life
be more complex, more interesting, more sophisticated, and not depend on the market
if we had more and if they were more advanced? Yes. Once you answer yes to all of that,
then you can start asking questions about how our broader tech infrastructure should look like,
what legal facets should it have, what property regime should govern it, how much money should
be put into it. These are the kind of questions I would be asking. To be asking a question of
what should replace it in the abstract, to me, doesn't make a lot of sense without first posing
the questions about why, for whom, and with what purpose. You already mentioned different functions
of what markets supposedly can do. What are the functions that you think that should be replaced?
I think you already hinted towards that maybe all of them could be replaced, but what are the ones
that we should pick up first? And what then are the concrete infrastructures, the concrete
modes of engagement that we can develop in order to bring about alternative mechanisms? Maybe you
could give us examples for alternatives that go beyond the timetable that we already know,
but maybe a hint towards examples that, for example, can be scaled in different forms in
order to provide modes of engagement that are able to replace certain functions of the market.
Maybe you could guide us through different aspects of this.
Sure. Look, from the three functions of the market I've outlined and mentioned,
it's obvious to me that I am that opposed to making the market the overall infrastructure
of modernity, if you will. So I don't want the market to be the tool through which we
move and advance forward. I think it's a completely mad bet to do it this way. So clearly,
markets should not be instruments of reducing complexity, of organizing different types of
coordination among social groups, of allowing new things to be discovered in a structured way.
Now, am I against markets as allocative devices in certain limited cases? No, I'm not. I think
markets, once they are well-designed and once they are supervised, controlled, and
monitored, they can deliver. And you know what to expect of them once you know what to expect of
them. And once you monitor for how well they're functioning, you can have them all you want.
With this very limited, if you will, focus, this very limited agenda. Now, beyond that,
I don't have the great technocratic
vision, because I don't think that division here should be technocratic. I think it should be
managerial. And this is kind of another dimension that I didn't really make clear in my previous
essays, which I will make clear in the book. So I think of traditional socialist in the European
sense of the world at least, and the kind of European, traditional European social democratic
movement, socialism, this workers movement and communism as well. I think of it as a movement
that in the economic sphere seeks simplicity. And planning is one way to get at it. So you
really want to make sure that things are under control and that you kind of know what goes where
and control the inputs, you can monitor the outputs. It's a system that you might think is
complex, but you're trying to make it simple. And you're using all sorts of tools, technologies,
techniques of knowledge and so forth to arrive at that simplicity. Capitalists, even Keynesians,
don't have this view. They accept by and large that the system is complex. And they think that
you can find ways to strive in the complexity. Corporations do that by essentially hiring
managers who go through, I mean, I know everybody, people think corporations are under idiots. I
don't. I think that good management is a craft and you have to learn it. And it requires all
sorts of techniques. I mean, try building a complex tunnel somewhere if you do it. I mean,
of course the government does it too. That's not the point I'm making. All I'm trying to say is
that something like project management requires a certain skill set, which you develop and then you
deal with complexity. But you deal with complexity without trying to make it simple by reducing it
into chunks that your system can digest, which I think is the default socialist temptation.
So whatever alternative system you would be building, I would suggest it becomes much more
managerial in its outlook than whatever the other equivalent was this insistence on simplicity is
and would be. And that means that the infrastructures we would need would need
to make it easier to manage things. So it might need infrastructures of prediction, of modeling,
of running simulations, of understanding how the world might be, because that's what managers do.
They try to anticipate the world as complex as it is without making it simpler. And I would
argue that the socialists have to go even further than that. They have to deliberately
make it more complex. So they have to take it upon themselves to make sure that the world is messier,
more chaotic and crazier than it is before they started working. I mean, many socialists succeed
in that just because of bad management. But I would argue that that has to be done structurally.
And this is what socialism is about. It's about allowing people who want to live in ways that they
want outside of the market, outside of whatever mentality and subjectivity is imposed on them by
this invisible Leviathan, as some people call the market, to pursue their projects without hopefully
hurting each other, but in a way that allows us to have all this immense variety of behaviors,
lifestyles, forms of lives, however you want to call it. And still making sure that the ship doesn't
think and making sure that the ship doesn't think is what really makes it complex. But this is really
where technology, big data and everything else can help, but not help by planning in the old
sense of the world, but predicting and managing and then delegating the functions farther down
the line so that you don't have to centralize all the management in the hands of the Politburo.
Now, this is how it works in the abstract. I'm not naive enough to think that in today's geopolitical
milieu, you can have as much decentralization as I would wish personally, because even developing
all these infrastructures of prediction, anticipation and management would require the pursuit of
probably a far more autonomous technology and science policy that
hegemonic powers of today would be happy with. So it will be a trade-off. So I'm not naively
proposing that we just have a bunch of communes interrelated with each other through a giant
network, but I think as a kind of as a horizon of where we want to be, that's not a bad vision.
In preparation for our conversation today, I listened to all of the six
Macy lectures by Stafford P. on designing freedom, and a lot of what you just said
kind of resonates with some of the ideas that we know from the work of Stafford P.
And I would like to kind of make a link to that, because when it comes to examples for
large-scale techno-political infrastructures from the left that have tried to provide alternatives
to both capitalist market economies and hierarchical central planning, one particular historical
experiment, of course, sticks out in different ways, and that is Project CyberSyn. You've worked
on the topic extensively in different formats, among them a soon-to-be-released podcast series
that I very much look forward to hearing. I guess many of the future history's listeners know about
Project CyberSyn, but some might not. So could you for a start give us an overview of what Project
CyberSyn is, and then go into how it is relevant for your thinking about alternatives today?
It's a good question. I don't think, well, I mean, I'm going to disappoint you.
What?
So I don't think that Project CyberSyn itself is necessarily very relevant, because essentially,
I mean, if you really want to be honest historically, you have to take it for what it was.
And what it was, was a system that would allow a ministry, essentially, or a state-run
state corporation to run a bunch of companies that were being nationalized in a way that would be
scalable. So that's all it was. And it wasn't some great insight that we need to move from
central planning to managerialism of the kind I was describing. It was just the circumstances
were like that. They couldn't move to central planning, even if they wanted to, and they couldn't
exit the market because of the political conjuncture on the ground in Chile. So they were stuck with
these companies buying and selling things on the market, but being state companies that needed to
be managed in a way that would soon involve the workers, and nobody really knew how exactly that
would happen. So this is CyberSyn. This doesn't mean that the ideas circulating in that milieu
don't have anything to recommend us. I think they do. Not necessarily ideas about cybernetics,
but ideas about technological dependence and the way in which technology plays a
certain role in geopolitical order. And this is actually the focus of my Morrison work,
looking at Chile and, to some extent, Brazil of the 60s and 70s. But in Stafford Beer himself,
there are many elements that are interesting and that I think can and should be integrated
with a certain type of socialism. But it's a certain type of socialism that I think itself
is in a minority position. And it's a socialism that really looks at
complexity as a good thing. And it tries to embrace non-neoliberal complexity
and live with it and profit from it. And I would say that people like Raymond Williams, for example,
who is one of the people who has actually written about complexity in socialism and how socialists
shouldn't system complexity, is somebody who could have had a very interesting engagement
with cybernetics. And to some extent, he did. He was a theorist of communication and transport,
in addition to being a socialist and transportation. Well, more communication, of course,
much more than transportation and culture. But having studied Stafford Beer very closely,
having spoken to many of his friends and colleagues and family and having spent a lot of time in his
archives, I also don't want to overstate the case. He was a management theorist who mostly, by luck
and misfortune, probably more than luck, and for him ended up working in Chile of Allende,
and that changed his life. But it was not a conscious effort to think through for a decade
of how do we rebuild socialism through cybernetics. That wasn't it. It doesn't mean that there weren't
other people who have tried to think this question, and there have been some. But Stafford Beer is
essentially a person who is a management theorist. And it doesn't mean that you cannot apply his
management theory to other domains. And I think that's what happened in Chile. He had a fan club
and they reached out to him. But even if they did not reach out to him, they would be pursuing
his ideas in government there, I'm absolutely sure. So it's a body of thought that you can apply
in domains that have nothing to do with corporations.
And I think this is the part of cybernetics that remains relevant. And I was just reading
a project management book the other day. I'm sorry, I'm reading really advanced project management
books in search for some deeper truth. And they almost use the same language. They talk about
variability and they need to control variability where Stafford Beer would be talking about
variety reduction and things like that. So I think a lot of this man, they talk about buffering.
I mean, it's all very cybernetic in its outlook. So from that end, I think for obvious reasons,
the legacy of people like Stafford Beer lives on in the business world. Partly because,
and this is where I think maybe I agree with what you said before, partly because
socialist praxis of management and administration hasn't really flourished, even though there have
been efforts. I don't know if you know what Stefano Harni was doing with Queen Mary University in
London, maybe 10 or 15 years ago. There was an effort to actually take over a business school
and reorient it towards leftist Italian autonomous principles. So this efforts have
occurred. And sorry, maybe I shouldn't have seen you last Stefano Harni. I don't know if he'll now
be hunted down somewhere if he's in Singapore or wherever he is. But essentially,
yeah, the socialist praxis has not had a chance to learn from it in part because
there has been a shortage of socialist regimes that would truly benefit from it.
Because part of Beer's agenda, if you read those lectures carefully and if you read his books
carefully, is of course, sorry, should I get controversial and start talking religion?
It's almost like the principle of subsidiarity in Catholicism, where you could basically delegate
and you want this individual social bodies and units of society to deal with their own problems
as much as they can before you involve the church and the state, especially the state.
Stafford moved between different religions and eventually he left all of them. But at some point,
he was really profoundly Catholic. And I think it partly reflects how he ended up thinking about
autonomy because for him, autonomy inside a company, it's that it's making sure that you
have these units that are on their own and buying their own business and the higher ups intervene
only when something goes wrong. And of course, it has all sorts of issues with it. And it's,
one can say it is an appealing vision of how you can organize society in a kind of non-statist form.
It's just that the kind of socialists that survived the onslaught of global capitalism against them
in the last 30 or 40 years have not been decentralized, but rather if you look at China,
they have been centralized. And one can as well argue that had Stafford's ideas in Chile about
decentralization and autonomy been implemented faster and sooner, it would have crumbled even
earlier than three years in the regime of Allende, in part because
it would be very hard for such a regime to survive longer than it did without either
mobilizing all the power that you have. And instead of talking about democracy, giving
ordinary people arms, which would have led to a Guatemala-like civil war with
hundreds of thousands of people dead, or you just forget about all the decentralization and
autonomy altogether and you just have a China-style centralized regime and you don't have all the
benefits of participatory democracy, but maybe you'll last longer than three years when you
avoid the coup. So I think we have to be also a bit historically conscious and pragmatic about
this question. But what does this then mean for the alternative that you are thinking about?
Because both in terms of this relationship between center and centralized and decentralized
elements, as well as with regard to the real challenge of not getting crushed,
as you just described it. So what does this mean for the project that you're imagining?
Sure. But I think I made it clear in my initial remarks that the kind of project and vision would
require, for it to survive, it would require still a much more centralized, central entity
with a very robust science and technology policy, with a very robust intelligence network, with a
very robust geopolitical outlook, alliances and so forth, to survive in order to pursue those reforms
and to pursue this project. About that, I have zero doubt I have about that. Still, I do think
that this utopian vision does need to be communicated and put at the center of the discussion,
because ultimately, I don't think that you can win over the population, at least in Western Europe
and North America, and some parts of Latin America, maybe, with the old socialist ideas,
and all socialists are kind of imaginary. And without having those people on your side,
your project will crumble even sooner. I don't think that that necessarily is the case
when you talk about countries that we used to refer to as developing or the Global South,
where I do still think that there are still important tasks to be done with regards to
industrialization and with regards to essentially making sure that they avoid all the traps of
underdevelopment, and where traditional 20th century socialist rhetoric is not just working,
but probably is what they need before they can move to this more, if you want to use a
fancy word, post-industrial kind of imaginary I'm toying with.
So, do you think about this question of transition in more concrete terms? Like,
what are the elements of power that one needs to think about in order to bring this about?
So, is this something that you think about?
I mean, we can't think about it. I'm just not sure it's of any use.
Oh, really?
At this point, the question is, you either try to convince the old agents of the left,
social democratic parties, trade unions, socialist parties, that this is an agenda
worth engaging with, or you just start a somewhat different movement and you try to,
I mean, we haven't even touched upon the question of class and what kind of class
relations emerge from this outlook. And there is a can of worms right there.
But thinking about the question of transition to me is premature, because I'm just not sure
that the political agent capable of even initiating that transition is there.
And I'm not sure that the current coalition, if you will, that still represents the mainstream
left, wants to take this on for all sorts of reasons. It's just not obvious how you're going
to win elections with this program. A lot of things. I mean, I think that framed properly,
you can. And to me, the number one factor is that capitalism for all its markets,
you know, however you want to frame it, but let's talk about capitalism. Capitalism for
all of the things that neoliberals say about its ability to coordinate information,
promote social coordination, discover new, facilitate becoming, it still does,
it still exercises so much power about alternative ways of doing things, of engaging with the world
and each other on ways that are not mediated by the market, of accessing knowledge that gets
suppressed and underdeveloped because somebody moves into that domain and grabs all the property
rights, intellectual property rights, and doesn't allow others to get in. I mean, the costs of
living under capitalism are much bigger than we think they are just in terms of kind of
imaginative power that we are losing by relying on it to be the central infrastructure of modernity,
if you will. And it would have been fine. We could live under this yoke forever, but we also have a
climate problem. And ultimately, if it don't solve that one, everybody's going to die. And
just very simple. And to me, that seems like the argument as to why anybody in their right mind
should be lining up for a political project that would remove that yoke and not just remove it
and replace it with nothing, but will actually target the very area where capitalism is weakest,
which I think is innovation. So in that sense, I do think that the main problem with capitalism is
that it forces society to under innovate, which in a sense is what Marx said of it in his critique.
The point was not that it's bad. It's that it innovates, but then it reaches a certain point
at which point class relations block it from innovating further and they're kind of stuck.
So you don't have to say that Marxist was an accelerationist. That was the whole point of
Marxist critique of capitalism as a modern system. And I think back in those days,
it seemed that the only thing we were losing was just maybe fancy and better technologies
or more efficient ways of organization. But now we're losing our future because
we're just going to die in the climate catastrophe. And if we don't move, then it will come faster.
So in that sense, you may start making new political arguments
that will somehow bring themes of knowledge, innovation, climate change, catastrophe,
all in one place. But I just don't see... So let's leave aside the hardcore left,
focus on the social Democrats. Social Democrats accept the mainstream neoliberal story about the
markets being good for knowledge and that they are the perfect systems for knowledge coordination
and they are perfect system for essentially making use of all the knowledge that's distributed
in society, to use one of Hayek's phrases. And it's just false. So for them to accept the story
I'm advancing, they'll just need to do some work on themselves and essentially understand that they've
made some mistakes. And then there is a space and a way to think about these questions without having
to say, no, we are with Stalin and with centralized central planning of the Soviet Union. And until
they do that, I don't think we should even be talking about transition.
It's so interesting to me that you put this aspect of discovery so much at center stage,
because my intuition would be that what you already pointed towards like the ecological question,
as well as the question of existential security, those are the ones that are, in my view,
much more important for a broader public. You could easily argue for a discovery through
existential security, since if you simply bring people into the position where they do not have to
hustle the whole day in order just to get through, then there's a huge potential of
creativity, so to speak, that would be set free.
But intellectually, I understand what you're saying. And a lot of people have made that
case with regards to the welfare state. But I just think that intellectually,
I mean, look, it's a much bigger battle than a battle between sort of neoliberalism and
whatever succeeds the people who win the socialist calculation debate. Essentially, it's a question,
it's a debate about action. You have a theory of action underpinning, I would argue,
both neoclassical economics and Austrian economics, to some extent, and much of social science,
to some extent, and much of social science, things like rational choice, which is a very
simplistic theory of action. And, you know, it starts with Weber, who partly borrows it from
Menger and a bunch of other economists of the first generation Austrian school. And it goes
something like this, you know, we're all rational, we have goals, then we find the most rational ways
of fulfilling them. And then that's it. And if we find a more efficient way of fulfilling them,
then this is innovation. And the person who does that is an entrepreneur. And what it is
to be an entrepreneur is to be always on the lookout for the more efficient means of pursuing
given ends. And that's a theory of action that I would argue, and I'm not the only one making
that case, underpins most of the theories of socialism in the actual praxis in the Soviet
Union and elsewhere. So, you know, Lange and everybody else, that's how they also think about
action. But this is wrong. I mean, this is wrong, because it doesn't account for people changing
goals along the way. And it doesn't account for much of the stuff that happens in everyday life.
I start doing something, I do it, then I understand I need to do something else. And I do it differently.
Then I realize it's all wrong, I need to do something else entirely. This is what human
action is like. And unless you build a political system that accounts for it, you're going to end
up wasting 90% of human potential and human creativity, what really makes us humans as opposed
to automatons and algorithms. Because our social system is not optimized to take advantage of the
sparks of creativity that really drive us and that make us human. And the only way that our
system currently is optimized to do that is by channeling our desires and incentives into the
price system. So if I really understand that there is something cool to be done and creative, yes,
and I want to share it with others. The only way to do that for me is to become an entrepreneur,
start a startup, seek money and put it on the market. And all I'm saying is that if we were
to build an alternative system that would actually account for how humans really are,
it would require very different theories of action, maybe informed by pragmatism,
maybe informed by something else. There are tons of, not tons, but some alternatives out there,
abduction. I mean, you can account for all sorts of things, which mainstream economic and social
theory cannot account for. Once you build an appropriate social system for that, then I think
the effects and the benefits you're going to harvest will go far beyond what you get by
currently making sure that artists have universal basic income or the welfare state is generous and
our funds arts. That's what I'm talking about. And in that sense, I don't think we are there.
And I don't think that people on the left are even interested in this question. And I think they
completely... Yeah, well, I don't know. You disagree? Tell me. Maybe there are some underground
circles that I'm not aware of. Well, I mean, I think that people are interested in so far as
I think there's a similarity of the way that you pose the problem to a certain kind of
not disappointment, but yeah, maybe it is a form of disappointment how the debate around
democratic economic planning is currently framed. Because in my view, at least, even though I'm very
much interested in the debate, obviously, I do think that it's a far too narrow scope that is
being talked about within this debate. And in so far, I think there is an interest in going beyond
this like fixation on markets as information processes, which is a scope that is not big
enough. And the way that I try to approach this is through this lens of alternative arts of
government, which is a way for me to ask different questions towards this complex of problems.
And for me, for example, this leads to questions of markets as sites of veridiction and production
of truth and stuff like that. And then you come to different, as I said, a different set of questions
and a different set of problems that we need to kind of engage with and bring up alternative
ways to approach it. So I would say there is an interest in thinking about these things in
different ways. I think I do have maybe a different timetable in terms of I would say the first thing
would be to provide some form of universal basic service and existential security.
And then on top of that, we should build these different kind of infrastructures of discovery,
so to speak, because I think that they can only be harnessed if the material basis is given for the
people who have to have basically time in order to engage with it. And so this is a different
kind of timeline. But I mean, it's not just the timeline. I mean, look, I fundamentally think
that social theory accepted in mainstream leftist circles is broken.
And it just is. And it's broken because the theory of action underpinning it is broken.
And unless you fix it, you're not going to have a robust theory that will be able to speak about
modernity, industrialization, postmodernism, whatever you want. You may say none of it is
relevant. We just want to make sure that people have tramps and enough food to eat.
And that's fine. That's a fun perspective to take. It's not either or. I just don't think,
well, sure, it's not either. Yeah, but if it's not neither or, then you're asking for the kind of
low-hanging fruit. I mean, who is going to argue on the left against universal basic services
or universal basic income, like continue to constitute it in a kind of way that will be
welfare state enhancing as opposed to libertarian Friedmanesque. So I see it as a default. To me,
that's not even an issue, to be honest. To me, the issue is that even if you engage with the
German-speaking world and you take somebody like Jurgen Habermas, he is the reference point
for German social democracy, whether you want it or not. Habermas does have a theory of action.
And the theory of action is very simple. The theory of action tells you the world is getting
more and more complex. In that sense, he agrees with Hayek and Luhman. And he tells you the only
way to reduce that complexity is by relying on markets and by relying on law, so money and legal
system. There is nothing else. And then all you can do is to eventually and sometimes push back
against the encroachments of all that complexity on the life world. And you do that through
traditional liberal institutions and the media. And that's a story accepted by and large by social
democracy. Now, is that story true? I would argue that story is not true for one simple reason,
because he's missing the most important mechanism of social coordination and reducing complexity,
which is information technology. And that you don't need to rely on
money and you don't need to rely on law. You can actually reduce complexity. And once you understand
that, then you understand that all sorts of other things become possible. You don't really need to
buy all of the bourgeois liberal political institutions we inherited from the French
Revolution whole scale, because you can have people organizing and still having all the
complexity that you want and all of the rights that they want, but doing it outside of the
traditional money system with banks and legal system with laws and bureaucracies. And I think
that unless, and that's just one example. So unless you go and piece by piece understand
what are the blocks, mental blocks and intellectual blocks, we're going to end up reusing and recycling
neoliberalism. Because to some extent for when it comes to non-communicative action in Habermas,
that's what he does. He takes Hayek and he basically says, yeah, life is getting more complex.
But what I mean by recycling neoliberalism is something very simple. The only way you account
for these creative sparks of action that I was describing 10 minutes or five minutes before
in mainstream debate is through the concept of entrepreneurship.
And now you have to invent all sorts of entrepreneurship. We have moral entrepreneurship,
ideas entrepreneurship, cultural entrepreneurship, religious, everything is entrepreneurship now,
because we have no way to account for truly new creative non-teleological behavior
in domains that are not the market. So we think everything is like the market. So we're going to
take the Austrian concept of entrepreneurship from it and insert it everywhere else in social
theory and how the world operates. And I think it's just dumb. And that will continue spreading
unless somebody stands up and says, look, you're basically working with the wrong concept because
the Austrian concept of entrepreneurship doesn't even describe entrepreneurship itself,
because it cannot tell you about entrepreneurs that suddenly decide to, I don't know,
switch from for-profit to non-profit status, pursue social entrepreneurship or completely
change their goals or completely reinvent themselves. You're still tied to the idea
that these people need to make something and that they're imprisoned by the price system.
And the only innovations they can introduce is in the techniques of production,
which is how traditionally they think. So you can switch to a better technology. You can invent
something or you can invent a new product that will be even better than your previous product.
So all I'm saying is that I think it's not either or and that I agree with you, but I do think that
without completely rebuilding social theory block by block to account for complex behavior,
to account for complex behavior, that's not just Santa Fe Institute like complexity theory,
whose whole purpose and there is own debtor, as far as I'm concerned, is to show you that
the state can never be as good as the market and kicking off economic processes,
like we need a different complexity. We need a non-neoliberal complexity favorable to the core
leftist ideals and ideas. And some of those ideas have to do with a diversity of lifestyle
and diversity of life forms producing fantastic social effects that will be disruptive, progressive,
and it will move society forward. The kind of effects that we currently attribute to the market.
And now you mentioned again that one of the tools that we definitely need to use that is
in our toolbox, but is not yet utilized in order to bring this alternatives about our digital
technologies. Can you sketch in a bit more concrete terms how specifically digital technologies can be
of use in this task? Yeah, but again, you will find it very banal. And that's all right. No,
no, no, but I just don't think that it's look, I'm the kind of guy who 10 years ago was putting the
word internet and scare quotes. And that's how I put it in my book to save everything click here,
because I didn't think that there was such a thing and that it needed to be talked about and be
ascribed all sorts of essential qualities as if it was, I don't know, something that is born with
this features and characteristics. So in that sense, if one community will be happy to use
abacus and a timetable, and another one would want an AI, I mean, great. Like it's not up for me to
like all I think all we can do as critical intellectuals is to look at the current tech
landscape and to see which parts of it make such a project unlikely or not favorable, right, both
in terms of use, because you can say that, okay, this technologies are easy to spy on, they allow
surveillance, they, they require people to pay for them with their data with money. So you can make a
critique based on use and praxis, so to say, or you can make a critique based on what the non state
ownership of this infrastructures in the current economic conjuncture means geopolitically,
because you want your basic communication, education, health care, transportation,
to be somehow run in a democratic way, where the policy decides on how to offer it, how to structure
it, how to reform it, which you would not be able to do if you integrate volunteer into your,
you know, health data, and you will not be able then to kick them back for all sorts of other
reasons, contractually and infrastructurally, right, so that this is a different side of this
is a different critique. There has nothing to do with praxis, because you can even buy into it and
say that Google offers you a fantastic tool, like a Google Calendar, great, we'll never invent
something better. You can even accept that argument on the level of use and praxis, but you can then
strike it down and strike it out based on the geopolitical meaning of delegating so much power
to a foreign company that you cannot control. So see, I think that these are the criteria
through which this has to be thought through. But beyond that, I just think you will end up
at a level of generality that will tell you that yes, overall, it's better to have infrastructures
that are generative. So you can build on them in an easier way than infrastructures that aren't
and that are closed. This is the truth we've learned in the last 50 or 60 years. Is it always
the case? No, because there are tradeoffs. And some of those tradeoffs may have to do with security,
with the fact that you just don't have access to technologies because somebody is not selling them
to you, which now is happening in China with microchips. And this is a constraint. And then
you have to live with that constraint. So I don't really think that you can arrive at a
beyond that, I don't think you can arrive at a set of more specific, at least I cannot,
at a set of more specific normative criteria that you want to have in this tech infrastructure.
Because ultimately, it has to be secondary to a political project. And unless you have
a political project, this infrastructure is not going to help.
Yeah, absolutely. And I'm actually very much looking forward to the way in which you will
hopefully lay out these ideas in your in your book at some point. Do you know when this will be ready?
Good question. You're not the only one asking me this question.
So now after two years, I'm almost done with this podcast on letter America. So I'm getting
back to the book. I think that the podcast has helped me a lot to sharpen
some of my points, particularly with regards to this managerial angle simulations modeling,
and the role that they can play in alternative leftist project on paradigm.
So my hope is to finally finish this book this summer. And if all goes well should be out next
year. Nice. Very much looking forward. Did it bring you the podcast project? Did it bring you
forward in terms of thinking about the political project as well? Yes and no. I mean, it was a
project very much focused on Latin America and the Caribbean. So in the 60s and 1970s. And
so it's a very different time with the Cold War and multinational corporations and spy agencies.
So it did in a sense that you see, you see how a lot of the challenges and problems that a country
like China is going through right now, for example, when it comes to technological sovereignty and
its desire to break from the technological dependence on Western Europe and North America,
how these debates already were had in the 60s and 70s and how in a sense,
China is doing what some Latin American countries in the end impact, for example,
where Chile and Peru were members in Ecuador, I think, that they tried to do in the late 1960s,
early 1970s. So in a sense, yes, I don't think maybe you can apply some of those lessons to Europe
too, in a sense. But I think to me, there is really no possibility of a political project
without a geopolitical project. So I think, if you will, the condition of possibility for the
kind of progressive political project that all of us are hoping for as a certain geopolitical
situation and a certain geopolitical outlook. And I don't think that we should ignore that,
that it would require a more bolder stance vis-a-vis the United States, possibly,
or at least vis-a-vis Wall Street and Silicon Valley and others. And yeah, I just don't think
that you can have harmony while at the same time pursuing some kind of an agenda that would replace
their tack with European tack. I don't think it will be easy. And as long as it's realized, then
it's fine. Very much looking forward to this book, I have to say. Evgeny, at the end, I always ask
the question, if you think about the future, what makes you joyful? Yeah, I've listened to a podcast,
I should have prepared for this question. What makes me joyful? I mean, ultimately, I think that
there are, how should I put it? Yeah, I know, I don't really know. So nothing makes me joyful
in the very specific sense, because I think optimism is the kind of luxury that we cannot
really afford at this point. But let me think about it some more. Well, I mean, I don't want to sound
like one of those accelerationist guys and celebrating the power of technology to solve
all these questions. But I do think that if there is a silver lining, yeah, that's the right term,
silver lining, to the kind of rise of big tack in the last 10, well, in the last 15 or 20 years,
it's that it showed us that so much social coordination is possible in a completely
non-market way. And we have not realized that yet. I mean, if you think about all the tools,
all the apps, that all these people in Silicon Valley and elsewhere obsessed with productivity,
with collaboration and coordination are using. I mean, yes, you might be paying something for them.
But what they probably don't realize is that ultimately, they're not coordinating through
the price system. I mean, they're using the price system to get access to a non-market system of
coordination. And Silicon Valley has consistently showing us that collaboration and coordination
happens outside of the market. And with enough money being poured into it,
it can become even deeper and better and faster and more efficient. And in that sense,
that is the best argument against relying on the market to facilitate social coordination
a la Hayek that we have seen. And that does make me optimistic, but that requires
somebody to see. And if a tree falls in the forest, then there is nobody to see it.
So if people will be able to see that element of it, great. But I think right now, the only
thing we have seen in this phenomenon, by and large in the public debate, is the opposite,
is the idea that the market is so much better than the non-market building these cool things.
And to some extent, I mean, it's not true, but they have built them. But that's not the point.
The point is what these things allow us to do and what they allow us to do is to completely
bypass the market when it comes to coordinating. And as long as you understand that, then you're
fired. That's so interesting that you frame it this way now at the end again, because I think
that, I mean, leaving aside the too narrow focus within the debate, at least this point that you
just stated, I think this is absolutely part of the like revived planning debate, that there is
potential in these types of non-market coordination, at least in future histories. This features
definitely features in future histories, I would say, no? The fact that these technologies do
provide some form of alternative coordination. Sure, sure, sure. But the question, I think this
is Jan, gets us to the heart of it. The question then becomes, what do you need this coordination
for? And I think that this is a philosophical question. And for a lot of people, including,
I would say most of the people involved in the democratic planning debate, this coordination
is just a way of fulfilling the need to distribute and allocate goods
by and large, because this is the primary focus, right? They're not really stepping into the world
of discovery, becoming creativity and so forth. Because ultimately, it's almost like they operate
with a Maslow pyramid of some kind, right? And this is what, for many people, that's what,
Marx operates with it to some extent, too. So if you look at this kind of the distinction,
and I mentioned it in some of my talks, you heard that the distinction in the realm of necessity,
what is it? The realm of necessity and the realm of freedom, right? Ultimately,
even if you want to be 100% just to Marx, you have to acknowledge that he put a lot of effort
into thinking about the realm of necessity and not enough into thinking about the realm of freedom,
right? And in a sense, because maybe it was too far into the future. Maybe it's because it's all,
maybe it would just have some kind of a liberal, I'm not saying that's what Marx wrote, but that's
one possible interpretation. Maybe we'll have some kind of a liberal interpretation of everybody to
their own devices. And as long as we coordinate production in the workshop in a democratic way,
what you do when you hunt and drink wine and write poetry in the afternoon,
like it doesn't matter. So we shouldn't think about it. And I think that's a mistake. So if
there is like one big message, I'd like to leave you with is that I think it's a mistake because
in a sense, the neoliberals understood that it's that element that accounts for the most exciting
parts of modernity. So this is the stuff that really gets people excited about technology,
cities, urbanization, modernization. It's that part. It's not the satisfaction of basic needs.
And they argue that the market is key to satisfying it. So this is one reason why I
think the lab should engage with planning in the realm of freedom more than it has.
And the second reason is that I do think that the realm of freedom, once organized properly,
is productive of value that can then, in the non-Marxist meaning of the term,
that can then feed back to satisfy the needs in the realm of necessities. And that's,
to some extent, what Silicon Valley has done. They allowed you to do whatever you want in your
everyday life. They get all the data through your devices about what it is that you do,
and then they monetize it. And then they do whatever they want with that money.
And so if you really want to have a socialist biopolitics, that's a good candidate.
They are appropriating that and making sure that value is generated from that,
not just individual everyday life, living your life the way you want, but also from
collectivity because we all engage in it collectively. And once analyzed collectively,
of course, this data has enormous value when it comes to traffic analysis or epidemiological
trends and so forth. But that comes from us being, I'm sorry, in the realm of freedom,
by and large, or at least in the realm of social reproduction, if you really want to
be middle-groundish about it. So in that sense, I do agree that the questions like this have
attracted the attention of people on the left. I just think they're asking them in the wrong register.
Intuitively, if you go to a person who is now struggling in subsistence and you ask them,
is it either the realm of necessity that should be covered first or should we immediately jump
into the realm of freedom, I'm pretty sure that the first will say, oh, please, let's start with
the realm of necessity. But again, if you were to talk longer,
I mean, I can tell you that I don't think that dichotomy is accurate. So I don't think that
that's the correct way to think about it. You're not going to get very far if you really pose the
question this way, because once you start with both of them separated like that, which assumes
a division between work and non-work that's very strict, that's separate, that's things that value
is produced in the workplace, of course, you're going to end up with the most obvious conclusion.
So me personally, and I think I even said it in the Berkeley talk and some other talk,
I don't think that that's a helpful way to think about it. So we need to get away from the
separation because most of the people on the left, them who did think about the realm of freedom,
they still end up saying that we need to reintroduce the realm of freedom into the realm
of necessity. The way Marcuse would, for example, he will tell you, oh, factory work should be like
a playground. And I just don't think that you're going to end up in a helpful way. But
just to counter back to what you said, if you stick with my analysis, then
you can say that, well, I mean, why is that person starving? I mean, if you really build a system
on my model, the money that currently ends up with Jeff Bezos and Mark Zuckerberg will be funding
his welfare. Because that money right now, I mean, my realm of freedom, if not his,
is being expropriated, appropriated and monetized in a way that leaves that person starving.
So why is that a trivial issue? And I don't know what the right answer is. It doesn't seem
to be trivial. It seems to me that clearly, once you understand that the rise of Big Tech,
to some extent, is linked to the ability to tap into everyday life and to tap into our social
coordination with each other and to monetize it and extract profits from it and to strip public
coffers of their avenues that would have otherwise been there, then yeah, I mean,
I don't think it's such a reasonable question to ask. So of course, that's why I was saying
earlier that I don't think that this is the right paradigm, for example, for the global south,
where you still probably need to be building factories and have people working there,
you need to industrialize, you need to build your own base, you need to recreate,
instead of relying on global supply chains, recreate some of the capacity domestically,
it will be fine with the older socialist program. So I understand the geopolitical
and regional bias, what I'm saying, but I don't think that the fact that there are,
I don't think that the fact that there are, you know, people who are poor or homeless or
who have troubles right now, which can be immediately resolved, should take off pressure
of us to find holes in legitimation strategies of neoliberals, or contribute to articulating
an alternative political project. Because the fact that people are hungry right now,
stripped of the ideological context tells you absolutely nothing, you might as well
believe that Elon Musk should give them basic income, or some philanthropist should fund
something for them. Right? So to me, the presence of evil in the world, as such,
that is easily fixable. It's no reason not to engage, which I think we both agree on that.
But I just want to reiterate it, because like, for me, they're not somehow,
one is not the reason not to think about the other.
Mm hmm. Yeah, no, no, I absolutely agree with that. Maybe it's that I
think about the ability to bring about the new in different ways. Or maybe I don't see it as
that much of a challenge. But I think I get the point you're making. At least I think I get the
point you're making in terms of providing... But that was the project for Marx, though.
So I really think that what is Marxism? Marxism is very simple. You have social relations of
production that eventually block forces of production from advancing further.
It's just a philosophy of the new. There is nothing else in Marx. That's the core idea,
it's that. And that you need to change relations of production so that the forces of production
can continue unimpeded. And you can, of course, make all sorts of cases for ecology and whatever,
and they're all important points. But ultimately, that's what it is. So I mean, the question of the
new and its sustained, almost industrial, methodological, theoretical production,
it's at the core of the leftist project. Yes, but there are a lot of questions that
are connected to that. The question of if we needed to think progressivism in a different way,
for example, I'm not sure if we can just jump into this competition, so to speak,
with the neoliberals and accept this premise in the first place of markets as the harbingers of
the production of the new, and then try to... But that's where we disagree, I think,
because I think it's just undeniable. It's undeniable. I also think phenomenologically
for the majority of the population. That's so interesting. I mean, you just need to open an
app store. I mean, don't you see all the apps? I mean, how you can possibly deny that that's
the production of the new? I mean, that's what people think... Well, I mean, there's an argument...
Well, there's a strong argument to make that capitalism is like the production of the ever
old in new forms. That's an argument that is out there and it has some form of plausibility
to it as well. The way in which markets and capitalism are able to produce the news is a
very, very narrow corridor in which we have this accelerated perpetuation of the old, actually,
and not really the production of the new, which is, I think, what you actually want to state,
what you are stating. So maybe we are not a part of this.
No, no, I believe in productivity improvements. So I believe that there are productivity
improvements in capitalist firms that are real. So they're not inventions. If they were just the
recycling of the old, there is no reason for capitalist firms to fake the production of
productivity improvements. Because if they do that, they're just going to be eaten alive.
In that sense, I do believe in competition. Yeah. But that's why I mentioned that it's
also important to talk about new ways of thinking about progress, because it's not only about
productivity improvements, no? Because this way of thinking, this logic has brought us into a place
where we are aiming through a catastrophe. But that's a different argument from saying
that they're repackaging the old. So I was invoking that in the sense that I don't think
they're repackaging the old, because if they're repackaging the old, they'll just be out of
business as individual capitalists. And in that sense, I think if you read somebody like Anwar
Shaikh, who I think is the Marxist economist who's done almost like his view on competition is the
same as mine and is the same to some extent as Hayek's. So competition is real and it does
produce new things, both on the consumption side and on the production side. You can make all sorts
of arguments. And that's partly what I'm saying, that there are other ways in which new is generated,
because there are other ways in which we coordinate. And so far, we've put all of our resources,
all of our thinking and money and laws into boosting markets as the only infrastructure
of doing that. But clearly, that's not the only infrastructure. But to me, it seems,
and we need it for all sorts of reasons that I accept have to do with redefining progress
and so forth. But to me, to deny that there is something new produced in the markets by both
producers and consumers, and that is valid. And that part of the neoliberal argument is correct,
just to me, since it's counterproductive, because it just rejects our phenomenological
everyday experience. And I see no problem in accepting that part of the story.
Yeah. Well, I mean, if you state it this way, then I wouldn't say that there is nothing new
being produced. But that's actually bringing us to a question that I wanted to ask you,
but I actually didn't, because maybe you could specify what you mean by the new. Is it just
productivity gains? So if you talk about that has to be replaced when it comes to this question of
the production of the new, what is the new? How do you define it?
Well, but I mean, does it need to be defined?
Well, it makes a big difference.
I mean, if you look at it in terms of practices, these are practices and ways of being and ways of
existing that were not there before when you started. I mean, we just need to introduce
a temporal element in this. And you're going to see practices and ways of doing things that
were not there before, ways of doing old things in new ways or ways of doing completely new things.
I mean, if you define it in this way, the new is being produced in many different social fields
all the time. But who's denying that? You are telling me things that are the core of my argument
and I'm trying to build an infrastructure for scaling them up and generating value out of them.
Yeah, I know, I know, I know. I think it's just that I think why we land at this position is that
I'm not sure if the thing that market competition is able to provide when it comes to
building the new is as huge as you or it should be
problematized much more than maybe you would do it. But I think we're circling around
in different ways. Yeah, but it also depends. I mean, look,
it depends on what your project is. It depends on how you think about
neoliberalism. I don't think about this as an economic theory. I think about it as a
theory of modernity. I think about it as a theory of civilization, essentially. That tells you
precisely, I'm sorry to say, how do you incorporate the new into your life and into the world?
If you read Hayek, it's just there stated very clearly that, yes, he tells you there are all
sorts of effects if you put the cash nexus where you previously had social relations or family ties.
But in the long run, the pie expands and the pie expands even if certain people end up as lawyers.
And it expands precisely because this new stuff is being produced and is being produced in a
sustainable way as far as capitalism is concerned. We don't talk about climate and other things.
And this is what market civilization does. It's not about coordinated firms and consumers.
It's about bringing novelty into the world. And I don't know, like, how is that not to me?
And if you look at the legitimation of neoliberalism, that's the reason why
it's of any appeal, unless it's imposed by force. That is the most exciting part of neoliberalism,
which is so exciting that social democrats are buying into it. And if you really want to
and if you really want to unthrone it or disrone it, you need to have an alternative account
of how society can move forward and structurally, infrastructurally produce the new in a way that
scales up. And that's not just about arts and crafts and artisanal people building things,
but that there are actually ways to interconnect people in, I don't know, Ecuador with people in
Moldova, which is what the market does and make sure the changes in one proxies then are reflected
in the life and in the proxies of the other. Ultimately, what I'm saying is that there are
infrastructures that allow people to coordinate, collaborate, produce things, whether these things
are effects or emotions or ideas or things that have all of the markings of what neoliberals
attribute to market civilization without most of the costs. And that if you, they're not developed
because public policy is such that it doesn't channel resources there. You cannot scale them
up properly. You cannot, your only turn, your only option is towards the market.
And that's why we have all these idealistic people who beyond protesting, if they really want to do
something, like what do they do? Like they form a startup and they become, you know, in most cases
and they seek money and they know that this will allow them to scale. If they don't want to be just
local operators and if they want to scale, that's what they need to do. Why? Because our entire
civilization favors the market as the default and only infrastructure of scaling up this coordination
and generating value out of it. But you can have a multiplicity of them. That's why in one of my
earlier articles in New Left Review, I basically said, look, Hayek has a flawed evolutionary theory
and what he says about how people become less altruistic as they move from villages to cities
is wrong. That evolutionary theory actually teaches us otherwise. And that you might as well say that
solidarity will be as productive, what Hayek calls discovery, as competition. It's basically like,
there is no reason to believe that he's correct on that point and I don't think he is. But it
doesn't mean that solidarity is the only thing that can do it. You can maybe list 10 values that
will do it. Maybe you can list 20 and maybe you can list infrastructures that will go along with
them to enable them and to elicit these behaviors and to elicit these orientations. So I mean,
I don't know. To me, that seems like the core question of how do you organize modernity
rather than a trivial one. It's not about making sure we have a different system for building apps.
It's a way for me of thinking about how do you move society forward and embrace the new
in a structured way that bypasses the dichotomy of the market and the state
and refuses the idea that the only way to do it in a scaled up way is by relying on the market.
I absolutely agree. I think it's maybe because maybe you are holding something back that is
in the book and in your thinking because there's something missing. I absolutely agree with
everything you just said. But for example, within capitalism, you do have private property
as a form of guiding lens that is able to unify these actions much as the
market as competition does. So you will have a mechanism that is able to provide a form of
like pre-coordination maybe. And in the way that you describe the alternative,
I think, of course, it's right to point out that there needs to be a multiplicity of different
approaches that look at different aspects of, for example, the market, but also different
regional contexts and stuff like that. But then still, you would have to come up with an answer
that provides this glue, this form of maybe directionality that is provided in capitalism
through private property and markets as competition. You would have to find a different form of
mechanism for the production of pre-configuration, so to speak, for the alternative.
But no, I don't think so. I don't think it's my problem. No. Why? Because we're not trying
to build, in that sense, I depart from describing what so far we have been talking about for the
last 10 minutes as a socialism. Because if you really wanted to, it's a non-capitalism at best,
what I'm describing. And as a non-capitalism, it's not post-capitalism, it's a non-capitalism.
And if you really want to go really far, you can say that you can have a multiplicity of
non-capitalisms. And I don't think that it requires any grounding, for example, in an alternative
property regime. I don't. You might argue that it would require certain rights to preserve those
forms of right, to observe those forms of life. You might argue that you would need a right to
ignorance of something, because that would be the only way to preserve certain core features.
We might argue that you would need some kind of an institutional slack so that you don't
over-optimize. But to generalize it to a theory that as a guiding lens here would be to convert
it into an ism, which is not what I'm trying to do. So at best, my ism is a non-ism and it's a
non-capitalism. Nice. Good answer. Even though I'm not saying that it would need to be a different
form of property regime that would provide this type of glue that I'm talking about.
I also think you're mistaken with regards to property, to be honest. I can easily imagine,
and in fact it exists, you can have capitalist relations now where property would be
very different from the one we have, property regime, and where you would be able to look at
the radical markets, people. If a certain piece of equipment is not used well by the capitalists
who owns it, we're just going to come in and take it and put it on the auction and somebody
will come in and buy it. That's a complete violation of the private property that you
think is constitutive of capitalism, and I just don't think that for them it's constitutive of
capitalism. Fair enough. Good point. I don't think I'm holding back. Sorry, maybe I'm just
in my bubble. To me, it seems pretty obvious. I live in a village here. Look at my books here.
It's not exactly the most exciting reading you have here. It's possible I live in a bubble here,
but I do think that there is something there. You're the person monitoring all the discourses
most closely, so if anybody is guarded against being too much in a bubble, I think it's you,
Evgeny. It's fair enough to say that there is a lot there, I think.
Evgeny, thank you so much for being part of Future Histories.
Sure, my pleasure.
That was our show for today. Thanks a lot for listening. If you want to support
Future Histories, you can do so on Patreon. For this, visit patreon.com slash future histories,
or you can simply tell a friend that you like the show and that he,
she, or they might like it as well. Thanks a lot and hear you in two weeks.