Welcome to Future Histories.
My name is Jan Gross, and it is my great pleasure to welcome Elisa Longcón,
Auntie Leo, in today's episode.
She's a linguist and professor in the Department of Education at the
University of Santiago de Chile, and she has been the first president of
the Constitutional Convention in Chile.
Just like the very recent episode with Matt Huber, I also recorded today's
episode at the The Great Transition Conference, where I was invited to
take part in a symposium on democratic planning.
Many thanks to everybody involved.
It has been a great pleasure to be able to meet so many interesting people there.
I really enjoyed it.
A little pointer to my German speaking audience.
I think today's episode connects really nicely to the second
episode I recorded with Daniel Leuch.
That would be episode 39 of season two of Future Histories, titled
Daniel Leuch zu Freiheit, Souveränität und Recht ohne Gewalt.
And then a little pointer to my English speaking audience as well.
You do have the possibility to subscribe to the English episodes only.
There's an RSS feed for Future Histories International, and there's
a homepage as well, futurehistories-international.com.
So go ahead and subscribe.
That would be great.
And while you're at it, if you like future histories, please tell your friends
about it, maybe they will like it as well.
But now please enjoy today's episode with Elisa Longcón Antilio.
Welcome, Elisa.
Hi, my name is Elisa Longcón Antilio.
Hello to everybody.
I'm greeting you in my mother tongue.
That is very important for me and for my people that you hear my
voice in my mother tongue, because we are a virginal nation here in Chile.
And our language is losing today.
So it's our role to recover it.
Thank you to invite me to attend this meeting.
It's a great pleasure.
Thank you for being here.
For those who don't know anything about the constitutional process that has been
started in Chile in 2020, could you give us an overview of the process that was
set up for the collective development of the new Chilean constitution?
What was special about it?
Yeah, I want to tell you that it was a very important process for
a lot of the Chilean people.
It didn't start at 2020 because it's born from the social movement.
Long time ago, I want to mention 2006 with a student from high school.
They initiate a very big demands for public education at that time.
So the student from university, they was also in the mobilization and call all of
the social Chilean movement.
So we had a very, very hard social situation in 2019.
Million of people took the streets at that time, demanding social rights for the people.
So the government and the parliament called for a special meeting in order to establish
an accord, a political accord to have a referendum to change the Pinochet constitution.
So they did it.
And then in 2021, we created the first Constituent's Assembly.
That included a hundred and fifty five conventional and that include also the
priority, also the indigenous nations and all the social movements and political parties.
So we started to to wrote the new constitution and in one year we got it.
And then we have a new referendum in order to approve or refuse the proposal.
That proposal included the right for nature, right for indigenous people,
parity in the women, equality between women and men, social rights and all of them for all of the
aboriginal nation too.
So, but we had a bigger difficult situation because the citizenship rejected the new
proposal. It was rejected in September 4th last year.
But the main topic, why it was rejected was the fake news, hate discourses, the people who are in
the rejection position, they create a lot of misinformation about the constituent process,
about the conventionals and people fear to give the votes for that new constitution.
Some of the fake news was they said that they will lost the house.
There is no right for to have a house.
There is no right to have, for instance, social security or they said that the indigenous people
want to divide Chile and the indigenous people hate the Chilean people.
So those were hate discourses and people have feared about that.
So they rejected the constitution, the new proposal that we wrote at that time.
So the government called for a meeting with the parliament and they decided to improve the process
and call for the second constitutional process.
We are today in the second constitutional process, but they modify the representation of the people
because they include a no democratic way to to vote, to elect the conventionals.
And they decide that half of all of the team that will wrote the constitution,
that they must be designated by political parties.
There wasn't a democracy process.
So they they decided to include people from political parties,
exclude the indigenous people.
And then there was we had a new referendum to to vote for the half 50, 51, a conventional again.
We had it just two weeks ago and but there was not a special seat for indigenous.
The indigenous people elected one Mapuche person to to represent the the indigenous
interests inside the second process.
But the designated conventional, they are today as assessor, political is a political teams
experimenting in contention in constitution.
They draw the the proposal and inside that proposal, there wasn't there was not people.
There were no there were people, indigenous people inside the design.
So in that second frame, there is no participation of indigenous people today.
The elected people from the council, they will review that proposal, the second proposal.
But we don't we are not agree with the misrepresentation of the indigenous people.
And we will have a next at the end of this year, we will have the new referendum to in order to
decide if we approve or we reject the new proposal.
The new proposal today, we don't know how that's that proposal will include indigenous
right or mother nature rights or women's rights.
Those are the more difficult topic for the conservative parties.
Today, the voice is for the conservative parties.
Were there special obstacles within the process for the Chilean constitution?
Because if I remember correctly, I think in Bolivia, for example, they had a constitutional
process, and it was different than the one in Chile.
And if I remember correctly, then I think in some talk that you gave you, I think you stated
that the way that it was set up, that there was a referendum after the process with a with
this certain percentage that would have to be reached, that this was a special obstacle
within the process for the Chilean constitution.
Is that right? Am I remembering this correctly, or is it was it a very regular process, the
way it was set up in Chile?
No, there is there is not a regular process in Chile.
The constitutional discussion is a democratic constitutional discussion is a new process
today in Chile, because the last constitution was written by the dictatorship regime without
social participation.
So this is the last process that we did from twenty twenty one.
It was a really new process because included all of the social movement.
It was for the first time in the history of Chilean society that a half part of the
conventional were women, for instance.
There is no constitution written by women in any in here and outside of Chile.
So that is was a very, very important.
And that is that was the difference between the Bolivian process, the Bolivian constitutional
process or Ecuador, a constitutional process, because here the the participation of women
was really were in equal relationship between women and men in that first process.
But today seem are very different because the this expert commission elected by political
party, they avoid all of the topic that we included in the first process.
So today is really different from the first process.
And one thing that is also very important is in the first process, we include the plurinationality.
The plurinationality is a political proposal that born in the Bolivian process, also from
Ecuador process, the indigenous people there, they they they speak about the plurinationality.
And we as we are also Chile is have a diversity of nation nation here.
So we included like plurinationality as the political way to resolve the conflict between
the state and indigenous people to overcome genocide, racism, damage, coexistence, also
to recover all of the collective rights, because there is no political solution from
the state to resolve ancestral or historical problem that that did the creation of the
states with aboriginal nation, aboriginal nation didn't participate in the creation of
the states. So for the first time, we included and we said, OK, we are different.
There are diversity of nation here.
So all together will define the framework, the constitution for all of the Chilean people.
So that is what's really strong and very important.
But in this second process, they avoid the plurinationality because they said that the
people rejected. But I told you that people rejected because of hate discourse.
It was not true that we are going we hope to divide Chile.
We need a relationship, equal relationship with Chilean society.
That's all.
And when it comes to plurinationality, how does that work if there are like conflicting
rights, since if there are different nations within the nation, so to speak, and these
different nations have different ideas of, for example, how the question of rights should
be approached? Is there a way how to address it when there are different opinions that
clash with each other?
Because I imagine it wouldn't be a good idea to simply overrule one over the other.
But there needs to be a process of getting to an understanding of the different forms
of how rights are being conceptualized within the nations in the nation.
I'm not sure if this was a question that can be understood.
Yeah, yes, yes, yes, I understand your question because people fear about the plurinationality
when they think that the indigenous will use the rights of the non-indigenous people.
And the question they did is, does the indigenous will have more rights than non-indigenous
people? You know, but there is no problem inside if you understand a lot of problem
that we had along the history with the indigenous.
The plurinationality first supports that Chilean society must recognize the pre-existence
of the indigenous because we were first here in that territory, then came the state.
The second point is, it's different to think about nations and state.
The state, it's an organization of nation.
But what happened with the internal colonialism inside the Chilean state?
They organized the state just with the white point of view, without the point of view of
indigenous people. So we have a long violation of human rights inside of our country.
We have genocide, the colonial project settled here in Chile and in America.
It was a genocide project that killed a nation, an aboriginal nation.
Not only nation, not only killed physically, they killed our culture, our language and
deprived us about our human rights.
We were not included as human inside the creation of the state from the beginning.
They said that we were like people from pre-logic, primitive, without conscience.
A lot of work in order to avoid our rights.
So your question is, we are in the 21st century and we are still alive today.
I am a teacher in the university.
I work every day with a Chilean student.
You know, my neighbor are Chileans.
So we need an equal relationship between them.
States, governments, after the dictatorship regime, they recognized that there was a
problem, historical problem, injustice problem inside of our state with indigenous people.
They create a law, they create a special commission in order to resolve that problem.
They vote in favor of the United Nations Declaration for Indigenous People, for
instance, or ELO Convention.
Our governments here give the votes in order to accept that ELO Convention that speaks
about a political right of indigenous people.
So, but what happened here in the country?
They, they erase the rights that they recognize internationally.
So what we need, we need those rights to be practices inside the country, inside the
society, and we need to live our rights.
I speaking about collective rights because they are individual rights and also collective
rights. Our rights are collective rights.
For instance, language is a collective rights because I can speak my language.
If I have, if I find somebody that is speaking my language, I need the collective.
Community is a collective right.
We the indigenous, we live in community.
We live with our family.
We have a big family because it connected with the community.
That is our collective right.
Autonomy and self-determination.
It's also a collective rights.
All of them was, were recognized by our governments.
So what we need today, we need to include it inside the law in order to live our right,
in order to, to, to be recognized as people, as human, you know?
So that's the topic that the Chilean people need to understand.
Those rights is not again the Chilean because we, we had our territory, but our
territory was occupied, but we need our territory in order to live and government
and a state have international instruments in order to solve that problem.
We need them, we needed to implement it.
And we are here talking about that topic in order to help to implement it.
The right, those rights collective that in our territory in democratic way.
This is the plural nationality.
So to resolve historical problem that have the state with the indigenous people in our
territory, using the democratic way of solution.
Very interesting.
One of the questions that I was asking myself when preparing is that on a certain level
that there seems to be a form of contradiction because you propose to use this element of a
constitution, of a constitutional convention in this case, of a constitution, which comes out
of a certain political tradition, a tradition of political theory as well.
And it is closely tied, for example, to a specific notion of subjects is and it's a
Western notion of subjects, a subject of reason.
You already pointed towards this, that is kind of underlying this notion of a
constitution as well.
And this is, of course, not unproblematic, because as you pointed out, indigenous people
were for a long time excluded from this notion of subject.
And I was wondering how these things can be brought together, because while there are
certainly aspects within this notion of subject that have served as a carrier, so to speak,
for also emancipatory projects, for example, broadly speaking, within a left humanist
project throughout history, this notion of subject has, of course, also been used as a
carrier for forms of domination and subjugation of other humans and also of nature.
So this has been an instrument of exclusion and oppression as well.
So my question would be, how can then a constitution, which is, as I said, an element of
Western political philosophy, you know, how can a constitution be thought of and enacted
without having to rely on this specific notion of a, let's say, liberal subject?
Yeah, yes.
So for us, I think that for all of the social movements around the world, we need to
understand that there is no, we are still keeping historical problems.
And the right wing, left wing, they promised to all of the society from all of the continent
that they will resolve the problem that we have in the society.
I'm speaking about Eurocentric philosophy.
I'm speaking about capitalism and about Marxism.
The idea of progress that it came to our continent is a political idea.
It's not an economical project.
It's an ideological project.
And European people believe at that time that with that solution, the progress inside of
our continent, they will solve the problem that we have here.
But progress never come to our territory.
Indigenous people, we are still, we are living without our rights.
I told you our collective rights.
Progress also doesn't solve the women rights.
Women were sacrificed by the progress ideology.
Indigenous was sacrificed by the progress ideology.
Nature was sacrificed by progress philosophy because they need to exploit it in order to
give social security for the people.
And that is not true because we don't, we are living without social security.
Indigenous people, there is no recognition of the right of women, for instance.
Women was considered like an inferior human from men, and men decide for women from the beginning.
I'm speaking about 1492 when the Spaniards came to our continent.
They did it in order to have a modernity in our continent.
But they sacrifice for the progress, sacrifice the people for the progress.
And Marxist ideology didn't say we have a violation of human rights
with that ideology.
They support the progress.
They support the progress because they said bourgeois are making progress.
We need that progress in order to resolve the, to have in the future unclass society.
But we need the progress.
They don't discuss the deep philosophy that was inside the progress.
Again, indigenous, again, against women.
Today we have those problems in everywhere.
So what we need today, we need to rethink about what we did in the past,
what the European culture did or philosophy, European philosophy did for all of the continent
because the progress born from Europe, it doesn't born from Africa.
It doesn't born from Latin America.
It was born in Europe.
And they use the ideology for all of the world.
Today the problem is in everywhere, in all the continent.
There is no solution for those, our rights.
So what we need today, we are in the 21st century.
We need to talk together.
We need to include diversity way of thinking because the colonial European Eurocentric
way of thinking doesn't give the solution to our problems.
And we support that there are philosophy, there are political models
or communitarian systems in our territory, inside of our society.
So we need to recover it in order to find together a plural solution
and include the plurality inside the democracy.
Because the democracies is defined by white people
and is defined by the idea of progress and democracy is still making sacrifice
of our people and also in everywhere.
So we need to modify our conception of state, our conception of constitution.
The way how to modify it is including the diversity, including different philosophy,
including all of our rights as human, individual and collective rights,
and also women's rights, but also nature rights.
Because we have other philosophy.
Indigenous people, we believe that nature is alive.
For instance, hers is alive and we need to be in relationship with nature.
And that's way of thinking is not include the right wing, neither in left wing.
So we need to talk, we need to share other way of thinking.
What would you say would be a good route to implement this different form of,
I would say, relationality towards nature for, in this case, in my case, for example,
for someone like me coming from a Western background.
Because I think that it's not a possibility to simply adopt Mapuche philosophy, for example,
because this is like a very different way, not only of thinking, but also
a philosophy that is enacted in a certain practice, as you already stated, rightly so.
And so for someone like me, for example, or for a constitutional convention in other countries,
let's say we would try to argue for a new constitution in Germany, where I come from,
and we would want to have a different form of relationality towards nature to be a part of this
new constitutional process and the constitution that will be brought about through this process.
We want a different form of relationality to nature to be inscribed into this constitution as well.
What would you say can be a framework that can be used for people that do not come from a
practice and from a also philosophical background that already has this different form of
relationality within it? How can we include it in processes that used to argue from a
perspective of Western philosophy, but will now have to develop into other forms of relation
towards nature as well? Do you have an idea of how to approach this task? Because it's a task
that is not only important for Chile, of course, it's important for the whole world, because
we can see how this very extractive logic, this logic of domination over nature,
how this is actually destroying the basis of our existence, and we need to find different ways to
relate it on a very foundational level. But it doesn't seem to happen somehow. Instead,
people are arguing for quick fixes without trying to really reflect upon this deeper relation.
I'm wondering if you have an idea of how to approach it in different contexts?
Yes. It's a very important question because we need to understand ourselves from a different
point of view. There are some theories that support diversity and plurality inside democracy,
but also there are a lot of practices that recognize ourselves connected because we are
not isolated inside the society. We need to have a critical point of view about development
I told you, but we also need to decolonize our mind, our practice, and we need to include a
new epistemology of the humankind way of thinking, because Eurocentric or European
philosophy, instead of European philosophy connected with capitalism, connected with
Marxism, I'm thinking about that kind of philosophy. It doesn't solve the problem.
We, as indigenous everywhere in every country, we have been in our territory
and using our own solution. We still keep our communitarian way of life. We are fighting to
protect our language because inside of our language, there is a philosophy inside. There
are a lot of knowledge that we need, so this is part of our struggle.
LW – But inside the big discussion, the global discussion, we need to problematize the
individualism that's born from the capitalist way of thinking. Today, the neoliberal system
destroyed the connection of the people, of human with the community. We are a member of a community.
We need to support the community inside of our life. Also, the topic about connecting with
the mother nature. We used to learn that, for instance, that the river is far from our
house, and we used to think about the water outside of us, the river outside of us,
wind outside of us. But what it is inside of our body? 75% of our body is water,
so the river is inside of us. What was the philosophy that supported the natural resource
are outside of the people? It was the capitalism system. It was the European philosophy
that just accept the rationality of man, not women. It's no difficult to include different
practice today, because we need that different practice inside of our family, inside of our life,
inside of our community, and inside of our country. On the contrary, we are not looking for the life
of ourselves, the life of my family, the life of the environment, because the pollution
is contaminated our life, so our environment, and there is no possibility to have life
in our place, in our space. We need to protect life, all kinds of life, our life, insect life,
animal life, because we need the biological diversity. We need it for the future of our humanity,
and all of the country, all of the culture in the world, we have the same environmental problem.
For instance, women problems, persecution of indigenous leaders, every, all of the country
have it, the discrimination, racial discrimination. So, my, the problem that the indigenous people
are have today in our community,
it's those problems you can also find it in your European, or in Europe, or in America, and everywhere.
So, but we need our, we need to pluralize our philosophy, our epistemology, and decolonize
our mind, because colonization put the one kind of way of thinking inside, like a rule for all of
the world, and that is not true. And within this process, what role does a constitution play,
or what role can it play in an ideal case? Because you have this plurality, but you also,
and that's like one possible role a constitution can play, you have the plurality within a larger
framework that is being defined through, in this case, the constitution. So, there is also
a form of, let's say, unity as well, created through the constitution itself as a certain
type of framework. So, what would you say, what's this relationship between the difference and the
sameness? And also, what can the role of the constitution be
in an ideal case? What can it do for the people? Yeah, there are different levels of solutions.
There is a communitarian solution. There are, for instance, participation of the social movement,
or the decision of women inside the social movement is one part of the solution.
And the state is an instrument, is a structure of power. But if that structure of power
doesn't recognize the rights of community, the right of women, the right of indigenous,
the right of the nature, that structure is a colonial structure.
And by the origin, the state was a colonial structure, but it's an instrument that all of the
country has today. We can't be autonomous. For instance, indigenous people, we claim for our
autonomy and self-determination in order to take our own decision. But the state, the state is
but the state is there. And the state is taking decision in using without us, without us today.
So, we need to be part of that, to be part of that decision inside the state.
But using our way of thinking, that will be an interchange between culture, I think. On the
contrary, all of the decisions that states take come from just from the white and the progress
and the progress philosophy or colonial philosophy. We need to contribute it.
That is the top level as the society was the design of society. The way of society is very
hierarchical way of thinking. That's hierarchy. The state is in the top.
But if the state respects our autonomy and self-determination, we can keep our
communitarian way of life. But the state had need to recognize it. On the contrary, the law persecuted
us. That's happening in our history. We were persecuted by the law of the state. When we
create our flag, we have a very beautiful Mapuche flag we created in 1992. And the state
persecuted us because we take the decision to have our own flag. What happened? And that was
because the state didn't recognize that the indigenous people have the decision
to have their own flag. Because the Chilean state didn't recognize that we are a nation.
We are not a state. We are a nation. And one state can have a different nation inside.
We apply for that solution to one state with different nation. And their experience in Europe
they are experienced in America. The state have different nation inside and recognize
the right of those nations. So we have plural state. We have multilingualism inside the state.
We also have juridical pluralism inside the state in North America, for instance.
Because there are people that are looking for the solution. And we can all go to find the solution.
That is, we just need to know what is going on in different parts of the world and to be responsible.
And to be responsible. All of us, we need to be responsible about nature. All of us
need to be responsible with cultural diversity, with multilingualism. We need it, you know?
So we need to talk about decolonize our way of thinking and the pluralism
right for nature, women's rights. All of those topics belong to decolonize, help us to decolonize
our way of thinking in order to have a new society, to have equal rights inside the difference.
Great. While you were talking, I was already reflecting that the word that I used
on the one side having plurality and on the other unity, that actually the word unity is the wrong
one, I would say, because I encounter these kinds of discourses also, for example, in the field of
there's a form of anarchist constitutionalism, and they have to deal with similar topics,
also with questions of plural forms of jurisdictions within a larger organizational form,
so to speak. And I have to correct myself in so far as it is not really about then creating a
meta unity. That's not the goal. It's to find a framework that works with the plurality
within it and can allow these different forms of approaches without bursting while doing so.
But I just wanted to note that I have to correct myself in terms of this word of unity,
because that's actually not the goal. It can have these parallel approaches without trying
to approach a higher level of unity, so to speak. So I just wanted to...
Yeah. One important thing to understand what I'm talking about is because I speak about the
diversity, about plurality, and our struggle is to have a society, a plural society, plural
way of life, different languages, different cultures, because inside the plurality,
inside the diversity, there are the richness of our humanity. So to force unity in one way,
as the European did, with unity connected with the progress.
That means the genocide for indigenous people.
Well, you know,
a very authoritarian way to think about the unity in one historical line.
Project develop European people
in one historical line, because they consider us, all of the Latin America,
means developed country that in the future will have the development, you know? Also international
institution speak about us like underdeveloped country.
They suppose that all of the policy that they did will help us for the development.
And what is the development? The progress.
But there was just one line of way of thinking. We were primitive, then we will be the Marxism,
said that we were first, we were primitive communism, you know, feudal society, then
feudal society, then capitalism, then the socialist, then we will have a
a common society without class. But in one line, in one progressive line,
in just one way of thinking, you know, and they implanted in everywhere.
Capitalism did the same. And state, neoliberal state today are doing the same. So this is,
this is why it's a part of our struggle to incide inside the state, to pluralize the state.
But it's not all of our struggle, because we need our communitarian way. We need to
keep our language. We need to recover our philosophy. We need to use our traditional dress.
We need to, to recover traditional knowledge about how to cook food, for instance.
What society today is wasting a lot of food on poor country.
There are children that they don't have food. The same happened with growth.
In Chile, we have a very beautiful desert at the north part of Chile. And the
company used our desert for clothes, old clothes. That's a pollution for our desert.
So this is why we need to pluralize our way of thinking, because just one way to consider
the society and the history destroyed our humanity.
Yeah. And I think I'll have to add that why I initially used the word unity, which is the,
which was the wrong choice. But what I wanted to initially actually point at is that,
that's why I find this notion of a constitution so interesting. And that you were the president of
this process, actually, because the very notion of a constitution can be such a tool to organize
this plurality. So that's at least from the contexts that I come from. For example,
I did interviews with Daniel Leuk, who's a person who works very much in the tradition of anarchism
and also looks closely at topics of how juridismus, juridism, I would say, maybe in English,
how this can be thought in very different ways without the coercive state, without the violence
of the state and stuff like that. And there are ways to approach these questions of, let's say,
societal-wide organization and regulation of plurality in this case. There are ways to address
this. And one of them, one way or an important tool might be the tool of constitution. And that's
why I think it's such an important and interesting combination that you are so heavily involved in
these both fields, like the insistence on plurality and the struggle for a different form of
constitution, because these two things fit together quite interestingly, I think, and not
only in terms of a defense against the state, because you can also think constitutionalism
without state at all. And that's like the next evolvement.
Yeah, you know, Aboriginal people, we had our own constitution, and it is oral. We learned about it
by oral tradition, because one constitution is a framework that organizes one society.
And all of the society, including Indigenous, we have our rules to organize our society
and to understand life, rights, our rights, and non-human rights.
So, but the modern society that is along the world have the state, and it's a reality. The state
is one reality. We need to change. Five centuries of colonialism,
the state is one reality. We need to change. Five centuries of colonialism.
And we had the state today making change inside of our children, for instance, by school.
Our children received the white history, not our history. White language, not our language.
Who did that? And who is doing that? The state law. This is why we need to change and modify
the inside, but it's not the last of our history, because we need to recover our spirituality.
We need to recover our mother's hair. We don't know the future today,
but we are suffering because what the monoculture and monolingual state and colonial state is doing
with our people. Maybe it's a transitory state, but we are suffering because we don't know the
future. Maybe it's a transitory solution,
because if you put the diversity inside the law, that will change the school.
If you put the language inside the law, we will have the right to listen to the news
on television, in our language, for instance. And that will modify. When I was the first president
of the constitutional process here in Chile, I was speaking mother tongue. And there are a lot
of people that never listened to Aboriginal language. For the first time, they listened
to the news on television, by the media, by TV. And that will make an impact, a social impact.
And we need those impacts to see we are here, we are alive, because a monocultural,
a monolingual state is denying us. And maybe you have a very strong anarchist movement inside,
or indigenous movement, but we just see ourselves in that movement. But what happened with all of
the society that are thinking that we are Barbaro, that we are not, for instance, here in Chile,
they said that we are a violent people, terrorism. So we need to make
to have the possibility to share with all of the society, because we are not isolated.
And we need to share in the majority of the mentality.
And we are here, we are the 10% of the Chilean society.
And when the first referendum about the constitution, 38% give the votes for the
plurality. But what happened with the other? We need to make change inside the mentality of
the majority of the people. And how can we do that? We need the institution, because the
system, political system use the institution in order to modify the conscience of the people.
Today they are not killing directly us, as the conqueror did long time ago.
But they are killing us using the institution, church, using media, school, military forces,
cinema, using all of those institutions to support one way of thinking.
So we need to make the plurality inside all of those institutions.
Elisa, there's a last question that I ask all of my guests. And this question is,
if you think about the future, what makes you joyful?
Yeah, the future must be diverse.
The future, I really appreciate the pluralism inside person. We need to be a plural person.
One language is not enough. So that is very important for the education today. We need to
recover the right for nature. Free lakes, for instance, free river, without pollution,
without pollution, without intervention. So also the women's rights,
because we are able to take our own decision. Why the man have to take the decision for us?
It's the same question in indigenous matters, because why white people have to take the decision
for us? We are not children. We are nations. So the future must be better without racism,
without colonialism. And we'll be better respecting mother earth as our mothers.
In my culture, we pray for the nature. We say thanks to the nature.
And I believe that if more people do and feel that
the mother nation will recognize us, all of us as their children or their
sons. So with different values. Society with different values that keep the life for us
and for the diversity, cultural diversity, biological diversity, and also with the
women decision inside the world. Because we have war today.
And women, we always keep, we take care, we know how to take care of other people.
And when one president, one country does the war, they don't think about children,
they don't think about elders, they don't think about the other. Maybe a woman
can think about other, but with other values. I'm not thinking now in Margaret Thatcher,
because he had a patriarchal way of thinking. We need to stop the patriarchalism too.
Thank you so much for being part of UJ histories.
Thank you for the interview. Have a good time.
That was our show for today. Thanks a lot for listening. If you want to support future
histories, you can do so on Patreon. For this visit patreon.com slash future histories,
or you can simply tell a friend that you like the show and that he, she, or they might like
it as well. Thanks a lot and hear you in two weeks.