Welcome to Future Histories, my name is Jan Gross and it is my great pleasure to welcome
Silvia Federici in today's episode.
She is a highly influential feminist scholar, teacher and activist known for her groundbreaking
work on the intersections of capitalism, patriarchy and reproductive labor.
I am very happy that this episode came together, since Silvia's work provides crucial insight
into the question of how the separation of spheres in which there is a sphere of production,
which is imagined as separate of a sphere of reproduction, how this imagined separation
might be overcome.
This podcast here has featured quite a few models of democratic economic planning, which,
I have to be honest, oftentimes struggle to treat this question adequately.
And it's great to have Silvia bring in her perspective on these topics.
And since we touch up on the topic of commoning and commons in the course of our conversation
as well, if you're interested in questions of how democratic coordination of commoning
on a scale, I wanted to point you towards the newly translated book by Stefan Merec
and Simon Sutterluty called Make Capitalism History.
You'll find the open access publication in the show notes.
And then another note, just like the episodes with Matt Huber and Elisa Longkorn anti-Leo,
this episode also came together because of a conference I was recently invited to take
part in.
The conference was titled The Great Transition, and I was invited to take part in a symposium
on democratic planning.
And I just wanted to take the chance to say thanks to everybody involved.
Before we start, I wanted to also thank Lukas, Wilfried, and Carl for their kind donations.
And now please enjoy today's episode with Silvia Federici.
Silvia, I'm thrilled and honored to have you on the show.
Welcome.
Yes.
Thank you so much.
And, you know, I would like this to be a conversation and you introduce me to the topic of today
and give me a little bit of the background of, you know, introduce your audience to the
issues and the topic that we're going to discuss today.
Yes, absolutely.
Well, I think we will start with a question that goes in the direction of your critique
towards the idea of progress, and then we'll kind of move along to topics of commons and
topics of democratic planning, maybe.
I'm very much interested in this topic.
And at the end, I will have some questions around the question whether or not we should
overcome the category of labor as such, because in some of the models for democratic planning,
for example, unfortunately, the category of labor is not overcome and there are still
some forms of connection between work and pay.
And I'm quite critical of this approach, so I would be interested in what you think about
it.
But we will start with a question on progress, if that's all right with you.
Of course, you know, but there is a broad literature to which, you know, I refer, actually,
that has criticized, you know, progress as enlightenment, bourgeois conception, you know,
that it's very evolutionary.
It's a very evolutionary conception, but has been used to actually justify, you know, capitalist
development, yes, justify and in a sense, you know, erase, erase the cost of it, erase,
you know, all the atrocities that capitalist development has left and in its wake.
So and, you know, sponsored in order to realize.
So progress, it's a great lie.
Progress is the great lie, you know, of capitalist ideology.
And in fact, we can really measure.
How do we measure progress?
I think this is a very fundamental question.
What are the value?
What are the core value that enable us to decide whether a society is progressing or not?
And within capitalist ideology, you know, progress is measured in terms of technological
development, so that today, for example, we can communicate Vienna and New York.
We can communicate this is progress.
Obviously, people could not do it in the Middle Ages.
But when we look, for example, today in terms of true exchange of knowledge, can we really
say that the technology has allowed human being as a whole, you know, the human community
to really exchange, grow in terms of its understanding of each other?
No, obviously not.
You know, we have a situation of permanent wealth here now in most parts of the world.
If we did have real progress, we wouldn't have two centuries of capitalist development
that have destroyed the life of millions and millions and millions of people.
No, so that when technological development is, in fact, as in fact, being primarily put
at the service, you know, of capitalist accumulation of individual private wealth and
military destruction, World War One, millions of people killed, World War Two, the threat
of nuclear warfare, we are now speaking of a society in which even life, even human life
is such because of the technology, because of the very so-called technological development
that is associated with the notion of progress, then we can see that we have to really
reconceptualize what is valuable, you know, what is that we should struggle for, what kind of
society we want to construct. So let's leave behind as totally tainted the notion of progress
and instead seeing that this development that is associated with progress, you know,
as in fact brought more and more misery, more and more impoverishment. Today there are millions
and millions of people who are totally impoverished, who have been expelled from their lands,
whose cultures have been destroyed, thousands of languages, species, you know, natural species,
and also human community have been completely destroyed. Entire cultural world is like,
what progress is that? What is the measurement we use? So this is my response to progress.
There is this strand within like orthodox Marxism, which likes to argue that first there
has to be capitalism that would sufficiently develop the forces of production and only then
on the basis of that, like real communism would be possible. And of course, you refuse this notion,
but I'm asking myself, what does this mean for alternatives to capitalism then for
this idea of transition as well? Because I have to think, for example, about the recent work of
Kohai Saito. I don't know if you're familiar with his work. He's developing this idea of degrowth
communism, which is kind of arguing in a similar direction that progress in the capitalist sense
is not necessary to develop communism. I would be interested in your opinion
on what does this mean to reject this specific idea of progress for the question of alternatives
to capitalism. Absolutely. So the question of, I think, Marx's idea, and you know,
it would be very interesting. I think that probably Marx lived at the historical
and political conjunction. This is the sense I can make of it, that he lived at historical
political conjunction, where the possibility of a broad social change, of a crisis of capitalism,
of the end of capitalism, seemed to be near, seemed to be soon possible. Therefore,
you know, this image, you know, of the worker who takes over the capitalist machine
and now redirects it, you know, once, you know, redirects it to a different goal, redirects it,
you know, to the benefit of humanity, to an egalitarian, the purposes of an egalitarian
society, etc., etc. So I think this is how I can justify Marx's idea that in a way, capitalism,
obviously, you know, capitalism, a necessary stage, well, necessary because it was an inevitable
stage from the point of view, you know, obviously of the power relation in Europe, but that it would
be necessary, you know, for constructing the condition, you know, of a communist society,
you know. As I said, Marx must have come to this conclusion only because he believed the revolution
was imminent. Otherwise, he would have had to consider what is the cost, you know, of a process
of large scale industrialization across the world, even from the point of view,
right, of, you know, what it costs to industrialize the globe in terms of its impact of nature.
But that's only one consideration. What he did not consider is the capitalist development
destroys the very condition for a communist society, creates technological conditions,
but destroys other conditions, destroy, for example, changes, people's subjectivities,
you know, destroys common solidarity, destroys commonality, and, you know, so whereas
it creates, you know, new technological means, new technological means, at the same time there's
a process of destruction, of destruction of human relations, you know, that makes the advantage of
a new technology, the advantage of a new technology, right, you know, limits tremendously what the
advantage, and there's a third consideration, which is, is it really technological underdevelopment
that was the cause in the Middle Ages or other society, you know, of people's misery, of people's
hunger, of communities inability to reproduce themselves, or it was the social relation,
the fact that in the Middle Ages you had a feudal old, a feudal world that was built on the
exploitation of people, where those who made decision was a military class, right, so the idea
that in a way capitalism was necessary because it provided the means to, you know, overcome hunger,
overcome poverty, overcome scarcity, no, technology was never the problem of scarcity,
technology, the lack of technology, and we know, for example, that there were other roads to
technological development, for example in China, China had reached a quite high level of technological
development by the 16th century, there were other roads to technology, other than the capitalist one,
that the fact that the capitalist road to technological development, you know, was built
on the exploitation of labor, on the destruction of community, on violence, all this also
undermined, you know, the advantages, and moreover, what, what technology was invented,
capitalism invented a technology that was instrumental to exploitation,
it's not the technology, technology is not a general term, technology is not a universal,
you know, road or a form of wealth, you know, what kind of technology capitalism has developed,
other type of technology, the technology capitalism has developed has always been a
political technology, a technology that served to defeat, right, to contrast, you know, work as
solidarity, work as capacity to resist, work as capacity to struggle, so it is the technology
that has always had built within it a political problem, capitalist technology has always built
within itself elements that made it impossible to take over by a communist, a real communist
society, for instance, disregard for nature, a technology that has disregard for nature is not
a technology we can use, it's not a technology that should be generalized across the world,
a technology that is built within itself, you know, a program that is antagonistic to work as
solidarity, antagonistic, so yes, capitalism brings workers together, but how it brings workers
together, not in a way that enhances their solidarity, so I think that Marx was wrong
in terms of this idea that of the transfer of technology, right, okay, so the revolution
and then we take over the machine and we put the machine to good use, well that machine could not
be put because it had built-in problems, other machines have to be used, no, and secondly,
it did not see the kind of devastation, you know, and now it's all too obvious,
now it's all too obvious. One last thing, I don't particularly, of course, I'm against the idea of
capitalist growth because capitalist world growth is capitalist development, it's capitalism,
right, but I don't think that growth is the enemy, the enemy is capitalism, growth is a
subcategory, it's a subcategory, it's one of the pieces, right, it's one of the strategies
that capitalism uses to reproduce itself, no, but it's not growth, the enemy is capitalism,
the enemy is the exploitation of nature and humanity, this is the fundamental and in this,
in a way, I agree with Marx, you know, that I think that the powerful expert and still alive
and still fundamental expert of Marx's work, you know, is having focus and identify capitalism
as a system that is built, you know, on the accumulation of people's labor, on the exploitation,
on expropriation, dispossession, right, on therefore these forms of, you know, alienation,
enslavement, et cetera, et cetera, and constant immiseration because once you take away from people
the means of their reproduction, then there is no limit to how much you can immiserate their life,
and we see now where we live in a world of permanent welfare, permanent dispossession,
millions and millions thrown, you know, into refugee camps, you know, entire areas,
you know, of the world destroyed by climatic change. So, yes, we really need to rethink
this idea about the necessity of capitalism, God forbid.
Yeah, and I would really like to explore a bit the question of alternatives because
if we do not go along the road of ideas of, let's say, socialist modernity, so to speak,
what is the alternative that you would like to come about? I mean, you already pointed towards
we, of course, need alternative social relations. We might also need alternative technologies,
you pointed out. I mean, you are quite famous for your engagement with this idea of commoning.
It's an important part of your research. I'm quite sure that commoning would have to be an
element of the alternative as well, but there are many examples where commoning works quite well
within communal structures up to a certain size, I would say. Community-supported agriculture would
be one example, and there are many, many more, and there are also examples for commoning on a global
scale in the realm of digital commons, which are easily reproducible and, let's say, nonrivalous.
There are less examples for global commons that are rival resources, so to speak. I would be
interested in how you think about what might collective forms of organization look like
at a level of society as a whole that are organized along this principle of commoning.
Yeah, so first of all, what commons will be like is almost very difficult, and I don't think it is
useful to actually have a map, a theoretical political map now, because even our own imagination
is very much conditioned by what we have, but the situation that we are living. So the definition
of what kind of a communal society will be, you know, is something that is a process,
and it's something that can be defined only in a process of struggle, and in a process of struggle,
and the coming together of different struggles across the globe, because there's not one model,
as Massimo de Angelis has written over and over and very eloquently, the idea
that, you know, in this great globe, Asia, Africa, with different history, different climatic
situations, different trajectories, that there could be a model of commons, that this is
unthinkable. Like the Separatists say, many yeses, one no, no to the exploitation,
no to capitalism, and then many yeses, many roads, different roads, you know,
shaped by the historic trajectories, the historic struggles that people have made,
right? So this is very, very important, and I think, first of all, no to global commons.
There's no such a thing as global commons. Who's going to be the agent to make decisions
on a global level? We don't have a global subject. Now we have the UN, and we know what the
disaster the United Nations has been. So if we're talking about, and here we are already entering
the discussion of what is democracy. Democracy is the rule of the people. So how do people rule,
you know, who is the global subject, right? The idea of a global superstructure, this is what
capitalism has, has created, and we know what the global superstructure is. Capitalism is the
United Nations, which is really the, you know, institutional face of capital, international
capital. So no to that global idea of a global commons. I want to quote here, over and over,
Maria Mies, who just died, you know, a great feminist, one of the most lucid, powerful
anti-capitalist voices within the feminist movement. And she was very adamant about rejecting
the idea of the global commons, right? And so, you know, what we are talking about, you know,
is instead replanting, you know, rerouting, you know, decision making, the construction of
community, you know, and the construction of commons, right, on localities, which doesn't mean
that they are fragmented, isolated, and unconnected. Absolutely not. And here I,
you know, I want to make reference, for instance, to what, you know, what we call Latin American was,
you know, before the conquest, before colonization, you know, when you had, you know, a vast world
all throughout, you know, from the south of the continent to the north, of local economies,
local society, and yet with a tremendous amount of exchange, with a tremendous amount of
interconnection, right? So it's not true that to think of local commons is to think,
you know, of isolation, of going back to the Stone Age. Not at all. Not at all. It means that
to have, for example, for instance, of confederacies of commons, you know, and of
course today we also, some of the technologies, some of the means that are in existence can also
be used, can also be used, but with great discrimination, with great discrimination.
And about digital commons. Well, digital commons, right? I'm always a bit hesitant
and skeptical, you know, before embracing them, because when I think of digital today,
I immediately think, you know, massacres in the Congo. This is what I immediately think.
Not only the Congo, but I'm thinking of lithium. I think, where's the lithium coming from?
Where's the coltan? Where's the real earth? Where are all the minerals?
And so far, you know, those minerals have been the disaster, have been the cause of wars,
have been the cause of massacres, have been the cause of recolonization of entire areas of the
world. So unless we find, you know, unless the question of not only what can be done with the
digital, but how the digital is produced, unless the question becomes central to the discussion on
digital commons, then I have to say, no, this cannot be the solution, because we have to
realize that behind much of the warfare and much of the predatory practices, the incredibly
predatory practices of international capital today, especially in Africa, Latin America,
there is exactly, you know, the need to feed this new technology, right? And unfortunately also,
you know, the new green technology, the one that is supposed to, you know, save the earth,
right? Which now depends on the production of billions of batteries, you know, for electrical
cars. Where are those batteries going to go? In which ocean? In which fields? Who is going to be
the beneficiary of all that poison that is going to leak out of those batteries?
So I think we have to be careful with the digital commons. And I think we need instead to see what
gives power back to community, back to the people who are knowledgeable about the condition of the
earth, of the soil, and the condition of the social relation of the places in which they live.
I mean, it's also the construction of humanity. You know, we are becoming, and now we're AI,
and you know, we are becoming zombies. We are really, you know, artificial intelligence is a
big problem. The problem is also the mechanization of human beings. The mechanization of human beings.
I'm really flabbergasted about how much, you know, population that seem to have all this power,
the computer, the little phone, and so on, you know, are in fact unable to really impact
in a significant way the politics, you know, of international capital. And at times,
I even think that precisely access to these gadgets, you know, have in a sense put back the
struggle, dozens and dozens of years. In other words, the capitalism, you know, with the computer,
with the iPhone, the iPad, and all of that, you know, as pacified, as succeeded in pacifying,
and giving people assimilated of a power that in fact we don't have. Yes, we can call this,
yes, we can call that, but actually decisions are being made that are extraordinary, extraordinary.
We have people in the streets in New York. We have people dying in the streets in New York.
We have the largest incarceration, the larger number of people incarcerated. This society,
which is, you know, the leading capitalist society, presumably in prosperity, you know,
is a society where people are dying in the street, where we have the life, where people have been
executed with summary processes, you know, not to mention, not to mention, you know, the 800 jails
that the US is running across the world, the military intervention in much of the world,
and we are not able to stop it. And so I've been wondering how much this technology,
which has been thrown at us and made more available, has also given this pseudo-empowerment,
pseudo-empowerment, and I'm not saying that there are not advantages to it,
right, but certainly we are very unaware on a day-to-day basis of the cost of this technology.
We don't know whose fields have been expropriated in order to create the iPhone,
right, that we use on a day or the computer that we use. We are totally unaware of that.
So the distancing also, the capitalism has produced the distances of the places where
things are extracted, where things are produced, and where things are consumed.
That distances that makes us irresponsible, responsible and irresponsible, right? It's
really a serious problem. So we need actually to bring together production and consumption
so that we know, that we know if the oranges we eat, if the clothes that we wear have caused
somebody's blood, have caused somebody's life, have caused somebody's loss of land and forced
migration. Yeah. Let's maybe dig a little deeper into that because this idea of bringing together
production and reproduction, or maybe in other terms transcend this idea of separation of spheres,
this is really important, I think, as you already pointed towards right now. I would
be interested in what this might look like in connection to this question of organization,
because you refused this idea of a global commons that would have a form of meta-organization,
so to speak, but you also pointed out that there will be quite a lot of coordination going on
between the different commons. So maybe we can cross these two. Then the question would be,
what would a form of organizing a mode of reproduction, so to speak, what would that
look like when these separations of spheres of production on the one side and reproduction
on the other is overcome? So how to organize a, let's say, mode of reproduction between these
different commons and projects and whatever entities there might be to coordinate with?
Yeah. This, of course, again, that cannot be a universal model. I mean, I imagine if you are
living in Eskimo land or if you're living in Mozambique, there are very different
possibilities, right? I'm thinking, for instance, in pre-Columbian America, the example of Peru,
you know Peru is a very elongated territory, and that elongated territory made for very different
types of cultivation, very different types of cultivation. So Peru, before the conquest,
was very alive, was an intricate system of exchanges that enabled people within a limited
territory after all, you know, to in fact benefit, you know, from production coming from different
areas, from different types of production. And, you know, of course, now we are in another world,
but this is something that now we can think of, right? In other words, when I was speaking of,
you know, the Confederacy of Commons, you know, I think that this also has implications on the
condition of production, which means that exchanges, yes, but not exchanges, you know,
you go to a supermarket today and, you know, perhaps the fish in the United States, you know,
may be coming from Africa or may be coming from across the world. And it's different if the fish
may come from Long Island or from areas. And so where, in fact, the possibility of the economic
exchange, right, is not only an ecological disaster as it is today, all these boxes,
all these boats, all these that are really destroying the planet,
but also allows for the circulation of human relations, so that you know the people from
which the food is coming. They are actually human social, cultural interchanges. This is a kind of
world that we want to reconstruct. And today we have in a very atomic form, you know, with the
community-supported agriculture, for instance, as a little, as a microcosm, right? But when you look
and analyze it and you expand it, as if on a computer, and you expand it, then you see that
what is being exchanged, you know, is not only the food, what is being brought to the city from
the farms and so on. It's not only the food, but there is also a whole set of relations, right?
People are getting to know, yeah, who are the producers. You begin to develop a relationship
of trust, right? You begin to understand more about what is actually being produced, you know?
What are the vegetables of this season? You don't have these, you know, plastic enveloped,
you know, universal, ever-present, you know, ever-available, you know, food production,
no? But you actually begin to understand. So there is a richness that we have lost.
There is a richness of, and I think of that way, I think of the way of expanding scale,
you know, every different modalities, obviously, depending on, you know, communities on the
mountains, communities on the sea, you know, but something along those lines, you know, it's,
I think, and I come back to my original point that much of this is also something that we learn
in the process of the struggle, which is, has to be a process of construction,
not just resistance, but construction, experimentation. The struggle is a moment
not only to say no, but to experiment with alternative. From the beginning, there is no
real struggle unless it is accompanied by an immediate transformation of relation among the
people who are doing the struggle. Unless the struggle immediately constructs something new.
It's not just a no, but it's a yes to a different kind of social relations.
Maybe we can carve out...
I say the commons are a condition of the struggle, are a condition of the social
transformation. They are not just the goal, the objective of the social transformation.
They are the conditions. They are the ones that make it possible.
Yeah, and I mean, I think even though you kind of are a bit hesitant to reach too far ahead in
order not to prescribe some form of model or something like that, I still think that there are
some, let's say, maybe basic coordinates that can be distilled from this type of approach. So,
one you just pointed towards, it's not just about resistance, but also about construction.
Maybe one might say creative construction, experimental construction.
I think there are some basic coordinates that one might distill from this approach.
For example, as I pointed towards earlier, this question of labor and whether or not in alternative
modes of, in this case, modes of reproduction, one would want to reproduce this category of
labor or not. Because within the models of democratic economic planning that I engage with,
oftentimes these socialist models of democratic planning that I know, they usually tend to
reproduce and maintain this category of labor along with a form of remuneration that is paid
in exchange for work. So, this remuneration is, of course, not a classical wage relation then,
because it doesn't involve a surplus that is going to a capitalist. But still, the category of labor
as such and this exchange relation in the form of work for pay tends to be reproduced. I would be
interested in how you think about this, because within these models, at least, the rationale,
the argument of the people developing these models is kind of along this traditional idea of
two-phase model developed by Marx in the Goethe Program, where the idea is that you would have to
have a first phase where this connection between work and pay is still in place. And then afterwards,
you would have the ability to come to a second phase. But this all rests on this idea of progress
that you, of course, reject. So, I assume you would reject this two-phase model as well and the idea
of continuation of labor as a category as such as well. Am I right in assuming that?
So, it's a long story. Too much.
A lot of things. No, I disagree. The idea of the two-phase is not the idea of progress.
I just, the idea of progress is the ideas of this almost natural development that is attributed
to social. It's a way of naturalizing social relation and particularly capitalist relation,
right? Inevitably. So, the old is bad and we're going towards the new and the new, of course,
and also the connection with technology. No, labor. First of all, the distinction,
I think also in Marx, labor and work, right? The idea of labor implies exploitation. Labor implies
exploitation. So, I think there's a difference between labor and activity, right? Activity,
creative activity, self-determined or collectively self-determined. Not individually, but activity
that is very different from labor which is done under somebody else's, you know, decision-making,
et cetera, right? So, I think in terms of the transition and the question of money,
you know, I think in terms of a transition and I faced this issue so many times because there was
a time in my life I was involved in a feminist international organization called Wages for
Housework and we were accused of institutionalizing women in the home. We were accused of
confirming capitalism, monetizing the only sphere of life in which, you know, love, et cetera, et
cetera. And I famously, you know, thought that, you know, famously because that has been the most
popular things I've said in my life. Yeah, you know, they call it love. We call it unpaid labor.
And I still stay behind it. I still subscribe to it. So, the question of money. The question of
money is two points I want to make. Number one, struggle for monetary compensation. It's inevitable
until we can change the power relation between workers and capital because as long as we do not
re-appropriate the material condition of our reproduction, then we need to use money. Otherwise,
we die. The Zapatistas who have been, you know, the group of people, to my knowledge, who have
been most advanced in refusing monetary relation, they still use some money. They sell coffee for
monetary compensation because they have not been able yet to create all the material condition
of reproduction that are necessary without some money. So, as long as we are in a society
where the capitalist class still monopolizes, you know, much of the material condition, the land,
the soil, the waters, the technology, et cetera, et cetera, money is both a way of guaranteeing
some reproduction and also sucking wealth away from the capitalists. Obviously, that struggle
is not the struggle that is going. It's a struggle that is necessary, but it's also a
struggle that has to be accompanied by many, many, many other, you know, struggles. It's not this,
the main road, you know, to revolution. But we cannot say, and I used to, my response to people
who were critical of wages for households was to say, well, very good. Give up your wage. You are
teaching a university. Give up your wage. Liberate yourself from this bondage to capitalism. Work
for free. Of course, nobody has done that. Of course, you've been conceivable, you know. So,
I found the hypocrisy, the double standard. You know, I found that, you know, once again, yes,
you know, women's work in the home is treated as something very different. And no matter how much
you show that is the foundation for every labor activity, that is work that is exploited by
capital, is work that produces accumulation, creates work, blah, blah, blah, blah, etc. And
that has put women in the condition of, you know, having to accept any wage once they went out of
home. So, I think the money, you know, there is a phase of struggle. And that phase of struggle,
the goal of it is to change the poverty relation and reappropriate. So, to me, the goal of our
struggling every, every moment, every place, every moment is reappropriate, you know, the wealth
that has been produced, the wealth that we are producing, you know, control, I mean, land,
the issue of land, millions of people, land, land, land, land means everything. Land means trees,
land means waters, you know, land means, you know, leaves, medical roots,
land has such, is such wealth that when you lose your wealth, land, you lose much more than
physical sustenance, you lose a culture, you lose knowledges, you lose a tremendous amount of
knowledge when you lose the land. So, that process, you know, and I think in terms of
a future society, you know, in terms of, I think of a society without money or with money,
but money, see, that's the issue. What is money? And I'm thinking, I'm now, this is the issue of
money is really matching my mind because I'm really interested in the relation between women
and money. You know, what has been historically women? Yeah. And, you know, I have this book in
mind, which is called Women, Money and the Devil, that, you know, begins with the pact on the devil
between the witch and, you know, the devil gives her money. And then of course she, she's desperate,
you know, and she's, you know, screaming to her misery, he comes, give us some money.
And eventually, of course, has become my servant, I'll solve your problem. It's a very marital deal,
totally marital. And then she copulates with him. But within a few days, the money has given her
turns into ashes. This has intrigued me. In many demonologies, you find that detail.
And this has intrigued me immensely. Why? Even once they made the pact, even when they sold their soul,
women could not keep the money. Even when they sold their soul, capitalism has instituted this
incredible incompatibility between women and money. But aside from this, money has existed. I
visited many years ago with my partner, we visited the first place in Turkey. And right now I don't
have the, I don't remember the name. Yeah, but it's a famous place, but 3000 years ago,
the first coins were minted. 3000 years ago. But money had a very different function
than capitalist money. Money had ceremonial function, money sometimes served, so you didn't
want to bring, to move cattle, et cetera, et cetera. So you'd use the money as a substitute
for the transportation of goods. But money is different in capitalism and begins to function
capitalistically only when you have a society where people have been expropriated from the
capacity to reproduce themselves. At that moment, money function a different way,
right? At that moment, money is not just exchange. Money becomes an instrument of exploitation.
It becomes an instrument of, because then those people can be forced to work,
can be forced because their sustenance belongs to them. The moment that whatever allowed you to
survive is sucked away from you, then money becomes really the way that basically takes your
blood away, can take your blood and your life away. So I think it's very important. So when we say
there will be a future without money, maybe there will be money, but we will be functioning in a
very, very different way. Maybe it will be like maybe a token that you go to a movie theater
and you have a token that you show and with that token you enter the, you know,
you can enter, gives you the right to enter it. But I agree with Mark's view that the last,
you know, communism as from each according to their ability and to each according to their need
and decision made by the association of the community. That to me, it's a good model to look
at and what could be a money, but certainly not money. Money will not be able to function
because it will be a society in which the wealth, the material condition of reproduction
will be accessible to everybody in the community.
And that's the basis of democracy. A democracy without that access is nothing. It's a world as
it has become. Today the market, you know, the big democracy of the United States, we have people
sleeping in the street, you know, where you have, you know, pharmaceutical companies, you know, who
have killed the millions of people with this, you know, narcotic medicine and so on, you know,
can go scoff free by paying a few, a billion dollars and are not held to the same standard,
you know. So you can go to jail for 20 years, you know, for a little theft, but you have big companies
who are devastating the life of people. So that's not democracy.
I just wanted to maybe clear up a form of misunderstanding that might be in place,
because I just wanted to state that I'm absolutely with you that within a, like,
let's say early transition phase or within the immediate future, it's of course necessary to
fight for higher wages and not kind of dismiss money as something that we would not need in order
to live within the context that we live in right now. The thing is that within these models that
I study, these models for democratic economic planning, they argue that even though a situation
is already in place in which there is democratic control over the economy, that still then there
would need to be some form of connection between work and pay in place in order to, let's say,
discipline its subjects, at least for a certain period of time, because it is assumed that this
would still need to be necessary, actually at the end, for reasons of efficiency, so to speak,
you know. So in order to be able to reproduce a certain type of wealth in material terms,
it would still be necessary to, you know, have these mechanisms in place. And that's why I said
there is a connection between this idea of a two-phase model and this idea of progress,
because then the argument is essentially we do not yet have enough capacity when it comes to
the forces of production in order to have full communism. And until then, we would need to kind
of discipline our subjects in order to get to this place of fully developed forces of production.
And that's why I meant that there is a certain connection between the two ideas, you know.
I understand, but I'm very suspicious of the discipline. Who's going to do the discipline?
Who's going to be disciplined? So that to me, that plan, that democratic planning is not something
that I would, you know, sign up for, because when I hear discipline, all my, you know,
practice say run for the gun when you hear these words, because very dangerous. This sounds like
capitalism. You need to actually whip people to work, decide who's valuable, who's not valuable,
and reproduce, you know, the whole mark, as Mark should say, the hierarchies, the control system,
the two-tier society. That's exactly what we are fighting against.
Yeah. I mean, to be fair, I think the people developing these models, they would, of course,
argue that there is a base income for everybody. And on top of that, you would have these
remuneration schemes that would allow to, as I said, kind of discipline its subjects.
I think they wouldn't call it disciplining. In my eyes, it is still disciplining, and I'm against
this kind of approach, but I just have to be fair in terms of showcasing their arguments for that.
And there's another argument that maybe complicates the whole thing a bit more,
and this argument is actually coming from a feminist perspective, in which the argument
goes that within a totally voluntarist societal organization, there might be a danger of running
into a situation where, again, people who are most vulnerable are kind of having a worse situation
when trying to organize this reproduction of societies. In this feminist critique,
I think the argument would be that the transparency that comes along with forms of remuneration and a
general obligation to work is seen as a guard against a continuation of unjust relations
in the sphere of reproduction within post-capitalist configurations. So this would be,
I think, the argument. I don't see anything
voluntaristic in what I'm talking about. I'm not seeing anything. I'm seeing a transformation
of social relation that occurs in the process of the struggle. I mean, look, if we want to look,
for instance, at societies that are running now on a more communal system, right? I mean, yeah,
look, there is a Guatemalan-taken feminist who has written a very beautiful book,
Gladys Tsutsun, where she discusses what has been the history and the organization
of communal work, society, of Totonicapan, which is in the Highlands of Guatemala.
And she describes a situation where there is a culture, there is a collective agreement.
Collective agreement, because it's stipulated through assemblies, is the assembly. The assembly
is the whole. You make the decision, but you have to contribute to the reproduction of the society.
So you may call that disciplining, but the fact is that you cannot, if you don't actually,
there is a general agreement that in order to keep the society going, something, you know,
you have a little responsibility, you have to do something, you know? And even if you migrate,
even if you migrate, you have to have something. And even when you return as a migrant after many
years, you can return as a tourist or you can return as a participant. Participating means that
you begin to take responsibility again. That seems to me very, very fair, very democratic.
By the time you are a child, nine or 10, there's little things that you're given to do, and you're
understood that you're part of a collective and you have to do, etc. That seems to me as nothing
voluntaristic. There is nothing voluntaristic. It's a collective decision-making on the basis,
calculated on the basis of the resources that are available, not out of some imagination,
but on the basis of this is like a high mounting place, but where there is a culture of collectivity
and is a culture that gives a tremendous protection. You're not born in, you know,
that the community will support you and where there's an immense solidarity also with the
people who die. You know, the dead, there is a cult of the dead, the dead are present.
You know, as soon as somebody dies, there's enormous amount she described by everybody. So
the death is not as fear as the end. The sense of belonging to something is something that you
understand, extend your life beyond your physical life, which is a great sense of power. Instead of
the sense of desperation and finitude, thinking, oh my God, all is lost, because you are actually
part of a collective body. You're beginning to feel that there's a collective breath and a
collective body, very powerful. And, but there are, you know, from the very early age, the idea
that, yeah, you have to do something. And if you don't, if you don't do anything, then you should
not make the decision. You don't speak in the assembly unless you've done the work. I think
it's a great idea, by the way. I think it's a great idea that we should use and it's not
voluntaristic. Yeah, I understand. And, but would you say then that this is always tightly coupled
to a contextual idea of community? Because this agreement, so to speak, is more or less based on
rules that are part of a cultural socialization, so to speak. And do you think that this can be
achieved in larger context as well, or in a really large scale context as well? Or does it need to be
kind of more or less tied to a community that has a certain size and is therefore able to,
let's say, put practice behind this ideal so that it is not just an abstract rule?
Yeah, but this is the idea, right? First of all, I think there's a struggle also in these
indigenous communities, and what I understand talking to women from indigenous communities,
to expand the community so that, for example, people who are not being raised in that culture
can also be part of it, for example, through marriage and other forms. And so these communities
are not frozen. And I think that the women are, in fact, the most important agent of change.
But this goes back to the idea of how to be organized, because if we are talking about real
democracy and people making decisions about their life, then there has to be a certain rootedness
in the sense that you have to know your locality. You have to know the possibilities.
You cannot make decisions for places far away for the fishermen when you are in the mountain.
So the idea of the Confederacy, the idea of exchanges, the idea of, you know, what I was
talking before, you know, the assembly might be a thousand people, but then you connect with the
assembly right all across the highlands of Guatemala. It doesn't mean that because,
you know, you have a decision making by a community which is somewhat limited in size
and has commitment that relate to all kinds of decision and cultural practices that date from,
doesn't mean that you don't also open to other similar communities and that you don't have
exchanges. The question is when you begin to have a decision making that is removed
from the people who are actually suffering the consequences of that decision making.
And here we cannot have it two ways. If you want to be in control of the consequences
of decision making, then you cannot make decisions on a global level. I cannot decide for people in
Patagonia. I cannot make decisions for people that cry. I can struggle with them when they ask me
solidarity to fight against fracking in Patagonia. I can struggle with them, but I cannot make
decisions for the people in Patagonia. And we don't have got to go as far as Patagonia, but I mean,
I cannot make decisions for people in Colorado or in Alabama, right? But I can struggle with them
because obviously we'll have similar conditions, et cetera, et cetera. And we have those agreements.
So I think that this is what we have. And of course, back to the original point,
that the struggle is the gray field of experimentation and the gray field of
transformation. This change to this new society, to a society where we have this culture, where
we have this commitment, where we have this solidarity, it's going to be a tremendous
process of transformation. We all carry a lot of capitalism within ourselves. The struggle does
not only transform the world, but has to transform who we are. There's one question I ask all of my
guests at the end, and this is, if you think about the future, what makes you joyful?
What is the alternative? I have to be joyful. I have to be joyful because I'm like, you know,
I often quote a poem, a poet from Greece, 1300 BC, 1000, Mimmo Nermo. He wrote something that I
learned as a, you know, a young person and stayed with me. Life is a tragedy, it's a comedy or a
tragedy. And you either learn to laugh of the most great sufferings, or you'll forever cry.
You know, and it's not laugh, but it's an affirmation of life. It's an affirmation of life.
And here I want to end quoting Maria Mies, quoting Maria Mies, my great sister who died,
and it's been a great pain to lose her. And she used to tell the story, she was full of life,
life-affirming person, very creative, very life-affirming. And she used to think of her
mother, who at the end of World War II, when the whole world in Germany, you can imagine,
right, in ruin, in front of a life of ruin, she pulled up her sleeves and, you know,
this was a peasant community and bought a few piglets and said, well, life has to go on,
I still have to feed my children. And this, you know, in Ecofeminism, a book that she wrote
with Vandana Shiva, in the introduction to it, you know, there is a beautiful, beautiful sentence
that I almost memorize, I see if I can, you know, it says that when in this world,
in this world of capitalism, that is devoted, seems to be devoted to the destruction,
to such a destruction of nature and human life, our world can be summed up in terms of a struggle,
you know, to nourish, to nourish the impulse, the great impulse, which is in every living thing,
which is the impulse to reproduce themselves, which is in how to live, to continue.
And this is what, you know, I, this is what makes me, makes me, gives me joy, is to see
that we have to start with what is living, with what is moving, with what the new children are
born every day. What do we say to them? Oh, too late, too late. Capitalism is destroyed
too much, but they are born now. So we have to give them something. Wonderful. Sylvia,
thank you so much for being part of Future Histories. Thank you. Thank you, Jan. Thank you,
Jan. All the best. Bye.
That was our show for today. Thanks a lot for listening. If you want to support Future
Histories, you can do so on Patreon. For this, visit patreon.com slash future histories,
or you can simply tell a friend that you liked the show and that he, she, or they
might like it as well. Thanks a lot and hear you in two weeks.