Welcome to Future Histories.
My name is Jan Gross, and my guest today is Richard Barbrook, who is, amongst
other things, known for coining the term Californian ideology as an early critique
of Silicon Valley techno-determinism.
He and Andy Cameron wrote their influential essay on the subject in 1995,
and the topic is as prevalent as ever.
I met Richard at the 10-year anniversary of the techno-politics
research group here in Vienna.
So shout outs to them as well.
Another person whom I was happy to meet again there is Jaya Clara Brecke,
my guest in episode six, which was, up until now, the one episode in this
podcast that I did in English.
So if you're not fluent in German, but indeed love future histories, then please
go and check out episode six with Jaya.
And whatever language you actually speak, if you like the show, then please
tell a friend, or if you can, then support it on Patreon via patreon.com
slash future histories.
Marianne and Paula recently did just that.
And I want to send my warmest thanks to them for doing so, but now please
enjoy today's episode with Richard Barbrook.
Richard, you have done so many different things.
I think it's easier if you introduce yourself.
Well, I teach politics at the University of Westminster in London, and I'm a
founder member of Class War Games, and we also run a cooperative called
Digital Liberties that makes games.
And I was sitting outside a cafe in Vienna and someone came up to talk to me,
who I thought might be begging for money.
But then I realized he actually did, because I'd never met the guy before.
And he said, you are the person who wrote the Californian ideology.
And I said, yep, that is true.
So that's the other thing I'm well known for.
That was in 1995, where we critiqued.com neoliberalism before its time.
And hopefully starting a process that will eventually lead into
different kinds of futures.
Ah, yes.
Well, it's one of the reasons I got interested in futures, like writing
histories of the future.
I wrote a book called Imaginary Futures, which is the start of the first chapter
that says the future is what it used to be.
So things like, you know, predictions of artificial intelligence or, you
know, fusion power or space tourism.
They've been around since at least the 1960s, and they come back with a
regularity, which is quite extraordinary.
And of course, the information society, we're always about to transition from
industrial capitalism to some sort of digital utopia.
And again, that goes back to at least the 1960s, or in its Russian
original version, the 1950s.
One point you're making is actually that there is this repetition of futures
actually, and you pledge us to invent new imaginaries of futures.
So why do we need these new imaginaries of future?
Well, I think the reason is because, I mean, I've just been to visit the
Red Vienna Exhibition, which everybody should go and see next to the Rathaus.
And that's an interest.
That's interesting because they had a very clear vision of the future.
So people in Vienna before the First World War had terrible housing and bad
health care and really poor education.
And so to raise the mass of the population up, they had a vision of a sort of social
democratic transition to communism.
And what you need to do is have a healthy, educated and well-housed proletariat.
And then they went and did it.
And it's quite extraordinary achievement.
And present day Vienna still benefits from that attempt.
And that's that's an example of if the left needs a way of thinking about a future,
because if you know, when you start doing things now, they're like a beta version of
what's going to come up, come eventually.
And so if you don't have that idea of an imaginary future, you're in a bit of a
problem because the right does have an imaginary future.
It has a sort of neoliberal dystopian, but in Britain, it's called Brexit.
You know, so you turn yourself into a sort of fantasy version of America, basically.
Or even worse, a native nationalism.
Well, that is partly America, yes, of course.
I can live there.
No, no, I went to school in America where they used to make them all pledge allegiance
to the flag every morning, which is a little English person I thought was very weird.
So, you know, they have to inculcate a nation, a multinational country and
homogenize them into one thing called Americans.
So how could these like really radically different imaginaries, imaginary futures
look like? Because, I mean, there's social democracy, but we kind of had that.
And it's at the end, I mean, at least in the way it has been done, like the
last 40, 50 years, it has always been a, like a compromise between a social
welfare state and a capital market.
I met an English guy who was living here on the, in the exhibition, who was
lecturing me about the awfulness of British politics because you don't want
to compromise, and I was saying, well, you can't compromise, that's the problem.
Yeah, you've had that advantage that the, I was told by an Austrian of the post
war generation who said the socialists and the Christian Democrats learned to
compromise in the concentration camp.
So, yeah, you've had that built into the system because of the trauma of the
civil war and the Nazi occupation and all the rest of it, and the second war,
and that you, which you lost, it went badly.
But the, but the, the imaginaries that you are calling for, they are aiming for
something different, for something more, actually.
Exactly.
What does it look like?
I mean, if you went to Britain today and showed them red Vienna, that would look
like an imaginary future, you know, 60% social housing, really good welfare
services, you know, okay, it's a very paternalistic vision of social
democracy, but nonetheless, compared to lots of places in England today, and
especially in America, it would seem even more utopian.
So that, that sort of vision I agree with, he does seem data, though, of course, if
you're Chinese, it seems like the future, of course, they are building social
housing on a massive scale and all this sort of stuff and adding digital
technology to it.
And they do think that they're going to build communism in 30 or 40 years.
As I, oh, yes, I met somebody from a party school in Beijing, who confidently
predicted that they would be there in 50 years.
And I said, if I come back in 20 years time, it'll still be 50 years away,
won't it?
To me, it doesn't look that way.
I mean, they are actually more going to a, like engineered capitalism, no?
Confucian socialism, as Daniel Bell's son calls it.
Oh, right.
That's the term.
I see.
Well, it's got a sort of, you know, particularly they've had a long tradition
for a thousand, well, I think Confucius is two and a half thousand years ago.
This vision that you have an enlightened elite who look after the people.
So, but it's really comes from the Han dynasty, doesn't it?
It's like 1000, 500 years ago, whatever.
Sorry.
What's the, the future that you are imagining?
I think it's, I think we should, I said, I think we should think the
Pali is a reassertion though of the old socialist future.
I think that is an important part of it.
It's interesting that one of the things that I found with continentals and they
think what's happened in the Labour Party recently is they find quite the strange
is this reassertion of socialist iconography.
So if you think of something like Podemos in Spain, they got rid of the red flag
and the international and all this sort of stuff.
Whereas in England, that scene is quite important to reassert that continuity
with working class history, you know, back to, I mean, obviously England's
had a long tradition, long history of working class struggle back to
the early 19th century.
So, you know, an interesting thing is, so one of the things are, which would be
seen as an imaginary future or a vision of the future is the Labour Party had a
conference about 18 months ago called alternative models of ownership where
you know, obviously the neo, the neoliberal model has failed, privatisation,
deregulation.
And so how do you replace that?
One thing is that go back to the old state capitalist nationalised industries.
That seems not a good idea.
So the alternative models of ownership is to look at things like municipal
ownership, obviously what a lot of red Vienna would be quite inspiring, but also
particularly cooperatives, you know, cooperatives were developed in mid 19th
century England, consumer co-ops, housing cooperatives and producer cooperatives.
And so if you look at places like Preston, which is the city in the north of
England, the local council has actually started to develop local cooperative
economy, partly to keep money, money, you know, when they private, previous
councils privatised services, money was being taken out of the local economy by
the privatised providers of services.
If you hand them over to cooperatives, the money tends to stay within the local
institutions. And this is now seen as a model for creating a new type of
socialism that's based on not just replacing private managers with state
managers, but actually to democratise the economy.
And this comes back to a lot of thought that was done, a critiques actually of
the old type state system that, you know, that they trusted managers and people who
were, you know, basically white collar, this was a paternalistic, this would be
the downside of the red Vienna model, this very paternalistic view.
But if you've got an educated workforce, they ought to be able to run the system
themselves. You know, who knows how best to run a railway, John McDonnell, who's
the finance spokesman of the Labour Party.
And he would say, well, who knows how best to run a railway, not the managers, it's
the people who drive the trains, maintain the tracks, look after the stations.
They know how to run the railway.
So what you have to do is get what they often call their tacit knowledge about the
system and get an input that into running things.
And I think that's an interesting vision, because actually that is a new modern
vision, particularly if you couple it with digital technologies, you know, using a
lot of the stuff that we do in everyday life with social media and polling and all
the other stuff that you can do and allow people to pass, you know, not just to turn
up to meetings, but to contribute knowledge in other ways and to be consulted.
But actually, also, it's going back to the middle of the 19th century.
This is what English socialism was about, actually, before the First World War.
So if you read Karl Marx, who's the German theorist of English socialism in
volume three of Capital, he said, what's the what's the future?
It's actually not the state ownership of everything.
It's the cooperative ownership of everything.
He's quite explicit about that.
And that comes from that experience.
So that's a good example where, in a sense, you have to look back at old
versions of the future and then think about how they can be redesigned and
inspire us to think about how do we create a new version?
Because obviously, the problems we're facing are some ways the same, you know,
capitalist alienation and exploitation, in some senses, have intensified.
But on the other hand, they're very different because we have a very
different workforce, for instance, much more ethnically diverse gender.
All these other issues have to go into it.
And I think crucially, it's much, much better educated.
So if you have a better educated workforce, more skilled, it's going to
think about how it wants to run its own life in a very different way than
people who are desperate, who are very happy if people provide them with
housing and education and healthcare and all the rest of it, particularly if
it's done by a very enlightened leadership.
Now, I think people feel that they want to say in all this, in a real say as well,
not just ticking boxes.
So that means the transition would actually start in the here and now by
establishing work-owned cooperatives that serve as practical examples for
this kind of economic structure.
But there would still be a market mechanism that is in place in between
the different cooperatives.
Is that just a transitional phase or is it also, what about markets?
Are they a part of the structure that you are aiming for?
Is it like market socialism or will there be a transition that, for example,
involves abolishing money and the commodity?
Abolishing the commodity labor power, the ultimate appeal.
We used to read this book by a guy called Jan Appel called Communist
Production and Distribution, which I finally managed to get a copy of at the
Anarchist Book Fair a few years ago.
And that's quite interesting re-looking at that because he was a Dutch council
communist, so he was writing, must have been in the late 20s, early 1930s.
And it's how do you do that?
It's really interesting.
How would you do that?
If you actually wanted to get rid of money, and it's always been this conundrum.
I mean, Robert Owen, who's the founder of English socialism, thought you could just
replace gold pieces with labor notes.
You know, you do one hour of this and one hour of that and you just swap the note.
But as Marks points out in the introduction to Gundersen, what happens is
that the labor note slowly turns into money and becomes the regulator and
commodifies the labor.
Yeah, and so that he has this really interesting problem.
And you think now, of course, with digital technologies, a lot of this sort of state
planning, which went massively out of fashion after the collapse of the Soviet
Union, suddenly it seems a lot more rational.
You know, I wrote about the invention of the internet in America, where they
pumped huge amounts of money in the 1960s to invent this very esoteric computer
network because they were terrified that the Soviet Union was doing it.
And one of the reasons the Soviet Union wants it is because they had the idea
that they could replace the state plan with a giant mainframe that would
instantly, you know, you go into a shop and buy red socks and it would send back
a message to the sock factory saying, produce more socks in this size than the
color red.
And of course, this seemed incredibly utopian then, but now any pre-supermarket
does it with barcodes.
And it's a debate that is being revived, actually.
I mean, there's this book, The People's Republic of Walmart by Leith Phillips and
Mark Michael Roswowski.
Well, it also goes back to the people that there's been a really renewed interest
in what happened in Chile with Stafford Beer and Cybersyn, I've met Raul Espejo.
There's this very brilliant, brilliant book by Eden Medina, which is called
Cybernetic Revolution, it was originally going to be called Cybernetic Socialism,
but surprise surprise, MIT Press quickly changed the title, which is interesting
because in a way they weren't revolutionaries, they were much more
socialist.
But again, in America, I guess words mean certain things, don't they?
And that's also interesting where, you know, they're using like one mainframe
Intellics machines, though the control room looks very good where you have all
these guys at the top, they're basically the guys who are coordinating the
distribution information, it's not really a top-down thing, it's a sort of
coordination.
And they all have these wonderful 70s chairs and they have a space for their
glass of whiskey and cigars, like a sort of gentleman's club.
Stafford Beer obviously thought there was nothing too good for the workers.
So that's, I think, interesting.
So there's that, yeah, there's that.
And obviously, the other thing that people don't talk about, but I think is
the real big thing, is China, because they still have state planning on a
massive scale.
And one of the, you know, it's the fastest growing economy in world history.
It is the great transformation of our generation is China in the last 70 years
and particularly in the last 30, 40 years.
I mean, and state planning is absolutely at the core of this process.
Yeah.
Well, but I think that the general argument from the other side would then
be to say, well, it might be that they still are dominant in terms of planning,
but just after they opened their market to a capitalist market logic of competition
and for-profit production, they made this like huge jump and that this would
actually underline the effectiveness of markets and for-profit motive.
On the flight here, I think it's called China Daily or something, I got a copy
of and it's interesting because they're talking about the 70th anniversary and
they quite correctly point out, you see, you couldn't have had that leap without
the previous Mao period where they increased the lifespan of the population
from the average age was 35 and it increased to 64 under Mao's reign.
I mean, extraordinary education, health, that, you know, to actually have those
people who were ready to make that transition.
And that's how you can't really disentangle one from the other.
I think that, I think a lot of historians now have started to get away from that
ideological debate.
I think for us, obviously, we find talking about red Vienna, isn't it?
It's one, it's an interesting historical example, but we're, we're faced with
very different problems, I think.
And I think what the question you ask is correct, which is, you know, we, you
know, you can take some mixture of the plan and the market and you can massively
raise living standards and you could, you know, in England, you know, we could build
2 million social housing.
We could lower people's housing costs massively if we essentially reversed what
Thatcher and her successors did, which is sell off housing and now a huge bubble to
take place and all the rest of it.
That's possible.
We know how you can do that and you can do it with even within the capitalist
system.
The question then is, but how do we move beyond that?
Because a lot of the problems people have, I mean, a great example is mental
health, for instance, is to do with the stress of living under this capitalist
society, causing record level of depression and, you know, various other
ailments.
And that is to do because people don't live, they live in socially alienated
lives, meaningless lives, they think.
And so you need to create that again.
That's a, that's a sort of different level of problems, isn't it?
Yeah, definitely.
And I think that the problem then lies at the end.
If you go down the rabbit hole, it lies within the question of political economy
and that's where you figure it in the DNA, you know, in the DNA of the political
economy.
Well, of course, I mean, cause you know, a lot of political economy was, had those
questions and then they very deliberately in the academic system split them in
half politics.
I mean, I teach politics and then there's another profession called economics.
And it's interesting that you could, you know, you could spend three years at a
university doing a politics degree and know nothing about economics, but how you
could talk about the modern state without it being a class state or, you know,
bureaucratic state or, you know, all these other things that it's like that
because of this transformation that took place when we were where we moved from
feudalism to capitalism, however you put it, you know, whatever that means.
But, you know, the difference between a medieval way people produce wealth, as
Adam Smith would say, the wealth of nations, you know, the difference between
that and how we live now is just profound.
And that creates changes in the politics and culture in relation to personal
relationships and all the rest of it.
And so it's extraordinary.
You can do, and then you have economics, which is just like astrology.
It's just a sort of, you know, very complicated mathematics, garbage in,
garbage out basically, you know, and that's not that, you know, the fact that
these, these people are even considered to be academically credible is what I
find extraordinary.
So one of the, one of the tasks at hand, I guess, would be to, to implement profound
change within the economics departments at the universities.
And we can by abolish them, but the statistic, I mean, to be fair, I mean,
obviously in bourgeois economics, as we used to call it, there is very good
statistical work going on, but it's just like the basic ground theory.
The fact that when I was taught a level economics, that's 16, I was 16, I did
economics school and I remember the Trevor Jones was our teacher and the
first lesson of the, of my first year of economics, two years ago, he did the
demand and supply curve on the board and said, it's all wrong, but you have to
learn it to pass the exam.
And it was only many years later when I read Adam Smith and David
Ricard and of course, Karl Marx.
I realized what he meant is like the wrong answer to the wrong question.
And so, so to do something like that, where you have a profession that's,
who's both basic theory is such an error.
They don't know what a price is and they don't understand how prices are defined
either, so that's a bit problematic when you're studying capitalistic economics.
But that's a, that's a very interesting point because I think that's exactly one
of the points that we need to address because it works as a narrative.
That's an ideology.
Yeah, that's an idea, but it does work.
It also works if you want to collect large amounts of statistical data, because
on the, it talks about the surface forms of capitalism.
So one of its functions is to create large, you know, have large data sets.
And then you can say something about, you know, I don't know what the stock
market is going to be like in a year's time or usually wrongly, but, or, you
know, what the growth rate is, all these sorts of things, but what it can't say
is, you know, why is there a capitalist crisis?
You know, they can't, you know, the most fundamental thing of the last 10 years
has been the implosion of the, near implosion of the financial system and the
really bad policies that were adopted to prop up the world system in the last
decade.
They can't talk about that because they actually don't have the theoretical
tools that allow them to understand it.
And that is really interesting.
And then, but it's not just that.
I don't think it's just the shifting of, you know, economics from politics, but
you know, the way that anthropologies are separate, you know, history is over
here, cultural studies is over, you know, there's a whole series of these, of this
division of labor within intellectual life, which isn't talking to each other.
And then once they say in their little bubble, especially as academics are a
bit like, I don't know, they're a bit like monasteries in the 90s, in the
middle evil period where they're all doing their own, you know, chanting
Latin masses or so the rest of the population are concerned, completely
outside practical engagement in what society is doing, which again is okay
because it's good that they're accumulating knowledge about obscure
things, but it's not being reintegrated back into our society and precisely for
the problem you're talking about.
If we want to think about how do we go beyond capitalism, broadly defined, we
actually have to be able to draw on all this human experience and think about how
you do do things like complicated things, like divide and distribute labor,
create social wealth in a way that people don't find alienating, find
fulfilling, have time to look after their children and all the other things.
Having a son, I always think that's the most important thing in life,
because hanging out with him.
But could you, could you like briefly sketch how this could be done?
Because I mean, if we talk macro level-ish kind of things, and we just
briefly touched the socialist calculation debate and how they...
Well, with the Austrians, you also, it's interesting that this...
Austrian economics, I have to...
You mean Austrian economics or Austrians?
No, the Austrian economics, which was for people who hated Red Vienna.
So you think like Hayek, Mise, Schumpeter to a lesser extent, but basically
they're all, they all hate it.
You can think Hayek was a snob, wasn't he?
The idea that the proles would actually have decent housing and hang out in
coffee bars was probably his idea of hell.
And he just spent the rest of his life trying to...
It's interesting because the Road to Serfdom, which was Margaret Thatcher's
favorite book, which he wrote in exile in London.
And what he says there is if you set up a national health service,
Britain's probably greatest beloved institution, it's the straight run to
the Gulag Archipelago.
It's a completely batshit crazy book.
I mean, I'm old enough to remember Thatcher being elected.
So I went and read this book because he said this is her favorite book.
So I was going around telling you, I said, this is like Mein Kampf.
This is, you know, read it because this is what she's going to do.
You know, this is craziness.
But she's doing it because they believe in this and they did.
That's exactly what they did.
So if we want to go back to actually countering that, we need our own type of
narratives, which again, take things like the socialist calculation debate and say,
well, actually, you were wrong.
You can calculate in different ways, particularly now we've got all this
computing bow that allows us to calculate.
But the question is, what are you calculating and what is the purpose of
this calculation?
Yeah, because otherwise you end up like in Chinese central planning, you know.
Exactly.
I guess, I mean, these are two points, I guess.
One is that we need to define what we are aiming for in the sense of what's,
what's the purpose, you know, because we agree that the purpose being just profit
is one of the huge problems right now.
So we, we can put in something like a general wellbeing, you know, for
everybody, each individual.
But then there's the question of how to, I mean, but I think that's.
Stafford Beer has a really great idea, which is, you know, you go to, I don't
know, you go to hotels or restaurants or whatever, and they're more like public
transports or things and they have these little smileys which go, I don't know
whether you have them here, they are like dark green, light green, something
on red, whether you're happy or sad and you press them.
And he wanted to actually have them in everybody's home and everybody every
day would vote where they were happy or sad.
So nothing, nothing else, just where they're happy.
And obviously some people will be sad because they're sick or they quarrel
with their partner or something, but he just said all in general that the
government would know every day, whether it was the people were happier than sad.
So you just said the government, that's, that's my, my, my point of entry, I guess,
because I mean.
Well, he was doing it for the Chilean government.
I think my question is just, uh, there's this, um, I do see one of the narratives
popping up that, uh, against the, you know, Austrian, uh, narrative of, uh,
price as being the supreme price and market mechanisms, uh, being the supreme
mechanism of allocation of resources.
You've got the Austro Marxist approach.
And then there's this, I mean, there's the narrative that is popping up right
now, which is kind of, all right.
Um, uh, we can see in, uh, large scale companies like Walmart or Amazon and
anything that, uh, planned economy is possible in general.
So let's try this with different, um, uh, uh, goals, of course, you know, not
for profit, but that would imply some kind of, uh, centrally planned economy.
But it, it seems as if what you're promoting is not a centrally planned
economy, but a more decentralized, um,
Well, centralization is inevitable though, in a way, because we're, you
think about the world economy.
It's also slowly going into three zones, China, Europe, and North America.
And these are very large.
Europe is a very large group of people who are all, um, okay.
We might be very, I think we're very diverse, but to outsiders, they
all think we're the same.
I had a Chinese student this year who came up with, she said to me very
soon, she said, I don't understand why the Europeans keep quarreling with each
other.
Why don't you form a strong centralized state?
Like we did.
It's been very successful from which country was China, China.
Ah, okay.
Yeah.
So for that Charles, she's concerned, you know, the last 70 years is the
best in Chinese history.
And it's because they created in 1945 a strong centralized state and it had
driven the country forward into the, you know, whatever, you know, prosperity
media, was it a mediumly prosperous ecological civilization, or whatever
the latest phraseology is.
So, but what would, what would be your
I'm not, I'm not really in favor of Confucian socialism.
Yes.
But what are you in favor?
Well, that's what I'm saying.
I think it's interesting that the, what, uh, from the experiences of, uh, labor,
local governments in the 1980s, which is, you know, the present leadership
lay party comes very much out of the Greater London Council, the GLC, and
other left labor councils in the 1980s.
Thatcher closed down because they were two good examples of what you could do
instead, and a lot of that was moving away from top down paternistic, but, and
to create bottom up cooperative type structures, but I don't think it's a
centralization seat decent enough, because often to make the, you need
economies of scale often to make them work.
So it's only the Preston model.
If they just had a few co-ops, they, okay, that works.
But once you start getting lots of co-ops and they all start to
collaborate with each other, sometimes they might be buying and selling.
Other times they just might be working together in other ways.
You start to actually generate more productive wealth, but also I think
the other key thing is it empowers people and it changes people politically
and culturally, and they feel more self-confident.
That's the other key thing.
Lots of the other problem, the high ECU model, of course, is it just treats
people as disposable commodities.
And, you know, we had zero, I don't, you know, zero hours contracts and stress.
And as I said, all the stuff we were talking about before, and if you
create healthier and happier people, that's what they want to do.
People want to contribute.
They would like to contribute to society, but they need to be happy as well.
So that seems to be a key thing.
So I'm a bit wary about the centralization decentralization debate,
particularly because of Brexit.
We suddenly, suddenly everyone's in favor of the federal Republic of Europe.
That's one thing the Brexiteers have done.
They've actually made the English, who had the major Europhobic problem.
They've actually created a mass pro-European movement in England, which is bizarre.
I had never thought I'd see demonstrations with large numbers of
people flying European flags.
And then if you go to the Labour Party, the two flags that people have on their
badges and all the rest of it are one Palestine, for obvious reasons.
And the second, the second is the European Union, which seemed
like a strange combination.
You can see that all around, I guess, because oftentimes it's also in the
public discourse, that's how it is being presented.
It's either the right-wing nationalists or the liberalism as we knew it.
And in the, let's say, mainstream media, in lack of any other term, it's described
as if there's nothing else, you know?
Well, that's what they have, and that is the classic mainstream media, like the
choice between a liberal or a fascist.
Yeah.
Macron had it, the Macron election.
You have a choice between a liberal or a fascist.
Yeah.
What's the choice?
That's not the choice.
So you'll opt for...
Socialism.
...cybernetic communism, I read somewhere.
Yes, exactly.
Do you have a catchy phrase, how you define cybernetic communism?
Well, that came out of the Imaginary Futures book.
I was just, I was interested, this came from this thing that the origin myth of
the internet is that somehow it was a system to survive a nuclear war, and this
goes back to the Paul Barron report in the early 1960s.
He wrote for the Rand Corporation, funded by the US Air Force, and notorious for
promoting the invasion of Vietnam.
But it struck me as that was just like very unlikely.
Why would you replace cheap, reliable switches with expensive, flaky mainframes?
I mean, we're not talking about the sort of chips we have in our mobile phones.
We're talking about computers the size of a room, right?
So this just, this didn't make sense.
And so it was only digging, actually, I didn't even do that much research, but
once you actually go and read some of the conferences from the early 1960s, the
1964 American Cybernetic Society, being an obvious example, they're terrified.
They all say the Russians are going to build the internet within four years.
So that's why they're doing it, because they've had Sputnik, the Americans lost
the race to put the first satellite, and then you have Yuri Gagarin, they lost the
race to put the first human into space, and Valentina Tereshkova, the first woman
into space. So they, you know, all these key milestones on that particular thing.
That's why they always go on about landing on the moon, because they have to
say that they lost all the early parts of the space race.
So that they then invented ARPA, or the Advanced Research Projectation, and its
next project was to stop cybernetic communism.
Nikita Khrushchev, in the 22nd Party Congress, actually said the Soviet Union
will enter cybernetic communism in the 1970s.
That we will solve all the problems of central planning by building a giant
mainframe.
But they didn't. I mean, there was the attempt in Chile, with Stafford Beer, but
and there were attempts in the...
No, they got terrified, they got scared, because in 1968, during the Prague Spring,
Radovan Ritka, and the Academy of Sciences in Czechoslovakia, published this book
called Civilization at the Crossroads.
And it says, Stalinism is the industrial age, and we're about to enter the
Information Society, and this will be cybernetic communism, by the Party.
And so they just got really scared.
They suddenly thought, well, if we set up computer networks everywhere.
So they weren't as clever as the Chinese, you see, they just got terrified.
They just thought people would use it to self-organize, which of course they did.
But, you know, still couldn't stop solidarity in Poland, could they?
So that's interesting.
So everybody shut down the different way of approaching cybernetics, actually.
The United States shut it down in Chile, and the Soviets did it by themselves,
actually.
They didn't need somebody else to do it, no?
No, no.
Well, that's one of the reasons they didn't get the internet.
I think it's really interesting.
I have friends who grew up in Soviet, and every computer network was, you couldn't
actually operate from one network to the other.
They already did this with telephones.
They used to have layered telephone systems, which is why you should see
those pictures of Soviet bureaucrats.
They have like six telephones on their desk because it shows you've got more
telephones the further you went up the hierarchy because you've got access to
a special network, and they did the same thing because they were afraid if you
had one telephone system, anybody could ring anybody else.
And that's another thing.
When we come back to, when we're thinking about, you know, how modernity has
progressed, the command and control, top-down command and control is really
important, because at each stage of technology, there's a debate, a struggle,
actually, a social shaping of technology over who's going to control it.
Is it going to be bottom-up or is it going to be top-down?
And the internet is a very classic example of that.
And it's a super important part you're just mentioning because one of the
titles of a chapter within an essay that Evgeny Morozov just recently published
in the New Left Review, the whole essay is called Digital Socialism, but one of
the chapters, it's titled Socialize the Means of Feedback Production!
So that would be an obvious barrier, you know, because right now the means of
feedback production, that would actually be the ground upon which such a cybernetic
planned economy could be done, you know, they are right now owned privately by
huge corporations and a necessary step would be to socialize these means of
feedback production.
Well, all to supersede them.
That's, well, in a sense, but you think something like Google is effectively owned
by the state, I mean, it's, you know, it's a creation of the National Security Agency.
But it's not owned by the state.
But it's effectively controlled by the Americans.
I mean, it's when they go on and on about the Americans, but not by the state, no?
By the elite, then, okay.
But you think when they go on about Huawei, they go on about Huawei in the back doors,
allegedly, in its technology, and you think they're just talking about themselves.
That's what they're doing.
Now, what's Google?
It's a giant information machine.
We're sucking up data for the national security state in America.
I mean, you have a choice now.
Do you want to be spied, use Apple and be spied on by the American secret police or
Huawei and be spied on by the Chinese secret police?
I mean, that's a great choice for you, isn't it?
Yeah.
So that there would have to be a different kind of entity.
When you talk about socializing, they are socialized already.
It's just how they're socialized.
So what does it, you know, socially, you know, it's what Mark, again, what Mark points out
in volume three of capital, a joint stock company is a form of social ownership.
It's just a social ownership.
It's structured in a particular way to benefit a particular class.
But you see, so it's not individual ownership.
It is a form of social ownership.
So Google is a form of social ownership, which, you know, the founder, the two founders
basically own it outright.
I mean, the shares are traded, but they don't really, they can't appoint the board of
directors. So so who they who they're accountable to.
I mean, that's another question.
You know, I said it was originally funded by the NSA.
So you could think if you go back enough through the interconnections of the American
elite. But it's not possible to right now.
It's that the information that is selected, you know, it's not possible to use to
build some, you know, I don't know, a cooperative project built upon the data
that is being collected because they are protecting it.
Well, not just that is that what we've all been using Google for 20 odd years and
building up its knowledge base.
That's the key thing. If you could, you could theoretically build a better search
engine. But what you wouldn't have is 20 years of searches done by millions of
people. And that's what gives it its edge over anybody else is that embedded
knowledge, which everybody has.
We've all helped build Google or Apple or Amazon or any of these companies.
So it is in a way they are socialized.
It's just how they're socialized.
They're not. It's like, again, it's not the Austrian school.
It's all about the individual consumer.
But that's actually not how society we're talking about millions, billions of
people collectively creating something, how it's captured and molded.
That's a completely different question.
But I don't think I think socialization is the wrong word.
Oh, really interesting.
They already socialized.
They've been socialized.
They've always been socialized.
They were socialized when they were funded at Stanford University.
The corporations are social institutions.
They just run as dictatorships.
Well, I think with the word socialized, I associate the common ownership, you know,
that everybody would have access to the benefits of it.
Well, you do. You do with Google.
You can use it.
Well, yeah, I can I can use it to Google something by which I just add some more
of the information to their databases.
But we want to get our hands on the databases.
And you benefit from that.
The fact that they've accumulated all this knowledge, you type something rather
esoteric into it, it suddenly throws up.
I mean, a lot of it is junk, but then by going through it and sort you help them
sort it by what's relevant and the next person who types in the same piece of
rubbish gets a more hopefully gets a more accurate feeding.
So yeah, yeah, yeah.
But still, I do not get it because I mean, if you take some industry and it
builds some houses and I can profit by living in this house, it's still the the
company that builds the houses is not socialized because the means of
production are not within common ownership.
So so that would be different.
It is a form of common ownership.
Come again, sir.
It's just run as a dictatorship.
It's not in the in the sorts of Austrian school fantasy economics that you're
taught at school or even Keynesian.
But you are always treated as an individual.
It's all about individual consumers, individual producers.
But that's why the joint stock company becomes an immediate problem.
You know, there's, I don't know, the theory of the firm and all that sort of stuff.
I mean, one of that thing is that they prove that companies by definition can
be more efficient than markets.
That's what Adam Smith says at the beginning of volume one of The Wealth of Nations.
There's two ways of dividing and distributing labor.
One is the market.
The other is the firm or the state, depending on how you look at it, the plan,
whatever you call it, then there's two different ways.
And so this is not something new that you can know.
The pin factory is not a market.
They don't buy and sell each the bits of the pin to each other.
But you could do it like that.
Theoretically, I mean, to a high equity, you think that's actually how you do it.
They don't want to have the firm at all, really.
They just want to have everything, you know, internal markets for everything.
There are people who tried that miserably.
I know they tried it at our university.
They were going to have a sort of bidding for office space in the same way.
Really?
Oh, yeah, you know, it was just like this.
It was like the I think it was actually was the Blair period
where they got even more bizarrely entranced by all this.
But you can see again, you can see that in the EU where markets
become a sort of technocratic solution because they're not democratic by definition.
And, you know, you want to have a solution and it all looks very nice.
You know, you can just set down a set of policies and it works in the university.
So I think I think that's the problem.
So when you think or talk about socializing, something like that,
they already are social.
It's just that they're not democratic or open.
That's the key thing.
So what you should be talking about is democratizing them or opening them up
and sharing the knowledge.
That's also, I think, very new because our starting point somehow was
that the need for new imaginaries.
And I think this is a very nice imaginary to democratize economies, you know.
So, you know, I have worked with a colleague called Christian Fuchs.
He's a very, you know, very smart guy.
But he was going on about nationalizing Google, basically.
And that's what friends of mine pulled out.
One, it basically is national.
It's one sense it is nationalized because it's because of its connection
with the security apparatus.
And the second thing, the whole point isn't actually to get away from
that type of model of software, you know, having one giant big server,
basically, model of software.
I mean, they, you know, they write the software.
So they would say, well, that's part of the problem.
Yes, just turning it from nominally owned by its two founders
and Wall Street Investor, the venture capitalists or whatever.
I think actually, I think it is basically owned by the two founders nowadays
because all the rest of the shares don't actually have any voting right.
But it doesn't really matter.
It's actually the model of centralizing all the information in one company
is the problem.
And really what you want to do is have, you know, distributed forms of,
if you were to do a search engine, it should be a distributed search engine,
not this particular model that came out of the 1990s.
So I think that's an interesting debate where they're actually saying,
well, you know, it's not just taking the same technology
and just changing the ownership to, you know, Google,
PLC or private, you know, private corporation to state corporation.
Or it's something more than that.
Or even calling it a co-op, you know, a co-op of its workers or something.
It's actually to change the technology itself.
The part of the problem is that it's designed as top-down technology.
And so simply just changing the ownership, calling it socialized.
It's like, as I said, it's like thinking, it's like Confucian socialism, isn't it?
The form of Confucian socialism.
And what you really want to do is actually not only change its ownership,
but change the type of software and the way the software operates in the network.
And again, I'm not an expert in software or hardware,
but this seems to be a very interesting idea.
When we come back to the shaping of technology,
that it looks, you know, we go around doing things because it's,
you know, lots of social relations are embedded in the technologies that we use,
hardwares and software.
And so we just adopt type of behavior patterns
because it's essentially, that's how it's the easy way to operate your life, basically.
And it's teaching you to operate in a sense of social relation.
So simply to, you know, declare Google red.
It's not going to make, it's actually not going to solve the problem.
Yeah, you're absolutely right.
So he already distributes his project for free anyway.
It is communism.
It's free.
I think they charged me five euros to go to that exhibition.
I thought that was quite overrunning, really.
The moza?
Ah, yeah, yeah.
I said, socialism should be free, mate.
They haven't got to communism yet.
They're obviously just in the transitional phase, aren't they?
Where they still have to charge you money to go in.
Oh, another approach that is currently discussed,
or actually since like three or four years is being put out there
and that I wanted to check what your position is towards,
is this concept of fully automated luxury communism by Aaron Bastani.
Oh yeah, that's wonderful.
I read that book.
I actually had to debate with Aaron on his books.
Oh, I'll have to check that one.
Is there a video?
Yeah, sure it is.
It was done in Newspeak House.
Okay, I have to get my hands on this audio or video recording.
It was done for virtual futures.
That's what I'm trying to think.
All right, so you like the book.
You like the concept.
How do I like the book?
That's a really good question.
I was being very polite.
I could have been nastier to it.
But I think the good thing,
I think there's lots of problems with the book.
I mean, there's all the things like mining asteroids,
which are completely bonkers in my view.
But that's a different question.
I think what's good about it is it's very positive.
And what you need, as you said,
in a way it's not so much whether or not you agree with the utopia.
It's whether it's the fact that people are going out and saying,
well, we can build a post-capitalist society.
It's very technological determinism.
That's my problem with it.
Because I think, and I just have been, as I said,
having read capital,
I have a big problem with the words fully automated.
Because I think that that actually is a vision
of being dominated by technology.
Because that's not reshaping the machine.
That's expelling living labor from the production process,
which you don't want to do.
What you want to be able to do is control the production of goods and services.
That's like, you know, it's like basic income.
I always feel this is a very dubious concept.
Because, you know, welfare for all.
That's quite good when you're in a 20-year thing.
That's great.
I could just go and collect a cheque every week and have fun.
But I don't think that really, you know,
what you really want to do is have basic services.
You know, the good example in Britain is that health care is free.
And so, in fact, she would have loved to privatize.
If we'd had charging for health care,
we'd have really expensive health care now.
But because it was free, she couldn't do it.
They can try and privatize the back end.
But if you tried to introduce charging for health care in England,
there'd be a revolt, even among right-wing voters.
And so, that's a really interesting thing.
So, there was a discussion in the 1980s about abolishing public transport fares,
which I spoke in favor of when they edited this.
And the unions didn't want to do this
because there were people involved in selling and collecting tickets.
And but if they'd abolished fares, they couldn't reintroduce them.
I just think now we have very expensive public transport in London.
But I think if they abolished it,
it's very, very difficult to reintroduce it once it's done.
That's a very good point you're making, I guess,
because that would be an essential first step would be
to create universal basic services for housing, for transport, for education, for health,
and really build thick structures around it that are able to last for a long, long time.
And thereby, what's the same with universities, because university used to be free.
And then it is here exactly.
And then Blair introduced very low fees.
And there were people making excuses.
And I remember saying at the time, well, if you introduce low fees, they'll be higher.
Because that's the point is just to get people used to paying something.
And once you pay something, then you can charge them 50 grand a year.
And that is the point.
So I think one of the things is taking things out of the market,
the basic things in life, health care, education, housing.
And then you can have, you know, then people want to buy and sell other things.
That's fine.
What's the next step after that?
Let's imagine a future where this has happened.
Where our children, where our little children are going to do.
Do a Keynesian, the future of my grandchildren kind of thing.
What would that be?
What do you mean?
The four-day week, the three-day week, you know, that sort of thing.
The Labour Party has actually adopted a policy of introducing a four-day week.
Yeah.
Which again, it's one of the mistakes the French Socialist Party did is
they reduced the working week, but not by a whole day.
And so they actually, it's been very difficult in France to push work back up again.
And it doesn't seem to have affected the French economy that hugely.
But they always have, if you read right-wing papers,
they're always going on and on about the restriction on the working week.
But you think if they give them the whole extra day off, that would have really screwed.
Because, you know, they've never been able to, even the Popular Front in the 1930s,
the 1936 Front Popular, they introduced the Grand Vacances,
which, so basically France closes down in August, thanks to the workers' rebellion in 1936.
It's a bit annoying sometimes when you're a tourist,
but you do think that was an achievement.
And the same thing in England.
We basically, from Christmas Eve to past New Year's Eve, the whole of England closes down.
And this is from the 1970s strikes.
We had all these massive strikes.
And the great achievement, even now, despite all these decades of neoliberalism,
is the whole country closes down on Christmas Eve and doesn't reopen until after New Year's Day.
So those sorts of spaces, I think, are really interesting.
It's interesting, though, things like National Health Service and
the long winter Christmas holiday.
Those are essentially what they find really difficult to roll back,
that shows you what really powerful achievements that people aren't really willing to give up,
however much shit they're reading from the mainstream media.
So we've got this, like, next step thing,
which would be the Universal Baker's Basic Services kind of thing.
And a shorter working week.
I think that would make people happy.
And then after that, if we get that, if we get a four-day week,
same payment, of course, then a three-day week, and then...
What do you mean, ecotopia?
I don't know.
Where do we go from there?
You know, what are you pushing for?
We hunt in the morning and read poetry in the afternoon.
Yeah, I mean, that would be one of the...
Not finalists, of course, the wrong term and the wrong idea to it.
But that would be a...
Charles Fourier, who thought he should overcome the division of labour.
That's what he...
Every four hours, you'd switch jobs or...
Yeah, but you needn't have to do that, you know?
For me, at least, there's an inner image where I'm free to
do the work that I intrinsically want to do.
And I'm not a lazy person.
I just want to decide myself what I want to put my efforts in.
And also, people like being with other people.
And if they got a collective project that's to the social benefit,
it makes them feel happy doing it.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, that's the difficulty is how do you turn
the sort of production of goods and services that we have
into a society which is democratic?
Because it's been so built on class hierarchy.
It's funny that here you get people who claim that this isn't a class...
They say, oh, England's terrible, it's divided into classes
as if Austria isn't divided.
I just look at them with that absolutely black...
I think you just...
Obviously, again, the ideology here is, you know,
it's all social consensus, everyone's happy.
There are still people, you know, in the hotel, cleaning the hotel,
I mean, waiting in bars.
So let's, I mean, maybe it's counterproductive,
but still I have to ask, let's put a name tag on it.
Communism.
All right.
Just to annoy Americans.
I used to call myself communist until I started going to America as an adult.
And then you really...
Because you say anything left with you, you try and explain,
no, I'm a social democrat or a...
Whatever, then you just gave up and just say, no, I'm a communist.
And then they get, I mean, probably not now,
but I always remember that people would be really shocked.
They never met anybody who actually would say this
and not be, you know, a Stalivist or something.
Yeah.
And I just recently heard that, because I'm really interested,
I heard that there are people calling themselves radical social democrats.
I never heard of that before, but I just recently heard...
Oh, this one of mine used to say,
we should call ourselves libertarian social democrats,
because that's LSD.
Okay, I see.
So I've got the class of the new, how's this at the end, libertarian social,
because it was his joke.
And I just thought it was such a great...
And the funny thing is the only person who got the joke were the Russians.
The Russians got the joke immediately and no one else did.
They all got the joke.
One last question I'm always asking.
If you think about the future, what makes you joyful?
My little boy.
I think he's my little...
He's my future.
Some Christian came up to me outside the shopping centre and said,
what happened to you?
Will you live on after death?
And I pointed to Artie and said, look, here he is.
I think, well, yeah, he makes you optimistic.
You see them crying up, hopefully he leaves them a better world.
Richard, thanks a lot.
Cheers, thank you.
Long live Red Vienna.
That was our show for today.
If you want to know more about future histories, please visit future histories.today.
You can support future histories at Patreon.
For this, go to patreon.com slash future histories.
And let me know what you think about this episode and the show in general.
For this, use Twitter, hashtag future histories, or Reddit,
or send me an email to future underscore histories at protonmail.com.
See you next time.