Welcome to Future Histories, my name is Jan Groos and my guest today is the economist Jeffrey Sachs.
I recorded this interview during last year's Globe Art Academy and I hesitated to release it for mainly two reasons.
The first one is that this interview came about more or less spontaneously
and I wasn't able to prepare myself as much as I usually do.
I also like spontaneous interviews, don't get me wrong, but in most cases I like to come prepared.
This was one of those cases and so this was a minus on my part actually.
And the second reason I didn't release the interview yet is that it's not complete.
Mr Sachs was kind enough to lend me his time immediately before his keynote speech at the Globe Art Academy
and then time ran out and we had to stop the interview before getting to some of the more
delicate questions in my notes. And I say delicate because Mr Sachs is a many-sided person
and I would have loved to get to better understand how these different sides fit together.
Just to give you an example, Mr Sachs was an advisor to Yanis Varoufakis during his time as
Greek Finance Minister and he endorsed Bernie Sanders as the Democrat presidential candidate,
which surely was a great help to the movement since Mr Sachs is an important figure in economics
and many try to frame Bernie Sanders' approach as specifically economically unreasonable,
which of course isn't true, but in these cases it of course helps to be endorsed by a person such as
Mr Sachs. On the other side, Mr Sachs was also at least partly responsible for what is called a
shock therapy approach and the economic liberalization of former communist countries
after the collapse of the Soviet Union. This arguably has a big part in oligarchic structures
within these economies today and it would have been very interesting to ask the Jeffrey Sachs of
2019 whether or not he would have done things differently given his views on politics and
economics today. Unfortunately, we didn't get to this part, but nonetheless we covered a lot of
interesting and important ground, so thanks a lot to the Globe Art Academy for making this interview
possible and my warmest greetings to everybody at the Globe Art team. Before we get to the interview,
I wanted to welcome Simona and the person with the pseudonym Monster aus dem Loch as Patreons.
Thank you so much for your support and since one of the questions during today's episode is
directed towards the possibility of different kinds of political economies, I wanted to point
you all towards episodes 31 and 32 of Future Histories with radical economist Daniel E.
Sarros as a guest. In these two episodes we take a deep dive into Daniel Sarros' book
Information Technology and Socialist Construction, which I highly recommend when
it comes to the question of how fundamentally different political economies could actually
look like. But now please enjoy today's episode with Jeffrey Sachs.
Welcome to Future Histories, my name is Jan Gross and my guest today is Jeffrey Sachs,
economist, director of the Earth Institute at Columbia University,
special advisor to the United Nations, secretary general and one of the world's leading experts
on economic development. Welcome Mr. Sachs. Thank you, great to be with you.
Mr. Sachs, all too often political actions are justified by economic parameters such as the GDP,
for example, the gross domestic product. Yet these numbers do not represent the actual
well-being of humans, animals, the ecological environment or anything as such, as well as it
doesn't factor in the future well-being of any of these. So I'd say it's high time for different
parameters to measure our actions against what could those be and what to do about the things
that cannot be measured but are equally important. We do indeed in almost all countries follow the
indicator of gross domestic product and I happened as a young student to be a student of
then emeritus, a very senior, very wonderful professor, Simon Kuznets, who invented the gross
domestic product. He developed it between 1919 and the 1930s when he came up with this concept
and won a Nobel Prize for it. But he always used to emphasize this is not a measure of our well-being.
This is a measure of the size of the economy. It is a measure of the market transactions taking
place in an economy. It's useful to know it was originally designed to help governments plan,
interestingly, to help them plan for two purposes. One, for war because in a war governments need to
requisition resources and for war planning they need to know how big the economy is and how to
mobilize those resources. It also then became used starting in the 1930s for macroeconomic policies
to fight depressions, to fight the contractions of a business cycle. It became part of macroeconomics,
the field invented by John Maynard Keynes. It was not then and until today, not now, a measure of
whether the economy is serving the people, whether it is promoting well-being, whether it is
protecting or destroying the environment, whether it is promoting or taking away from longevity.
In other words, a tremendous amount is missed from this indicator. But crazily enough, it is
probably the most watched number in any economy by the business sector and by the broad public
in almost any place in the entire world. So that's the long answer to your question,
do we need a new measure? Absolutely. We need measures that track whether what we want out
of an economy, ability of people to meet their needs, the ability of people to live with comfort
and safety and dignity, the safety and sustainability of the natural environment,
the quality of our lives, the quality of our society in terms of trust, the functionality
of our governments in terms of honesty, competence or corruption. We need measures because those are
all important. And when you follow one measure to the exclusion of the other measures, you follow
or you pull, I should say, your economy and society right over a cliff. If you're following
a wrong goal, just maximize GDP. Of course, we're going to destroy the environment.
We're going to put favor of the mega wealth over the fairness of the society.
We're going to privilege things that are sold on markets, not things that are
non-markets such as our leisure time, our time with children, our own time for learning and so on.
So you follow the wrong measure, you pursue the wrong goals. It's as simple as that. And that's
why we need better goals and better measures for the things that are really important.
What could those be? Are there actually models that take all these things into account? Is there a
good way of approaching this that already has been established?
There is a worldwide movement, sometimes under the rubric beyond GDP, because it is really about
measurement other than GDP that is trying to answer your question. What should we be measuring?
There's one idea which I rather like and pursue, in fact, with colleagues, and that is to try to
measure happiness directly. How could you do that? We don't have a galvanometer to put on
your skin to measure how happy you are. So what is done is to ask people about their life satisfaction.
And then I and colleagues and now a whole worldwide industry of researchers
studies how people answer the question, are you satisfied with your life? Or on a scale from zero
to 10, where would you place your life from the worst to the best? The answers to that question
are very, very informative, even predictive of how people are going to vote, whether they support
populism, whether they are suffering, because an answer to that question also is often very revealing
of the mental illness or depression of people and so forth. One learns a lot about society from
looking at the changes over time in the answer to that question. In the United States, for example,
where that question has been asked for decades, we have seen over the last 15 years a significant
fall in the response to the measure of well-being. And it seems pretty clear that
Americans, my own country, are feeling worse and worse about many things. And so that is an important
indicator. The OECD, the Organization of Economic Cooperation and Development, which is the club of
the high-income democracies, Europe, the United States, Canada, Japan, Korea, and a few other
countries, has been pursuing a broader range of measures that are measures about quality of
the environment, measures about the work-life balance, leisure time,
measures about the quality of jobs, the safety of the work environment, the job satisfaction.
So they have come up with actually dozens of indicators. And what the OECD
staff says is, here are your indicators. They're all online. You can put the way to aggregate them
according to your own values. So we won't give you the weights to add up across all those different
dimensions. That's something for you to do. If you think that the most important issue
is leisure time, or you think the most important issue is life expectancy, or you think the most
important issue is the environment, well, take the indicators and you make your own
weighting. But their idea is that we don't know how to add. So we have to use our two eyes,
our two hands, our toes, our fingers to look at 20 or 30 indicators rather than just one or two
indicators. I think that has a lot of merit also. Now, there's another way that I work on,
which is to take into account that back in 2015, all 193 governments in the United Nations
unanimously adopted the sustainable development goals. These are 17 goals that in principle,
at least, are shared by all countries of the world. They include ending poverty, ending hunger,
promoting health, ensuring that all children of school age are in school, gender equality,
safe water and sanitation, renewable energy access, decent jobs, good infrastructure,
low income inequality, sustainable cities, circular economy that cuts
waste, control of climate change, protection of oceans, protection of land, ecosystems,
the rule of law and global partnerships. Now, if you were counting carefully,
you would have seen that I named 17 SDGs. Those are, and I know them because it's my job at the
UN to help advise how to achieve those 17. So, another thought that I very much subscribe to,
because I think these goals are very important, is to examine how the 193 countries of the world
are faring, whether they're making progress to achieve those goals or whether they're going
backwards or whether they're just treading water that they're neither going forward nor backward.
So, my colleagues and I at the UN produce each year what we call the SDG index. That is a single
number or a ranking which says if you take all 17 goals and you measure how each country is
performing on those 17 goals with a score of zero if it's the worst and a score of 100 if it's
achieved the goal and then you add up across the goals, take the average, then you get a score
and we find that some countries, especially in Europe, Austria is doing pretty well,
Scandinavia is doing even better in general, are making good progress towards the SDGs
and some of the poorest countries are in absolute desperate shape and really need the help of the
rich world but typically are not getting much help because our world is not a very generous
world these days. But that SDG index is another approach to your question, how can we measure
what's really valuable in life? That SDG index, if I could summarize it, says that societies have a
three-part objective. They want to be prosperous, they should or they claim to want to be fair
and they want to be environmentally sustainable. So, a high score means that you are both
economically, socially and environmentally on the right track. My own country, the United States,
comes in around 35th in the world on this, a pretty dismal score for such a rich country
and the reason is that the US is quite rich but it is not fair and it is not environmentally
sustainable. So, of those three pillars of sustainable development, the economic pillar,
the social pillar and the environmental pillar, the US does well only on one of them, the economics,
very rich country, very technologically sophisticated country. But Boyer, we unfair
because the gap between the rich and the poor is the highest gap of any high-income country
and of course, we have a crazy president, Donald Trump, who thinks that it's his job to
increase the carbon emissions rather than to decrease the carbon emissions because he is
trying to help the coal, oil and gas industry to make more profits whereas what we know
scientifically is we have to get out of those fossil fuels and move to wind, solar, hydro,
geothermal energy. So, the US scores pretty poorly even though it's a rich country and that
to just add that long description is a good example of the question that you posed. Here is
a country, the US, very rich, very high GDP per person but not achieving the quality of life,
not achieving the protection of the environment, not achieving social justice. So, we want a measure
that says, aha, don't think you're so good. Your quality of life is evidently suffering and the SDG
index has that property that it flashes a warning red light to the United States you're on the wrong
track. And because you're talking about the question of fairness within the United States
but there's another aspect to the question of fairness which would be the international one
because for me at least living in a country like Austria where the social welfare net is at least
kind of working. I mean, it's getting worse but it's kind of working. And internationally seen,
it's of course pretty good. But still, at least for me, it's pretty striking that we are still
living on the backs of others. So, even Scandinavia, which might have a good ranking
within this score system, this kind of leaves out to factor in this fact that the western world is
actually living kind of on the backs of others and there are people dying on the borders,
there are like strong protectionist economic policies and stuff like that. Does that come
into play somehow? When our group, which is called the United Nations Sustainable Development
Solutions Network, makes this SDG index, we have tracked as closely as we can a large number of
what we call spillover effects, exactly the kind of problems that you're talking about.
For example, we may say we're green and environmental because we're using renewable
energy. But the products that we're buying from China or from other countries are produced with
fossil fuels. So, what we did was we shifted the production to other places and we don't count that
as part of our own effect on the environment. Or when we buy soybeans or buy meat that is coming
from Brazil and those soybeans are being produced on the fringe of the Amazon and contributing to
the deforestation and the forest fires that are underway, we wouldn't see that in our own
consumption but it's a very real effect. Or when we purchase a product and it has been produced with
bonded labor or child labor or slave labor, like the cobalt that's used in the batteries of
every one of our smartphones around the world coming from the Democratic Republic of Congo,
the DRC, and we know horrendous work conditions there, we don't take that into account.
The phone manufacturers say, well, that's not me, that's cobalt, I just buy it as an input.
But that is a direct effect. Now, some of the adverse effects are even starker than that.
Every two or three years, we have a scandal erupt because someone leaks the data on
the Panama files or the other tax havens or New York banks are shown to have been involved in the
mega-corruption in Malaysia and so forth. And these are treated then as, oh my God,
how did that happen? But of course, what we really know is that the tax cheating
and the secrecy is the system, it's not the exception. It is the way the system works.
There are tens of trillions of dollars that in the electronic ledgers are kept in the Caribbean
tax havens, even when there are almost no people in those countries, because under the law, which
is pretty lawless, those places don't charge taxes on the mega-rich. We've just had data
come out in the United States in the last few days that the billionaires now are paying less
than the working class in the most recent tax year. And the billionaires use these tax havens.
Even more direct effects, of course, are when the US or Sweden or others sell armaments to
the Middle East that then end up killing people in Yemen or killing people in Syria or killing
people in Afghanistan and so forth. That is a pretty direct spillover effect that comes out of
the bay of a bomber. It kills a lot of people. So we try to measure those spillovers. That's
one of the reasons why the rich countries definitely are not scored as achieving
the sustainable development goals. And one of the key alleged planks, self-declared planks,
of the SDGs is SDG 17, partnerships of the rich and the poor countries. But I'd say in general,
the rich countries are pretty lousy partners because they do not really honestly look at what
poor countries need in order to escape from poverty or to escape from the environmental
crisis and so on. Of course, the poor countries need to govern themselves properly, but they have
every right, literally right, to expect that the rich countries will be acting honestly,
fairly, and without all of these dire spillovers. The poor countries also have the right to expect
financial help from the rich countries, but that also comes only in small amounts.
There is a category of spending called official development assistance, sometimes called foreign
aid. That's what governments in the rich countries give to governments in the poor countries. We're
not very generous about that. The total amount of so-called foreign aid or official development
assistance is about one-third of 1% of the income of the rich world. And that's a very
in the United States, it's less than half of that. Well, it's about half, about 0.16 or one-sixth
of 1% of US GDP. So we're really nasty and greedy in not providing help for the poorest people
in the world. Now, here the Scandinavian countries do better. They're providing about 1% of the
national income in development aid. Austria could do much better. It's such a rich,
beautiful country, and it wants people to stay home and not be migrants massively to this country.
But one way to do that is to ensure development in the poor countries so that people have a
future in their own countries. And that does require that the rich countries step up and
help to provide the health care, the education, the infrastructure that makes it possible for
the poorest countries to develop. So that's definitely an area where Austria could do a lot
more. And isn't it a problem that oftentimes when financial aid is given, that it is given
tied to certain obligations? Conditions. Yeah, conditions, oftentimes economic conditions of
privatization, opening the markets in order to let international corporations come into the country
and take over the markets. And yeah. Well, the aid is given for all sorts of reasons
of which fighting poverty is often way down on the list. One reason why aid is given is purely
for military or foreign policy reasons. And often those foreign policy reasons are
a pretty unpleasant ones. The U.S. has a lot of allies that are rather thuggish countries.
Those countries get aid because the U.S. wants those countries as allies. Maybe there's a U.S.
military base there, for example. There's a famous phrase about why aid is being given to
particularly horrible country. And the statement is that the leader is really a son of a bitch.
And the answer is, well, he's a son of a bitch, but he's at least our son of a bitch.
And this is a real problem with foreign aid. Too much of it is about war, the military,
or foreign policy alliances. Conditions on foreign aid that
are conditions that the aid should be used correctly are conditions I believe in. In other
words, if you say, I'm going to help country X to keep the children in school, then putting
the condition that the money we're giving, we want to see the schools and the teachers,
and we want verification, and we're going to audit that program, that's perfectly appropriate
in my view. Because if you give the help for a reason, it should actually be fulfilled.
If the aid is given instead, look at the crisis in the United States with our absolutely dangerous
president, Donald Trump, who's surely the worst president we've ever had in American history.
He's giving aid to Ukraine, we now know, based on the Ukrainian government agreeing to
investigate Donald Trump's political foes. Oh, this is straight corruption in the United States,
so the aid is being used for the political objectives of the president of the United States,
not anything about Ukraine, and not just the objectives of the president of the United States,
absolutely constitutionally illegal objectives. So we're rooting for impeachment, I can say,
just as a parentheses, but the point is that aid gets given for all sorts of reasons. Now,
but let me clear up one important point, because I've been involved in this question for a quarter
century, very intensively, often day to day. Once in a while, aid is given for the right reason,
to fight a disease, to help children in school, to ensure access to safe water and sanitation
and so on. And I just want to assure everybody that when aid is well-intentioned and professionally
directed, it actually works. So the most important point is that development aid
can really help poor people, help them to stay alive, help the children to get vaccinated,
help the mothers to survive childbirth, help to fight AIDS, TB and malaria, and many other
incredibly important, wonderful things. And it can be done honestly and professionally.
So we shouldn't confuse the fact that the likes of Donald Trump or George W. Bush misuse aid
as a general condemnation of the concept of rich countries helping poor countries,
because rich countries have a moral obligation and a practical need to help poor countries.
We don't want a world of instability, of starvation, of mass force migration. And
when we're serious about it, which our governments are too infrequently serious,
but when we are serious about it, the aid can actually work.
One of the things that I'm arguing for in this podcast is the need for a plurality of political
economies. This brings up a couple of problems and open questions, of course. One of these
problems is the repression of alternatives when it comes to the political economy on a national
level. At least from my perspective, it seems as if the moment a movement comes into power that
wants to do things substantially different, and Syriza and Greece would be an example for this,
then there are very effective mechanisms in place that are able to prevent this from succeeding.
First of all, I'd like to know if you would agree with this assessment. I guess Venezuela
would be a second contemporary example. Allende in Chile in the 70s would be a historical third,
but the list goes on and on. So first of all, I'd like to know if you'd agree. And if yes,
could you explain to us some of the mechanisms, the toolkits that are being used in order to
prevent this plurality of approaches towards political economy from happening?
Well, it's a little bit complicated because if you take the case of Greece, for example,
the fact of the matter is Greece largely got itself into a mega crisis. The governments
in Greece borrowed too much in the first decade of this century, ran up big budget deficits.
Then the financial crisis came, and oh my God, they owed so much they couldn't repay.
So the starting point of the Greek crisis was rather bad luck combined with rather lax
economic policies. No country should expect that they can overspend what they have
and get away with it for a long term. If you look at Venezuela, it's not different from that,
actually. In the case of Hugo Chavez and then his successor,
they followed a rather classic left populist strategy of Latin America, which is that
Venezuela is an oil country. When oil prices were high, Chavez spent very, very amply and
and overspent, borrowed against future oil earnings. Then oil prices collapsed in the
world markets in 2014. Chavez died of cancer. His successor, Nicolas Maduro, is not so clever
and spent down the country's reserves. Basically, Venezuela went broke around 2017.
Now, in both of those cases, one could say that the alternative project wasn't so accurate.
I can tell you as a personal matter, I went to see Mr. Chavez in 2002 in Caracas. I know a thing
or two about the Venezuelan economy because I worked on it. I studied it. I know a lot about
oil rich economies from a lot of professional experience. I warned him, don't live only on oil.
Don't keep your exchange rate overvalued. Don't borrow against your future income.
I have to say either he heard the opposite of what I said each time because he didn't hear the
don't and he thought I said do, or of course, more realistically, he had other things in mind
and wasn't interested in listening to a university professor from Columbia University. But the fact
of the matter is the economy was badly mismanaged. Now, having said that, there are two very important
things to understand. One is that when countries get into economic crisis, really for whatever
reason, out of their own mistakes or by international bad luck or by some pressure from abroad and often
it's a mix of those, we should never tolerate mass suffering because for whatever reason a crisis
comes, mass suffering is immoral in this world and very dangerous. It leads to terrible outcomes.
People die, children die, there's mass hunger, there's destitution, there's disarray, and in
Greece there was an extremely serious economic crisis. So I tried to help several Greek governments,
in fact, when George Papandreou was prime minister and then when Mr. Tsipras was prime minister,
so really across the political spectrum, I tried to help by saying to the Germans,
look, you're the creditors, but you can't just squeeze this country so brutally because the
pain that's involved is absolutely brutal. Well, they didn't listen and I think the outcomes
were far more serious, negative and harmful than they ever should have been. Maybe Greece is
starting to come out of that right now, but there still is a massive overhang of debt
that should have been lifted from the books years ago. In the case of Venezuela, it is worse than
that because it's not just that the world didn't come to the aid of Venezuela. When Donald Trump
came to power, because Trump is a thug, he decided that he would try to overthrow Maduro. Now, this is
absolutely against international law. It's against common sense. It's against basic decency
and it is a very bad habit of the United States because the US is a kind of neo-colonial power.
It is the world's most powerful country and it has a very bad track record of overthrowing
governments of other countries. I was quite aghast at this. Donald Trump even told
Latin American leaders, maybe we'll just invade directly. He said that in September 2017 at a
private dinner of a number of Latin American presidents who subsequently told me about the
dinner conversation. That's not just not helping. That is being a thuggish. That is being absolutely
reckless. Well, it got worse than that because Trump, rather than invading, decided to squeeze
the life out of the Venezuelan economy. They were bankrupt already but then
Donald Trump essentially said, we will block Venezuela's access to the financial markets,
starting with the oil companies, the main oil company in the middle of 2017. Then in January
2019, just this year, Trump issued an order which said, you can't do business anymore and we're
going to seize the assets of the Venezuelan government. The situation went from a self-inflicted
wound, which Venezuela certainly had inflicted on itself, to what is a human catastrophe
created by the United States. Hunger, a lack of access to medicines. It's an extraordinarily cruel
policy. It is a war on the civilian population, not through a military attack but through a denial
of food. Our international system is extremely weak at stopping that. Where is Europe to say to
the United States, you can't do that? Well, Europe barely has a foreign policy. It needs one. It needs
a backbone to say to the United States, you can't get away with such thuggery. In fact,
Europe has said, well, Maduro is a dictator, so we don't really want to stop the US pressure and
so on, but the means of pressure is absolutely immoral and illegal. To answer your question,
it's a bit complicated. Countries get themselves into trouble, but then I have two rules. One,
when a country and a population is in trouble, they need help, period. These are human beings
and leaving countries to suffer is a gigantic mistake, but worse than that, if you add on to
the pressure and the US has a bad habit of doing this, then it's worse than merely a lack of effort.
It's actually, in my view, a crime against the domestic population. Now, I can tell you that
in this story, we are at the 100th anniversary of the Versailles Treaty and everyone should
note and remember the meaning of that. 100 years ago at the end of World War I,
France and Britain put heavy reparations on Germany at the defeated country and the victors
said that the defeated country would have to bear an intolerable burden. The great economist John
Maynard Keynes wrote in 1919 in one of the most important books of the 20th century called The
Economic Consequences of the Peace. It is a mistake to levy such a harsh peace on Germany because it
will lead to a backlash. He said within a generation, if this is done, there will be a
terrible price to pay. Of course, it was 14 years later that Hitler came to power,
in part because of the devastating economic conditions of Germany. We should never push
countries through economic policies to despair, whether it's at the end of a war,
whether it's because of even the self-inflicted wound of overborrowing, which gets a country into
a debt crisis, or because a president of the United States doesn't like the political party
in power in another country. All of that is extraordinarily dangerous and we should have
learned the lesson of the 20th century and we should not be driving countries to despair.
And if you look at what we're doing today, it's not only Venezuela, it's not only the harshness
with which Greece was treated. Iran, because of the US again, is being squeezed to the point of
hunger and despair through US sanctions and Europe opposes those sanctions but doesn't really fight
them adequately. They just say, oh, we can't really do anything. The United States, you know,
it's an important market and our businesses don't want to violate US sanctions. Well,
Europe should have a backbone and should stand up and say the US sanctions are against international
law, they're against common sense, they're against the Europe's security interests, they're against
the world's security interests, and we absolutely reject them and will not honor them.
I'm so terribly sorry that we have to stop this interview at this moment because I'm being signaled
that it's time to move on. I would have had so many more questions, but unfortunately,
it's no time. Well, I hope we can do it again sometime. Thanks a lot for taking the time,
Mr. Sachs. Great to speak with you. Thanks a lot. Thank you.
That was our show for today. If you want to know more about future histories, please visit
futurehistories.today. You can support future histories at Patreon. For this, go to patreon.com
slash future histories and let me know what you think about this episode and the show in general.