Welcome to Future Histories.
My name is Jan Groos,
and it is my great pleasure to welcome
Troy Witteze and Drew Pendergrass in today's episode.
They are the authors of the newly released book,
Half-Earth Socialism.
And since Troy and Drew do see democratic economic planning
as an integral part of what they propose
as Half-Earth Socialism, I was intrigued to read it.
And it has been an interesting read for me, I have to say,
because there are quite some elements in it
that I kind of stumbled over, I would say.
And this is, of course, always great for a good interview
and an interesting discussion.
We didn't really touch the veganism aspect
of their proposal in detail.
I'll leave that to others to discuss.
But we did go into planning, of course, in quite some detail.
And I think it made an interesting exchange.
I certainly enjoyed talking to Troy and to Drew,
and I hope you will enjoy listening to it.
Before we start, I would like to thank David, Fabian,
Lucas, and Wilfried for their donations.
And I would like to welcome Björn, Manuel, and Gereon
as patrons of Future Histories.
Thank you so much.
If you want to support Future Histories,
but you do not have the monetary resources to do so,
then first of all, thank you too.
It's highly appreciated.
And then there is an absolutely brilliant way
to support the project in non-monetary form
by transcribing your favorite episode.
There's a collaborative transcription project
that has formed around Future Histories,
and I want to thank everybody who has already contributed.
So if there's an episode you like,
and you see a value in providing a transcript of the episode,
and I would argue there are many benefits from a transcript,
then please find a link and a contact email
in the show notes.
So go for it, and thank you.
But now please enjoy today's episode
with Drew Pendergrass and Troy Wieteser
on Half-Earth Socialism.
["Half-Earth Socialism"]
Welcome, Troy.
Welcome, Drew.
Thanks for having us.
It's a pleasure.
Let's start with the definition.
What is Half-Earth Socialism?
Half-Earth Socialism is a kind of socialism
based on the recognition of ecological limits,
but also the limits to our understanding
of the natural world.
And therefore, we're saying that the environmental crisis
can only become overcome by socialism
because it is only socialism that humans can decide
to manage economic growth,
which is impossible under capitalism.
And then we're also saying that socialists
have to be environmentalists
because they have to realize
that total control over nature is impossible
because the more we intervene in nature,
the more risks we take,
such as pandemics or climate change.
So Half-Earth Socialism is that in a nutshell,
and it's also arguing for noiratian,
no conscious control of the economy.
And we propose rewilding half the planet,
which is the Half-Earth component,
and having energy quotas and veganism
to reduce our impact on nature
while also ensuring a good life for all.
I actually know if I have anything to add.
Troy, you did a very good definition.
Thanks.
And before you set out to describe your ideas
about how to address climate catastrophe in the book,
you dissect some other approaches,
three approaches actually,
that are brought forward by others.
And those are bioenergy carbon capture and sequestration,
it's short B-E-C-C-S, nuclear power,
and the idea of Half-Earth itself, actually,
because the origins of this idea of Half-Earth
are not quite innocent.
And there are strands tied to this concept
that have, I think, some quite Malthusian ring to it,
as well as some nativist tendencies, if I'm not mistaken.
So these are three approaches that you dissect
before you lay out your own proposal within the book.
Maybe let's take a look at these three approaches,
and maybe you can tell us what the shortcomings
of these quote unquote solutions are.
Yeah, so you're describing here our kind of look at
the sort of half solutions on offer
by sort of mainstream environmental slash modeling.
So we can take them in turn.
So the first option, BEX,
is an interesting kind of modeling artifact.
So the idea with bioengineering
with carbon capture and storage, or BEX,
is that you have plantations of probably trees,
and then you cut these down,
you burn it for energy, for electricity,
you capture the carbon emitted from the trees,
and then you bury that carbon underground.
And the idea is that this is a carbon negative energy source
because the carbon released by the trees,
the trees capture carbon, they grow,
capture that carbon, you put it underground.
And this is, believe it or not,
integral to pretty much all of the intergovernmental panel
on climate change, IPCC's 1.5 degree models.
So limiting climate change to 1.5 degrees,
and even a lot of the two degree models,
the idea is that they're trying to model
how you might do this energy transition.
It's very hard to do a massive transition very quickly.
So a lot of the models have overshoot
or emit too much or something,
and you need to have negative emissions
to push you back down.
They're often very large amounts of negative emissions.
So the models produce,
these are models that are running blindly.
They're just neoclassical models
with a climate model attached.
And they kind of blindly are like,
okay, let's take three India's worth of land,
plant some tree plantations, burn it.
Let's make some nice assumptions
that this is a carbon negative,
like that there's not an unintended consequence
by like say, soils control a lot of the biosphere's carbon.
Maybe by doing this, we might mess up the soils
and the soils might start emitting carbon,
bracket all that.
And then if you do this, okay, you have a nice solution.
You can have your energy transition
with a lot of fruit to spare.
And the bottom line is this is sort of
obviously never going to happen.
It's a massive project with no movement behind it.
It's just, it's a modeling artifact.
And if anything, it's harder to do the energy transition
than these models make it sound
because BEX is so integral to many of these models.
Now there are models that don't involve BEX
and they involve a much more rapid energy transition.
And that's more aligned with what we are talking about,
things like large amounts of energy use reductions.
The second proposal that we talk about is nuclear power.
And we're more specifically talking to a specific strain
of environmentalists who wants to build
like a nuclear power plant a week or something like this,
or maybe even more.
There's two nuclear power plants a week,
Troy is telling me.
Yeah, so the idea is,
we build up this massive electricity capacity
and then together with a big electrification project,
you solve the climate crisis
by putting everything on this big nuclear power grid.
But this is also seems a little bit ridiculous.
For one thing, nuclear power plants are very hard
and expensive to build and very complex machines.
And we said in the book that
even if nuclear power plants are safer now,
there's still a pretty high risk
of something like a Fukushima like disaster,
even with our current number of nuclear power plants.
So if you add a bunch more, that risk goes up.
We still haven't solved the nuclear waste problem.
The fact that nuclear power is connected
to nuclear weapons in an intimate way
is also another existential threat to worry about.
And then also the fact that
if you build this many power plants,
you are manning a lot of uranium.
Uranium is a pretty nasty thing to mine.
It gets impure pretty quickly
once you mine out of the good, I guess,
the high quality ores.
And then you end up with some problems
and propose solutions to do different kinds of reactors
like fast speed reactors have problems
because they use sodium as a coolant
and sodium explodes when exposed to air.
And that's just, so we just don't think
that this is a plausible plan.
And then the final one we talk about is the half earth.
And many on the left are familiar
with the difficulties of the conservation movement,
the quite nasty side of it.
And we don't hold any punches here.
So the half earth idea comes out
of an intellectual tradition
that has pretty nasty relationship
with indigenous peoples and this sort of thing.
And E.O. Wilson, who ends up taking it on
and popularizing it in a 2014 book,
he is better than some of these conservationists,
but that's not saying much
because he is quite notorious for his sociobiology
is sort of determinism on the basis of genes
and that sort of thing.
So pretty antithetical to what we believe on the left.
But while interrogating this tradition,
what we think is important is that mass extinction,
the ongoing sixth mass extinction in earth's history
is something that we on the left need to care about.
So the sixth mass extinction is going on now
driven by human activity.
There have been five previous mass extinctions.
They are disastrous for life on earth,
not just because we should care about other species
on this planet, but in terms of...
In science, we call it ecosystem services.
So nature does things for us, like keep the water clean,
pollinate our crops, make sure that disease is kept at bay,
all sorts of vital functions.
And if this ecosystem functioning and also carbon capture,
like half of the carbon we've emitted has been captured
by either the oceans or the land.
Some of that's inorganic,
but a good bit of it is through life on earth.
So these are just parts of the planet
that we can't afford to lose.
And the thing that drives mass extinction,
perhaps the most is habitat loss.
So we need to take seriously the idea
that habitat loss is a problem.
It's driving a major environmental crisis.
It's a crisis that will affect all of us
that affects our prospects of having a good life.
And it affects other species on this planet
that we should care about too.
So basically we shouldn't throw the baby out
with the bath water, but we shouldn't like maybe
not interrogate the bath water, I guess,
to use this metaphor badly.
So we talk about how biodiversity is higher
in indigenous managed lands than nature preserves
in many cases.
So there's no need to inherit these nasty sides
of conservation, but we still need to take seriously
the need to protect nature.
Okay, that's interesting because now you kind
of implicitly already answered a question I had regarding
why you stick to this concept of half earth,
because to me it felt as if maybe because of this history
that this concept has and the line of thinking
that underlies it, which has a, in some parts,
slightly semi-authoritarian touch, I'd say.
It begs the question how to avoid including
these highly problematic aspects of the concept
of half earth, because it's not just the ignorance
towards indigenous knowledges and different other problems
that this conservative conservationist movement has,
but also, at least to me, when reading the book,
you will always come into a position where if you start
by having a very concrete idea of how things should be
in the beginning, you will come into the position
where you will kind of have to construct a system
that necessarily, quote unquote, forces people
into what you believe is the correct answer to the problem.
And so there's a specific line of argument,
a line of reasoning underlying this whole idea
that kind of brings you in the territory
where you will have to confront the question
of, in this case, also central authoritarian tendencies.
But I don't think we're naive liberals here
where we think that, oh, it's just a matter
of individual choice that's gonna solve any of these problems.
I mean, we don't use, we don't think this way
when it comes to fossil fuels.
I think socialists are comfortable enough saying
we have to get rid of fossil fuels quickly,
and that's going to require how we live,
and it's gonna force how a lot of people
who use a lot of fossil fuels to change how they live.
And that's, we're also quite comfortable saying
we want equality, that means no more rich people.
I mean, we're happy saying all these things,
but when it comes to meat or the animal question in general,
then people say, oh, hey, you can't say that.
And I think on the left, we need to have a real discussion
about what is a socialist ethic towards animals
and what is the relationship we want with animals.
And this book tries to push that forward.
But we make clear in the book that our approach
or what we're arguing in the book
is really two separate things.
One is a way to think about what socialism is and practice.
And this is where we draw Noirat.
He's saying it's important to have this utopian tradition
where people come up with total plans
or what he calls like social engineering,
and then people compare these utopian future plans
and then vote on them and they decide upon them.
And versus, and the second part would be
what we think those future plans should be.
We offer our own future plan.
But we say quite clearly,
also because at some level we have no power,
we can't force anyone to do anything.
But we say, if you don't agree with us, that's fine.
But then we have to make trade-off somewhere.
We have to say, okay, we're happy to have
synodic disease and mass extinction, and that's okay.
Or we have to live with more nuclear power plants.
And it's, you know, maybe as we can't produce enough energy
for easily high energy quotas or whatever it is,
but we need to have this discussion
about what kind of life we want.
And to kind of keep the veil over this future society
is not proven to be a successful strategy.
And I think it also is missing the key insight of Noirat,
which is socialism is this collective decision
over our future, and to keep it obscure
is actually quite a neoliberal move.
Like only the market can know something as complex as this.
So again, the book is doing two things,
and we like to think we make a good case
for vegan rewilding,
but we want to have more debates
about what this future should be.
Yeah, democracy is a very big theme in the book,
and it's a major part of,
in the portion of the book that's dealing with planning,
because we kind of take that,
the magnitude of changes required
to do the energy transition alone,
let alone address other parts of the climate crisis
is simply a massive task for planning.
And the question is, how can you plan
in a way that is democratic
and doesn't concentrate power in the hands
of maybe a small bureaucracy or some bureaucracy
that's unaccountable to the rest of humanity?
So we take this problem very seriously,
and I was sort of saying,
we have this idea of these total plans
where you might have a plan that involves
higher use of fossil fuels
with solar geoengineering to cool the climate,
and that would come with huge amounts of risks
and maybe many disasters caused,
but perhaps that would be the one that wins out
in our imagined parliament,
and the intro would just be unhappy in the opposition,
but that's the way the cookie crumbles sometimes.
But the hope would be that we make a clear choice
about what's going on,
because right now we're fumbling blindly into the future.
People aren't aware of the trade-offs of decisions,
like having a massive animal industry
causes huge amounts of land to be used
in a very inefficient way,
burning down the Amazon to make new pastures for cattle.
It's not exactly a great planning choice,
and I think these things are talked about blindly
in an isolation, but when they're combined together
and the trade-offs are more apparent,
that's sort of when democracy can really begin
and when kind of a more sensible,
I don't know, control of the planet can start.
Before we get to the planning part,
and this will be, of course,
a big part of our conversation today,
before we get to the planning part,
maybe you could say some words about your position
towards epistemic groundings of this proposal
in terms of planning,
because I think what is very much relevant
for the whole concept that you propose
and relevant for also a lot of the questions I had
after reading the book is,
what information do you think we need,
and how much can we actually know?
Because in the book,
you make use of certain types of modeling.
You propose that we can use modern modeling technology
in terms of climate modeling.
We could repurpose it for questions of planning,
and also when it comes to the question
whether or not a maybe more decentralized version
of planning would be interesting or a central one,
again, the question of epistemic assumptions
about what knowledge can somebody have
and where can it be located comes up.
So I would be interested in what was the epistemic grounding
when you were thinking about how this planning procedure
could be sketched out.
So one of the foundations for the book
from the very beginning is this dialogue
with the neoliberals, with Hayek and von Mises.
And what the neoliberals use,
and Troy, you can jump in a little bit
and talk more about your favorite baddies,
but what the neoliberals say is basically
that markets are information collecting machines.
They're machines for information
where the price acts as a decentralized signal
that allows everyone to respond in concert to changes,
and they don't need to necessarily know
why the price is that,
but it allows them to make according plans.
And a big part of the idea here
is that human intervention in the market
will always be misguided
because the market is sort of beyond human.
It's a machine that is too complex
and important to mess with,
and therefore we should leave it alone
and let it go about its information business.
And we should add markets in as many places as we can,
even where there aren't markets already.
So it's an epistemic argument.
It's an argument that we can't know about the market.
And interestingly, they use a lot of natural metaphors,
biological metaphors to back up this claim.
So they use biology as a metaphor for the economy
rather than the neoclassical metaphor of physics
to understand making equations, right, to model the economy.
What we point out is that the obvious point
that if you're using nature as a metaphor
for how complex the economy is,
well, surely nature is more complicated than that.
And we talk a lot about how complex nature is
and how it evades attempts of management,
many attempts of management.
We talk about the ozone hole, right,
where the chlorofluorocarbons were used
to replace dangerous refrigerants.
And these were supposed to be completely non-reactive,
like all chemistry up to that point,
we're like, yeah, you know, these are tightly bound.
Nothing's gonna break these molecules apart.
It turns out that in this stratosphere
under certain conditions over Antarctica
and to some extent over the Arctic in the winter
and in the spring, you know,
you can get this breaking apart
and then you can get chlorine radical cycles
just completely eviscerate the ozone layer.
And we just got lucky with this.
We got lucky that it only destroyed
the ozone layer of Antarctica.
If the rate constants were different,
then maybe it would go all over.
So it was just lucky.
This was an intervention
that had all the kind of basis behind it,
all the kind of research behind it.
And so it's just kind of a lesson
that interventions into the environment are risky.
They, it's a very complex place.
We also use the metaphor biosphere two,
which was an attempt to make
an artificial closed ecosystem
with like an artificial coral reef,
a bunch of different biomes,
like in a little dome
and have some humans inside and be supported.
And it completely collapsed rather quickly
because of unintended consequences
like the concrete reacted with the oxygen
and they needed to pump in more oxygen
so people wouldn't die.
Most of the species died
but the invasive cockroaches thrived.
It was a disaster.
And it's a lesson in how complex ecosystem services are.
So we point out that basically the question comes down to,
are you going to plan nature?
Basically, are you going to use geoengineering?
Are you gonna, for example, spray sulfur
into the stratosphere to cool the planet
and make the world safe for markets
to continue to go about their business?
Or are you going to step in
and say that humans must plan our own activities,
the economy and not attempt to plan nature
more than a certain amount described maybe by a vote.
We obviously have to intervene in nature to like grow food
and to supply ourselves with the resources we need.
But we argue that we should set
some conscious limits there
so that we allow nature to have its continued functioning.
I definitely agree with what Drew said
and Drew can speak more about the technical aspects
of how do you relate a global plan
to a series of regional and local plans?
How do you use linear programming
to plan the future as well,
which is one thing Kantorovich worked on.
But what I'm gonna say is relating more
to this neoliberal question of what can be known.
And we can be engaged quite a bit with neoliberals
because we think they really raise an interesting point,
which is economics is where is a question of knowledge.
And we think socialists haven't dealt very well with this
or at some level, a lot of the market socialists
just say Mises was right and Noyrat was wrong.
And therefore, you need markets under socialism.
And we still think Noyrat's critique
of pseudo rationality holds true
where if you have markets based on some kind
of universal metric, this labor time, chits,
or is it energy or what have you,
it would eventually lead to irrational outcomes.
And the only way to rationally manage ourselves
as a species is to recognize
that they're incommensurate units.
And we have to judge the totality,
which is again, what Noyrat argues.
And we're not saying this is gonna be easy.
We're not saying that it's gonna work perfectly.
I mean, we get into Cornyn and this idea
that socialism leads towards shortage often.
And at some level, we're saying we have to make a choice
between do we want restraint and shortage
or do we want excess and disaster
and excesses that we don't want as well.
The other thing I would say is that I think it's true
at some level what socialists and neoliberals point out.
I mean, I think at some level it's true
that it's hard to make up for or compensate
for or replace tacit knowledge
as the person on the ground will have a better view
of things than the planner far away.
That is true, but there is also a value
to having an attempt to see the whole.
And the problems that we're facing now,
I think are better faced with the latter,
with attempts to grasp the whole
than with attempts from a point of view of a single person.
And that's the wager we're making.
That's very interesting.
And we will come back to this
because I have some follow-up questions
regarding exactly that.
But before we do so, I think it would be important
for listeners, for the audience to maybe take a step back
and like cautiously get into the planning stuff
because you argue actually for a synthesis
of different approaches, including,
as you already mentioned, in Natura calculation
as proposed by Otto Neurath.
But you also include Kantorowicz's linear programming,
cybernetics in the form
of Stafford Beer's viable systems model.
What elements from these different approaches
do you think should be incorporated
in contemporary eco-socialist planning?
And how does the resulting planning mechanism
actually look like?
Yeah, so to do a high-level overview,
the basic idea is to have,
we kind of imagined sort of roughly
that you would have some set of total plans,
so visions that are coherent for the future
that are then made available for a vote
and then are produced in turn also with lots of input
from people and various interests.
And so how you would devise these sort of,
you would call them maybe blueprints for the future.
And you might use many different methodologies
to produce such a blueprint.
One important historical algorithm
that is still very important today is linear programming,
which is a way of doing constrained optimization.
So if you have a set of constraints that you propose,
like we have only this many people working this many hours
and we need to produce these goods,
what's an optimal solution
or an optimal way of distributing this work?
And this is used all the time in corporate planning.
This is used all the time
in designing renewable energy systems.
It's a very commonly used algorithm,
but there are of course many other ways,
many other tools that one can use.
The idea is to make like kind of a rough draft,
no need to go into super deep detail
and it's not even probably possible,
but to give people an idea of like, okay,
if we have a high energy use future,
this is the sort of resources we'll need.
This is the amount of maybe mining labor,
this is the amount of XYZ
and these are the natural risks,
the risks of climate change,
the risks of geoengineering,
the risks of XYZ involved in this plan.
And then you might have another plan
that's more in line with what me and Troy are proposing.
So you give up a meat
and maybe there could be variations of how much meat
and animal products are given up.
And then you can talk about the benefits
and the sacrifices involved.
And then hopefully you come to a vote
and you come up with a particular path forward.
And then from there,
you have to go to day-to-day management.
And this is where we draw on more of the Stafford beer.
Yes, Troy.
I just wanted to point out
that Drew has already made a model,
a very basic linear programming model
with these constraints between energy use
and land use and extinction rate and all that.
And we use that in the book and we say,
okay, well, what if we want this quota for energy
or what if we want to protect this much land?
And then we test the constraints
and see if that plan is viable.
And again, this is a very basic model
but it's already more complex
than Nordhaus' DICE model, right?
And this is not hard to do,
to have like a very basic discussion about what's possible.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Very basic model, but the idea is basically being like,
okay, if you assume a certain amount of electrification,
how much, what would your energy mix look like?
That sort of thing.
But from there, you have to go to day-to-day management.
So we talk a little bit about the Cybersyn experiment
in Salvador Allende's democratic socialist experiment
in Chile in the early 1970s.
And the idea here was that the Allende government
was bringing in industries into the state controlled sector
and they needed to basically organize and plan
this rapidly growing sector of the economy.
And so some Chilean engineers brought in Stafford Beer
who was a British cybernetics person.
And Beer had this model that he had been working on,
this kind of management model that was hoping
to your earlier point,
try and balance the appropriate amount of centralization
to make sure that resources are being allocated sensibly
with enough decentralization
to prevent any irrational outcomes
or violations of the democratic socialist principles
that Allende's revolution was built on top of.
So both kind of making use of sort of tacit knowledge
of closer to a particular circumstance
and also preventing any unjust
or undenocratic bureaucracy from emerging.
And it's a lot of detail to get into,
but the basic idea of the viable systems model is there's,
you can kind of let say a factory manage itself
most of the time, kind of letting higher authorities know
its inputs and outputs.
Although Stafford Beer would hate me saying higher authority.
He considered this whole thing level,
but like letting a more central information managers
knowing inputs and outputs,
and then emergent skills could be bumped up
to higher levels of coordination.
And again, Stafford Beer would hate me saying higher,
but this proves its metal in a CIA backed strike
against the logistic sector, against the trucking sector.
So basically the entire transport of materials breaks down
in Chile and they had some loyal trucks left.
And the question was, how can we make sure everyone gets food
and how can we make sure that the economy
continues to function?
And this sort of system allowed basically people
on the ground to kind of almost in dialogue
with the center, direct resources in the most wise way.
So like mapping out where this truck should be driving.
So it was this very remarkable evenness
between kind of people out in the field
and people in the center where all this information
was kind of coming in and being distributed,
where these scarce resources are being allocated reasonably
and the country was able to make it
through the strike successfully.
So it's a really interesting kind of management experiment
that did use technology,
but not as much as I think it has a reputation for.
These were like primitive fax machines, right?
That was required.
The computer itself was important, but not hugely.
And then we bring in some more modern ways
of fusing information with modeling from climate science.
So climate science and weather are,
I think something that we should be talking about
because what the weather system is,
what the weather kind of prediction system is,
is a truly global system of information.
So we have weather models, which are models of physics,
but the weather system is chaotic.
People have heard of the butterfly effect, right?
Butterfly flaps and swings,
and then all of a sudden there's a hurricane.
And the basic idea is that if you have slight changes
in your initial conditions,
days later you have a totally different weather system.
It's a chaotic system.
So you need your initial conditions
to be as close to accurate as you can
so that your forecast is accurate.
And the reason why weather forecasts have improved
is because we have better initial conditions.
We have better initial conditions
because we have a global network of sensors, monitors,
and information.
We have satellites, we have buoys in the ocean,
we have ships, we have aircraft,
we have monitors on the surface.
In fact, during the COVID pandemic,
weather forecast got slightly worse
because you didn't have as many planes flying
and you didn't have that kind of mid-atmosphere input
into your weather model.
It's a truly global information system.
And the algorithms designed to run this system
views the sort of model of like
what you think should be going on with what's in the world.
And if there's divergence between what the model says
and what the world says,
there are optimal ways to combine those.
So if you have a plan for how the economy should work,
that plan will obviously fail because, you know,
things will not work out the way you assumed,
but it should be relatively accurate
because it is what the plan is.
And so you can update that plan on the basis of, say,
like a factory not receiving its steel shipments,
and you could maybe go in and see where the problem is
and be able to intervene in a way that's sensible,
but that also makes sure that autonomy is preserved
to as great of an extent as necessary,
but also make sure that everyone's working towards
common, coherent goals.
So it's a balancing approach.
And these are really remarkable algorithms.
I think there needs to be more conversation about them.
They're very powerful tools that are already being used
to do a form of global information management.
And I'm very sorry, Drew,
but I have to pick up on the question of higher authority
because you rightly point out
that I would be skeptical of this phrase,
but when I read specifically the narrative part
at the end of the book,
there is a sense of quote unquote higher authority
in terms of the like central planning board.
And as far as I understood it, at the end,
the model that you propose will end up in kind of calculating
optimal plan or the best variety of plans
that all try to be as efficient as possible
and then propose these plans to the public to decide over,
but then you will always come into the situation
where people will have to enact this plan.
And this might lead to a situation
where those people who will have to enact the plan
will perceive this plan as external from themselves,
depending on how much they were involved
in creating the plan, of course,
but still, at least for me,
when reading the narrative part at the end of the book,
there was a certain sense of this
like detached planning commission,
which seemed to be a bunch of experts, quote unquote,
that calculates this optimal plan
that we are now forced to bring into being into practice.
So there is this element of higher authority coupled to,
I would say the concept of central planning per se.
And I would be interested
how you conceptualize this in your model.
I got the feeling as if your main point would be,
it's urgent, we need to fucking do something.
This is the only way we can do it.
That's the kind of vibe I got more or less,
I have to be honest.
I mean, I'll start,
Drew is definitely the more the mathematical whiz
of the two of us by far.
But I think I just want to point out that,
what's nice about linear programming
is that the math, as Drew's saying, is not so complex.
So I think we imagine at some level
that everyone would be taking linear programming
in school and anyone could make a global plan
or anyone can use the modeling tools
that one puts out to make a plan
and one could make their own plans.
And this is the very Noiratian approach to socialism
where you are showing the working class
what the economy is, let them see it through isotype,
make it as visually easy to understand
and appealing as possible.
And they'll set up museums
and get hundreds of thousands of people
to see what the Austrian economy looks like.
And then you can imagine taking it over.
And I think with this kind of mathematics,
people would see a relation between their own work
and what kind of world they want.
And I think this is an important part
of what socialist democracy would be.
And that's not to say that people are always gonna get
the plans that they vote for,
but that they want, right?
But I think it would be one important way
to overcome maybe any kind of reluctance or disagreement.
I mean, again, humans are always gonna disagree.
I don't think that's going to go away,
but there's also a reason why it's important for us
to have a more nuanced relationship
between local and central planning.
And I think a lot of debates on the left
are just like, oh, we'll just have a tiny little communes
that are extremely inefficient,
but they'll be autonomous and that'll be fine.
Or we'll have some gigantic tanky solution,
like a super plan.
And I think what Kantorovich and Bjerg get into
is a much more nimble relationship.
It's important to have some things centralized
where you can, I guess, not efficient for everyone to make,
I don't know, their own high grade aluminum
or something like that.
It's better to do in some areas than others.
But we also want to,
we also will have problems with information.
That's why you will have a central plan
that is relatively vague,
and then you get down to finer detail the lower you go.
But of course, if a planning bureau
or the parliament that we imagine that we put in La Paz
votes to have mandatory veganism or something like that,
well, I'm sure lots of people won't like that,
no matter how strong the animal rights movement
has become by 2040 or whatever it is.
I mean, there still would be opposition,
but I think that's just what politics is.
And socialism would be at some level
of the politicization of everything
because that is what democratic control of the economy is.
I don't think we should be afraid of that.
And that's where I think market socialists
escape back to the market.
I think they come close to seeing what socialism looks like,
which is what Neuert tells us in 1919,
and then they withdraw because it's too terrifying,
it's too much conflict.
But I think this is a mistake.
Yeah, I think the environmental crisis
throws a wrench into a lot of things.
And I think it's just important to remember
how challenging the questions facing us are.
Like they're more challenging,
as we talked about earlier,
than the IPCC 1.5 degree report that's on
because that report assumes so much facts.
For example, this is an extremely hard problem,
making sure that the dream of socialism that I have
is that everyone on the earth has the resources
for a good life, there's equality,
everyone has the things they need,
and we have a planet that's able to sustain this.
That's a hard goal.
And it's a goal that requires coordination.
And we do try really hard in the book to make sure,
to emphasize how if this is not democratic,
it will fail, right?
There's no way that we imagine this working,
that the democracy is not just like a value,
it's just like a functioning.
Like if you're going to basically get rid
of the capitalist engine,
which is saying that if you don't work, you'll starve.
If you're getting rid of that,
then you're going to have to have buy-in,
and democracy is how you get buy-in.
So it has to be democratic to work.
I don't know if this is convincing to you.
Yeah.
No, no, but I would say your democracy part
is also important because Kantorovich comes up
with linear programming in the 30s,
and he talks to God's plan in the 40s,
and it doesn't go anywhere because God's plan
gets all its power from,
and let alone all the ministries and the government,
get their power from powers of distribution.
And if you had people voting on a plan,
and then people carrying out the plan,
that would take away this power from these ministries
or planning bureaus.
So therefore you needed democracy
to actually have linear programming.
That's why the Soviet Union never did it at scale,
because it would undo the power
of this authoritarian regime.
Well, but the way that the plans would come about
in your proposed scheme of things
is not through mere linear programming,
as you rightly state in the book.
This is maybe a tool for certain types of questions.
It might be useful,
but it is not that people could use linear programming
at home to make a plan on their own,
because the plans that the central planning board,
quote unquote, would produce
would have so much more components included in them,
from like high level modeling
that was repurposed from climate modeling,
to like data from, I guess,
billions and billions of sensors throughout the world,
and so on and so forth.
So it is not that people could,
through this playful participation,
really take part in this planning in a meaningful way.
So my question would be,
how is this interrelationship between central and decentral
really working out in concrete terms
when it comes to A,
the question of how these plans come about,
and B, how people are rightfully so perceiving it
as a democratic act of participation within this process?
So we finished this book a year ago, right?
Maybe even a little more.
But we've kept thinking about these issues
because you're pushing on the right pressure points here.
So we've been thinking about some other literatures
and thinking about some older papers and ideas
that revolve around this idea of iterative planning
or multi-level planning.
And the idea here is that you would have some rough draft
from the middle that might say something
like some rough estimates.
Then you kind of give that out to stakeholders.
And in the original papers,
this is not overly concerned with democracy,
but we would want it to be democratic.
So you give it to stakeholders,
you'd be like, okay, to this factory,
do you think this is a reasonable like kind of downscaling
what the implications of this plan would be?
Do you think this is reasonable?
Do you need more of X or more of Y?
Is this just way too much work?
Is this too much food to expect from this piece of land
given X amount of pesticides are going to be used
or not used, that sort of thing.
And then is this going to cause harm
to this environmental region or these practices here?
And then you get the feedback and then use that to refine
and then maybe you cohere the feedback in some way.
So try and make coherent these things
and produce a new kind of rough idea of the future.
You propagate back down, get more feedback.
And hopefully after a few cycles of this,
of these sets of inputs,
you would have a set of coherent plans
that are plausible at a local level.
And then of course, when the plans are enacted,
you would have of course,
wide leeway on a local level on how to enact them.
It would be that the sort of central goals
are much more about,
are we going to cross planetary boundaries
and are we going to make sure
that everyone gets the raw amount of energy
or food that they need for a good life?
Is there going to be enough grain production?
Is there going to be enough energy production
in the right ways?
Are our grids stable?
Is the key ecosystems being managed well
by whoever's managing them?
That sort of rough idea of things.
Then when the plan is enacted,
you would have a more local manager.
So that's how we've come to imagine
from more engagement with these questions,
how you might produce these plans
in a way that has more democratic input.
And there've been some experiments
with participatory planning out there.
They're often very short-lived or partial.
I think there's a way to make it work
that's necessary both for the construction of the plan,
a fair bit of information and input,
but also in making sure that there's democratic.
There was an experiment in Kerala, India
in the 1997 to 2002 five-year plan,
which was basically an attempt to
have these participatory planning meetings
and hundreds of thousands of people got involved.
The idea was to have this input go into the plan.
The problem was that there wasn't,
this sort of iterative process didn't happen.
So you had a lot of great ideas
that didn't quite get adhered into something cool.
So there were some cool things about like pollination.
Like some people knew about how pollination worked
in their fields and they were able to get that incorporated.
But it was more like tweaks rather than like a dialogue,
which is what we would imagine being an ideal.
So this is an inspiring experiment.
But I mean, obviously you're pointing out
this is a challenging problem, right?
Like we don't feel this job, but like, yeah.
True, I mean, correct me if I'm wrong,
but I think the idea is you would have these
linear programming models as a rough draft
that people could examine and vote on and all that.
And also the linear programming models would relate
from like a central, like a global plan
down to a regional and local plan in various ways.
For example, if you vote globally,
okay, everyone gets 2,000 Watts
and they have 2,500 calories.
And then like the region will say,
okay, where are we going to get this energy from?
And then make another plan and say, okay,
it's more efficient getting it from solar versus wind
and we'll put things here and there.
And then you have that kind of relationship
of being specific more and more
as you go down to the local,
but with parameters set by this larger model.
But it's not like you just vote once on a plan
and then you have the data assimilation,
the cybernetics kind of run the plan for infinity.
The way we're imagining is you would have a series of plan,
maybe like a five-year plan or whatever timeline you want.
And then people can say, go to parliament and say,
okay, what are we going to do
in the next five or 10 or 20 years?
What are our plans for that?
And that can be voted on.
So I think the linear programming is a guide
and the cybernetics is how you implement these things.
But I don't think it's once you've allowed cybernetics
to suddenly becomes undemocratic.
It's just a tool.
Well, I'm so sorry, but I have to disagree.
Please, please.
It's not just a tool.
Yeah, I'm very sorry.
Because I mean, I think at least two points within the book
where this idea of just being a tool comes up
with regard to linear programming.
And now Troy, you just mentioned it
with regard to cybernetics, but it is not just a tool.
Let's take the case of cybernetics.
It is founded on a functional equalization
of humans and machines as information processing systems.
And by looking at the situation from such a perspective,
one will find very different solutions to problems
compared to someone who looks at the problem
informed by a different paradigm, so to speak.
So these are not neutral tools or neutral theories,
but they incorporate a certain perspective on things
and that carries along certain assumptions
about the things that are addressed within the models,
so to speak.
And I mean, at least as I understood it
in the case of linear programming,
the way that you build up your idea
of synthesizing different approaches towards planning,
as far as I read it, it more or less said,
all right, we have this idea of linear programming.
We have this as a mode of approaching certain problems
where it might be adequate,
but you cannot adapt to constant changes very well.
And because of that, trying to approach planning
merely through the perspective of linear programming
is insufficient, and I would totally agree.
And because of that, you go on to take a look
at different other approaches, one of them being cybernetics.
But that does also mean that what you just tried
to describe, Troy, that we would all be kind of able
to understand or maybe even reproduce this process
would not be possible, because as I said before,
linear program is just one piece
within a very complex system of producing different plans
that will then be decided upon.
I'm not sure where this is leading me
because it's not really a question,
and I stated this before, it's just that I think for me,
it was a bit difficult to get to grips
with this directionality
and this emphasis on a center that has at the end
the knowledge that is needed in order to compute these plans,
and because there are so many problems
that go along with this, because it is also not innocent
to have five or 10 or 50 or 100 plans,
because by choosing, by pre-selecting the different plans,
you already enact such a huge power,
because you kind of present the field
upon which the further game will be played,
and this is such an immense power,
and it is not that these are merely neutral technocrats
that are just kind of doing this for the sake of humanity,
even if they do, it would be problematic
on epistemic grounds and on grounds of question of power
and stuff like that.
So I think I was kind of arguing with myself
with this type of constellation between the individuals
and the center, and then, of course, the question comes up,
how do you get people to do this?
If you have this plan, how do you get them to enact it?
So if there are no monetary incentives,
which I absolutely loved about the model,
you do not want to force people into doing anything,
and you want to give them a very high level
of existential security,
which I absolutely loved about the model,
and this is absolutely right, the way you approach it,
but there are so many questions that come up after,
came up for me after reading this constellation,
which for me, at least, kind of tended a bit too much
in the direction of central planning,
because I'm absolutely convinced as you are
that both is needed.
We do need central elements,
we do need decentral elements,
but from my kind of understanding,
there were so many open questions
after reading the proposal,
and most of it came out of A,
the high level of centrality,
and B, like implicit assumptions about knowledge
and where the knowledge can actually be
brought together at the end.
And this, yeah, this was just something
I ended up with at the end.
This is not really a question.
Well, thank you for expressing this.
This is a sort of an early stab, a first attempt here,
and we don't claim that our modeling here,
it's certainly not been the pause of our thought.
We continue to think about these issues.
We've continued to read new stuff,
think new stuff, think about new models.
So, I would really love to read more of other people's
thinking about how we might build a non-monetary economy
an economy that does manage to navigate
the very difficult challenge of the environmental crisis
and the amount of coordination that involves
without the undesirable consequence of over-centralization
or of our current system,
which is complete and blindly walking into disaster
that, and everyone is blind to the full picture
or not everyone, but like that we're all making
small decisions based on small incentives
and it's creating a force that just leading us to ruin.
So obviously we need a middle ground, right?
How does that middle ground get constructed?
And what we've tried to do,
and so I guess I'll respond to a couple of the comments.
So about technology never being neutral,
this is of course true.
And about technocracy never being neutral is of course true.
True.
What we tried to do is try and,
but we also think that there needs to be some,
I guess, administrative division of labor.
We don't want everyone coming into meetings every day
to plan things, I guess.
So there's some amount of administrative division of labor.
So we imagine still a parliament sort of system.
So we have this sort of elected official sort of thing
going on, which is already a compromise.
We all know how representative democracy has its failings.
And so there's all these compromises we're trying to make
along the way to try and balance
all these different tendencies.
And that technology is never neutral,
it's an important one, but that technology is,
that the tools that we have developed
to think about the world system,
the earth system scientifically,
seem to have promise in balancing environmental constraints
is also there.
And the question is, can we use this technology
in a way that is democratic and is able to be just?
I guess we're optimistic.
Yeah.
But I don't know, I'm sort of trailing off here, Troy.
What do you want to say?
Yeah, it's true.
I think you can see too much.
I mean, yeah, and I would push you to formulate
your questions or your criticism more clearly.
I mean, are you saying like, okay, no,
there's no one mind with all the knowledge in the world.
And I mean, it's kind of Hayekian argument.
And you're like, okay, sure, I agree.
But I mean, and this is why, again,
we're talking about having these layered plans.
Like the central planning, the global planning bureau
will set fairly loose guidelines
according to these planetary boundaries
and orders boundaries for a good life.
Like how many calories or energy does a person need?
And then how to actually carry that out
will be left up to regional and local government.
And so I think there's that aspect.
So I would agree with that,
but we don't make this claim of having total knowledge.
And then of course, technology isn't neutral.
I mean, sure, but I also would say that cybernetics
being some kind of like wicked military form of thinking
is also a too simple critique.
Not that I'm saying you're saying that,
but some people are of course,
are very skeptical of cybernetics for this reason.
I mean, Beer was a huge hippie.
Wiener himself was incredibly antagonistic
to the military after the war as well.
I mean, I think it's, and we're not proposing,
yeah, merely, okay, we'll just see a bunch of experts
to figure things out.
That's not what we're saying.
And again, we're trying to make this
much more Noiratian point of you have to get
as many people involved and as many people
to understand what the economy is.
And will that be perfect?
Or will everyone have complete knowledge?
No, but I think one should try.
And then how exactly does one organize socialist democracy?
Do we have referendums?
Like, do we have a parliament?
I mean, these are things we should be thinking about,
but I think the alternative to say,
oh, these things are too difficult.
And therefore we have to do a market socialism
and then rely on a market mechanism
will not suffice to solve the problems we need to solve,
which again, you know, mainly environmental problems.
If we need to have us agree at the species,
okay, we want to have only this much carbon emitted.
We want to have only this much land deforested.
If we want to stop climate change or the sixth extinction,
if only part of us agree,
then it doesn't really matter what the rest of us do.
So I mean, again, maybe if you could reformulate
what your critiques are, I'd be interested to hear it.
Yes, absolutely.
But first of all, I neither said that I think
that cybernetics is just some form of military wishwash
or anything as such.
I just pointed out that it is not,
that all these theories are not neutral in any way,
but that they do imply some pre-assumptions
that make a difference.
I'm absolutely pro, including cybernetics,
100% into our thinking.
So I'm not actually stating that.
Neither am I in any way, shape or form a market socialist.
So if you pose it like either we do it your way
or people are market socialists,
then this is also an inadequate description
of the situation between the three of us right now,
because I'm not in favor of market socialism.
So just to make that clear.
And then maybe I can make it a bit more clear
when it comes to the question of detail,
because right now you stated that the central planning board
would only kind of give out some like broad guidelines
or something like that.
And this would be something very different.
And when I read the narrative part at the end of the book,
and this is the part that maybe created this sense
of over-centrality the most, I guess,
there were some points within this narrative
where people were like, all right, okay,
because of the central board deciding
that this labor should be allocated over there
and people should do X, Y, that over there,
we will now have to kind of try to enact it.
And so there was a very clear sense
of this directionality coming from the center
in terms of the center has computed some kind of ideal plan.
And I'm being polemic here a bit just to make the argument.
There was this sense of there is this central board
computing this ideal plan.
And now we will have to find ways to enact it.
And this kind of directionality is important, I think,
because it will decide over the question
whether or not people do experience
democratic plant economies as democratic plant economies
in terms of democratic in all caps,
because this, as you rightly stated before, Drew,
this is essential to actually making this work,
because if they do not, and you do not have any types
of monetary incentives or other forms of coercions,
then this whole thing will not work out.
To me, it seems as if the way it is set up right now,
this form of over-centralization leads to a point
where the plan maybe by being too detailed
is first assuming epistemic aspects
that I guess I would not share in terms of
can this knowledge actually come together at this point?
And Troy, you were rightly so,
I think pointing towards tested knowledge
and the question of how to handle this one.
So this is the first one.
And then if it is too detailed,
and not only in the framework of like loose,
not loose, but broad guidelines,
you will come to a point where it will be experienced
as external by the people who will have to enact it.
Those are the two things.
And this makes a very big difference,
because if you, for example, look at models
where questions of economic planning are handled
through like prices for central categories of production,
then you will have a very broad set of indicative prices
that then kind of indirectly lead to a form
of coordination within the system in a very loose way.
But I had the sense that within the proposal
that you are bringing forward,
this type of detail in terms of what is planned
and what is not planned and who is involved
in which aspects of planning is a very different one.
So I hope this is a little bit more clear.
Yeah, no, this is nice.
And this is actually, this is a really good place
to be talking about the appropriate level of detail.
And I definitely think that this is,
I think the right area to be focusing on,
what is the appropriate level of detail
at each level of the plan, right?
We're imagining some sort of kind of federative, right?
Like structure right where that,
and then the concreteness goes down.
And I think what we're trying to get out with the narrative,
and I think is insufficiently clear,
is that the planning and sort of the central valley
of Massachusetts would be done in terms of like,
how many, like we have these factories
and these farms here, here, and here,
and how much labor is required for each.
And then if someone puts in an application for work
and they wanna live here,
like these are the options to choose from.
That level of detail would be at that kind of county
to city level, I guess.
And so this would not be set up by the US
or the Eastern US or the North America
or the global level, right?
It would be more like we need,
we think we want some vegetables, right?
And then we can grow some amount here, right?
But that was sort of what we were going for.
So we don't imagine that that,
we imagine that that detail is more local.
From there, we can have a conversation
about whether that's too much or too little detail.
And I think that would be a really,
that's the sort of, I think,
really nice conversation that I would love to have
in this sort of discussions of how we might do planning.
And the question of,
do you, quantities, do you do indicative prices?
Do you do, what is your mechanism for doing this?
We've been talking about sort of in the Torah units.
So like, we, I guess, have been leaning more
on the sort of quota such quantity side of planning,
but perhaps there could be a case
that in for playing certain aspects of things,
an indicative price and then allowing things to do this
in some controlled way might be a reasonable way
of doing local planning or something like this.
I think we kind of intentionally leave it a little vague
about how these plans are carried out.
So I think,
I don't actually think we disagree very much,
which is of course a classic thing for me to say,
but I think, I don't actually think we,
I think this is the sort of detail
that we kind of didn't flush out too much in the book,
maybe to our own detriment.
The book is quite short, just for listeners to know.
We cover a lot of ground at a very high level,
which might get us in trouble.
But I think,
I think that this is a good conversation.
I would be nice to build up a more detailed model
to like answer all these questions
and try and think about like,
what the right level of detail is,
what planning tools might be used at different levels?
What is the appropriate level of detail at different levels
in terms of both information gathering
and in terms of both experiencing it
as a non-coercive system?
I don't know if that was coherent,
but those are my thoughts to what you just said.
Yes, and I mean, I just want to point out
that there were a couple of things
that I really liked about reading all of this.
So that it's not that I was reading
and it was constantly thinking,
oh my God, this is too authoritarian central planning.
There were quite some elements that I really enjoyed.
For example, this whole engagement
with the question of modeling
and how this could be a nested way of modeling
in order to kind of avoid this idea
of just having one central point
where the data comes together.
Because as you state in the book,
in the case of climate modeling and weather modeling,
this could never be accurate
because you will have to have a form of nested approach
in order to get to a point
where you will be able to more or less get a picture
and an idea of a very, very dynamic system
that you are trying to get an idea of.
So I thought this was really interesting
and I immediately thought,
okay, well, this would be interesting
to get into contact with some people
who are actually doing this
and how this could be then re-appropriated
to kind of use this Neurethian innatura approach
that you obviously like very much.
And since this was a really big question mark for me,
how would this innatura calculation actually look like?
I didn't really immediately had an inner image or idea
how this would be approached in concrete terms
because of course there are so many things
that a modern economy is made up of
that comparing everything innatura, of course,
kind of brings you in a difficult spot as well.
And since I was very much interested
in how to approach actual innatura calculation
in modern economies, and on the other hand,
you were pointing towards these types of modern modeling,
I was very much intrigued in how this would go about
or how do you think about this pair
which I was perceiving as an interesting fit actually.
I suppose like the next step for this kind of project
would be to think more seriously
about making like a world model, right?
And then, or work with people on regional or local model.
Let's just assume the global model says this,
and how would, let's say, Austria figure it out
and what would Vienna look like based on those constraints
and kind of work it out.
I think this is, again, the Neurathian part
where socialism is imagining these features
and having discussions about how we should live.
But you're right where I think the innatura
parts of the plan would have to be a different radiance
of detail, and I think,
and I can imagine, you would just say,
like how large is the chemical industry
or how many fertilizer or pesticides do you want?
And then, as in you could have some kind of way
to group that, but then there would also be a way
to zero in and say, okay, what does that look like
in terms of phosphorus versus ammonia and so forth, right?
And I think you want to have enough,
less detail to look at these things in total,
which again, we try to get into the book
because we want people to really engage
with these questions of energy and land use
and the kind of nature we want.
And then one can zero in if they want.
Great, so at the end of every interview,
I ask my guests, if you think about the future,
what makes you joyful?
I think writing this book has been a joyful experience
because at some level, I think it's possible for us
to overcome the environmental crisis
and to overcome capitalism
and to ensure the good life for all
without sliding into some horrible dictatorship.
I think it's not beyond humanity at some level.
And we just want to convince more people
that this is the case,
because otherwise there's too much doom and gloom.
Yeah, I think in writing this book,
we've encountered people who are thinking very hard
about issues like the practical details
of transcending capitalism
rather than simply critiquing, critiquing, critiquing.
It's easy to critique, but as soon as you offer something,
then people can come after you,
which is good because it helps us refine our ideas.
But it's being introduced to all these people
thinking about these issues has been really, really wonderful.
And it makes me very excited that we can hammer out
the details in an appropriate way
that we are able to walk these many tight ropes
that we'll need to walk to build the future we all want.
Great, and I hope you didn't get the sense
that I was coming after you because I wasn't.
I really enjoyed that you were putting out
this concrete ideas on how things could be approached
because I absolutely agree that we do need more
of this type of engagement
with how things could actually be done differently.
No, no, I mean, this Think Tank podcast is amazing
because there aren't that many that really get
into the nitty-gritty of planning theory.
And it's been a real joy to listen to your podcast
and to have a place where we can really get into the weeds
of some of the more obscure stuff in the book
because not everyone wants to talk about Soviet mathematics.
So thanks so much for having us.
Thank you too.
Yeah, this was really great.
Yeah, it would be wonderful to talk even more
and think more and maybe we have this iterative democracy
thing for a Philip Dapricks conference
in late June, early July.
So maybe we could get more feedback there.
So, I mean, we're still working and thinking.
So, I mean, hopefully we can continue to talk
and develop ideas.
Perfect.
Okay, Troy and Drew, thank you so much
for being part of Future Histories.
That was our show for today.
Thanks a lot for listening.
If you want to support Future Histories,
you can do so on Patreon.
For this, visit patreon.com slash future histories
or you can simply tell a friend that you liked the show
and that he, she, or they might like it as well.
Thanks a lot and hear you in two weeks.