Welcome to Future Histories, my name is Jan Gross and it is my great pleasure to welcome
David Leibman in today's show.
He is Professor Emeritus of Economics at Brooklyn College, New York and editor of the journals
Science and Society.
David has written extensively about economic coordination and developed a model called
Multi-Level Democratic Iterative Coordination, which will be at the center of our conversation
today.
I am absolutely thrilled that this episode came together and that it did so right now
because the new special issue of Science and Society's project Envisioning Socialism has
just been published and these special issues, they are released only once every 10 years
and are concerned with a topic that is of great importance for the investigations of
this podcast and that is democratic economic planning.
The three predecessor issues appeared in Science and Society in Spring 1992, 2002 and 2012
and so I marked my calendar for Spring 2022 in order not to miss this very special opportunity
and I am very happy to announce that I did not only record the interview with David Leibman
that you are about to hear today, but also lengthy conversations with Robin Hannell and
with Pat Devine who are both, just like David, enormously important contributors not only
to these special issues starting from the first one in 1992, but they are also central
contributors to the debate around democratic economic planning in general.
This means there will be quite a couple of English language future histories episodes
spread over this spring and summer devoted to the topic of democratic economic planning
and I have a couple of remarks regarding this.
The first one would be to my German language audience, I am sorry, I had to do it, I simply
had to do this, Future Histories is a predominantly German language podcast and it will continue
to be so, but this was simply too perfect and so I couldn't resist and as regular listeners
will know, I argue for podcasting as a form of extended research practice and this deep
dive into democratic economic planning is to be understood as a part of exactly that.
So danke für eure Geduld, thank you for your patience with this long detour into English
language episodes and in the spirit of podcasting as research, I have an important plea directed
at all of you.
At one point in the interview you are about to hear with David, he states, and I quote,
the truly international discussion is still in front of us, end quote, and I could not
agree more, so please, if you know about interesting positions on democratic economic planning
from the global south, then please write me.
If everything works out as planned, I will feature guests from Chile soon and planning
in Kerala, India is also on my radar, as is the history of Soviet cybernetics, but I cannot
stress this enough.
If you know about interesting contemporary thinkers or experiments in democratic economic
planning from the global south and non-western positions in general, then please write me.
You can reach me via jan at futurehistories.today, that's J-A-N at futurehistories.today.
Very much looking forward to hearing about all these different approaches and experiments
from all over the world.
So now please enjoy today's episode with David Leibman on multi-level democratic iterative
coordination.
Welcome David.
Okay.
Thank you Jan.
It's good to be here.
It's my pleasure.
Before we get to your model specifically, let's start with a very basic definition.
What is democratic economic planning?
Okay.
I was going to back up a little further before that, but I'll get to democratic economic
planning in a moment.
I wanted to start by referring to all of the buzz in the world around the concept of socialism
as such.
There's a lot of discussion of socialism, a renewal of interest, and this is of course
very important for us, I think, and very important for the way the world is going to go.
So I wanted to suggest a few distinctions.
For many people, the word socialism means what I call ameliorative socialism, ameliorate,
make better, improve, and they can think of, and I can think of, all sorts of improvements
that we want to make in the world.
We want a world of equality, a world of solidarity, a world of participation, a world of security,
dignity.
These are some words that clearly come into the concept, and I'm happy to situate all
the work that I'm doing, and everyone who's working on what I call systemic socialism
would be part of, you know, we're all part of that, but we need to go further.
The second distinction is what I call inspirational socialism, and it takes its cue from some
phrases from the classics of Marxism, and not only Marxism, but there are inspirational
socialists who refer to thinkers going much farther back.
And here you have phrases like the world of the associated producers and the working
class in power and the commonwealth of toil.
One can go on and on, you know, with these wonderful inspirational phrases from the past,
and the kind of socialism that I, and I gather many of the people who have participated in
your symposium series, is interested in, is going beyond that.
In other words, we need to not just talk in general terms about the working class in power,
or to use a phrase from the manifesto where Marx and Engels speak about the condition
for the free development of each is the condition for the free development of all, you know,
this kind of language, which is wonderful, but it clearly needs to be transcended.
We need to put some meat on those bones, so to speak.
And finally, you have speculative socialism, you know, speculative utopian, where just
like the kind of thing that Marx was so concerned to transcend in the early part of the 19th
century, where there were all these writers, some of them very brilliant, putting forward
completely arbitrary idealist visions of how things would work and telling everybody
things will be done this way, and you will have this kind of institution and that kind
of institution.
And Marx wanted to get away from that totally.
So what's left?
What's left is what I call systemic socialism, which is somewhere in a middle ground between
simply saying we want to strive for equality and so forth, the thing, the values that socialists
uphold on one side versus a kind of utopian or speculative arbitrary engineering of institutions,
which Marx was quite clear.
And I think most of his followers have gone along, gone on from that.
You simply can't preordain, you can't write what Marx called recipes for the cook shops
of the future.
It just doesn't work.
You have to see socialism as something that grows organically within the existing society
and partakes of all of that history and sort of concentrates that history.
So it's in that framework that I would talk about democratic coordination, democratic
economic planning.
And yes, like as with my colleagues, Pat Devine, Robin Hanell, Al Campbell, Cockshot and Cottrell,
Alan Cottrell and a new contributor who works with them, Dave Zechariah and many others
who don't write in English.
And for that, I apologize.
I do read some Spanish and some Russian, but not enough to really say that I can
represent the people who write in those languages.
And the truly international discussion that we need is still in front of us.
We haven't yet achieved that.
And I'm as much to blame as anyone for that.
But anyway, we're all talking about democratic economic planning and trying to figure out
what that could possibly mean.
So that's a sort of a preamble that gets us to the doorstep of the question we need to pursue.
And apart from the way that you approach it specifically within your model, is there
some kind of definition of democratic economic planning that you could provide?
Well, I think the definition emerges in each of the separate models.
And I'll have something to say about that, because what I've tried to do in a recent paper,
the subtitle of which is A Model of the Models, clearly the subtitle implies what I'm trying to
do is look at the way the various models are related to each other and to understand whether
some kind of synthesis might be possible.
When I know you have a separate agenda, we'll talk about the science and society special issue.
And here I'm tempted to hold it up and show everybody, but I realize there's no visual here.
We're on audio only.
But it just came out.
We have the special issue of science and society, which is the fourth special issue,
which have been issued at 10-year intervals in the 02 years, in 1992, 2002, 2012, and now 2022.
You know, at specific 10-year intervals, kind of why it worked out that way, but it didn't.
And on the re-envisioning of socialism or envisioning of socialism and
what struck me about the work in those issues, it made a real attempt to bring everybody in
we brought in proponents of market socialism, which is the idea that,
first of all, very important contribution markets and socialism are separable.
They're not the markets and capitalism.
Sorry, I misspoke.
Markets and capitalism are separate.
They're not the same thing.
And that you can combine the advantages of markets with the advantages of socialism into
something called market social.
It's not my view, but it is one of the views that we sought to represent and various views
of economic planning and democratic economic planning on the other side.
Put them in a whole big circle.
My perception of this from 1992 forward as we did this work was that
people were talking past each other to some extent.
We were saying something in one of the special issues.
And then those of us who repeated and participated in the next special issue
were saying the same things again.
But that to use a very favorite socialist economic term convergence, convergence was
not occurring.
In other words, we didn't seem to be getting closer together.
We didn't seem to be moving forward in that sense.
And part of my recent work is an effort to overcome that or an effort, at least to address
it, to address the problem of synthesis, convergence, transcendence, moving on to another stage.
So that if we have another special issue in another 10 years, I won't be around to see
it, but it'll be, you might.
It won't look the same as the one that came before, the one that came before that.
It will have moved forward.
Of course, a lot depends on the world moving forward and the progressive and working class
movements of the world moving forward and taking these things to heart.
And that is something that I cannot directly influence, but can hope for.
Anyway, I like also to take it a little further.
I like also to distinguish between different stages of socialism.
And here lies a major confusion in my view that is very present in many of our minds
we fall into it, we mix these things up.
We forget whether we're talking about stages of historical development.
And if we're talking about that, then we definitely mean
looking at actual historical societies in all their complexity, where you have the
coexistence of different social forms.
You have the coexistence of state administratively
organized production, production directly under political control and managed by a
bureaucracy of some kind that's carrying out the coordination functions and the
control functions.
And those bureaucracies have existed for thousands of years.
You might just as well call some of the dynasties of ancient China
socialists because they were very large and sometimes very efficient.
Surprisingly, so if you look into that history, systems of coordination with legal structures,
which the Chinese ancient philosophers were concerned to elaborate.
And of course, they've existed in the modern world in recent centuries and they continue to exist.
So you take a country like China, for example, which has a large and important state sector,
but that state sector also has state-owned enterprises, SOEs,
which are often managed and run on a small scale.
They're managed locally, but they exist as state-owned enterprises.
And in the midst of that, you have capitalist enterprises competing with them.
As we know, there's been some resurgence of actual capitalist relations in China, plus
cooperatives, plus the international capitalist sector in special zones, where some regulations
apply to them and so forth and so on.
In other words, you have a huge mix of systems.
You have a mixed economy, to use a phrase from the Western political economy literature.
And if socialist relations are, to the extent that social relations are dominant there,
you might call it a socialist mixed economy.
In fact, that's what the Chinese Communist Party basically puts forward as its view of themselves,
the market economy, with Chinese market socialism, with Chinese characteristics,
you know the phraseology that they use.
And from my point of view, that is all on one side.
What the model, the MDIC model, as you named it, multi-level democratic iterative coordination,
is about is not that.
It's not about combination of different things in historical admixture
with all of the contradictions and complexities that accompany that.
Not that.
It's a model of the way core institutions in the modern socialist economy interact with one another
and mutually determine each other.
That is the central idea, what we'll be talking about in a little while.
That's the main thing I want to get to.
The point, just to finish this up, about the stages, confusion that exists,
is that it has overtaken huge sectors, not just of the mainstream capitalist intellectual environment
where these people talk about mixed economies and institutions from here and there,
and the eclectic picture, transforming the complexity of the real world that they
observe into their theory directly with no organization, with no intervention on the part
of logic.
So you have the Cubans, for example.
They have their regular party congresses.
And obviously, discussion is going on all the time there, not just at the party congresses,
but it becomes very prominent at those periods when they wrestle with the question of what they
call reform.
The question is exactly the same as the Chinese question.
It's how can we mix socialism, I'm putting inverted commas, quotation marks around the word
socialism here, which means state production, state central planning, etc.
How can we mix that with just the right amount of, now quotation marks again, capitalism,
so that we get the advantages of capitalism, a spur to incentive, competition, dynamism.
That's what capitalism gives us, whereas the state sector gives us what we like from socialism,
security, equality, coordination, addressing the ecological problems which are always at the
forefront of our minds, those kinds of things.
How can we, so they're not talking about socialism, and I'm talking about the fundamental
levels of the Cuban leadership and of the Chinese leadership.
They're talking about a socialist capitalist mixed economy, the advantages of both.
And if you read their literature, that's very much the way the thinking goes.
Now, the implication of that is there's a one way highway with strong central planning,
state control at one end of the spectrum, and total deregulation market processes,
atomistic competition and so forth at the other end of the spectrum.
That's your spectrum.
And what we need is a mixed economy somewhere in the middle.
In some ways, it's not too different from the Keynesian conception within mainstream economics.
The mix of private and with the appropriate degree of state intervention or state intervention with
the appropriate mix of market competition in order to spice it up a little bit.
I think that's totally wrong.
I think MDIC and the other models that people have put forward is on a different dimension.
It's what the word, I'll just say perpendicular to, it's often in a different direction.
It's not that at all.
So if people say, and friends of mine in Cuba have said this, we need reform.
I say, well, reform in which direction?
In which direction are you going to reform?
And so multi-level democratic iterative coordination, if I can use my term,
the way I put it together, other people have different terms, of course,
is not somewhere on the spectrum between the market and central planning.
It's something completely different from it.
And that's the essential idea that I want to try to get across.
Yes, great.
And I mean, I can only highlight that we absolutely need an alternative because I mean,
it's not only, as you referenced, someone like Keynes who posits this as if there was only
hierarchical central planning or absolute atomistic market forces.
It's also Hayek who famously used this dichotomy as if it was only this or that.
And then we definitely have to transcend it.
And so I'm very happy to talk about exactly that with you today.
So let's get to your model.
Could you maybe as a start, give us a broad overview of multi-level
democratic iterative coordination?
What's the basic structure?
What are the basic assumptions and premises of your model?
Oh, when you take the concept of democratic planning, just take those two words.
An average person is going to scratch their head.
They're going to say, what in the world can you possibly be talking about?
Planning is creating something according to a single consistent vision.
When a painter plans a painting, he doesn't consult a whole roomful of people and say,
well, should I put a tree here?
Should I put a house there or a stream there?
The conception has to be kind of integral.
It's kind of almost inherently coordinated.
That's in the concept of planning.
Democracy, on the other hand, is a multitude of individual wills pulling in different directions.
Now, if you're not going to coordinate that with a market or with elections in the
political sphere, we'll just decide by having votes.
If you're not going to coordinate that way, how are you going to combine planning and democracy?
If people are involved in planning, they're going to say, well, someone's going to say,
I think we should do this.
And someone else is going to say, I think we should do that.
Well, what if this and that don't work, don't fit together?
Someone else is going to have to figure out a way to reconcile them.
It might take the form of a compromise or something is going to have to happen.
Anything you want to say about the constraints so that nobody's vital interests are threatened, sure.
We can obviously bring that on board.
But you still have a conflict.
This is the binary.
You referred to it before, the idea, and it's present in Hayek and the libertarian
thinkers at one end of the spectrum, plus the mixed economy people.
Everyone is worried about this.
But you never get away from that single dimension.
You never get away from that single idea that somehow we're going to have to
find some kind of a muddled up compromise in the middle if you want that.
If you're Hayek, you want to stay at one end.
But that's clear.
How are you going to do this?
The answer that emerged from the experience of first attempt socialist construction
in the 20th century is the iterative concept.
So I can start with that in answer to your question.
It was a central aspect of multi-level democratic iterative coordination.
The idea is really very simple.
The center, I'm going to speak of the center and the enterprise.
I'm going to speak of, first of all, I'm going to speak of two levels.
The model says multi-level, and that implies there could be more than two, which we could
analyze later, but I'll work with a simple conception of two levels, top and bottom,
center, and I don't want to say periphery.
That brings in another level of thinking.
The center essentially defines a brand plan for one of its enterprises, for all of its
enterprises, but we'll talk about a particular one, which is the basic nature of the enterprise,
the basic nature of its function, the kind of goods or services that it delivers
to the society as a whole.
And it says, this is what we see as your baseline.
Essentially, this is a point at which my model says the enterprise is not autonomous.
Now, there's an idea out there, which is another one of these unanalyzed terms that
people sometimes use a lot, self-management, and a lot of pro-socialist and socialist advocacy
people speak about self-management, and what we have to have is a lot of self-management.
If you analyze self-management, you have to ask, what does that mean?
Who is the self?
And of course, the self is a hierarchy of levels.
At one level, the self is a single individual.
At another level, the self is the society as a whole, but who speaks for the society as a whole?
And there are many intermediate levels.
There are sort of like non-governmental organizations.
There are stakeholders at middle levels of that process.
Some of the people you've been talking to and are continuing to talk to talk about
stakeholders a lot and stakeholder democracy.
Good.
So there are all these levels.
The enterprise belongs to society as a whole.
Society as a whole consists essentially, let's assume, of its working people.
It is the working class in power.
Okay.
We'll assume that remnants of the billionaire class are no longer a significant social force.
They're gone.
So everyone is working people, but with all differentiations within us,
different kinds of work and different levels.
But that's the overall social control of the enterprise.
So the first starting point is the enterprise can't simply
sell its assets and move to another country or change fields completely,
change from being in manufacturing production and move over to
services or agriculture or something else.
The enterprise has a defined role and it has certain
properties that have been devolved upon.
It means a production that are under its control
and which it is responsible to society for the management of.
So I guess the first point is the production units of our MDIC socialist economy are not
autonomous entities existing without any connection to the rest of themselves,
the rest of the economy.
And so that's the first level of control.
Now, from that point onward, the enterprises are responsible for determining their plan.
They're responsible for figuring out for the forthcoming period what they're going to do.
And this is the importance of the planning phase as well as the execution phase.
Planning in highly authoritarian systems like the capitalist one,
people say, don't worry about planning, it's the results that matter.
It even works its way into the epistemology of the economic theorists, positivism.
We're interested in results, don't worry about planning.
Planning sort of takes place in the head of the entrepreneur
and is kind of a fleeting moment that we can hardly analyze.
But a socialist conception sees planning and execution as two interrelated phases.
They aren't separate in time, although in early phases of 20th century planning often they were.
But the planning and execution are simultaneous but never merged into one another.
They flow into one another, but they have distinct qualities.
So you have a central body which essentially at the beginning of
what I'll call the planning phase of this process says, okay, get started.
And the key thing is that the enterprise is responsible for figuring that out.
The enterprise has to figure out what it will produce, the quantity of output that it's going
to target, the assortment of that output, the quality of the output, the measures of quality,
the intended, a rough idea of the intended recipients of the output, where the demand
will come from, how the output will be distributed to either other producers or final
stores for distribution to consumers.
The enterprise will have to figure out its technology plan.
It'll have to figure out what resources it wants to devote to technical progress.
It'll have to make organizational goals and set them.
It'll have to do all these things.
And then that will require a lot of interactions with the rest of the economy
because there's a great deal of division of labor.
And therefore there will have to be exchange in the raw sense that goods will have to move
from one producing unit to another, goods and resources of all different kinds,
including human resources, will have to be shared out and allocated and coordinated.
So the enterprise, when it produces its plan, has all sorts of implicit demands upon the rest
of society, raw materials that it needs, our sources, et cetera, et cetera.
And in the next round of this iterative process, the center has to take all that and say,
does it fit or doesn't it fit?
And you can think of this momentarily in a very simple supply and demand way,
which is an element of the whole picture.
It isn't the whole picture, but it is an element.
Is the total amount of a certain grade of steel
that is being demanded by all the enterprises for the work that they intend to carry out
equal to the amount of steel that the steel industry is slated to produce?
Has slated itself to produce.
And if those two numbers don't match, then you have a coordination problem.
And so we'll try to solve that problem by allocating additional resources to steel,
by finding workarounds, or by scaling back the production plans of the other enterprises.
And so it's a vast interconnected network that has to be rendered consistent.
Now you can render it consistent in the abstract by solving a system of equations.
There are millions of equations.
And then we get into the old millions of equations critique of socialism.
It's really a critique of central planet.
The central planners just don't have the information
and they don't have the technology to do it.
They can't.
It's too big.
And so we have to let the market do it.
That's the old binary.
That's the old way of thinking.
In the iterative way of thinking, the center sends modified plans back to the enterprise
based upon the enterprise's original plans, but with certain modifications.
Now the center's right to make those modifications is part of the conception.
The enterprise, as I said, is not an autonomous, self-managing entity
apart from any constraints.
And it's an old philosophical debate.
Does freedom boil down entirely to absence of constraint?
And Marx and Engels wrote about this, Engels particularly,
in an essay which was called On Authority and several other things that one could look at.
That's really important.
So the enterprise now has a modified plan, but along the lines of its original plan
because it signals its intentions by sending that plan up.
And so now, not having to start from fresh, from scratch,
the enterprise can make the necessary modifications and send the information back up.
Now in sending information up that way in each round or each iteration,
it's a crucial concept in the whole model.
So in each iteration, the enterprise sends information up to the top.
The enterprise is revealing its actual potentials, its actual capacities to do things.
And it is using its local knowledge.
So here again, we get a concept from Hayek, right?
And Hayek used the idea of local knowledge
as a way of attacking the very concept of central planning.
But the iterative conception is a stage by stage coordination of local wills and general wills.
You know, the general interest of society is expressed in the central plan.
That's a crucial idea in this.
And in principle, and I emphasize in principle,
because there's where the reply from the libertarians could come.
You know, what you can do in principle, you can't do in practice.
But I'll say it.
I'll say it in principle.
If the enterprise is incentivized to do it, if the enterprise has the incentive,
it can put its local resources and its local knowledge unknown to the center,
its particularities into the process and therefore send back to the center
in the form of its next round of proposals precise, accurate, detailed knowledge,
not only of what exists at the local level,
but what the local level thinks could potentially exist if it mobilizes its resources,
if it mobilizes its collectives and sets itself an ambitious project
for technical transformation.
And then that goes back to the center.
So the center keeps on getting corrected, better information.
And on the basis of that, better information puts together
one more iteration of a consistent plan and sends that back down.
And the enterprise can then work with that.
If each iteration results in a plan that's less different from the preceding one
than the time before, so that the plan is progressively getting,
in other words, what the enterprise gets back is more like what it said the last time.
And the same at the level of the center.
The center is constantly getting back from all the enterprises
a picture which is closer and closer to consistency.
Then the plan is said to be converging.
And that's where the word convergence comes in.
And work is being done and has done, it was done in the 20th century,
mainly in the socialist countries, the countries where this was a practical matter,
not just something that a few academics like me batted around, you know,
but they were really working on this.
The idea is how long will convergence take
and how efficient can the convergence process be?
So that if eventually you get convergence,
what you get is a plan which is not merely a political compromise,
as it's sometimes thought of in a mixed economy kind of a situation,
but something that everyone will have been involved in producing.
And there you have the potential to draw workers into the production process.
In other words, you have people being drawn into planning, conceiving
what our work is going to accomplish, you know, and jobs become not just jobs, you know.
You get to a situation where qualitatively, the workplace experience is not just an experience
of being an instrument of someone else's will for a period of time during the day,
in exchange for which you receive wages, creating a separation between a production sphere
and a consumption sphere, they're totally separate, you know,
but you gradually get the meaningful integration of this.
And that's a goal. Now, if you want to talk about something socialism is supposed to mean,
it's supposed to mean that. It's supposed to mean that people actually begin to experience
practically control over their own lives and theoretically in the sense that they're not just
carrying out orders and so forth and fitting into a scheme of things,
and fitting into a scheme of things, which everyone has to do. I mean, that's necessary
if the whole system is going to work, but that they understand the way the scheme works
and participate in making it happen. And I'll just say that my way of interpreting the great
legacy of Marx and Engels, you know, and their followers, everyone else who has come along
since then, is that they created a view of socialism, which was not that it's something
that strikes in one moment in time, like a bolt from heaven. You know, socialism is not a
miraculous occurrence, a kind of biblical event, but it's something that has to be built. You want
to talk about the working class in power. You have to have people with sufficient education,
sufficient political consciousness, sufficient fundamental human resources, people and their
institutions. Okay. And so that's part of it. We'll get more in a moment into the actual
organization of MDIC. Yeah. And we will definitely get also to the point that you just touched upon
at the end, which would be somehow related to the question of transition and transformation,
but we will kind of push it a little bit further to the end. Before we get there. I mean, there was
a lot in there when you just described the basic outline of the model. And I would have a couple
of questions actually that might serve as a follow-up. And I mean, one of the initial
questions would be the starting point where you said, all right, we have this center, which will
come up with a like first idea of a basic plan, which will, as you just pointed out, not be a
detailed plan because the detailed planning will be what the enterprises are going to do. But what
will be the basis of the, you spoke of a grand plan that the center provides in the first place?
So what are the components that this plan is based upon? And yeah, maybe let's just leave it
there. What's the basic starting point when it comes to that? Okay. It boils down to what is
the center there for? What is the role of the center? And every question is a big question,
but that's a big question. I'll try to be as brief as possible. The first point is we want to avoid
another conceptual miscue that is often present in people's thinking about this. People associate
democracy with the lower levels, the local levels. If you have people participating in planning,
they're participating at their enterprise, at their workplace, for example. They're not
participating over there. I would like to emphasize that what I'm calling the center
is also a site for democratic participation. And I mean this in two different ways. Now,
first of all, we have to be clear. If we're talking about a society with several hundred million
people, a huge country, I mean, countries are different sizes or at least dozens of millions
of people in a country of a reasonable size. We can't talk about everybody cramming into a
room and participating in the decision by raising their hands and exercising a democratic voice in
that direct democracy sense. We can't imagine a town meeting democracy on the level of a modern
country. And no one is trying to do that. So government will be representative.
And how representation is secured, whether by vote, whether by lottery,
there is a proposal for doing it by lottery. I don't follow that line of thinking myself.
I'm not convinced about that, but it's part of the debate, and it should be,
is another question that would have to be worked out. But you have
a system of democratic control in sort of formal sense. But I'm talking about more than that. I'm
talking about a culture of critical democracy surrounding central planning. Now, modern
technology plays a role in that. We have the internet. A central planning board doesn't have
to be a distant place. It doesn't have to be somewhere far away in a capital city, which is
thousands of miles from where I live, let's say, and where people do things that I have no control over.
Needless to say, in the 20th century, in the socialist economies of the 20th century,
there were quite a few instances of situations like that. It was a highly mixed
sort of situation. But it's a process, just as I said before, in relation to
worker participation. These things are processes, but it's also a process, the participation of the
worker citizen in central planning, at the level of central planning, where a certain degree of
openness of the process itself. In other words, the evolving plan doesn't have to be something,
let's say, a certain stage of the central plan moving toward consistency along the path of
convergence. You have a central plan. You don't have to wait until it's announced.
You can read it on the internet. You can go on the central planning website
and you can see what it is. And then there will be enormous critical commentary on that.
I like to say we're talking about central planning within the sites of the bloggers
and the cartoonists and the critical process in society as a whole. This would be part of the
culture of central as well as de-central levels of planning so that
quality has got to be part of our deliberations. Now, that having been said, what does the
central planning do? Because I think what your question actually was, well, first of all, it
achieves overall coordination, but that's just part of it. Beyond that, it organizes
the discussion of planning as such. Now, you'll notice that I use the term
multi-level democratic iterative coordination. I used the word coordination at the end of that
little acronym, MDIC. I didn't call it multi-level democratic iterative planning,
and I had a reason for that. I think the word planning has a connotation that ought to be
preserved. It's planning for the future. It's forward-looking planning, and that is not just
the problem of how do we put the puzzle together now, but how do we think about the way we
want our society and eventually our societies, think of a global level, to evolve in the decades
to come? Foremost there is the question of sustainability, the question of how do we want
to evolve human activity in a way that enhances and protects the Earth's environment and the ultimate
constraint, the limitation of planetary resources available to us. I won't talk about
Star Trek and the Federation of Planets or anything. That's science fiction or speculative
fiction, so we'll leave that for the future, but right now we're talking about planet Earth and
its limited resources and so forth. A view to the future, a long time horizon, is very central to
what a central planning element within the overall planning process, not central planning,
but the central component within a dynamic iterative process. That is something that
the central planning component can contribute, a sense of the long time horizon, of the need to
protect the Earth from global warming and the need to protect the ozone layer. I can go on,
but there's a huge literature on this and this aspect is very important. Those constraints
involve studying the interaction among the activities of all of the economies and all
of the local units of all of the economies together. In principle, this cannot be done
at the local level. This is something that can't be, obviously people everywhere can have opinions
on it and should have those opinions expressed and the critical deliberative process should be
taking place. There's no question about that, but this is something that can only be worked into
meaningful long-term plans, dynamic future-oriented plans at a level which coordinates,
has a coordinating perspective for the overall, so that's one thing, major thing, that central
planning can do. There's also something that's very hard, we need to do a lot of background
on this and I'd need to do a lot of background for myself because I'm teaching it to myself
over the years, but I want to say something very controversial about prices. There is a
widespread idea that we can develop some kind of optimal prices, the best prices,
but that if we do, what we will be doing is imitating what exists in a general equilibrium
of competitive markets, that the market model is the model for what the price vector, that is
the list of all the prices, ordered list in the economy, what that should look like, what the
should look like, what the internal proportions in that list will be, is somehow
planning something that is what a spontaneous market mechanism with either socialist or
capitalist property relations regardless, a market mechanism unplanned would accomplish
and I think that's wrong. I think there are socialist production prices, if you like,
I call them social reproduction prices and work that I've done on this,
which would incorporate
actual quantitative calculations of price relations that are determined by social
relations forces, things going on in the social relations of society, such as, for example,
the ecological considerations, which no spontaneous mechanism involving interaction among
uncoordinated entities, resulting in convergence towards some kind of equilibrium prices
can possibly accomplish, it just can't do it. So one of the things a central planning board
would be responsible for is the massive problem of calculating optimal prices for purposes of
prices for purposes of calculation, income formation, decision making,
and I'm taking the point of view and it's a controversial point of view in the socialist
spectrum and some people say all of that is capitalist thinking, you shouldn't be thinking
that way at all, that you shouldn't be thinking about, first of all, you shouldn't be thinking
about optimality, you shouldn't be thinking about finding the best ways of doing anything
that's foreign to socialist thinking, I don't believe that, I believe
optimization in that sense is too important to be left to capitalist property owners,
when the workers own the resources of society and are in charge of its legacy, are in charge of
what we become, you know, that responsibility weighs heavily on the shoulders of people who
have to actually make decisions and carry it out and they have to do it the best way that can be
done in the name of all the people whose blood sweat and tears are congealed in all of those
resources that we have, you know, and the futures and whose children and grandchildren depend upon
upon that and that's a very important element of socialist leadership. So it's another thing that
a central planning board would have to do. So finally, I'll just end with a very short one,
a central planning board has got to address taking into account the entire background
democratic debate and all the information that's flowing into them all of the more near-term issues
about how society should develop, how should we arrange the relationship between production
and residential spaces? You know, it's an old question, but clearly an obviously relevant one
will continue to be, should we put factories and homes close together, save on commuting time,
you know, but there are obvious environmental pollution issues, you know, should people have
to live near sources of environmental pollution, noise pollution, environmental pollution, you know,
particulates in the air, anything like that, you know, or should we separate production locations
and residences, put them miles apart from one another, you know, then we can create nice
residential enclaves which don't have to see the factories and the stores and the offices, you know,
but we create enormous commuting problems, burdens on the transportation network. How do we work out
consumption, production, residence, transportation, how do we get all these networks,
water, power, you know, obviously the technology is improving and the trade-offs are getting better,
you know, over time, unless ecological problems, you know, tightening environmental constraints
are working in the opposite direction, but all of this has to be put together and it has to be
thought through and has to be eventually transmitted into viable five-year, ten-year,
fifteen-year, thirty-year plans, you know, which reflect the formation of a democratic consensus,
they reflect the best that technology can give us and they reflect the overall balance of resources
and these are problems that can't be solved at a local level. The local level participates in them,
but the local level can't, you can't have 10 million separate plans to address
the problem of human interaction with the environment over the next 20, 30, 40, 50 years,
can't happen. That's the central component and some of the things which it has to do.
Let's try to pick this apart a little bit at least because oftentimes when, also when reading
a text and now when hearing your elaborations, I mostly agree with the overall sentiment,
but there are like huge question marks in terms of how can this be done? So, when it comes to
the question of what kind of information would the center need to have in order to be able to
make these decisions that you think the center should do and which I would largely agree with
that this would be a problem of collective problem solving and not only a domestic one
because certain topics cannot be addressed as you clearly pointed out on a decentralized level alone,
but what is the flow of information? So, I need to come back to this question. If you state that
the center, for example, will have to calculate, I think they are called price lists, which include
social reproduction prices for broad categories of goods as I understand it, then what would be
the informational basis on top of which this would be calculated and you also explained that it would
not only be a parametric part which needs to be considered, but also a very social one that needs
to be considered and it needs to flow into these forms of calculation done by the center, but I
think it is of crucial importance first to ask, okay, what's the information, the exact information
that flows into it? If you do not have, for example, prices for consumer goods or something
like that that will serve as an indicator, for example, and then how would a meaningful
participation of the enterprises as well as the rest of society, how can this be facilitated in
order to not end up in a situation where the people that receive these quote unquote directions
from the center do not perceive it as external to themselves, but do like legitimately feel it
as something that they took part in creating. I mean, this is a very crucial element and I think
it's something that you are very much interested in that people will be able to participate in this
forming of plans, but you will have this kind of difficult question to answer how it can be done
that it is not like too many meetings problem, as you just stated, it's not possible to have like
20 million people deciding on this, but still have people left with a reasonable
way to take part in this overall coordination. So how do you approach this kind of difficult problem,
I guess? Well, I think you're asking me a question which can only be answered
historically, it can only be answered by the process of history unfolding itself. I think
you're asking the kind of the working question, which isn't going to have a simple answer with
the capital A, it's to an ordinary, we always use this word ordinary, but a rank and file
socialist and socially conscious and socialist educated working person
in an enterprise, a price list is announced and is available on the internet,
which is a very big now in price theory, you discover and there was a lot of work done
in the Soviet Union and other eastern countries about this. If the price list is a sort of a core
than an enterprise can apply for variations based upon detailed things. My general point is that
the person working in an enterprise can say, okay, these are the prices we have to work with,
we just take them, we take them parametrically, we just say these are the prices and we don't
need to be concerned with how they were constructed, but they don't have to do that,
they can understand the theory behind it, they can understand something. Now, there's obviously
on different levels, I'm not necessarily assuming that every worker in a production
plant at an enterprise is going to be able to independently solve the matrix equations,
which result in the formation of a certain set of optimal prices, but they will have come up
through the education system and the ongoing education system, the process of political and
political economic education that's part of being in a socialist enterprise, it's part of existence
in that enterprise, they will acquire some sense of the underlying principles and they will know
something about that and they will have read the equivalent of popular science articles,
which explain and transmit as much of this. One of the goals in this integration of planning and
execution as two phases of human activity, really, is to break down those barriers, to
to create the greatest possibility for rational understanding,
as the sociologist Mannheim, Karl Mannheim, would have said years ago,
rational understanding rather than merely functional understanding. Now,
we have functional understanding of a lot of things, I personally have only functional
understanding of this computer that I'm talking to you on and what you do to move around on it,
I wish I were more of a techie, but I'm not, and we struggle with that, but in all fair
phases of life, we want to understand and especially when it comes not to the technical
things, where we understand that better, but when it comes to the social side, when it comes to
actually knowing how human relations are managed and that we're part of that,
you know, we aren't just recipients of it, we have a role to play in grasping it
theoretically, not just practically. But beyond that, it's hard to say,
you know, it would depend on and it will be very different in different places and times,
you know, different, I don't think there's a simple formula that can answer that one,
it has to be answered practically. And I mean, quite a huge part of this relation,
specifically when it comes to enterprises and the center, is the question of,
I think you posed it as the question of incentives before, I mean, because at some point,
the question comes into mind that you have this iterative process and the center sends some
initial prices for broad categories and then you have the detailed planning by the enterprises
and the enterprises then are expected to submit truthful information. So, I mean, as we know,
this was a problem in the Soviet Union, so this was not truthful information because we had the
perverse incentive problem, so to speak, where the enterprises did have a incentive to kind of
hoard stuff because they knew that they would get like way too hard goals to manage and so they
were hoarding, et cetera, et cetera. So, you will have in this iterative process, the question of
what's the incentive for the enterprises to give back truthful information in order to make the
whole thing work because if they do not, then it kind of implodes, so to speak, because it won't
work and related to that is the question of what will be the reward for the given enterprise.
So, I think there's a, I think you call it, let me take a look, socialist rate of return
and as far as I understood it, this would be a kind of rate at which
enterprises would be allowed to profit, quote unquote, from the whole thing. Maybe I got that
wrong, but I would be interested in this constellation. How do the given enterprises,
how are they incentivized to do as they are told, quote unquote, plus being semi-autonomous in
being effective in actually producing the stuff and not wasting resources and then truthfully
reporting back and taking part in the iterative process? So, what's the gist to all of that?
Because it needs to be a collaboration and not an opposition.
Well, wow. These are questions which could take a long time to answer and I want to try to...
But they're central, I guess. I mean, for me, it's absolutely central to understand the model.
I'm sorry if it's too...
One thing, no, don't be sorry. Very good. One thing, I'll break it into two parts. I'm trying
to figure out which part to do first. I'm going to do the reverse order. I want to take the
incentive. That's part of your question, which is very good. So, you have this iterative process
and we're somehow assuming that the enterprise is going to get together and is going to make
truthful reports of the resources it controls and is not going to manipulate the process for
its own strategic purposes. I think that's key and there was a huge literature in the Soviet Union
about deformations that resulted from exactly that kind of behavior, which is exactly what you'd
expect at the stage of development that existed there. Then you'd hardly, from a serious materialist
point of view, expect anything else to happen. You had people... How did Marx put it? He says,
society only come into existence stamped with the birthmarks of the society from which they emerge.
This is a process. We understand that. So, how do we address strategic distorting behavior on the
part of local entities, enterprises or whatever? First, I want to mention there's a whole literature
on that, which I believe was in some ways stimulated by the economic reform in the
Soviet Union. Back in the 1960s, the Lieberman reforms, as they're called in the West, which
essentially amounted to setting up something like at least an early stage of an iterative process
that MDIC focuses on, where the enterprises were told, we will no longer be sending you detailed
plans. We will be sending you a few overall control figures. Within that, you need to work out
the detailed plans. You need to do a complete accounting for your resources and
a specification of how you're going to change methods of production and what you're going to
do. Was that successful or unsuccessful? It's a long, complicated story. I want to skip over it,
but it gave rise to the incentive design literature, which a number of European scholars...
There was a large French component, an economist by the name of Tirol,
and a number of Americans also participated in that. How can you devise truth-telling
incentive mechanisms? Essentially, I have an answer. I'm not going to try to
elaborate it too much, because we don't even have visuals. We only have sound,
and even to the extent that I understand it, which is that I've been able to take it.
I think in the usual thinking about this, there's another binary, another one of these
either-or kind of situations. In this case, the either-or is that people say,
some mathematical economists say, either you assume that people are socially motivated and
have high moral values and will simply act in the public interest because that's the kind of people
they are. You assume glorious people out of whom you will build a glorious society, or you have
to give up. Those are the two alternatives. The only kind of incentives you can possibly
have that make sense are market incentives where people are actually made to suffer for bad
decisions. If we don't produce efficiently, the business will go out of existence and the workers
will be fired and so forth and so on. That's control. You can't do it anyway. You can't provide
people with an incentive to act in the social interest. You don't have to provide them with
an incentive to act in their personal interest. That's human nature. They'll do that by themselves.
Is there an answer to that? I believe there is, and it resides in something I call,
that's a complicated phrase, but I'll give it to you because then I'll be able to refer to it.
The collective morale function. Let me set an environment to explain this. There's an enterprise
and the enterprise is required to form a plan. The enterprise personnel sit around a table,
the enterprise director and some of his technical people and some other people,
representatives of each of the departments of the enterprise, some kind of a little group that,
as best as possible under now given circumstances, represents the enterprise. What should we do?
The enterprise, I'll just use a term, say the enterprise director
has a problem. Let's say he's in charge of this meeting. He sets the agenda.
He or she can set a target and say, this is what we're going to achieve. I'll put a number on it,
a target of 100. We're going to set a target of 100. The question is, is that the best the enterprise
can do? In order to find that out, this director is going to have to consult the people in the
enterprise. He's going to have to say, okay, people, do you want to roll up your sleeves
and really get to work? Do we want to really make a run at transforming ourselves into something a
little bit different from what we've been and really improve the way we work? This can mean
the level of output. It can mean many other things as well. I'll get to that part. That's
the second part. Are we really going to do this? Are we going to push ourselves to the practical
limit? If we do, then let's say that's 100. Now, if we do a little less than that, it's 95, 96.
If we do more, it's 103, 104, 105, that kind of thing. That's an index number
that we can use to measure our level of performance. Now, here's the collective
morale function. It says that when you have an enterprise in a society that is technologically
and educationally and socialistically advanced, we have a society of very intelligent, committed,
working people. We are not talking about people who trudge unwillingly into work every morning
and do what they're told, take a list from their supervisor, pay you to do this, this, and this,
and you carry out those tasks, go home, buy groceries with your wages, and come back the
next day. We're beyond that. We have a society where in order to achieve something, you really
have to have people motivated to do it. People really have to be involved. You have to bring
your teams on board, so to speak. Now, suppose the enterprise director is a very ambitious person
and wants to make a real good impression on his or her superiors,
and says, the information coming from all my colleagues is that our best level of achievement
is 100. I'm going to push for 103. Let's see if we can get it up to 103. This is the kind of person
who's really a rouser, a very, very high taught planning kind of a person, a person who is going
to try to push the enterprise. Let's suppose the actual effect of that has a demoralizing component
to it. Let's suppose people are going to sigh and say, okay, well, I guess we can put in some overtime
and I guess we can rework all these procedures that we have and I guess we can recalculate
everything. We can go over everything, but it's really impinging on other areas of life
for your staff, for the people around you. It's tough. This is not an easy thing to do.
What the collective morale function says is that as a result of pushing beyond 100
and calling for 103, what you'll only get is 102. In other words, you'll get people to do a little
more, but various forms of conscious and even unconscious resistance will develop.
What you will get, I need you to imagine a sort of a line. I realize I can't put anything on a
chalkboard. A horizontal line at a level of 100 and then a curve which touches that line at 100.
It's below the line. It touches at 100 and falls off in either direction. It's like a
downward-facing parabola. It just rises to 100 at a certain point at 100 and then falls off.
You see? If you push too far in the upward direction, you will get an increase,
but you won't get the increase you push for. Similarly, and this is where the other side is,
suppose you get an enterprise director who wants to game the system and wants to go for less than
100. This is the concealing reserves case, which was talked about in the old Soviet literature,
where an enterprise director would have an incentive to try to achieve a plan which is
less than 100. In the iterative MDIC context, he would want to announce a plan less than 100
and wants to announce a plan of 97, let's say. Once again, what's going to happen is that
that is also going to be demoralizing because people are saying, this enterprise director
is not asking us to do what we really can do, as much as we really can do. This enterprise director
is asking us to do less than that. Maybe we'll take a cue from that and we'll just cut back a
little bit more. Instead of 97, you would get 96. Again, part of the collective morale function.
In other words, the central idea is that under modern conditions,
moral matters. For morale to be invoked, for a collective to achieve a certain high level of
functioning in its own terms, it has to know that it's doing the best it can do. But the best
doesn't mean the most. It doesn't mean the farthest out along that line, as we can possibly go. What
we need to do is we need to get it... In other words, the point of a collective morale function,
if it exists, is that the actual need to motivate your collective, the actual need to put people
into motion, to make things happen well, and to get people to reveal their own reserves and to
come forward with suggestions and interventions and activities. The way to accomplish that is
to be truthful. And if you're not truthful, the forces around you will undermine you
to some degree. Now that idea, if it's true, if I can justify it,
and if anybody ever pays any attention to it, there will be many attacks against it,
it'll be contested. And in a certain sense, from my point of view, it should be, because if it isn't
solid, it won't hold, is the essential guarantee of the MDIC system. In other words, the center
can count on the enterprise to do approximately the best it can and therefore to send good
information up and enhance its contribution to the overall planning process. Because if it doesn't do
that, its own moral energy will be sacked, its own moral energy will be undermined.
And to the extent that that's true, it's not, many people may interpret this as
saying that you're relying on the goodwill or the high moral fiber of individuals,
the way the old critique of decentralized planning had it. But I don't think that's what I'm doing.
I hope that's not what I'm doing. I hope what I'm saying is that the enterprise, which means the
people themselves, I speak of the director, but he's speaking for everybody knows this,
everybody sitting around that table knows what the situation is. If we don't work ourselves to
our reasonable best level, and if we don't participate in the planning process in a
principled way, not in a strategic undermining way, then we're not going to feel good about
ourselves. And if we don't feel good about ourselves, we won't do the work that we need
to do. We will be undermining our own work. Here it is in a single folksy expression,
the last thing I'll say, okay, get another question from you. If it's worth doing,
it's worth doing well. And you hear workers say that. There are even writers who talk about the
invisible heart. That term has been used in a number of different ways. But my point is that
the ultimate blue, which holds so-called market system together, is that there's an underlying
moral foundation to incentives, which can't be gotten away from. And I'm relying on it here as
well. Well, I mean, I would say it's based on a lot of assumptions for sure. But it's based on
assumptions that I personally kind of favor, I would say, because at the end, it's not about
like relatively dumb economic incentivation, which I always think of not really holding up.
Because if I look at myself, for example, I always found being forced to earn money for living
is like one of the biggest obstacles for me in trying to pursue things that I'm good at,
actually. So I personally like this approach, that it's not so much about economic incentives.
I'm not so sure about the morality part, to be honest. But I think it refers back to
the question of how autonomous the enterprises are actually, how autonomous they can feel in terms of
the, I have to use the phrase, self-management of the enterprise. I mean, at the beginning of
our conversation, you refer to it as something that is not a given within your model. And I
would say we do come back to this right now, because it's part of the question of incentivation
that is not based on economic incentivation. How much do I legitimately feel involved in the way
the given enterprise is being run on the level of the enterprise? And then how much do I legitimately
feel being involved in the overall plan that gives me the like broad categories, broad directions of
what I am supposed to do. So I would say that given this constellation that you just described,
the question of, at least the perception of some form of autonomy within the workplace
comes back into the picture as a form of motivation. So this is something that I might add at this
point. And then I wanted to ask something, because I, when trying to picture your model,
never really got to the point of understanding it correctly because I will just say it as directly
as I can, but is there profit? Does a given enterprise have the possibility to, for example,
pay a higher remuneration depending on how good they have done their job? I'll be as stupidly
obvious and blunt about it as I can. Is there something, it doesn't have to be like money,
it can also be like more leisure time or anything as such. Because if there would be something like
that, some form of indirect economic incentive, then it would really, really, really alter the
whole picture, I would say. And it would also alter the picture in terms of if there is some
form of competition between the enterprises. So this would introduce a very different level
to the whole thing. So maybe you can help me kind of get a better picture of the whole thing.
Wow, we're covering everything in one session. This is amazing. We have to have a whole course.
It's good. I don't know whether I could, even this question, I'm trying, I didn't take notes,
I'm trying to remember everything. But yeah, okay. One aspect of your question is the,
you speak of profit. Now, let's assume for our discussion that we don't mean capitalist profit,
we don't mean surplus value extracted, you know, anything like that. But we're talking
about a socialist enterprise. The enterprise is owned by the workers of the country as a whole,
let's say. But it's also the workers who are actually at the enterprise and participate in
it have a major role, you know, and their interests have to be represented. One aspect of
your question is differentiation of income. Should people be rewarded for more product or for better
work? You know, should people be rewarded? So we can boil that down to saying,
start by asking the larger question, should the enterprise be rewarded? Should there be a stream
of income to the enterprise? We can even call it profit as long as we understand that the word
profit is one of those tricky words that means different things in different contexts. We know
that. So we'll just use it. Should the enterprise receive a profit based upon an evaluation of its
work? So first of all, the question is, how do you evaluate enterprise performance? How do you measure
it? How do you measure how well or how poorly an enterprise is doing? And the second question is,
once we have that thing, once we have that reward, I mean, sorry, let me start this sentence again,
once we have that measure of enterprise performance, so I can say of this particular
enterprise, and it can say of itself, well, we did this well, or not so well, or whatever,
you know, whatever level it is. Now based on that, and the reward we receive as a result,
how should that reward be differentiated and broken up into the rewards of individual members
of the enterprise? How should it be reflected in individual wages? And how should those,
what I'll use the standard term for them, material incentives be harmonized with or related to
moral incentives, the kinds of incentives that are given in the form of collective appreciation,
you know, trophies, banners, but not in a simplistic, cynical sense, but things that might
could at least be meaningful, they could at least have meaning for people. So come back to
the first question, how do we measure what an enterprise does? In the old days, earliest
experiments in socialist planning, of course, it was simple, the more the better. You know,
how did you measure the output of the work of a steel mill? How much steel it produced,
you know, millions of tons of steel, that was the measure, you know, and any other industry
the same way. Clearly, that's not sufficient. You have to measure not only what is being done,
but how efficiently it's being done, whether targets are being met for variety of output
and for quality of output, many different things. All of that boils down into a single measure,
a rate of return. Okay. Now, it's not a rate of return in a sense of a property income to
ownership of the means of production. The society as a whole indivisibly owns the means of production.
This is not a market socialist model. The enterprise does not own its own means of production.
But we're talking about a rate of return in a sense that enables us to evaluate how well
are the resources entrusted to us being used? And that's important, as I said before, you know,
that's something that socialists need to be concerned with. And you need to convince
the workers that we will, that we presume to lead in political struggles and eventually
revolutionary struggles, you know, that we will do that. You know, people understand that.
People say, we don't want clowns running the society who don't care about the resources that
represent generations of our effort and our collective labor, you know, to have created
these things. We want these things to be well managed. And that means being concerned with
rates of return. So what kind of rate of return? Well, not the capitalist one. Capitalist rate of
return is profits divided by capital. Right? Socialist rate of return, and this is an argument
I'm taking from a whole literature around what used to be called full income prices,
is not profit, but the entire net income.
In other words, wages plus profit divided by the value of means of production.
I won't use the word capital in this context. So that in standard macroeconomic notation,
it would be Y over K, not P over K. It's not profit divided by K as a symbol for the means
of production, for the value of that, the resources being deployed to create this result.
But the entire income, the wages, in other words, what in conventional capitalist accounting are
wages and profits, all of that is returns to us as a whole, whether individually or collectively,
doesn't matter. So that's one thing about what rate of return do we use. And that rate of return,
if you analyze it, think about it, has all sorts of efficiencies taken care of within it. It's like
an aggregation of attending to levels of productivity, saving of raw materials,
efficient technical changes, which use the capital stocks in the most efficient way,
never mind what the details of that. But all of those kinds of decisions,
if taken properly, would result in a higher rate of return.
So that's one. Let me just very quickly, then I'll get back, continue with another question.
The other half of it is that in a socialist context, the measure of enterprise performance
can very well have a whole additional component to it, something totally different. And this would
be a component that's based upon ratings of the enterprise by stakeholders. And here I'm adopting
some of the thinking of Pat Devine, whom you've interviewed, you've had him present his ideas
directly. But I think that's a contribution to this. Stakeholders, which can be the workers
in the enterprise, but they can also be the surrounding community of the enterprise. They
can be people who are interested in and qualified to examine the enterprise's work in relation to
ecology goals, sustainability and so forth, and emissions and so forth.
Industry representatives, people who vote essentially on how well the enterprise
relates to other enterprises in the industry. Soviet Union, for example, they used to have
programs where an advanced enterprise would take a lagging enterprise under its wing
and form mentorship relationships, where they would work on the technical skills of the workers
in the lagging enterprise and try to eliminate deficiencies. And finally, very importantly,
I would say, this is a socialist society and we're interested in building a solidary and
working class. We're interested in overcoming all existing vestiges of racism, misogyny,
exclusive nationalism, nationalisms, all of these perverse ideologies that keep us from
unifying fully and developing our potential. How well is the enterprise addressing that?
How well is the enterprise addressing gender relations within the plant and helping to
address problems there and advance equality in that sense?
And all of those things, those various evaluations would be supplied to a component of the formula.
In other words, it would just be good things to do, but this would be how you actually
put it right into the formula, which determines the measure of enterprise
performance, which in turn determines the reward that the enterprise receives.
Okay, so there would be the possibility of a reward in terms of
money, so to speak, depending on basic performance and social indicators, I think you call that.
Not money as such, but money as representing real income, real purchasing power,
a material incentive. Yeah, but there is money in your model, isn't it?
Well, yes, in the sense that it's implicit, it's being assumed. I don't build equations involving
a quantity of money. I don't worry about the velocity of circulation or issues in monetary
theory, but yes, I am assuming that for a reasonable period of time in an early stage
of development of mature socialism or MDIC socialism, some form of monetary unit would
be used as monetary units were used in the planned economies of Eastern Europe and the
Soviet Union, or we could speak of the currencies in place in capitalist countries since today.
Here, there's a lot of confusion on the left. I think a lot of people on the left go immediately
to a very utopian view. We should abolish money. I think what you want to abolish is what social
relations get carried in monetary form in a capitalist society, and not necessarily even
abolish those, but eliminate them as the possibility arises. It's one thing to say,
we're going to abolish something. It is stroke. It's another thing to say, we've reached a level
of development where this can now be attenuated or these aspects of money can wither away.
But Marx was very clear on this. He said, money is one of the last forms of coercion.
You know, and in order to eliminate it, development through a lower phase of communism
is necessary before that ultimate coercion of human beings by other human beings in the sense
of their circumstances surrounding them, like a monetary constraint on consumption, the connection
between labor and income. You know, you can say, let's just get rid of it right now. Let's just
throw it away. But if the foundations have not been laid for that, if the prerequisites have
not been established, the results could be disastrous. And we'll take you farther away
from the goal of reaching a society where those constraints on human activity, including labor,
would no longer be binding constraints, increasingly wither away, become attenuated.
We will get there, I guess, in more or less one of the last questions, which will be on transition.
But before that, I would very much be interested in your opinion on markets, because I think you
have a distinction or not, I think, but I know you have a distinction between a core sector
and something that you call, I think, the informal sector. And I never really got my head around
that. And it really reminded me of the, I think, the Chinese dual track system, the experiments
around that, because I had a very interesting guest on Isabella M. Weber, who wrote about how
China escaped shock therapy. And how they did it was through forms of cautious experimentation
with something they called the dual track system. And I felt very much reminded of these
experiments when I read about this distinction between a core sector and a sector that is
forming around that within your model, which will, at least it sounded to me, Bill, will be
some form of mild market socialism-like sector. But I think you would disagree with that. But I
would certainly be interested in your opinion. Maybe you could explain to us what the core
sector is, and what the informal sector is, and how both relate to markets.
Okay. Well, the core sector is the MDIC economy, you know, multi-level democratic
iterative coordination. And it's not a market economy, you know. Prices are planned. Now they
may be planned with lots of local input, but they are eventually centrally planned. The central
component within MDIC is constantly forming and perfecting a system of prices which takes
regular account of the natural environment, the future, the actual social nature of the
productive resources which shape rates of return. It's hard to explain without presuming some
economics, you know, in the audience. And here we have no presumptions. We have a whole
varied audience of people listening. But the connection between profit rates and prices,
you know, and the whole price structure depends intimately upon that. And the idea that
a general rate of return needs to form, which also I believe is true of an MDIC economy. But
I'm digressing. Let me try to stick onto your question. That's the MDIC economy. It is not a
market economy. So it's not a model of market socialism. And neither is it simply a state
central planned economy. This is important because in the non-socialist literature and
anti-socialist literature, socialism and state enterprise are equated. They practically mean
the same thing, you know, that when you talk about socialism, what you mean is the government will
make all the decisions and will decide everything. And we're not talking about government. To have an
MDIC economy, it would have to be within what you could call the state sector. It is governmental,
but governmental itself does not define it. There would be plenty of state enterprises
that are not part of the multi-level democratic iterative coordination system. It's a real
discipline. You have to be part of an everlasting, always existing, a continual, a system of
iterative coordination, a system of up-down and not just talking to each other all the time,
but regular stages of perfection of plans, which are to be implemented in the near future,
just while you are already implementing the existing ones. Implementation and planning are
interrelated and continual processes. People are at different stages of both
at all times. That's the multi-level planning system, and it has a distinct and necessary
central component to it, unlike models like Robin Hanel's and Mike Albert's paracon,
participatory economy, which says the central has got to be excluded because it's the source of
necessary, unavoidable evils, so we've got to have an entirely decentralized system.
There are many other variations on the model which could be described.
Now, the informal sector,
well, on the one hand, it doesn't really play a role in the model of the MDIC system. You can
form that model and you can think abstractly of a socialist economy which functions that way,
which functions as a multi-level democratic iterative coordination system. In the real world,
well, every example of a society that we know of, from the Asian countries, China, Vietnam,
to the Eastern European ones from earlier, they've gone in a different direction now,
now, temporarily, I hope, and the Soviet Union no longer exists. You have examples of societies,
even the society, and Cuba, even the socialist economies that have existed in real historical
situations, even the ones that have been the most pure, non-informal, have had huge informal sectors.
The Soviet Union had the collective farm sector. It had a kind of an informal services
sector because they always had difficulty integrating services into the planning
mechanism, so people used their skills to fill in the vacuums. The Soviet economy,
annoyingly, did not solve the problem of repair services for material goods that they were
producing. You could buy a TV by the late 1950s, 60s, but you couldn't get it repaired,
or most annoyingly, washing machine, so people with those skills, with the necessary skills,
set themselves up as informal suppliers of these services, and that was part of their informal
economy. There were others, as well, that one could go into, but of course, you're going to
have that. That's going to be part of the real-life process. The crucial thing is that
just because you're in the public sector doesn't mean you're in the core economy.
I regard the public sector also, if it's a traditional public sector, as may have existed
centuries earlier, or even millennia earlier, that doesn't make you socialist. It becomes socialist
when the democratic planning process becomes established. That happens by stages. It doesn't
happen all at once. This perfectly leads to the question of transition, because the whole
model, as I understood it, as I read it, with all these elements that I sometimes intuitively
would kind of tend to want to reject, but I absolutely understand that the whole model
is formed around an idea of process, and that we need to actually keep in mind the imperfections
and hybridity of actually existing conditions as we find them and as we are living within them.
I would be interested, maybe you can just sketch this idea of a model as process or a model as
transition, maybe, because this was really an interesting read for me when engaging with the
model, maybe the tendency within me might be too strong to kind of skip a stage or something like
that, and you would maybe argue if I would lay out my ideas in terms of, okay, there should not be
any form of wage labor relation or any connection between labor and pay and stuff like that, and you
would possibly answer me, well, Jan, this is not the world we're living in right now. You should
keep in mind that people are socialized within these forms of relations, and we should consider
that when developing our models, and I can absolutely see that you do consider this. So
maybe to make it into a question, how would we go about this idea of transition, like in the sense
of how could we transition to a multi-level democratic iterative coordination, and how do
you think about the transition within the model and the maturing within the model? Because this
seemed to be something that is very much on all of the groundings that you think about,
that there is a process of maturing and that we should keep this in mind. Maybe you could just
give your thoughts on that, because I think it's really important, actually.
Oh, well, okay. First of all, your speculative utopian projection of why do people have to
receive wages at all is very good. It's very smart. We should never forget that. I think what you're
doing with that is you're saying we can be in what Marx would have called the lower phase
of a communist society, and we could be dealing with the realities of that, and the fact that
the higher phase cannot be just jumped into immediately. We can't immediately go to what
we later on started to call full communism. Okay, let's assume that's true, but that doesn't
mean we can't think about it and keep thinking about it constantly in our minds.
If you were in a precursor stage of socialist development, let's suppose you had made
significant progress at removing the capitalist class from its residual power, from its ability.
It's lost the state in a political revolution, let's say, but we're in a kind of a very early
socialist environment where capitalist principles out in the real world are still simmering below
the surface and could reemerge. We have a mixed economy, or China. We have a strong state sector.
We have a socialist mandate at some level, at least socialist in the sense of an understood
politically supplied central
state enterprises providing some forms of stability and security for working people.
But we also have a spontaneous market system, and we don't stamp it out. Our goal isn't to
stamp that out any more than in the Soviet Union. They want to stamp out the television
repair guy who plays a very important role. He fills a need, but of course that can obviously
could have negative potentials for income distribution and stratification
farther down the road. We keep an eye on it. There we have our informal economy.
What we're trying to do is, through stages, gradually building up to the point where
rather than allowing a private market sector to coalesce into a small capitalist sector and then
a not so small capitalist sector, and recreate class divisions of the sort which could undermine
the material base for our political project overall. It could overturn us. We don't want that,
but we also understand that by trying to stamp them out at a stage before we have the kind of
flexible and systematic and sophisticated planning mechanism,
I'll use my term, MDIC kind, that could absorb them. What we want to do is we want to create
the conditions where those kinds of spontaneous entities with their negative potentials
increasingly can cease to exist because we have the opportunity to create alternatives to them.
That means creating a really good, well-functioning, flexible MDIC system.
One of the things that we can do politically is attempt to support that MDIC system
in the context of a precursor economy, not now thinking about the MDIC model as being
dominant, but thinking of it as just something we're attempting to start to build.
There are many tricky problems here, most of which I assume I have never even thought through,
or we haven't even begun to think about this stuff.
You can't set up an MDIC system on a tiny little scale. You can't create a tiny little pilot
project within a state sector. The state sector and its overall characteristics, it's got some
stabilizing characteristics to it and probably even some economic advantages. It has
economies of scale that you can draw upon for society as a whole, but it also creates
huge bureaucracies which have their own little centers of power that begin to develop, and it
creates bad politics internally within it. This is part of what we're dealing with, and I'd love
to be able to say, well, we could just develop a tiny little socialist planning sector, democratic
planning in this environment, and it would gradually grow. I came up with an idea a few
years ago, totally controversial, and many people hate it, but that's okay,
that you could actually have a bicameral legislature. Of course, the problem here
is how would you get to a bicameral legislature if you didn't have the political will to achieve
this? If you had the political will, you might not need it in the first place, so I'm not sure
whether this really makes sense, but it's the way my mind is heading. You would have a popular
assembly which would be elected by direct vote of the population. It would be a real,
a democratically, talking about the electoral form, and you'd also have another house
of the parliament, which would be a core economy council, and to elect representatives to the core
economy council, you have to work in a core economy enterprise. You have to be part of the core,
so if you are a core economy council enterprise member, you vote for the core economy council,
but you also vote as a citizen for the popular assembly. Other people who work in the private
sector or also the informal economy just vote for the popular assembly.
In a society where electoral traditions are very strong, if you're in Western Europe, the United
States, in these kinds of society, some kind of a bicameral legislature of that kind, existing
temporarily might be a useful way to go, because it provides an additional incentive
so that we're an enterprise, and let's say we're privately owned, or maybe we're a state enterprise,
but not part of the core economy, and we have meetings, and it can be pretty contentious
meetings, it can be difficult meetings, at which certain people say, look, we should be part of the
core economy, we should apply for membership in the core economy, we should become an enterprise
that's part of this iterative planning, democratic iterative planning mechanism.
Many advantages to it. Now, in addition to just the economic advantages of
the resources that you have available, and you might have expertise of the central planning
folks can come and work, be in residence with you, help you develop your computer systems,
connect you to the intranets and internets that run the whole thing on the basis of
internet doesn't run it, but it's a tool for running it, and participation in some of the
deliberations and the meetings of sub bodies within the planning system, you have a lot of
connections, but in addition, you can vote for the core economy council, you get to vote twice.
It's just an idea, it's just an idea, I don't know.
You could get into a low level equilibrium trap kind of a situation, you could get into a
situation where the resources to push you past that threshold where the core economy
begins to be able to become dominant simply by demonstrating its superiority,
by demonstrating its superiority as a mechanism for ensuring democracy, human development,
the whole thing. So the core economy isn't quite strong enough to do that, and you have a private
market sector with various divisions within it, you may have a cooperative sector, and you may
have a state sector, which is not part of the core economy, but which exerts a strong political
influence on the society, and people who operate within that, the mandarins,
they like their power, they like being where they are, they also recognize that their power
is constrained because of the existence of these other forces, it's kind of like a political
stalemate, and how do you move beyond that stalemate and get to the point where the core economy can
develop? But I'll finish by saying the core economy in principle should be able to pick up
those informal sectors, it should be able to absorb them. There's no reason, for example,
why there can't be consumer good repair collectives that form and that are superior
to individuals working by themselves and in ignorance of who their potential market is
and where people can't find them, and I can give you plenty examples of where spontaneous
market mechanisms produce non-optimal results, even in the narrowest terms of
the most efficient way to accomplish some task, so you can do much better by forming collectives
and operating as a non-core collective subject to rules, I mean there are going to be rules
regarding wages, regarding health and safety, all of that is going to be there, and eventually
applying for membership in the core economy, which you could obviously do, and there's no
reason why the MDI system couldn't incorporate everything that we now think of as agriculture,
services and so forth and so on. There's one more issue which I could talk about,
but I won't, I'll stop, and that's entrepreneurial labor. What do we do
about entrepreneurs and innovation? Maybe we'll do it another time.
Well, I mean we already covered a lot of ground, and before we finish up, I just wanted to
give you the possibility and also simply hear about it. I mean the science and society special
issues on envisioning socialism, they have been such an important driver of the debate.
Yes, I could see the new issue, nice, very nice. I mean the audience won't be able to see it, but
it's out right now in April, so go and get it. I mean they have been such a huge
driver and important driver of the debate, and I mean not everybody will know about the project,
so could you maybe explain what envisioning socialism is to our audience, and maybe also
give an idea of what it meant to try to push this debate all over these, I mean now 30 years,
and also specifically during a period which was termed the end of history, quote unquote.
I mean the first issue came out in 1992. This was peak end of history, so yeah.
Well, not too much I can say. People should go to the science and society website,
which is just scienceandsocietyand.com, and there's a link for Guilford Press,
which is our publisher, where you can order the issue or subscribe to the journal. I'd love to
have you do that. First, I need to clarify some things. The journal, Science and Society,
does not necessarily endorse, people have different views on it, you know, obviously everyone
at Science and Society thinks it's a worthwhile project, but there's a variety of different
positions and takes on it, and among the participants in a particular issue, this is the
fourth issue in the project that I'm personally looking at. I'm sorry I can't show it to
the listeners to this podcast, but authors range from a major Chinese contributor, Enfu Cheng,
Pat Devine, Robin Hanel, their names have been mentioned before as being people who have
participated in previous Science and Society special issues, but a number of other, I won't
name everybody who's here, the guest editors of this issue are Al Campbell and myself,
and I also ought to emphasize that I do not speak for that group of people as a collective,
there's a lot of different views, a lot of controversy on how to think about all of this,
but the one thing I think most people would agree upon is that we do have to think about it,
it's very, very crucial, and even those of us who are thinking about systematic socialism who go
beyond the level that people for whom socialism is just human goodwill and eliminating the gross
inequality and crises of contemporary societies, moving beyond that and moving to something that
fulfills our human potential more than we have in the past, and who haven't gotten beyond that,
who aren't ready to embrace any concept of systemic socialism of any kind,
I think we play a very essential role for being an attractive potential for
a much wider community that could play a very significant political role and a necessary
political role in the society of the present, so I urge everyone to be part of that conversation,
whether through our journal or through all other media, including podcasts and
Zoom conferences and everything else that we try to do.
Absolutely, so let's all get engaged with systemic socialism, or at least everybody who's interested,
it's desperately needed. There's a last question that I ask all of my guests and that is,
if you think about the future, what makes you joyful?
I'd have to say I'm just joyful about the possibilities.
We're in a period of time when it's not always easy to be joyful.
I won't go into details, everybody knows what's happening in the world and why.
Our joy might be compressed a little bit by dwelling on that too much,
but we have the ability, we have the potential to get beyond that, and
even if you're not sure it's true or not, but you know that other people do think that it's true,
that systemic socialism in some sense, socialism as more than just a set of shared values,
which is important, but socialism in the sense of an actual alternative to the way things are done.
One of the things that Al and I, the co-editors of the special issue
of Science and Society, insisted on as part of this is that we simply have to get
further. I won't say beyond, I'll say further than. The level of thinking which says,
why don't we just all treat ourselves well? Why don't we just apply the golden rule?
If socialism is going to be a serious contender and is going to be the foundation for real
oppositional politics in today's world, socialists are going to have to be able to answer the question,
how would you do things differently? How would you actually make things work?
And I think an awful lot of people, be honest with yourself, maybe you're in that category,
will say we love the values that are, otherwise we wouldn't be listening to this podcast, you know,
we love, you guys are, you have a good vision of humanity in place, but do you really know how to
get things done? Can you really get things done the way the financial institutions and the
stock markets and the corporate bureaucracies, you know, that run this world for a capitalist
entity that is in charge of it? Can you accomplish that, what they do, let alone do it better than
they do it? And if you think honestly, you may say, well, I'm not sure I have an answer to that.
Well, that's what we're looking for, we're looking for answers to those questions,
and we won't find them all at once, we won't find some grand magnificent answer,
which answers every aspect of every question, won't happen, it'll be by process, and people
will be entering into that with partial solutions, which we can't even imagine what they are right
now, we don't know, because that's the democratic part of the total picture, you know, we need those
inputs, even though we don't yet know what they are, because they will help us to form continuing,
not complete answers, but continuing answers to the questions of how we can get on with developing
everything that human beings are capable of being. And that's, that's, in simple terms,
what the project is all about. Awesome. David, thank you so much for taking the time and being
part of future histories. All right. So long.
That was our show for today. Thanks a lot for listening. If you want to support future histories,
you can do so on Patreon. For this visit patreon.com slash future histories, or you can simply tell a
friend that you liked the show and that he, she or they might like it as well. Thanks a lot and
hear you in two weeks.