Welcome to Future Histories. My name is Jan Gross and it is my great pleasure to
welcome Trevor Schultz in today's episode. Trevor is the author of
Uber worked and underpaid how workers are disrupting the digital economy and
editor of multiple books such as hours to hack and to own platform
cooperativism a new vision for the future of work and a fairer internet. He
is professor at the New School in New York and founding director of the
platform cooperativism consortium and the Institute for the Cooperative
Digital Economy both of them at the New School as well. In general Trevor is
highly involved in the platform cooperativism movement which will be at
the center of our conversation today. Before we start I would like to thank
Bernhard, Wilfried and Fabian for their kind donations and I would like to
welcome Anna as a patreon of future histories. Thank you so much for your
support. If you as well would like to support future histories then please do
so. This could be as you just heard through a donation or monthly support on
patreon but it also could be in the form of simply telling a friend about the
show or sharing the content through your favorite channels of sharing content. So
thank you very much it's highly appreciated and now please enjoy today's
episode with Trevor Schultz on platform cooperativism.
Welcome Trevor. Hello thanks for having me. It's a pleasure. Trevor let's start
with the definition. What is a platform cooperative? Right so there I guess this
is sort of a three-part question right so I mean you know like people need to
understand what cooperatives are in the first place so here this is I'm mostly
focusing on two types of cooperatives there are many more mostly interested in
worker cooperatives where the company is owned by the workers that all have an
equal say in the operation so it's based on the principle of one worker one vote
and so it's democratic ownership right and then the second type of cooperative
that I think is most relevant to the digital economy and a good example of a
platform cooperative is multi-stakeholder cooperatives so this means that there you
don't have this wall around a small number of members who all like benefit from this
this cooperative form right by having higher wages or by having
secure place to work and by having a voice in the workplace which is like really quite rare
when you think about it globally and when you think about how this idea of participatory
democracy has propagated like across countries right so who claim this concept right as as
something that is very central to their aspiration but in the workplace where most people spend like
most of their day that is like quite absent right and most workplaces so quite fascinating
so that's cooperative so with a focus on multi-stakeholder cooperatives and worker
corps multi-stakeholder cooperatives including also people from the community that are so not
just a small number of the members but it can also have classes within the cooperative that are
that are you know like in the community that are other you know other than the workers
you know so and that breaks with this idea that cooperatives can only benefit a small number of
members and there are you know tens of thousands of examples of that in italy with social
cooperatives and i mean really all over the world yeah so and so that's a cooperative then
a platform cooperative is really like a digital platform now we also think about you know web
three like with protocols and other technologies but a company for whom the digital operation is
central number one so it's not you know a cooperative with a website or so right so
like really where the that's at the heart of their operation as a business and they followed the
cooperative principles that were you know designed by the international cooperative alliance
so essentially those yeah two two characteristics and could you give us an example of a platform
cooperative maybe yeah absolutely so there's a you know wonderful project and in europe it's called
uh it's called smart which is in nine european countries and it's focused on freelancers and
it's makes this very interesting move of building on this sort of legal a legal hack you might call
it to transform freelancers so to speak into employees so that means basically they give
freelancers employee status by making them employees of the cooperative and thereby affording
them all the benefit under labor law that are significant in some countries not so significant
in others so it really depends but including things like unemployment right and
you know it's i mean labor law is in most countries designed mostly for employees and
not for freelancers so freelancers do are not protected right and this move to make them
employees essentially grants them that right so that's smart they're doing that specific to
each country like so in italy and spain and germany mostly in belgium that's where most
members are and also in france and they have 35 000 members they you know wrote over 100 000
contracts and have like a revenue of 200 million euros a year so quite a significant operation
they have co-working spaces for freelancers and so they are let's say an opera singer and
you get engaged by like an opera house or so you basically the the co-op the platform co-op
acts as your employer and the opera house essentially interacts with the co-op not with
the freelancer so the the money then goes to to smart and smart pays the freelancer a salary
so this has the advantage that often freelancers suffer from not being paid on time and the
in smart's case they pay seven days after the work is performed no matter if that
organization has paid or not so and as smart is quite significantly large
nobody really dares to not pay because they would be added to a blacklist right which then no
freelancer would work with them so it's it takes the anxiety out of freelancing too
interesting model and when you were talking about the definition of platform cooperatives
you mentioned multi-stakeholder cooperatives and you said that there are different you said classes
within the multi-stakeholder cooperative what is the kind of representation that these classes are
involved with because i mean this might be a form of ownership a part of ownership or it might be
something different like really taking part within the the the structures that form the
the given cooperative so are there different models of representation as well
yeah that's a good question so one platform co-op that is in the process of converting from a worker
from an italian worker co-op of tech workers to a multi-stakeholder platform co-op is fair bnb
which as the name suggests right offers short-term rental and 50 percent of the revenues
go to local communities so for projects that the community can decide on such as whatever you know
building a playground or you know whatever the community wants so that so that the
the money the revenue that is generated is not simply going to silicon valley right as it does
with the competitor but stays in that community so the way they are doing this is quite obvious
right so this is where the hosts of course would be a class right and and then potentially the
guests as well and then what you point to is a complicated question which is really not so easy
to answer because it really differs from from co-op to co-op so like how you know do they are
for example also non-voting classes right so that you have actually you know stakeholders that
you know they are let's say really involved with the company but they but they don't have voting
rights right that also exists so it's it's it's complicated as i can't really generalize on that
but it's it gives you the way to you know but everybody is still part of it right so in
like a wonderful example of this is also in the italian mountain ranges like in so many countries
in the rural areas right so there are many small towns that have a significant retention problem
right so people are leaving and were so it makes it very hard for the people that
stay that are left behind to still operate let's say the restaurant the cinema the hotel etc
and so they form cooperatives right they form one cooperative like a community cooperative
that does everything so the same person might work as part of this cooperative
in a restaurant in the afternoon or in the evening you know might be a shepherd in the morning
and maybe work in the post office at lunch or so you know so essentially and this is important
right cooperatives always emerged in moments of crisis right so they they emerge when like the
government or markets fail or even in the global south like support networks or families fail
then you have you know people turn to each other and and and found cooperatives in the
united states in the 1930s a significant part of rural america was not electrified
because the big utility companies didn't find it lucrative enough to electrify this last village
in montana right this just didn't pay right and so you know with the help of president roosevelt
at the time who wrote legislation making that easier people in those rural areas got together
and founded rural electric cooperatives and this is how over 40 of the electric grid in the united
states today is cooperative so essentially like there was a there was a problem and
the market right did wasn't interested to solve this problem and so people had to take it on
themselves and this is very important to understand because that is a very different framing than
creating a tech startup to dominate the world and you know extract from communities worldwide
and out-compete the competition and be like that let's say like one startup that dominates the
sector it's a totally different way of thinking right so it's that's not why they ever emerged
and one thing is to have one cooperative but what you are working on goes beyond that because
what you're involved in and what you kind of co-founded i guess is a form of movement so
platform cooperativism is a form of movement and i would be interested in what is the state of
things when it comes to platform cooperativism as a movement and specifically
going into the question of how do you succeed in networking the different cooperatives with each
other and therefore kind of creating some form of i don't know a better word but synergy effect or
something that goes beyond what one cooperative might be able to do and create something that
points towards maybe even an alternative form of political economy as such
yeah wonderful questions yeah so it's i think the big vision for this work is really
pluralist cooperative commonwealth and so i think what you point out is essential
because it's so we are working with over 500 businesses and there are many more that we are
aware of in two countries and so there are tens of thousands of people involved it's
truly global there are definitely challenges and which have to do with startup funding
right so like because the venture capitalist model banks on you know investing it's in
like for a venture capitalist to invest in 10 projects and seven of them failing two of them
succeeding moderately and one having this like windfall of money so profit which which will
just never be the case with cooperatives because that's just not that's just against the principles
and so just with like these other projects that i described earlier it's a community right that
sees that that having this business creating this business solves the problem that nobody else is
willing to solve for them right so like these social cooperatives in italy that i mentioned
earlier when i talked about multi-stakeholder cooperatives i think there are 11 000 of them
much of that emerged in after 2008 when italy significantly reduced its budget for social care
so there are lots of cooperatives that emerge to help people with disabilities to have jobs elder
care etc so yeah so but to to come so so basically people see that there's a need
and they put their money together so it's crowd equity right so now there are also experiments
like in new york city where a lift competitor a taxi platform called drivers cooperative
has over 4 000 drivers and and they have taken a significant amount of investor funding
traditional investors who want to see profit but they did not give them controlling interest right
so they they can contribute but they will not control the business right and that's
that's what really matters with cooperatives right i mean you can take
uh this money maybe even from a municipality so i think there are there are thoughts in that
direction as well like why couldn't um i don't know the city of hamburg or
others be a class in one of those cooperatives now this is quite controversial for like you know
people with a sort of co-op dogma they would not agree to them but i think it's interesting as long
as there is no as long as there is no controlling interest i think it would be wonderful
when municipalities get involved right so we are working with municipalities because you ask of
the state of things um we're particularly interested in municipalities where this is
really supported right so obviously the regulatory framework is really important for for this to
thrive and uh it just happens that this is particularly the case and emilia romagna in
italy so the area around bologna which you know some people frame as co-op valley right so sort
of antidote to silicon valley and with platform corps like concerning a teacher but also fear bmb
and others but then also carola in the south of india which is a very progressive state which
has added platform corps to their government directive which means that we will help them
my organization will help them my institute will help them to to implement and some 4000
platform corps in the next five years that's their goal and then there's california and
also now there's work in bonas arias so like on argentina more broadly and then there's a lot
going on in brazil as well like so rio de janeiro sapaulo uh state the states of rio de janeiro
and sapaulo so um these are sort of the highlights right but it's you know also the netherlands and
and uh finland are of course also very open to this work states countries like kenya have uh
i think 48 percent of gdp in kenya is cooperative so it's significantly a cooperative culture
there is an organization like a sister organization of the platform corp consortium now also in
in berlin in germany and the platform corps uh germany uh it's called and um there's now also
you know there's a platform corps uh platform corp consortium in hong kong
there's uh just uh one starting now in indonesia in java and so it's sort of in many
many different places and i think right now i think people are really interested and i taught
a course on this just a few weeks ago uh on this overlap with web3 technologies
so how can dao's wide distributed autonomous organizations inform platform corps in terms
of their governance perhaps and i think many people in that space many technologists in that
space mistake what they are doing for cooperatives often not so clear on what a cooperative actually
is so but that sort of helps a little bit because people get more interested and open and also
thinking about how one could organize data cooperatively so how could you have cooperative
data trusts so this is essentially like a group of people creating a small pool of data and then
giving like fiduciary rights over those data through a bomb to the cooperative or some other
entity so these are all like experiments right like this is just starting but that's sort of the
state of things we we had some small successes let's say with policymakers so
andrea nales made when she was the leader of the social democrats
you know added platform corps to the you know part of the vision of the spd
uh but you know her candidacy wasn't her leadership wasn't exactly thriving wasn't
but it's uh but nevertheless you know she did that and so we tried to pick up on that the labor
party uh under corbin and also under the current leadership still has it as their vision for the
internet is one of their 10 guiding posts for that so so yeah so stuff going on in the policy level
we have an institute at the new school the institute for the cooperative digital economy
which has like a fellowship program so we are just about to announce our new cohort
which will essentially research exactly what i just talked about so like all of these little
points i had this is what they're all time and i guess one very interesting topic for further
research would be the question of governance because this is something i'm really interested
in because i mean it's pretty easy to imagine like smaller scale structures of cooperatives
where people are involved in the really involved in the governance of the given cooperative but
the more things get scaled up and the bigger the the organization gets the more difficult
it becomes to imagine a like meaningful um meaningfully taking part within the governance
structure and the self-governance of the whole thing so are there experiments with like large
scale self-governed um platform cooperatives and what are the takeaways of of these large-scale
platform cooperatives because i imagine you you run into very different problems once things get
bigger well that that um it's not just a question of for governance but it's also a question of
scaling right and so how do we think of scaling and it's really it's really um important to
detach yourself from the i guess silicon valley's thinking because it's co-op scale very differently
so they scale worldwide um through federations and alliances and collaborations so in a way that
is drastically different to anything uh coming out of silicon valley so the the traditional platform
as you may say has uh is an umbrella right an umbrella of many small cooperatives so
let's take for example and i gave that example in my chat talk when you if you want to
hear this a bit more in detail about this cleaning cooperative in new york and it's essentially three
very small worker co-ops and they sit under this umbrella of this second level cooperative the
platform co-op that's its own entity and each of the three groups uh has a representative to the
board of the platform co-op so and then this is how they all decide then how this platform
corpus operated which really functions more as a labor supply for them right so it allows them
access to jobs better jobs uh better gigs than they would have gotten than when they would have
pinned a flyer to a tree right so they reach more affluent clients that can pay them more
and then this is something we have mentioned yet you know allows them to make twice as much as
they used to make before so this is often the case with worker platform co-ops in that way they
in care and in cleaning right they make twice as much okay so how do they scale like well
like this sort of federal federation is is one model of scaling and it allows them to still
retain this interpersonal trust and um and friendships uh that are so important to
cooperatives so they are much more resilient than other business forms uh which is the research
show set after 2008 like there were far fewer cooperatives that went bankrupt than other
businesses and you know it's not that they have any magic sauce or anything it's just that they
you know they they suck it up right so they stick together and they want this business to succeed
because and you could say this a bit more pompously uh because they have a purpose right
i mean it's not it's not about business it's not about profit right it's about purpose
and um and so uh and that's also what you see with other groups and in in india for example
we work with the seva federation and uh that seva is a federation of cooperatives and a union
so the union is uh has over a million members and the co-op federation has over 300 000 members
and well that's another topic altogether like how those two uh bodies act right like
i would you need a union and it turns out to be a very good idea but um the the point here is that
this is also over 105 cooperatives in this federation of several several men so and together
they for example with covid right like coordinated their help efforts to you know provide
workers with money and food and you know medical supplies like masks etc sanitizer hand sanitizer
so um that really makes sense and another huge cooperative federation in india is amul which is
i think the largest milk producer in the world and it's 1.7 million milk producers
small milk producers all networked in this federation and so so i mean i can talk a lot
about that there's lots of examples in italy as well that illustrate this well where essentially
like most italian businesses are very small but then they federate to be able to compete with
larger companies but with the web3 right you have like another thing coming and i'm not sure i would
call those cooperatives but they they are i think it's an interesting thing to explore and they
could work in that direction where through blockchain you can split ownership across
i don't know hundreds of thousands of people right so uh i don't know if you followed this
at all in the united states there was an attempt to buy the constitution so i think there are i
don't know how many copies probably a dozen or so which were printed uh you know initially
and uh they i think it was 40 million dollars for one copy and uh this online group that tried to
purchase it they raised 19 million which you know is not 40 million but they raised 19 million
dollars right i mean that is incredible and uh so then they set their next targets on buying a soccer
team uh jointly and then uh a vacation resort like a spa in florida uh that they wanted to jointly
buy so i think nobody really knows it's just i think it has something to do that you can
you can do that with blockchain right um what that would look like and i think it's completely
unresolved how how people would then vote that's it let's say they managed to buy this result that
now what right i mean so how do they run it um that would be a huge experiment but i think to
to split i think the huge the really interesting question is like it's the research is really
clear that like worker corps and to an extent multi-stakeholder corps are better businesses
for people right i mean that's so you know like it's you know more sustainable it's better for
the planet it's uh they are they're better jobs there's dignity in the workplace uh you know
people are treated as human beings but it's it's it's not um you know obviously as large
as corporations and so well this this would be an interesting way to scale as well right through
this type of like ownership fractals if you want you know uh but like i said there isn't really
an example yet of where that is actually happening but it's very promising interesting
yeah well i understand the interest the initial interest i'm highly skeptical i have to say because
i mean it's it it still very much stays within a very particular paradigm of private ownership and
then uh is able more or less to spread uh this over a given asset so to speak but well let's
let's say um it's always interesting to see experimentation i guess um so you mentioned
that platform cooperatives are the better businesses um because they are very much
oriented towards a humane setting within one works and gets paid and has social interactions
and so forth and so on so what i think is really great about platform cooperatives is that they
offer a very concrete alternative in the here and now and um that they also by doing that represent
some form of let's say building block for how transformations to post-capitalist futures might
actually look like so i really really love that but at the same time it's important to ask and
also to be aware of what exactly they they are able to do for what kind of things they might be
a solution and for what they might not be a solution so what are the what the what the
boundaries of of this concept are i heard an interview with you in in which you said that you
are often asked whether platform cooperativism is an alternative to uber google facebook etc
and in at least in this interview you you replied that this is the wrong question
and so i would like to to frame it a little differently and the question would then be if
you consider platform cooperatives as a solution for certain kinds of social problems um for
which problems might they be a solution and for which problems maybe not right i mean if you want
to run a platform or start a platform and you have an interest in a social justice lens
or if that is your mission if you're interested in social justice right then i think there isn't
a question that that's really the model to go with right but you know obviously like that is
really not the objective of most businesses so but if that is your objectives then i think
that would be the form to pick i agree with you i don't think it's the answer to everything at
all i mean it's not a panacea it's not a silver bullet or anything but it is very suitable to
uh like picking up on the historical narrative of what they have responded to in the past
so when you think about like one of the fastest growing uh largest areas of the economy that
is really failing that is care right elder care so uh you have we have in all countries all over
the world and like a explosive growth of people over 80 80 and older and uh there's a significant
i mean millions of workers missing to fill those spots to care for them and uh that is also true
in germany and uh yeah it's also i think hundreds of thousands of workers missing in that industry
and the reason is that it's a low prestige and terribly paid job right and so with platform
cooperatives organizing this cooperatively and we see some examples of this actually
in in california in los angeles where platform co-op started by a union by the way has
um started to work with two hospitals and they have been doing this for a very long time they
had a pilot in 2016 or so like with 10 nurses and now they are working on scaling this up to
2000 and then the hope is within two years to 10 000 nurses and to essentially offer
uh care work flexibly through an app while paying the nurses
better than they would have been paid otherwise
so so i think it's a care and care sector is one example where i think this is very much
uh predestined to work very well and then also we see i mean you know it seems sort of
counter-intuitive but i mean this model in new york is working right with this competitor to
lift not so much to uber right so this is also interesting it's not so much in terms of scale
also i mean it's tertiary right so it's like the third biggest player in new york
um and has a chance at that you know um but otherwise definitely in uh for food course
so we see that in berlin and i think also Vienna but all over the world i mean there were i think
eight or so of those founded in Barcelona in the last year alone so um they uh you know they're
really emerging quickly not that they all stay around right this was specific to the pandemic
but uh but there is a large uh federation already it's called co-op cycle uh coming out of paris
which uh has more than 60 uh uh cooperatives under its wing of couriers and provides them
with digital infrastructure right so they offer them the software and in return they
uh all abide to certain principles for example they are not allowed to use motorcycles
it has to be bicycled for ecological reasons so um that's where i where you see this can really
work but we see it emerging in all kinds of sectors so it's very hard to say actually because
you know we see it with this my cool classroom which has language teachers organizing through
platform cooperatives which is essentially language teachers all over the world
and being members of that we see it for designers we see it for photographers with stuxy
we are seeing it
in many different sectors but i think a chaos care and
and transport transportation i think probably uh will be the most likely ones to succeed
yeah yeah and you know in some countries for example like in brazil um the one of the largest
domains of the cooperative movement in brazil is actually hospitals and doctors and nurses
and so i think this is really where that is together as well and what do we have to do if
we want to use this principle this this this type of social organization so to speak platform
cooperatives as something that that is the nucleus for going beyond itself because there is of course
an inherent danger in in the in the way that it might also by being the go-to place in crisis
kind of letting the state like from the hook which would be a problem as well because i mean
this is an obvious danger so i would say we need to like work in tandem with other movements with
other like ideas for alternative ways of doing economy doing social organization and all of that
in order to to make platform cooperativism something that like really
is a building block of a post-capitalist future maybe no i absolutely agree so i mean again like
another really great question um the uh yeah i mean i think it's essential to work with other
movements and political movements so i think you know unions are a great place to start
and just to just in passing to mention like why that matters i mean for many reasons
very interesting to look at that in the indian example but just to stay in new york where
you know like when they started when eric foreman and his colleagues started drivers
cooperative like one of the the main problems for a startup like that is that they don't have
marketing funds right so you can run because so much is dependent on supply right like you also
need drivers right that are available so if you aren't known right if people don't haven't heard
about you that's a real problem so this is where the vc backed companies spend you know millions
of dollars so they didn't have that money so but by working with the union which has contacts to
hundreds of thousands of people right so they were able to reach out to lots of new yorkers that to
tell them about this and well it helped when the new york times picked up on it as well so
um uh that's uh i guess one one answer to that question and if you think about like models of
political economy that go beyond this notion of platform cooperativism what are the frameworks
that you that you think about because i mean they are i recently uh read a bit more about paracon
participatory econ economics i will do an interview with robert and now tomorrow by the
way and and they when they describe the processes of transformation they very much point towards
cooperatives as a necessary and very much uh important fruitful building block of this
like of course long-lasting phase of transformation of transition into
other types of political economy so we already established that cooperatives
essentially have to be an important element of that but how do you what do you think about if
you think beyond that like because at some point cooperatives will have like over lift themselves
no i completely agree with that comment as well but i wanted to say just let's go for a second
back to the your previous question because i think there's more to be said about this so james
mahoon has just published this book platform socialism where he picks up exactly at this point
i think a very interesting and fruitful book but i think very much from a european perspective
where the i mean what we saw basically in the united states and in poland and in hungary and
in so many other countries is that people just realize that the i mean there's the reason that
they lost trust in government right and that is in the united states when you imagine a worker
having entered the labor market in 1978 perhaps all these promises right in 50 years nothing has
changed for that worker right except that productivity increased significantly
and wages stagnated since 1978 right so like if adjusted for inflation so
i mean how can you blame anyone that they would be disengaged from fed from federal government
right so now now i would not i mean it's just it's just a fact do i like that of course not
right and do i think is that participatory democracy is a project that nobody should ever
give up on and and electoral politics of course of course not right but then there's also the
reality that those systems are just deeply broken right so you see this even with the current
presidency to an extent right and so this is i think where municipalities become much more important
right and because on that level you can it's limited what you can do which we saw in the case
of barcelona but you can do something and and and can actually really support a model like that to
an extent and and make changes to an extent right so so i want to be really careful about this
because i think i agree with you completely and i don't want to say i fully want to support what
you said about you know like not letting the government off the hook but they also have to
acknowledge that not every country is germany right and like when i look at the united states
i mean it's a deeply flawed system right to be polite and very very dysfunctional and
and that's not theoretical so you can say like well but you know we should we should
hope for this to change you know but then look at the real lives of people this is real people
living real lives every day and they are getting all these promises you know from politicians
and they just don't come through it's not felt in their lives and i think this has to change right
and uh and they there's i think a significant feeling of a lack of voice right that you don't
have a voice in society which also cooperatives are in response to because when you think about
in the united states incarcerated people are returning from prison so you know returning
citizens entering the workplace so they are excluded from federal elections right i don't
know if you know this so like when you come out of prison in the u.s you cannot vote anymore
and uh so well those are the only workplaces where they you know actually have a real voice
like they are equal members and have a voice and i think that is um i mean i think ultimately it's
about uh social democracy i think that's a social democracy where people really have a felt
relationship to what's happening in the government really changing their lives
and the government that also really represents the types of people that actually constitute the
population right so that kind of uh stakeholder society right like where people really feel
part of that uh well i had talked about the vision before you had asked before and i appointed to
a vision of a sort of pluralistic uh commonwealth right so where cooperatives are part of a global
network of businesses that can also change the sort of north south dynamic right this gap
because which of course is a criticism of cooperatives today which is like even the
largest cooperatives like mondragon are dependent on supply chains that are just as deeply
exploitative as um as anyone else and if there would also be cooperatives in the global south
that then produce for cooperatives in the global north right and you would establish this um this
commonwealth you could change that you could even extend that vision to what some people have called
like data colonialism right and to to push back against how which which i think affects people in
the global south much more than people in the global north uh because the data collection is
much more ruthless um to actually put people in the global south in charge of their own data
through data trusts or things we had mentioned earlier and maybe push back on that in this way
as well so i think that's a vision yeah i mean i'm i think paracorn is a great approach
as well there are many right of the sort of post-work society and many others
which i support but you know i think they are often so far away that and this is very important
you know i'm not at all taking away from that but i think what's there is a lot of that you
know there's a lot of these long-term visions uh what is there's very very few of uh these sort
of next steps right and i think uh like a lot of academics like really discourage this right they
say like wow this is just too pragmatic and you get stuck in this sort of presentism or whatever
you want to call it and i really disagree with that and i think it's it's uh deeply disrespectful
of the lives of people now of the workers now that are living in these super precarious situations
so i think to build something as you said a nucleus of like a scaffolding right a scaffolding on
which you can then erect uh like a post-capitalist vision or let's say like a social democracy just
on the way to that is is deeply valuable and and something i really support
and there's one question i ask all of my guests at the end and this is if you think about the
future what makes you joyful well i mean maybe i can talk to you about a class i taught which
sounds um may be expected but um in 2020 in february uh mondragon the largest workup
worker corp in the world right so they came to visit me at the university
and shortly thereafter the pandemic started and we immediately uh you know we signed a paper to
collaborate and um and we started a class an online class on platform co-ops like an emergency
response and we taught over 1200 students from 57 countries and uh and managed because there was
a sense of urgency to engage uh over 50 organizing over 60 organizations actually in those countries
so they supported the course locally helping people with their local knowledge about the laws
and language etc to start those those uh projects and we had weekly meetings uh everybody in their
lockdown and in a time which was really rather dark and possibly depressing uh and for me this
was just i mean it was an incredible experience because you saw all these people you know like
from i don't know transgender entrepreneurs in malaysia connecting with like african-american
entrepreneurs in selma alabama i mean like who i mean just to see these like in front of you like
all these people all over the world right having this wonderful spirit and all dedicating themselves
to changing their world uh i mean i guess if anything could give you hope i mean that was
definitely a moment um to and it really uh sowed the seeds for further work right because now these
organizations uh learned about platform co-ops and they are now incubating them right also after
a couple classes over and uh and we still hear from projects coming out of that
um and so on so it's a very it's a very beautiful experience
great trevor thank you so much for taking the time and being part of future histories thanks
yeah thank you for your great question
that was our show for today thanks a lot for listening if you want to support future histories
you can do so on patreon for this visit patreon.com slash future histories or you can simply tell a
friend that you like the show and that he she or they might like it as well thanks a lot and hear
you in two weeks