Welcome to Huge Histories.
My name is Jan Groos, and it is my great pleasure
to welcome Robin Hannell in today's episode.
He is professor of economics at Portland State University,
and together with Michael Albert,
he developed Paracon, short for participatory economics,
which is one of the most popular models
for democratic economic planning there is,
and it has been around for more than 30 years now.
I really wanted to cover Paracon as thoroughly as possible,
leading to more than four hours of material
of which you will hear roughly the first half
in this episode.
The second part will be released in two weeks.
And just to give you some orientation,
we begin by going through the model bit by bit,
and I kind of spared my critical questions
for after the model has been laid out in full.
This conversation is part of a small series
in which I cover some of the classical models
of democratic economic planning
by talking to their creators.
I already did an interview with David Leibman
on multi-level democratic iterative coordination
in episode 19 of season two,
and soon there will be a double episode
with Pat Devine as well.
Since all of these episodes are in English,
and since there are quite a couple
of other Future Histories episodes in English by now,
we created an English episode only feed
that you can subscribe to.
So if you don't speak German
and you are simply waiting
for the next English episode of Future Histories,
please go ahead and take a look at the show notes
where you will find a link to the English only RSS feed
as well as the newly created English version
of the homepage.
Please share among your English speaking friends.
I'm always very grateful for propaganda.
This is really very helpful
and maybe share in all of your different networks too.
Thank you so much.
And speaking of thanks, thank you Bernhard, Fabian
and Wilfried for their kind donations.
And there's a special kind of Patreon support that happened.
Happy birthday to Daniel from Malte
who became a Patreon supporter of Future Histories
as a birthday gift to Daniel.
And this is very heartwarming to me.
And I feel honored that this was gifted.
So double thanks to Malte and Daniel.
But now please enjoy today's episode
and in-depth interview with Robin Hanell
on participatory economics.
Welcome Robin.
Good to be with you.
It's a pleasure.
We will hopefully get into quite some detail
about Perikan today,
but let's start with an overview and broad definition.
What is Perikan?
It's an attempt to say something concrete
about what it is that we think that socialists
should be proposing as the kind of economic system
that we wanna replace capitalism with in the 21st century.
In the light of all of the experiences
with different attempts to create a socialist economy
in the 20th century, what lessons have we learned
and what should we now be proposing?
It's our proposal of what we left us
who wanna replace capitalism
with a far better economic system,
a kind of socialism that's very democratic
and that encourages popular participation.
And the other thing is that we thought that for too long,
anti-capitalists have just been very vague
about what it is they want in light of the Soviet experience
in the Eastern European countries and Cuba.
In light of all that, we felt like reasonable people
would expect, you have to say something
a little more concrete than just your values
and your wishes for how the economy should work.
So we thought, well, let's begin that process
by making some very, very concrete proposals
about how all the different kinds of decisions
that have to be made, how they might best be made,
and then we can all talk about it.
So that was the motivation, that was the purpose
for putting something out there.
And then we had to discuss what label to put on it,
and we ended up with, well, let's call it
a participatory economy.
So that was the origins.
Michael and I were very much together on that wavelength
and the first books we published about it were back in 1990.
So at this point, it's been around a while.
And after the fall of the wall
and the sort of crumbling of the centrally planned economies
in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe,
there's now been a 30-year debate
about what should socialists be championing.
And there's various schools of thought.
There's a lot of proposals about market socialism.
There's basically proposals about taking
social democratic capitalism as far as you can take it.
I would call that's Alec Nove.
And then there are other people who have continued to say,
no, we want a lot more planning than that.
Market socialism isn't really what we socialists
should be championing in the future.
We really need to talk seriously about planning
and different forms of planning.
So this proposal is one of the proposals that's out there
that sort of fits into that 30-year debate.
And in that context, it's been argued about
in various journals and at various conferences
over the past 30 years.
And there are some basic principles that inform pericon.
And these are in short, self-governance
through democratic councils of workers and consumers
and their respective federations.
That's the first one.
The second one would be jobs balanced for empowerment,
desirability and caring labor.
The third one would be remuneration according to sacrifice
or effort as judged by coworkers.
And the fourth one would be economic coordination
through a participatory planning procedure.
I would very much like to go through all of them.
Let's start with self-governance.
How would democratic self-governance
be achieved in pericon?
You did a brilliant job of summarizing
the major features of the proposal,
so I don't have to, thank you.
First, we've argued that it's very clear
that it's very important to think very hard
about exactly what you think economic democracy means.
And there's two different views
about what economic democracy means
that are really dominant.
One is, well, it's like politics.
I mean, democratic politics is everybody gets a vote.
Everybody gets a vote and everybody gets the same vote.
How else can you do this?
In economics, there's also this concept
that's been around for a long time
that right-wingers like Milton Friedman
called economic freedom.
And that is, well, I should be free to do
with my person and property whatever I want.
And we want a system that allows people to do that.
And so we have begun, we try to begin the discussion
by pointing out that both of these approaches
to what economic democracy or economic freedom means,
they don't apply in most situations
because particularly when economic decisions are made,
what will happen is any economic decision you look at
will affect some people more than other people.
So one person, one vote works
as a notion of economic democracy in those cases
where everybody is affected more or less equally
by the decision.
And economic freedom works for decisions
that really only affect me.
I mean, what color underwear should I put on today?
So yeah, of course, we want economic freedom
is the right way to make that decision.
I get to decide, nobody gets to tell me that.
On the other hand, most economic decisions
are decisions where some people will be affected,
more than one person will be affected,
but some people will be affected more than others.
So we have begun by saying,
let's be clear what the goal is here.
The goal is we want to design procedures
for making economic decisions
so that people would approximately have influence
over a decision to the degree that they are affected.
And that's sort of, that's our starting point
in terms of how we go about thinking
about what a democratic economy means.
And we call that self-management.
We define self-management as decision-making input
over things to the degree that you're affected.
And in some cases, that means I'll have more
decision-making authority or input
than somebody else does.
And in some cases, it'll mean I have some input,
but I don't have as much input as other people.
And in the particular context of workplaces,
what a workplace produces and what technologies they use
and how they go about organizing their work process,
clearly those decisions affect people
in what we propose to be a worker's council,
far more than they affect all sorts of other people.
But it's not that,
their decisions clearly affect other people as well.
What they decide to produce is going to affect consumers.
And if they use these inputs rather than those inputs,
it means, well, if they use particular parts of land,
if they use a piece of land,
that means somebody else can't use it.
So we start with that.
We start with that.
You mentioned that we also start with sort of a position
about, well, what would be a fair way
to distribute the burdens and benefits of economic activity?
And this is something that's hotly contested
by socialists and has been for,
since socialism first became
some sort of an ideology in a movement.
What is a fair, just how should workers be rewarded?
On what basis should people be rewarded?
And we've argued that when you go through all of that,
and you think it through clearly,
that a desirable economy would be one
in which workers are rewarded according
to the sacrifices they make when they work.
We've also used the word effort.
Sometimes some people, I mean,
I know there are times when I'm working harder.
I know when there are times when I'm working less hard.
And those who work harder
probably deserve more compensation.
And certainly people who work,
who make greater sacrifices than they work.
I mean, neoclassical economists
call it the disutility of labor.
You're working right now,
but your disutility isn't very high.
You're doing something that you find more,
you're doing something you find more or less pleasant.
The coal miner who goes down a shaft
and exposes themselves to coal dust
and is sweating and coming home sore at the end of the day
is making more sacrifices than somebody who,
somebody like you or me is
during most of the time when we're working.
So we just think those things should be taken into account.
Those are legitimate reasons
for why some people should sometimes be compensated
by more than others.
Now, how you go about doing that.
So how you go about arranging for economic decisions
to be made according to this principle
or goal of self-management
and how it is that you arrange for people to be compensated
according to their sacrifice.
Well, but at least we understand
what we're trying to accomplish.
And we were very self-conscious from the very beginning
and coming up with proposals
for how you would actually achieve those goals.
Now, one thing I'll be very honest about,
we did not think about very much back in 1990
was environmental sustainability.
So I will plead guilty
as long as most of my socialist comrades of my age
are willing to plead guilty along with me
because we really should.
Leftists and socialists, I believe,
where Johnny come lately to environmental awareness.
We were just so concerned
with all sorts of other things we cared about.
Oh, economic self-management and economic justice
that we sort of took environmental things for granted.
And in many ways, we're just like everybody else
in terms of being woefully un-woke
on the subject of what was happening with the environment.
But one of the things I'm really proud of is,
and this was, I will give my wife credit for this.
My wife is an environmental economist
and she brought her leftist husband
to awareness about just how negligent
me and my fellow comrades were
in our thinking about environmental issues.
And now I have become, as a professional economist,
I teach political economy, I teach economic theory,
but for more than 20 years,
I've also taught environmental economics.
I can almost prove my point about negligence on the left.
So I taught in an economics department
at American University,
known as sort of a heterodox school of economics,
a PhD program that studied political economy
as well as mainstream economics.
We didn't have a professor, you know,
who was a specialist in environmental economics
for the first 15 years I taught in that program.
And I became an environmental economist
because somebody had raised their hand
and said, who's gonna teach
the environmental economics class?
And I said, you know, okay, so I'll do that.
So that's how I became somebody
who actually learned enough about environmental economics
to realize that you have clearly in the year 2020,
clearly any economy to be desirable
has to be an economy that's designed in ways
that is going to help us protect
and preserve the natural environment
far better than any economic system
that people have used up until now.
So I very self-consciously now add the goal
of environmental sustainability, you know,
to economic democracy and economic justice.
And we will get to the mechanisms
that have been incorporated into Perrican
in order to address this question.
Before we go there, maybe you could like guide the audience
through this basic setup of institutions within Perrican.
So this is sort of a thumbnail sketch
of what the major features of a participatory economy are.
We propose that,
that the first is workers councils.
So we don't have private corporations.
Workplaces are governed by a workers council
where every worker has one vote.
And we can go back to our suggestions or proposals
for how it is that workers councils might want to proceed
in their own process of self-governance.
But we have workers councils.
We also have proposed that consumers,
that consumers be organized
into what we call neighborhood consumer councils.
Because we want to enfranchise consumers
in our planning processes.
And if they act as individuals,
it's very difficult for us to incorporate them
into planning procedures.
But if we simply say
that we organize neighborhood consumption councils
where we're talking about maybe 5,000
or 6,000 families that are living in a neighborhood.
So these are geographically defined neighborhoods.
And we just want the size of the council to be such
that you could reasonably participate
by going to meetings in your neighborhood
consumption council.
So that's another sort of major institutional proposal
that we have.
It's a way, we think it's important
to enfranchise consumers in planning procedures
along with workers in their workplace.
What's probably most innovative about our proposal,
I believe, is that there's two different ways
that people have thought you could integrate
the interrelated activities
of hundreds of thousands of workers councils
and hundreds of thousands of consumer councils.
And one would be simply through the market.
Because consumers have to buy what workers,
consumers have to get what workers councils are producing
and different workers councils have to receive inputs.
So there is a, you have to coordinate all this.
And the two ways that the dominant thinking
about how to coordinate all this is,
well, you either have to coordinate it
through market exchanges,
or you're gonna need some sort of central agency
that gathers all the information
and then puts together a coherent plan
for how all this could work out.
And what we have said is both of those are a disaster
that we now can foreseeably predict sort of some,
at least with the, I mean, hindsight's perfect,
but we have the 20th century of hindsight
to see what happened when socialists tried
to somehow have a central planning agency,
be in charge of this coordinating process.
And it's not a good outcome.
And then the question is, but is there an alternative?
And our answer was, there is an alternative.
And what's I think particularly interesting about it is,
I think the alternative is exactly what early socialists
always thought would go on if you go back
to the late 1900s and early 20th century.
What they always thought was, well, these workers councils,
of course they have, their activities are interrelated.
They're gonna have to plan together
how that interrelation works out.
And so we very self-consciously tried to design procedures
that would essentially take that view
of what it is we're attempting to do.
Is there some way that we could have workers councils
proposing what they wanna do,
consumer councils saying, this is what we wanna consume?
And is there some way that they could make
what I call sort of self-activity proposals
and then discover what the consequences of that are,
and then go back to the drawing board
and revise the proposals and resubmit them
so that we could find a feasible plan in this way.
And we wouldn't have a central planning agency
sitting on top of everybody saying,
well, what you propose doesn't work,
you're gonna have to do this.
And we wouldn't have market forces driving the outcome.
Is there really any reason
that we couldn't do things that way?
So we've worked on it sort of theoretically,
and now we've worked on it with sort of computer simulations
to see whether something that we can prove
under certain assumptions would reach a feasible
and desirable and efficient plan under.
This is what economists do.
We say, well, if you make certain assumptions
about preferences people have,
if you make certain assumptions about technologies
that producers have, then under those assumptions,
you can prove that some procedure
will reach a particular outcome.
And way back in 1990, we essentially said
under far less rigorous assumptions
than you need to prove that a market capitalist economy
will reach an efficient outcome.
We can say this process,
which we think was what early socialists
and most people drawn to socialism always wanted instead.
This process will work out.
This process could, it works in theory.
Now that left the issue of, but is it practical?
And we'll come back to this,
but I mean here to put the issue very, very bluntly.
Well, in theory, if we still have,
if we allow the workers and the consumer neighborhood
consumer councils to keep making proposals
and revising their proposals enough times,
in theory, we'll come to a feasible plan
that we can start the year with.
But what if it takes 1000 revisions?
Well, then it becomes a practical impossibility.
So that question was left aside until,
I mean, the best way to answer it
is to convince some country they wanna try it.
But until that happens, then the only answer is
you try and do some computer simulations
to see what happens.
And we now basically have done that
and we have some, I think some pretty interesting,
at least preliminary reporting
that we can do on that subject.
Besides the workers councils that are self-managed,
the consumer councils that are also sort of self-governing
and participate in the planning procedure,
our specific proposal for how it is
that annual participatory planning can substitute
for a central planning board and markets
as a way to come up with a plan.
I think that's the sort of unique and it is unique.
And I think it's a very central part
of what our overall proposal is.
And maybe just for the audience
in order to give some orientation,
the mechanism that is an essential part
of this participatory planning procedure
that will take up all of this information
and process it in a way in order to provide
some first estimates on how to proceed.
This institution is called the IFB,
the Iteration Facilitation Board, isn't it?
Yes, you know, when you're creating things
and you have to put names on them,
some choices are felicitous and some are less so.
And Michael Albert and I remember we talked for,
I mean, we had long conversations
about what name do we wanna give to this system or proposal?
And I mean, I remember one of the early ones we thought of
was decentralized socialist planning.
And I'm the economist and Michael's the political activist.
So that appealed to me.
And Michael argued in this time,
I mean, we've had various arguments over the decades
and sometimes I think I've been right
and sometimes I think he was right.
And on this one, he was dead right.
He said, you know what?
I mean, we should call it a participatory economy.
If people wanna call it participatory socialism, that's fine.
If people wanna say, well, how does it fit in
to left ideology?
We can say it's libertarian socialism.
In Europe calling something libertarian socialism,
it works because everybody knows what you mean.
In the United States, that's a huge problem
because the only people who call themselves libertarians
in the United States are right-wing libertarians.
So if you say libertarian socialism,
you mostly just confuse people in the United States.
But in any case, we had to come up
with some sort of a name and he was the one
that was just very insistent.
We really decentralized socialist planning, no, no, no.
We should just call it a participatory economy.
I think he was right about that.
The iteration facilitation board
is a very unfortunate name.
And in anarchist circles,
it's also a very hotly contested issue exactly what it is.
So besides the name being unfortunate, it's clunky.
The real issue is, well, what does it do?
And I'll just go straight to the issue here.
Anarchists are suspicious
that it's just a different name
for the central planning bureau,
that it's a central planning bureau in disguise.
You told us you didn't have a central planning bureau.
You told us that this was an alternative
to central planning,
but you really just sort of hoodwinked us.
You gave it a different name,
but it really is doing what central planning bureaus do.
And so I wanna take care of that immediately.
This thing, whatever you call it,
we haven't got a better name yet,
iteration facilitation board.
This is what it does.
At the beginning of the annual planning process,
it announces whatever the current estimates are
of the opportunity costs of using different resources,
the opportunity cost of using different kinds of labor,
the opportunity cost of using machinery,
stocks of machines that we have,
and whatever estimates the current estimates are
of the social cost of producing different things.
So for an economist,
what it does is it announces an initial price vector.
Now in left circles, I don't wanna use the word price
because as soon as you talk about a price,
somebody thinks there's a market.
As a matter of fact, as soon as you talk about a price,
some people don't even wanna talk to you.
On the other hand, as an economist, I can insist,
well, in order to make a sensible proposal
about what our workplace wants to do,
we have to have some idea of what does it cost society
to use different things we're asking permission to use,
different inputs.
And we have to have some sort of idea
of whether or not consumers would rather have shoes
or shirts.
So you can't make a sensible proposal
without some sort of information along those lines.
So this is what the iteration facilitation board does
in our annual planning process.
It announces some initial estimates of what those are.
Now in our simulations for the first year,
we said it's just gonna have to announce something arbitrary.
But in the real world, of course, what it would do is
it would begin, it would have a much better initial estimate
to offer than just an arbitrary answer
to what those things are.
It could take whatever they were from last year
and say, let's start with those.
So in either case, and I can tell you something
about when we did the simulations,
how much difference it makes.
You know, if you start from last year,
take advantage of some information you already have
instead of assuming you have no information.
But anyway, they make the announcement.
At that point, all of the workers councils respond
with what I call a self-activity proposal.
We wanna produce this much of these different outputs
and we want permission to use all these different inputs
in order to do that.
The neighborhood consumer councils submit
on behalf of everybody in the neighborhood.
So the neighborhood consumer council is gonna have
to approve individual consumption requests.
And we can come back to whether or not
that's an intrusive process or not.
But in any case, people don't participate
in annual planning as individual consumers.
It's the neighborhood council that participates.
So it sends in, it says, this is the sum total
of all the approved consumption requests
of the people living in the neighborhood.
And this is the sum total income that all those people have.
And that income can either come,
it's either income because they worked
and their sacrifice effort ratings gave them
that much income or we're gonna, I mean,
obviously you're gonna have social security payments
and disability payments.
You're gonna have need-based payments.
So all that income basically,
and so the consumer council responds to
how much are the consumers,
what's the social cost of making different things?
Responds to that by saying,
here's what the neighborhood consumption council
wants to consume, we've approved,
and here is the total income that we all have.
When those come in, supplies and demands
for everything will not be equal.
So there'll be, when all those proposals come in,
there'll be excess demand for a whole bunch of things,
and there may be excess supply,
offers to supply or availability,
not everything is being used of something.
All the iteration facilitation board does
is adjust its estimates of any price
where there was excess demand, it adjusts the estimate up.
And if it's excess supply, they adjust the estimate down.
That's all they do.
So, I mean, that has been my answer to the anarchists who,
look, given the history of socialism,
it's very sensible to be paranoid
about whether anything called an agency
in charge of a planned economy
is gonna turn into one of those evil
central planning agencies.
So I applaud the fact that somebody really wants to,
that somebody wants to be very careful about that.
On the other hand, my answer is what authority
did this agency exert?
What decisions did they make?
They didn't tell anybody what they had to propose.
They didn't say, your proposal is unaccepted.
They didn't say, well, your proposal doesn't fit
and we need a plan that's feasible,
we're gonna revise your proposal for you.
They don't do any of those things,
which is exactly what central planning agencies did.
All they do is adjust the estimates that they send out
for the next round of revisions and proposals.
They adjust the estimates to give us more accurate,
to basically give us more accurate estimates of social,
of opportunity costs of using things
and the social costs of producing things.
That's all the iteration facilitation board does.
And maybe you could dig a little deeper into the question
of how these indicative prices
are actually being calculated.
You state that they are basically estimates
of opportunity costs and social costs,
but how are these measured in concrete terms
and how does one measure opportunity costs,
which is foregone benefit basically,
for all goods and services if individual benefit
is actually a highly subjective and context specific
and also dynamic value.
And this is all additional to the question
whether or not individual benefit
is really the right measure to begin with.
So I was asking myself how this is being done
in very concrete terms,
maybe also for someone who's not an economist
and doesn't really know about the concept
of opportunity costs.
Okay, I'm gonna smile a little bit
and be a little facetious.
I mean, and so I'm gonna be a little facetious and say,
part of the brilliance is that it happens organically.
So there's two sort of ways you can think about
where do these estimates of opportunity
and social costs come from?
And one way of thinking about it,
which is the common sense way to think about it.
And it's the way most people do think about it.
And I think it's the way that most people approaching
socialism have always thought about it is,
well, somebody would have to sit down
and sort of try and calculate that
and take all sorts of factors into account
as part of their calculation.
And that's not what, that's not how it happens at all.
That's not how it happens at all.
Instead, I told you that the initial estimates
can be arbitrary.
And then I said, we start with initial estimates,
the workers councils and the consumer councils respond,
that gives us some excess demands and excess supplies
that tell us the plan isn't feasible yet.
We know to make the plan feasible,
the way to do it is to increase the estimate of things
that are in excess demand and decrease the estimate
of the things that are in excess supply.
An agency does that, but it's a mechanical thing.
It's not sitting down and trying to actually do some study
that leads to the answer.
Now, and the other reason I'm gonna smile and claim
there's a certain genius at work here was,
is well, but what we proved
and all the economists have had to acknowledge
is that, yeah, you did prove this,
is that under standard assumptions
about what people's preferences are like
and standard assumptions about what technologies are like,
the kinds of standard assumptions every economics has
to make in order to do any theoretical study
of what would happen in case.
Under standard assumptions, actually more lax
and there's some assumptions we don't even have to make
that are made to sort of do this kind of analysis
for a market system,
that this process will lead to two outcomes.
The first outcome is, and this is the one
that I would think is the most important,
and this is the one that I would think
is more important to us is,
the first outcome is it'll lead to a feasible plan
where everything that somebody's counting on,
I've been authorized to do this,
but that means I have to be,
I'm also authorized to receive this in order to do it,
that everybody will be able to actually carry out
the last thing that they proposed.
That's the first thing.
We've demonstrated that you'll get to a feasible plan.
We've also demonstrated that the plan will be efficient.
You won't be misusing resources.
You won't be using a resource to do something
where you're producing something less valuable,
whereas if you'd used it for something else,
it would have produced something that was more valuable.
More valuable to whom?
More valuable to consumers,
given what it is they're telling you they want
and they don't want.
The third thing is that your final estimates
of these opportunity and social costs
will be as accurate as any estimates
of social opportunity and social costs you can expect.
So it's not that non-economists approach this
in a very sensible, straightforward way.
While you're saying that we're not going to be able
to do that, while you're saying that we need
to know the opportunity cost of using a piece of land,
that's probably a hard thing
to figure out what that would be.
And if somebody were sitting down
and trying to calculate it, it would be hard.
Basically, it would be impossible.
But that doesn't mean that certain procedures
will not generate that information.
And that's what's happening.
It's not that somebody's calculating it,
it's that that answer is being generated.
And it's generated by the process I've described
as the annual participatory planning process.
And at some point, there will be a situation
where all of the councils will have to decide up on
whether or not the different proposals
are being accepted or not.
So maybe let's move a step further
within the planning process
so the audience can kind of understand the different steps.
So we reach the point where there will be a feasible plan,
as you call it.
So how are the next procedural steps then?
Yes, if there isn't a central planning agency
that says no, well, then who says no
if a worker council proposes to do some,
they're the only ones allowed to make proposals
and nobody gets to revise their proposals other than them.
So what's gonna prevent a worker council
from doing something that really isn't fair
to the rest of us?
And what's gonna prevent a consumer council
for doing something that isn't fair to the rest of us?
Let's first figure out, well, what would it mean
to do something that isn't fair to the rest of us?
For a worker council, what it comes down to is
you're making a proposal to produce certain outputs,
but you're also proposing that you would be allowed
to use certain inputs.
Well, those inputs have a cost to society
because if you use them, somebody else can't.
And those outputs are presumably
for some other worker council
that finds them more or less valuable
or for consumers who find them more or less valuable.
So there's sort of the social benefits
of all the outputs that you have proposed
and there's the social cost of all the inputs
that you've proposed.
An irresponsible proposal,
I'm gonna call it socially irresponsible.
It would be socially irresponsible for a worker council
to make a proposal where the social benefits
of their outputs aren't at least as large
as the social cost of their inputs.
Because if they do that,
the rest of us are gonna be worse off
if they go ahead and do what they're proposing.
What would it mean for a consumer council
to be irresponsible?
So for a worker's council, the real issue is,
are you gonna contribute more to social benefits
than you do to social costs?
And before I move on, let me point out,
as long as you're not,
as long as the social benefits of your proposal
are at least as large as the social costs,
the rest of us are not any worse off
if you go ahead and do it.
You're not making any of the rest of us worse off.
And so why would we care what you do?
As long as you don't make me,
as long as the rest of us are not made worse off,
go ahead and do whatever the hell you want to.
Now the consumer councils.
So the neighborhood consumer councils are saying,
we wanna consume all this stuff.
Well, it costs society a lot to make all this stuff.
Social responsibility for them amounts
to comparing their aggregate income,
that is their right to consume socially costly goods
and services to the social cost
of their consumption request.
So as long as the income, the sacrifices from work
and the allowances and disability and all,
as long as that is sufficient to pay for
the social costs of a neighborhood
consumption council request,
well then they're not asking for anything
that's not fair for them to have.
If they're asked, if it turns out the social cost
of that neighborhood consumption council request
is greater than their income is,
then they're being greedy.
And the rest of us have every right to say,
no, you can't do that.
Unless you can make some special argument
about why it is this year.
There were a bunch of people who got sick
and they had medical expenses.
Of course, we're gonna have medical expenses free anyway.
But so there are special circumstances that might come in.
So the basic point is,
there is an easy way for everybody to evaluate
first their own proposal.
When you make a proposal,
presumably you'd like to know
if it's socially responsible.
So the only way you know that is to look and see
is our social benefit to social cost ratio
at least one, if not higher.
And then you'd like to know if your consumption proposal
is socially responsible.
And that basically comes down to is the social cost
of what you're asking to consume,
greater than what your income and your fair income
based on sort of efforts and needs and things
and various things that we've worked out.
So you wanna know that about your own proposals,
but there's a way to do it.
We've got these estimates of social costs
and opportunity costs that allow the proposers
to figure out whether their own proposal
is socially responsible.
And importantly, it lets all the other councils
do the same, which is why you don't need
central planners to say no.
We've provided the councils with the information
necessary so that they can self-police
and do it fairly quickly without a lot of,
you know, debate and discussion.
And I think that's the thing that I'm sort of most anxious
to emphasize that aspect of it.
Because I think a large part of the reason
that people are drawn to sort of models
of market socialism is well,
the market takes care of all this for us.
And the only alternative is just going to be
a tremendous amount of arguing.
That's just gonna go on forever.
I mean, one of my colleagues here in the United States,
a socialist feminist economist named Nancy Fulbright.
And early on her reaction to participatory,
you know, the participatory economy proposal was,
Robin, you're a really nice guy.
I understand what you're trying to do here.
We're all in favor of all that,
but this is gonna lead to the dictatorship of the sociable
by which she meant, and as anybody who's been in the,
as anybody has participated in left politics long enough,
you know, one of the nightmares is that the meeting comes,
the meeting is called to order,
probably starts an hour late,
and there's arguing and debating and back and forth.
And we've gone on for two or three or four hours
and sensible people have to go home.
And in the end, the argument goes on and on and on.
And it's whoever was most stubborn
and whoever stayed till two in the morning
who finally ends up deciding things.
And you don't want a system that comes down to that.
And one of the things that I think is very important
about our proposal is,
we think we have made the central planning agency obsolete.
You don't need it.
And yet we have not burdened people
with endless amounts of meeting time and discussion time.
And we haven't put people in a situation
where the only criteria for making the decision
is who was just most stubborn and held out the longest.
That there's sort of objective ways to quickly decide
was that proposal socially responsible or irresponsible.
And as long as it's socially responsible,
whether it's coming from a neighborhood consumption council
or a workplace,
the rest of us should be totally happy to let them do it.
And there's an easy, and we think that this can all,
I mean, we now know from the simulations
that this shouldn't take more than five or six simulations
to come up with an annual plan,
which can easily be done in the month of December.
That's not to say that there won't be
some special circumstances
that need to have further discussion.
And we can talk about that,
but unless you can take care of the bulk of the decisions
in a way that doesn't require a long trial of some sort,
or a tremendously long and long set of meetings,
as long as you're only using those procedures
for a very small number of cases
that really are special circumstances
and deserve special attention,
we think then it's not a practical impossibility.
Maybe as a quick follow-up question,
so I absolutely understand that you have this notion of,
let's call it parametric coordination
that makes all of these processes very much easier
as you just stated,
but within these situations where the councils decide
over the proposals of each other,
and they do have these parametric indicators
that are at the end boiling down
to a ratio of social benefit and social costs,
which makes it easier to decide
whether something is really of social benefit or not.
What would be the mechanisms that allow
for going beyond this kind of parametric decision-making?
Because as you just stated,
there might be situations in which this is not sufficient.
This is not like addressing the specific context
of a given situation,
whether in a council or a workers council
or consumers council for that matter,
it might not be sufficient to address
the complete context of the situation.
So what would be the mechanisms to address things
that go beyond this parametric evaluation?
Yes, but there will be situations
where some sort of special consideration is warranted.
So what might that look like?
Before I answer that,
let me just summarize what it is that any worker council
or neighborhood consumer council has to do or not do.
It has to make its own initial proposal.
It has to revise that proposal, its own proposal.
And it has to revise that proposal maybe five or six times.
It also has to vote thumbs up or thumbs down
on all the other proposals.
Now, ordinarily thumbs up or thumbs down
is just if the other proposal
didn't have a social benefit to social cost ratio
that was at least one, our vote is thumbs down.
So it doesn't take a big thinking process.
So that's all that any worker council
or consumer council has to do for itself
and its own proposals.
And it's when they're voting thumbs up or thumbs down
that they're doing what a central planning agency
would do in a different kind of economy, okay?
But it shouldn't take any time.
Now, what about,
so here would be an example.
We have a worker's council and they've made their proposal
and if their social benefit to social cost ratio
is one or higher, they don't have to make any appeals.
They're gonna be approved.
It's not, it's only 0.9.
So it looks like somehow the social costs
of all the inputs they're using are larger than the social,
but they know that's wrong.
They believe this is wrong.
They believe the numbers lie.
I think we need to set up what I call appeal procedures.
So while the whole plan is being made,
it should be possible for a worker's council to say,
look, we know there's something going on
where the numbers are lying
and our proposal really is socially responsible
and we want the opportunity to explain that to somebody.
And so I think that you need to include that.
I mean, in a real world version of this,
you would have to allow for councils
to do that kind of appealing.
But notice what a successful appeal
isn't going to be presenting a whole long description
of how wonderful they think their workplace is
and how wonderful their ideas are.
No, no, a successful appeal will have to take the form of
the estimates of the social benefits and the social costs
is accurately, inaccurately measuring
something that we're doing.
And I think therefore, appeals,
as long as appeals are a small fraction
of what we have to deal with,
and as long as the appeal procedure
takes a very coherent form,
which is the applicant has to basically make a case
that they're being charged.
I mean, here being an easy example,
there's an opportunity cost
of using a particular kind of machine.
And they can say, well, it's right for most of the machines
of this kind, but ours are dilapidated.
So it looks like we're using things
that have a higher opportunity cost than it does,
because so essentially the appeal process
takes a form of challenging the accuracy
of what's being used to measure in the particular case.
The appeal procedure for a neighborhood consumption council
might also be on the grounds that,
although they could do this out of savings too.
So a neighborhood consumption council could say,
we were hit by a flood.
And sure, we could go ahead and say,
we need a lot of stuff for repairs,
and it comes out of our income,
and we can even go ahead and be approved to borrow,
but we really shouldn't even be charged for this.
I mean, we are victims of the disaster,
and therefore there needs to be an exception in our case
of what it is that we're asking for,
and we shouldn't have to pay for all of that
out of our entire income.
I mean, you could handle that
through disaster relief programs too,
but something that's not a disaster relief program magnitude
that might not qualify for it,
still is something that a neighborhood
consumption council could appeal.
For me, the trick is design a procedure
where it's only a tiny fraction of cases
where you would need appeals,
and then make sure that the appeal process is one
where the appeal process has some grounds for adjudication
that are sort of rational and make sense.
So we do have a feasible plan right now.
This plan has been approved by all of the different councils,
consumer councils and worker councils.
So maybe as an addition that the audience
has not yet have as an information,
the information that the different consumer
and producer councils have provided into the process,
this information is aggregated information.
It's not detailed information.
It's not that every consumer council has proposed
every detail of each good
and provided this information for the process,
but it's aggregated information.
So we are now within our imaginary planning process
at the point where we have a feasible plan.
It has been approved,
but the plan entails more or less broad informations
about what has to be produced.
What are the next steps?
How is this aggregated information transformed
into detailed products by the worker councils?
So on January 1st, we have a feasible,
efficient annual production plan,
but there's two problems.
There's still two problems.
One is at plan says the categories are gonna be categories
such as women's dress shoes.
It's not going to be size such and such.
It's not going to be, I don't remember what I called it,
but I had a funny name for it.
You know, the woman's leather high-heeled shoes
with the yellow toes problem.
So the plan is going to be in terms of sort of
broad categories of goods and services.
And yet you have to produce a particular shoe
that might be a little bit different.
How does that all get worked out during the year?
That's one question.
And another question that's, it's related.
It's a little different, but it's related.
And that is by January 15th,
something we assumed when we made the plan
isn't gonna be true anymore.
So there's both the, how do you translate
broad categories of goods into detailed categories of goods,
and how do you adjust for things that happen
that were not foreseen when the plan was drawn up?
And here's where the conversation has been very difficult
amongst leftists.
And I'll give you two examples.
The Jacobin dismissed the whole idea
of a participatory economy entirely on the grounds
that obviously planning, you know, for an economy
that has, they use the example on Amazon alone,
there's so many millions of different goods.
So how could you have a broad category of goods
so how could you ever plan for how much
of those millions of goods?
And that's just Amazon alone.
David Schweikert, who is a proponent of market socialism,
where he says, well, markets can handle this, but you can't.
Basically said, well, the whole thing is very interesting.
This idea of a participatory economy,
but it's just nonsense on stilts
because it can't handle this.
It's been 30 years now since there were any planned economies.
Now there's still a planned economy in Cuba.
I don't know what they have in North Korea,
but I think it's a planned economy.
So, but nobody knows anything about them anymore.
So in popular consciousness,
there's no memory anymore apparently that, you know,
the Soviet economy did actually manage, you know,
to plod along for, you know, going on 50 years
in the Eastern Europe.
And as anybody should now realize,
I'm not a proponent of that system,
but the whole notion that comprehensive planning
is just a practical impossibility is belied by the fact that,
well, it obviously wasn't a practical impossibility.
It might've been a very undesirable way to do things,
but it wasn't a practical impossibility
There must be some way to translate, you know,
from broader categories to more refined categories.
And there must be some way to make adjustments
during the year,
because there were a whole bunch of economies
that managed to do that for decades and decades.
Not to say they did it well,
and not to say that it wasn't,
and that some of the sort of obvious problems
that those economies had,
which, I mean, the major problem
that the centrally planned economies was that,
I mean, one major problem
was they really disenfranchised consumers.
So everybody's aware of the, oh yeah,
I mean, in the Soviet Union, you know, you could get shoes,
but everybody's shoes all look the same.
Well, by the end of the Soviet Union,
that wasn't really true.
On the other hand, the variety that capitalists
and market systems had to deal with,
the variety that capitalists
and market systems had to offer,
I don't think that variety was ever offered
by any centrally planned economy.
So it's a reasonable idea that maybe planned economies
are not as nimble in these regards.
But that's what it comes down to.
It's not like it's a practical impossibility.
We know that's the case.
Well, here's how you would translate.
So you have a plan,
you're a workers council and you're making shoes.
And you have a plan that's approved to you,
you know, that's been approved for you
to make certain amounts of shoes, you know, for adult women.
And you go ahead and make them.
And they get shipped to the distribution centers
and people start picking them up.
And it turns out that the red ones are going like hotcakes
and the yellow ones are just sitting on the shelf.
Well, you do just exactly
what any capitalist shoe making business does.
You know, you shift over
and you start making more of the red ones
and you make fewer of the yellow ones.
So in terms of detail,
it works out in a planned economy,
just the way, there's no reason it can't work out
in a planned economy that is sensitive
to what the consumers want.
Now, I mean, this is an interesting question.
And I do think that one of the things
that capitalism has done has disempowered consumers
relative to producers in all sorts of important ways.
So what it's gonna come down to is,
so I'm shipping shoes,
but the shoes I'm shipping aren't being picked up.
What if I don't change?
What if I continue to ship the yellow shoes
when the red ones are going like hotcakes?
Well, then the issue is, well, do I get credit for that?
And another issue is,
and this is sort of relevant to sort of empowering consumers.
One of the problems consumers face in market systems is
you didn't get something that you thought you were getting.
Now, of course, every capitalist business
mouths the slogan, the consumer is always right.
But it's totally insincere.
I mean, what they mean is,
we're gonna tell you you're always right,
but we're gonna make sure that we don't have
to exchange your product unless we absolutely have to,
and we're gonna make it as difficult as possible for you.
So, I mean, one of the things we've suggested is,
wouldn't it be nice if as a consumer,
something you get delivered isn't what you expected.
Instead of you fighting with the workers council
that produced that and delivered that,
you just turn it back over to your consumer federation,
say, it's unacceptable,
and let your consumer federation battle
in a much more powerful position with the workers council
and its federation about whether or not this was up to specs.
So my answer is, there are answers to these problems.
The popular consciousness,
we now have 30 years when none of these economies
that were comprehensively planned have existed.
And so people are having a hard time imagining
how it's even possible.
There's an analogy to this.
Before Adam Smith came along,
popular consciousness was, how could it possibly work?
How could a market system possibly work?
I mean, how will the producers know
what the consumers want?
So, I mean, feudalism made economic decisions
in a certain way, and Adam Smith was saying,
we don't need to make economic decisions that way at all.
We can just leave, we can have individual producers
and individual consumers out there,
and as long as they can buy and sell
from one another in a market, it's all gonna work out.
And there was a time in history
where people just had a hard time imagining that.
And he became famous for saying,
see, something you can't even imagine
is actually readily possible.
And I think we're back in a similar situation
where we're arguing
that you can do comprehensive planning.
It's not a practical impossibility,
but for 30 years, nobody has seen it
and everybody just can't imagine it anymore.
But I think we've got perfectly sensible answers
for how the more broad categories
get translated into more refined categories.
It's simply, when it's delivered,
some things will be picked up and purchased
and some things won't,
and you do sensible adjustments
when that turns out to be the case.
That means you're gonna have to order more red dye
and less yellow dye, and then that's an adjustment
that's gonna have to be made too.
My answer to the doubting Thomas's is,
that's not rocket science.
Do you really wanna argue about that?
I mean, maybe as an addition, you used the term
that the producers will need to be sensitive
to what people actually consume.
One might add that, I mean,
there are sensors proliferating throughout the world today,
and we have digital technologies,
information and communication technologies
that are very much able to sense much more
than was able before.
So this might also be a factor that comes into play.
That's something that is out there
in popular consciousness, and I think it's good,
which is that technologies have changed a lot
in terms of just supply-side management technologies
have changed a lot.
And the ability, I mean, I buy all my books,
I probably shouldn't admit to this
because I'm obviously not supporting
my local leftist bookstore.
But when I can buy a digital version
of a book I want on Amazon and get it on my Kindle
in literally five seconds, yes, I do that.
So there's been changes in technology
that basically make all of this adjustment stuff
a lot easier than it would have been 40 years ago.
But I wanna point out,
so I think that the things we're talking about
in terms of how speedy and efficient
can the detail and adjustment process be
given today's technologies as compared to 40 years ago,
actually a lot better.
But I don't wanna concede the point
that we could have still had this kind of economy
40 years ago.
It just wouldn't have been quite as quick and efficient
about making the adjustments,
but it would have been fine 40 years ago too.
It wasn't like the new,
we didn't have to wait for these new technologies.
And there's a similar,
sort of the socialist calculation debate
had a similar issue,
which was the original objection
to socialist economies that came from the Austrians
was, well, it's just too many equations.
You could never solve all the,
they were imagining central planning
and they were saying,
there's no way you could possibly solve all those equations.
And that's the beauty of the market system.
You don't need a huge computer.
And they were right that in 1900
when the debate was going on was like pre-World War I
and sort of post-World War I.
They were right that we didn't have powerful computers.
And people like Paul Cotshot and Alan Cottrell,
they've made the point,
but now we do have these computers.
So we could calculate a very, very detailed,
large central plan.
And my answer is, yes, we could now and we couldn't then,
but we still don't want to, but for different reasons,
just because we can do it doesn't mean we want to do it.
But in this case, yeah,
of course we would want to use all that new technology
to make the adjustment process.
You want to adjust for details,
you want to adjust for unseen events.
And if we've got new technologies
that would make all that easier and more efficient,
of course that makes the whole thing work better.
We should be very happy about that.
So now we have actually transformed
these aggregated information
into aggregated pieces for production,
inputs for production,
and they have been transformed into detailed products
by the workers councils.
And from there on, people will go to stores
just like they do nowadays
and will purchase these items,
depending on how much credit, so to speak,
they have coming from their work
within each workers council.
So I'm a consumer
and I had an annual consumption proposal
that's been pre-approved.
And so now, and I want to admit to something personally,
I don't shop.
There's only one thing I shop for,
I'm the cook in my family.
So I shop for, I go to food stores.
So I shop in food stores,
which is why I know how people shop,
because I don't think I've ever bought a piece of clothing
I've ever worn.
So I shop for books and I shop for food.
When I shop for, and when I shop for food,
I'm a bargain hunter.
So that's why I know when I go up and down the aisles,
I'm looking to see what the price tag on that thing is today.
And if it's not a sale price tag,
I'm gonna probably pass it up
and hope for something better tomorrow.
So that's why I know that when people shop,
you show them price signals and that's how they respond.
But the whole idea of sort of shopping
is really foreign to me.
And I had a group of students
who came into my office one day
and they said, well, we're in your class
and you've been talking about this participatory economy.
But there's just one thing that
we either don't understand or we don't like about it.
And what they said was,
you don't really understand the pleasures of mauling it.
And I thought they were saying maul, M-A-U-L.
And then it turned out, no, no,
they meant the pleasures of going to the shopping mall,
seeing and being seen and just deciding on the spot,
what do you wanna buy or not buy?
And I told them, I said, you're absolutely right.
Your dream is my nightmare,
being caught in a shopping mall for more than five minutes
it would be a death sentence as far as I'm concerned.
It's the last thing I'd ever wanna do.
But I understand, you have a reasonable demand here.
And so that is a question of how do you accommodate that?
And so the whole idea, I never thought about
how the goods are actually being picked up and distributed.
I just thought of people as,
well, you're going to your local food store
and that's how you get the food
that you're gonna go home and cook.
But there's no reason that you can't have shopping malls.
I remember at one point in time,
and I think it's still true in Cuba,
they used to do, they did these big displays.
They wanted to show people in Cuba,
what new kinds of goods might become soon available
that they hadn't been seeing for a while.
And so they would do these sort of demos.
And they would put on sort of like a fair
where the economic ministry was basically saying,
basically saying, come out to think
like a shopping mall thing,
we're gonna show you new products
so you're gonna see the kinds of things.
There's no reason that we can't,
those would all be good ideas.
But essentially my vision always was certain items
would get distributed to distribution centers,
which really are only for one neighborhood.
Other items is probably gonna have to cover
four or five neighborhoods,
the kinds of goods that get sent there to be distributed.
But I always envisioned is you're picking it up,
you've got your swipe card.
At some point along the line,
your swipe card starts to tell you
that you're actually picking up more of certain things
than that you had ordered.
Do you wanna make an adjustment
or is this just something that you're gonna make up for?
That's where the new technology really is,
really should help in making the adjustments.
But that's the kind of process that I think
from the point of view of a non-shopper,
that's about the best I can say.
Yeah, and I think it's quite important for many people
that there is some form of flexibility still
and that you do not,
that you're not hold to buying exactly the things
that you were thinking of at the beginning of the year,
but this could be done in a fashion where,
I don't know, if you achieve an amount of like 80 to 90%
of things that you already knew
that you will consume, this is very good.
And then if there rests 10 or 20% of goods
that you consume over the year
are those that are being consumed in a more dynamic
and flexible and spontaneous way,
then this is still an improvement, I guess.
So this doesn't have to be an either or situation.
I would concur, that's the way I think about it too.
There are two issues.
I mean, one is easy to take care of.
What if somebody during a year ends up
consuming less than they were,
I mean, the sum total social cost of what they consume
is less what they're approved for.
Well, that's easy.
Then it just goes into,
it adds to their savings and the savings account.
Now, what about somebody who ends up consuming more
than they were approved for during the year?
Well, in that case, they're basically borrowing.
And it's some, I mean, I don't think you ever have
to sit in judgment over us.
If somebody wants to save,
who the hell is ever gonna say no?
If somebody wants to borrow,
and oh, but you're borrowing every year
and you've been borrowing every year for 15 years
and it's kind of becoming clear
that you aren't really planning
or whether you're planning to pay it back
or you're just, you think you're planning to play it back
but it's becoming rather obvious to the rest of us
that you can't, somebody has to sit in judgment over this.
One of my daughters works for credit unions
and basically has, one of her jobs is
people taking out new car loans to buy new cars.
And so she's constantly watching cases where,
yeah, you thought you had a credible plan
about your payments, but in fact, you don't.
So I think of it more as you're still gonna have
something like credit unions
and a credit union is going to have to sort of,
they're gonna have to monitor
whether borrowing has become insincere.
But there's total flexibility about saving and borrowing
in terms of the grand sum total of what you're spending
in a year being different from what you proposed.
There's really no problem in handling that.
The difficulty is for particular items.
So if certain things, for a certain item,
the grand total amount that consumers
are taking off the shelves
is greater than what was planned for,
then we have a decision to make,
well, who's gonna get it and who isn't?
And there you would have a complicated,
I mean, there I think you have a somewhat complicated issue.
Well, I had it in my order
and so should I have priority over somebody
who didn't have it in their order.
And there's another issue about,
well, do we just also take care of this
by adjusting the price?
And in the latest book I wrote,
I sort of discussed these very,
what are the pros and cons of handling these situations
which will inevitably arise one way or another?
And I think there are some pros and cons
of handling it one way or another
and there are issues that will arise.
I mean, like from the tip of my head,
I would say like you could easily reserve some item
for a period of time
and if it's not consumed during this time period,
it will be free to consume for anybody else
who's interested in the item.
And then additionally, this question of pricing
comes into play, but that's just a side note.
There is a complimentary aspect
to this question of consumer flexibility
and that is the question of flexibility
on the side of producers
because another thing that the Austrians brought forward
and you mentioned them already
in the context of the socialist calculation debate,
another thing that the Austrians brought forward
is this question of competition as a discovery mechanism
and the question of how does innovation come into being,
into the world, into how is this idea
of the new being handled within an economic system?
So how would Perkin go about this process of innovation?
How is it being decided whether or not resources
can be allocated sensibly into a direction
which might not be like fully developed
where the odds are not clear
whether or not something might succeed or not.
So how is all of this being decided upon?
Yeah, by the way, the, I mean, the tooth,
that the whole Austrian school and the Austrian debate
in the popular consciousness in the United States,
it's quite different than in Europe.
In Europe, you all know the Austrian school,
you all know von Mises, you all know Hayek
and then you know the names of a few other people
who I don't.
In the United States, the only name we know in this regard
is somebody named Milton Friedman
who was not part of the Austrian school,
but who sort of,
he took their arguments,
dumbed them down, also screwed them up to a great extent
and basically that became sort of what his popular
consciousness about the impossibility of socialism
being sensible to a US audience.
So I just wanted to throw that out there in terms of,
there are certain subjects where,
I mean, it's the same as social democracy.
You all know what that means in the United States,
nobody knows what that means.
It's the same as libertarian socialism,
you all know what that means and in the United States,
it means something very different.
But anyway, to your question about innovation
and I think this is a very legitimate concern.
I think the conclusion
that the centrally planned socialist economies
were deficient in terms of their ability to generate
sort of innovative economic activities.
I think it's well taken.
And so when I study those systems to try and figure out,
well, what was it about their incentives?
What was it about their decision-making and reward systems
that led to such poor performance in this regard?
I think there was poor performance
and there have to be reasons for it
and it's important to understand what they were.
And so I spent a decent amount of time
studying the logic of central planning
and seeing why it would not be in the interest
of enterprise managers to innovate.
Why would they disguise their capabilities
rather than sort of try and stretch to?
Now, the first thing I would point out is
think of a worker's council in a participatory economy.
Anything they can do,
any innovation they could introduce
that would increase their social benefits
of what they're providing
or decrease the social costs of what they're using
is gonna rebound to their benefit
because it's gonna make it easier
to get their proposals accepted.
So if an enterprise could come up,
broadly speaking, there's two kinds of innovation.
One is anything that cuts down the costs
of what we're making
or anything that increases the sort of quality
and the quantity of what we're producing.
So we certainly have incentives
for workers councils to be searching for all those things.
Here is where there's a real dilemma though.
What if a worker's council comes up with a new innovation
that reduces its social costs
or increases its social benefits?
And any economy faces this dilemma.
So we have one unit that came up with the innovation.
It's very inefficient if the innovation
doesn't get immediately used
by all the other worker councils in the industry.
I mean, to have one council in the industry
doing something that's more efficient
and the rest of them aren't allowed to,
well, that seems silly.
And yet that's what patents do.
That's essentially what a patent does.
Now, maybe not forever,
maybe the patent only lasts for 20 years.
And once you have the patent,
you could sort of negotiate with other firms in the industry
and you could negotiate a price
and also allow them to use the patent for a certain payment.
But essentially what patents do
is they slow down the spread of innovation.
Oh, but they also provide a tremendous incentive to innovate
and that's the argument in favor of patents.
So my first observation is you really cannot have,
it seems like you can't have your cake and eat it too.
If you want what economists call static efficiency,
you want everybody to use the innovation
as quickly as possible.
But if you want quote unquote dynamic efficiency,
incentive to search for the innovation,
then you have to prevent it spread.
So it seems like there's a trade-off
between these two goals.
Well, we've taken one extreme position on this,
which is any innovation immediately
becomes available to everybody else.
So we're gonna spread immediately.
Does that diminish the incentive
for an enterprise, for a workers council
to look for innovations
because they basically can't sort of hoard it?
And I think maybe it does.
I mean, I think we have to honestly say, well, okay,
let's consider the consequence of immediately saying
all innovations are open to anybody.
And then the question is, well, what can you do?
And my answer is there's still two things you can do.
One is if you actually take a look at research,
a lot of innovative research in the United States,
in the United States,
there's sort of famous studies about innovation.
And what they've discovered is
the federal government of the United States
has paid for so much more innovation than anybody realizes.
Everybody thinks it's that creative entrepreneur out there
who did the innovation.
You'd be amazing how much your tax dollars
paid for innovation.
You'd be amazing at how much innovation
your tax dollars paid in the US military,
that became important innovation throughout the economy.
So there's another way to stimulate innovation,
which is basically just to pay for it.
So why shouldn't we have industry federations
with very large research institutes attached and budgets?
And why just have industry federations with that?
A lot of the innovations have to do with new products
from a consumer's point of view.
Let's have the consumer federations
also have very large research institutes
that are associated with them.
And then any research that those federations
manage to come up with, innovations that they...
Well, then of course, those federations...
It immediately goes to all the enterprises in the federation
because that's who the members of the federation are.
So that's one way.
And the other way is, and I've said this,
I think it would be very important
for a participatory economy to keep very close tabs
on whether they think that the economy
is sort of lacking for innovation.
And despite the fact
that they've got these big research institutes,
and despite the fact that if you can come up with a way
to improve your social benefit to social cost ratio,
it's to your advantage,
but everybody else is gonna get to use it right away too.
So if that proves to be a problem,
is there something we could still do?
And I think there is.
You simply grant prizes for innovation
to individual worker councils.
So if you need to dangle a sort of material benefit out there
for individual worker council innovation,
there's no reason you can't do it.
I would argue you're doing it at the expense of fairness.
I mean, it depends.
If you think that innovation is the result of extra effort,
then in some sense, it's not even at the expense
of economic justice if you're paying bonuses
for innovations coming from enterprise.
On the other hand, if you think that innovation
is largely not a result of that,
it's sort of luck and innovations are basically,
what they really are is it's a whole sort of process
through time that takes place.
And it's hard to say any particular person
was responsible for this whole thing.
And then I think that would simply
have to be a decision-making.
If the people in the economy felt
we're not being innovative enough,
we need to do something further,
then there's something you could do.
I would just quite, I think it's important
to always be honest about what you're doing,
at least with yourself.
And in this case, I think that what you might do is say,
we're worried about innovation,
we're putting a priority on it,
and we recognize that to some extent,
it might be at the expense of sort of economic justice.
I think there are plenty of ways to go about this.
And some of those you sketched,
I would definitely totally agree with.
And I think that additionally,
there might be some type of kind of crowdfunding.
There might be some budgets that are explicitly put away
for like some wildcard kind of stuff
where people that have an idea, an initial idea,
and that like carry some form of risk
in the form of resources that are needed
and that are not already like covered
in some way, shape or form,
that might apply for this kind of funding
and that is specifically put away
for like wildcard innovation or something like that.
Crowdfunding is very popular in the younger generation
and it's a pretty big deal.
There's a lot of it that goes on.
The crowdfunding that I am most impressed by
is that in our elections in the United States,
Republican candidates traditionally always get,
are much more adequately funded
than Democratic party candidates
because they're getting the big corporations
and the wealthy contributions.
And we basically don't prohibit that.
We don't say there are limits
or it's easy to get around the limits.
But one of the things that's happened basically
with the Bernie Sanders campaign
is that small donation funding for progressive candidates
has proved to be,
partly it's because of the rise of the internet too,
has proved to be remarkably,
it's even the money spending field
in a lot of races in the United States over recently.
And I know, and there's all sorts
of socially worthy projects and business ideas
that have successfully fundraised in this way.
So there's actually been a debate about
whether this would be a good idea or a bad idea
or what the pros and cons of it are on equity grounds
on the participatoryeconomy.org website.
Because there's a lot of people
that are interested in this.
Sometimes crowdfunding basically allows the person
who has donated to get a share of whatever comes out of it.
So there's two kinds of crowdfunding.
One is it's basically, it's just a donation.
And the other is, no, you're actually,
in some sense, you're buying into the business.
And at some point you would get some reward
for having done that.
And those are two very different things
in terms of what the equity implications are.
It could also be implemented on a structural level,
because when I was thinking about crowdfunding,
it's not in the typical sense
that you would have to take some of your money
and put it into a crowdfunding project
or something like that.
But it could be implemented on a structural level
where each and everybody gets a certain amount of tokens
that you cannot spend for anything else,
that those are associated with some form of fund
for innovators who are kind of trying to test out new ideas
and stuff like that.
So this would be a slightly different type of scheme.
And one of the outputs for the people
who put in the tokens for a given project
could be that they might simply get the use value
that is being produced earlier than the others
or something like that.
But this is a sidetrack, I would say.
Yes, I mean, when I was thinking of research,
when I was thinking of Workers' Federations
having large research enterprises
that are affiliated with them,
I was thinking of them funding that.
And I was thinking the same thing on the consumer side.
On the other hand, you could basically have...
The tokens could be basically tokens
that individuals are saying, I want that research.
I'm putting my token toward that research.
Yeah.
And another question that I was asking myself
in terms of what you call user rights,
how do you distribute user rights over a given comments
so that whoever can make the best use of the comments
is actually allocated the right to use it?
Because this is a difficult question.
I mean, there might be many people
who propose to use a given comments that is there to use,
and it's difficult to decide who might actually get it.
This is the same subject as, well,
public versus private ownership.
So let's step back to sort of old socialist times.
The first thing that the old socialists used to say is,
well, the means of production need to be...
The means of production shouldn't be in private hands.
The means of production should be socially owned.
And what kind of means of production
were they thinking about?
I mean, they were thinking about the factories
and the machines and the factories.
They shouldn't belong to the capitalist.
They should belong to all of the workers collectively.
That means the economy still has to figure out
how to assign a particular factory or a particular machine
to be used by this group of workers
or that group of workers.
And that's what the plan supposedly does.
Well, I mean, that also applies to land.
I mean, land is like a machine.
You use land to grow food.
And in the Soviet Union, I mean,
I was thinking the other day in the early Soviet Union,
I mean, what actually produced the Russian Revolution
was when the peasants actually took over the land.
It was 80% of the population.
There's no Russian Revolution except the peasants say,
the feudal lords who used to own the land
and we worked on it as serfs
and then we became free to serfs
and we basically had to pay them rent.
We're taking it over.
And then they set up, sometimes they set up state farms.
That was the form in which the land is public was manifest.
Sometimes they set up collective farms,
which were somewhat different in terms of
how the land was handled on a collective farm
than a state farm.
But certainly we have a sort of a history
of socialist believe that that land
and those factory and those machines,
it's what I call part of the productive commons
and it belongs to everybody and nobody.
And the issue simply is figuring out
who gets user rights over it
on what sort of basis.
And that's what the plan does.
So if you look at our participatory planning process
and if you're a worker council
and you're proposing to produce so many tomatoes
and so many heads of lettuce,
then you're also saying, well, one of the inputs is
we want these many acres of lands, et cetera, et cetera.
And we don't want you to grow tomatoes on it
if it would be better for avocados.
And if there's another worker council
that is wanting to land for avocados,
then they're gonna put in a proposal saying,
we wanna use it.
So that's the importance of we wanna know
what the opportunity cost of using that land is
because we want it to go,
we want a system that will assign it
to whichever workers council
can make the most socially productive use of it.
And I think that's part of what the planning process
is actually doing.
Now, there's another part of the productive commons
that has been a lot trickier.
So there was the traditional ideas
of the machines in the factory
and that sort of extends to land.
But there's also that, I mean,
mainstream economists will call natural resources,
they call them natural capital.
So you have produce capital machines, buildings,
you have natural capital and then you have human capital.
And human capital is sort of my native talents
and my education and my training
is what gives a particular person
a certain amount of human capital.
Well, should that be socially owned?
Should we view that in the same way
that we view the machines and the factories
and the land and the natural capital
as it belongs to everybody and nobody?
No, it's me.
I mean, it's mine.
Well, how's that any different
from the way people used to think of this land is mine?
This machine is mine.
That's the part I think that sort of
both politically and philosophically
and personally and psychologically becomes more difficult
for people to think in the same terms.
We have argued that it's all the same.
And so we sort of said,
it's all part of the productive commons
and it doesn't belong to anybody or it belongs neither,
it belongs both to all of us and none of us.
And the question is simply how to use it
and how in a planning procedure to award user rights over it.
There's of course a debate about,
I mean, when you're thinking about compensation,
there's been a long debate among socialists
about whether, well, if I have more human capital
and therefore the social value of my contribution
when I work an hour is higher than yours,
then I deserve higher pay.
And then there are people who've argued,
no, that actually isn't, you don't deserve higher pay.
You deserve higher pay if you made greater sacrifices maybe,
but not simply because you have more human capital
than somebody else.
So those arguments have gone on forever amongst socialists.
And what it reduces to is whether or not human capital
is are we gonna now consider human capital
the same way we consider natural capital,
the same way we consider produce capital
as it belongs to all of us and none of us.
It's something we collectively in our generation
inherit from all those previous generations before us.
And that's how it should be treated.
And we wanna design an economic system
that treats it all that way.
And that's been our vision and that's been our argument.
But I know in terms of coming up,
I know that in terms of meeting opposition
from some fellow socialists
about whether or not they agree or don't agree
that this is an area of great disagreement.
And when you think about it,
of course we know it's an area of great disagreement.
It was hotly debated in the Soviet Union for 50 years
where there were time periods
when there were big bonuses given out to people,
to engineers and people, I mean, one of Stalin's,
in the early days, it was sort of,
well, everybody gets paid the same
and maybe we'll all argue about
everybody's gotta put in more effort
and we'll fight with each other
about you're slacking off and I, et cetera, et cetera.
But there was no sort of,
in the early days of the Russian revolution,
there wasn't strong support
for the more highly educated and the engineers
getting much higher pay scales.
Whereas at some point during the 30s and the 40s
and the 50s, that became,
Gorbachev finally sort of voiced
that as what socialism was.
He literally said that we,
people deserve to be paid
according to the value of their social contribution
and some people's social contribution
is objectively higher than other people
and it's perfectly fair that they be paid more
and they should be paid more.
Gorbachev finally arrived at the point of just saying,
that's what the, that's the justification.
We're doing it and we should be doing it.
Whereas I think that I would always have argued
against that as being fair
and I think many socialists throughout history
have also felt no, that isn't particularly fair.
And just to check back whether or not I do get it right.
So like very specifically on the question
of how it is being decided upon
who gets user rights over a given comments
and you already explained that your notion of the comments
is a very like enlarged version of the comments actually.
So the answer to the question
of how this is being decided upon
is again, this question of social benefit.
So whether or not a given resource
is actually being used in a way
so that the social benefit is higher than the social cost
and the way that this is being calculated
is along the lines of opportunity costs.
Do I get that right?
Just to check it out.
Yeah, I wrote an article where I talked about it as,
I talked about it as the productive commons
for modern times.
I think there was a time period
when socialists thought about the commons,
they just thought about the machines in the factory
and land.
And now what we, I mean, modern times requires us
to think about the productive column.
So I'll list everything that's in the productive commons.
It's those machines in the factories, just like always.
It's land.
It's any other natural resources,
including that big thing up there
that is storing all our greenhouse gases,
which is basically like a commons
that whenever you use it and exploit it,
it's something that we need to take account of.
I think that everything that mainstream economists
call human capital is part of the productive commons.
And technology is part of the productive commons.
And that's when we were talking about patent rights
and who gets to use it.
And then we were talking about it in the context
of sort of stimulating innovation.
Whatever clever ways we have come up
with making things in the past.
So all of that is part of what I simply call
the productive commons.
And it doesn't belong any more to one person than another.
But it's important that we want to allocate user rights
over it to whoever can make the most efficient use of it.
But nobody gets to reap the rewards personally
of the fact that they're using it.
So if we give the machines to the workers in this factory
because they can make the best use of that machine,
that doesn't mean the workers in this factory
get higher income than the workers in some other factory.
And here's the real hard dividing line.
So in our annual planning process,
we're going to come up with the estimates
of the opportunity cost of using an hour
of electrical engineering labor.
And we're going to come up with the opportunity cost
of using an hour of carpentry labor.
of using an hour of just ditch digging labor.
And they aren't going to be the same.
Now does that make sense?
Now does that mean that somebody in our economy
that digs ditches or works as an electrical engineer
or works as a carpenter is going to get paid higher wages?
And our answer is no.
That'll be depending on inside their worker council,
whatever procedures their fellow workers set up
to decide whether they're putting in extra effort,
working extra hours,
working under less favorable or desirable conditions.
So that's the way that we think there is,
we think it's a separate logic
for how you allocate user rights over things,
including different categories of labor that doesn't,
but that doesn't have to,
for different categories of labor,
it does not have to translate into
that's how we therefore pay people differently.
Which at a certain point in the early 1940s,
Stalin was just advocating
for those who were fortunate enough
to get the engineering degrees
and have those skilled kinds of labor
in the Soviet economy during that time period.
I know the early years of the Cuban revolution
and when Che Guevara was still around,
they were very clear on this point.
And the Cubans always had an attitude about it.
I mean, their attitude about it in the early years
in the Cuban revolution was we only have the resources
to send so many people to school to become doctors
or to become engineers.
And anybody that we sent to school doing that,
they're already lucky.
They're the ones that got the extra education
and we couldn't give it to everybody.
And they owe society.
So the whole idea that you were lucky
that you were the one that was trained to be a doctor,
we have every right to send you out to work
for five years in the countryside,
giving, making sure that little kids
don't die from dehydration.
I mean, that's fair.
The idea that you deserve to be paid 10 times more
than somebody who didn't get that extra education.
In the early years of the Cuban revolution,
there was a very broad consciousness.
I think there still is in Cuba
of a relatively healthy consciousness,
I would call it on this subject.
I think before we move on to the more long-term questions,
long-term questions, actually,
I think it would be important maybe in order to close
the case of the basic elements of Paragon
to take a closer look at some elements
we kind of touched upon,
but haven't yet really talked through.
One of those would be balanced job complexes
because this is actually a very important basic principle
within Paragon as well.
And we haven't actually laid it out in concrete terms,
I think.
So maybe could you explain what are balanced job complexes
and why do you think that they are a good idea to implement?
Okay, there's two different issues.
You can balance jobs in two respects.
One would be for empowerment
and the other would be for desirability
or undesirability, whatever.
So first, let's look at how it is
that most jobs look in capitalism.
We could also look and see how do most jobs look
in the centrally planned socialist economies too.
In both cases, what you find is that
a small percentage of a workplace
have jobs that consists of a number of tasks
and sort of approximately how many hours a week
you work in these different tasks.
These are tasks where you're sitting in on meetings,
where you're going over different options
for what might happen.
Or these would be tasks where you're just,
I used to work in steel mills in the summers
when I was going to college.
And they would throw us into the crews
where we would have to go out
and underneath the open hearth furnaces,
all of this sort of burnt coal ash would come down.
And at some point the tunnels would fill up
and you have to send somebody in there
to shovel it out into wheelbarrows.
Rote labor, not pleasant, nothing empowering about it.
It just made your muscles sore when you went home at night.
So in almost any capitalist workplace you go to
and I think in most of the centrally planned economies,
certainly by the second half of the 20th century,
what you're gonna find is you've got a small number of people
who do managerial type tasks.
And then you've got most of the people
just carrying out somebody's orders,
doing something that's more or less mind numbing.
Well, clearly some tasks empower people
to be both more knowledgeable about the kinds of decisions
that have to be made in enterprise
and to sort of have the skills and habits
to be effective in expressing their opinions on the subject.
So the whole idea that, well, we want our workers councils.
We're giving everybody one vote.
Ultimately, we're saying at a stockholders meeting
in a capitalist corporation,
ultimately you get as many votes
as you have shares of stock.
In a workers council, everybody gets one vote.
But if you have some people doing all of these empowering
tasks day in and out and you have other people
in the workplace doing these rote sort of mindless jobs
day in and day out, then clearly although they have
an equal right to vote in the meetings,
they aren't gonna arrive at those meetings
sort of equally empowered to be effective in the meetings.
This is something that, I mean, in Yugoslavia,
we had a 20, 30 year experience
with workers self-management in enterprises.
And one of the very discouraging trends
was that in the early years,
there was a lot more active participation
on the part of a much larger percentage
of workers in the enterprise.
And as time went on, all the sociological studies
about the activity of the participation declined over time.
And I think there was a reason for that,
that they didn't balance jobs for empowerment.
They made no particular effort to do that.
So if you really want what I would call
real workplace democracy rather than just formal,
everybody gets one vote democracy,
then there's a very strong argument
that I think socialists should want to see.
Job descriptions revised so that to the extent
that it's reasonable and possible,
you want to include empowering tasks
along with disempowering tasks
in everybody's job description.
And does that mean that in a hospital,
sometimes a surgeon might actually have to spend
some hours changing bedpans?
My answer is yes.
And then we can argue about whether that's
not a very inefficient use of that skilled surgeon's time.
But any case, so that's what the balancing
for empowerment about.
It's basically saying if you look at our,
if you look at both capitalism and state socialism,
really was a remarkable similarity
in terms of how jobs were structured
and the fact that some of them,
a small number of them were rather empowered,
had the effect of empowering the people
who carried out those tasks.
And for most people, the effect was to disempower you
in terms of your, in any case.
Now that's a little different from desirability.
So the argument in favor of empowering for desirability
is that's how you encourage and make sure
that you don't have an erosion of the exercise
of economic democracy in the workplaces.
Balancing for desirability is an equity issue.
And there is another way of taking care of that
and that is the worker's council.
So, I mean, where does that come from?
Well, why should somebody's job be remarkably,
why should somebody's job be much more unpleasant
than somebody else's job?
Where's the justice in that?
So you can put the question simply that way.
And my answer would be there is no justice in that
unless there was some compensation.
So that's where there is sort of an alternative way
to take care of the injustice if somebody's job
has a whole bunch of tasks that are really unpleasant
and somebody else's job never has any tasks
that are unpleasant, the changing bedpans.
In that case, you could compensate the person
that has the job that is less pleasant to perform.
And you could say that's part of why somebody
would deserve greater compensation.
So in that case, there's two ways of taking care of it.
Our actual proposal is, we basically propose
consciousness raising amongst workers
about these issues in their workplace.
And we propose that we think you should set up,
like we used to, originally we just called them
effort rating companies.
We just called them effort rating committees.
But we were thinking more along the lines
of sort of any differential sacrifice.
And we think you should set up procedures
for trying to balance the tasks and the time people
are spending in tasks so that you,
so that you don't have this terrible imbalance
in terms of the empowerment effects of work life.
But you obviously are gonna have to go about this
as you see fit.
So these are what I call injunctions and arguments.
But the bottom line is, nobody from the outside
is coming in and telling you how you do it.
And if push comes to shove and a workplace,
a bunch of workplace council and then a workers council
doesn't wanna do these things,
I would be very loathe to say somehow you get called up
before a tribunal and put on trial for it.
I mean, if you don't do them, you don't do them.
In our mind, they're part of what socialism should be like
and should be about.
But we're very libertarian in our anarchist tendencies
in terms of whether this is something that is imposed
or this is something that we are talking about
building a culture for.
Yeah, and I think at least for me,
the last statements are very important to me,
I have to say, because I'm not a big fan
of the effort-raiding committees, to be honest,
because I sense the real danger of this becoming real ugly
and creating some form of toxic workplace.
And I would very much advise
anyone to not go this road,
but I very much appreciate that within Paragon,
you give this kind of flexibility
in order to approach the things that you recommend
in the terms of, for example, balance,
job complexes or effort-raiding committees.
But if a worker council does have a different type
of culture within the given worker council
and wants to do things differently,
this is absolutely compatible with Paragon
as such, as I understand it.
Well, there's the largest actual experience
of a group of workplaces trying to apply these principles,
including, and in particular, the job balancing,
balancing for both empowerment and balancing for,
you know, for desirability and effort-raiding.
There was a lot of, you know,
there was a whole network of,
they were called the Mondragon, it was called the A-Zone,
and they were called the Mondragon,
not to be confused with the Mondragon cooperatives
in the Basque region of Spain.
And I'm not quite sure why they chose,
I think they might've chose the word Mondragon in Winnipeg
in sort of honor of that,
but they're very, very different.
And there was a coffee house, a restaurant,
a radio station, a bicycle repair,
sort of a delivery business.
And they all were in this sort of,
they all had offices in this sort of building
that they jointly had,
and they very self-consciously tried to operate
their collectives on the basis of paragon principles.
They did it for about 20 years.
And so I'm aware of debates and discussions
that went on amongst them.
One of the founders, Paul Burroughs,
has gone on to do some other things,
but he now is,
he's now been active back on the forum
on the participatoryeconomy.org website,
discussing exactly this thing.
Because it is one of the things
that has been most controversial.
And I can say that what Mondragon ended up doing
was not really trying to do
any sort of detailed effort rating.
They argued about it a lot.
It was quite controversial.
And they ended up saying,
no, it's gonna come down to hours.
And if there's a real problem with just,
you're not putting in effort,
then it's an issue of firing,
it's an issue of the rest of us saying,
this is just too detrimental to the rest of us.
You either have to ship up or you have to shape up
or you really shouldn't be working here anymore.
Rather than sort of having an effort rating committee
where at the end of every six months or so.
So I know that's what they came up with.
I am sure that, here's my dilemma.
My dilemma is the following.
Those of us who are even talking about it,
we've already decided that we're leftists and we're socialists.
And therefore, we don't think it should be necessary
to get into this kind of invidious comparisons.
And we would just find it toxic.
And my answer to all of us is I have two,
and I have two things to say about that.
Just like you, when I go to search for a worker's council
to work for in a participatory economy,
I will look for one that adopts that attitude
toward effort rating.
Because that'll make me happiest there.
I mean, one of the things that people should look at,
I mean, people do this in capitalism.
They look to see, well, what's your pay structure
and how are you gonna, when can I first put in
for a promotion?
So I think one of the things that people will sensibly look
at in a participatory economy when they decide
where they want to apply to a workplace is
to look and see what is the workplace's procedures
in this regard or the ones I would like
or the ones I would feel comfortable with or not.
But here's my dilemma.
I talk to people who would not be comfortable
in a work environment where they think
that people who don't work as hard
are gonna get just as rewarded as they are.
And I know that they would want some sort of procedures
where slackers would be identified by fellow workers
and would be told, look, it's okay
if you don't wanna work as hard.
But please recognize that that means
you shouldn't be rewarded quite as much.
So that's another issue.
And the usual way of handling this,
I mean, the way it was always handled
in the Soviet Union was everybody should be working
harder than anybody can imagine.
And I mean, I grew up as an, I grew up
as enough of a hippie to know that is insane.
That's not a good life.
So there's nothing wrong with somebody saying,
hey, you wanna go out there and bust your hump?
That's fine.
I don't have to do that.
I don't wanna, I don't choose to do that.
On the other hand, I think one should concede
that if somebody else is making more sacrifices
then they deserve some degree of extra compensation
that's commensurate with that.
And it is my personal choice.
So I wanna give people the,
I wanna preserve personal choice
over how much effort people put into work.
But I think there's a responsible way to do that,
which is I choose more, I mean, we know there's a sort
of choose between leisure and income,
who we think of it as in terms of hours.
You can also choose between leisurely pace of work
and income.
There's no reason people shouldn't make,
people should have the right to choose that.
They make that choice for themselves.
Why not?
There's nothing socially irresponsible about saying
I want a more leisurely pace of work,
but my more leisurely pace of work,
I think basically entitles me to what I'm saying is
I want that more leisurely pace of work.
And yes, I accept somewhat less compensation
for the fact that it's not as big a sacrifice
as somebody else is making.
So that's where that all has landed.
In the end, we leave it up to workers councils.
We recommend that people take that into consideration.
When you decide where to apply to work,
you wanna go to work someplace
where they have the same values on that,
where they've come to the same set of values on that subject
that you feel that you're comfortable with.
But I do know that there are people out there
who are very loathe to think that this system
would be a good system that they would be happy in.
If they imagine themselves working in a place
where they work hard and other people don't,
and the other people get away with it
and get paid the same as them.
And they find that something, I don't like that system.
And I think there's a point to be made there too.
I also think there's a real bias.
Those of us who even talk about this
clearly are more inclined to don't wanna get into it.
People will be responsible.
And if they're really irresponsible,
then you admonish them in some sort of way.
You give them a warning and finally you just say,
well, you just don't wanna,
the rest of us don't wanna work with you.
But I think that there's a real,
I think that leftists are predictably farther
in that direction than your average person out there
in the population that we talk to
about different economic systems.
Cause I know this reaction to the students in my classes.
Cause students in my classes are basically
the average US population in some sense.
They're, a tiny percentage of them are leftists.
And I know from their reaction over the years,
they find it comforting that there'd be procedures
to distinguish between people who are working hard
and people who aren't.
Yeah, I think I subsumed this also somehow
under the question of transition,
because the way that you approach it
by providing a plurality of approaches
to different people who might be in a different
state of mind towards these questions
so that they can build it in a way that works for them
for the moment.
I mean, this also includes some danger, of course,
in the sense that it might lead to structures
that reproduce this kind of thinking
that you just described from your students,
this kind of like a bit greedy and competitive type
of behavior of thinking about one another.
And there's this danger of like reproducing this
by producing institutions and structures
within a given workers council that, as I said,
produces this kind of thinking as well.
But as I said, I absolutely appreciate this plurality
and my vote would go out for not like going down the road
of effort-raiding committees.
And also in terms of sacrifice and effort,
I find it very difficult to really evaluate
whether or not someone is putting in effort or not,
because this could look very differently
for a different type of person.
And at some point within your newest book,
you also write, but are people equally able to sacrifice
or is it easier for some to make sacrifices
than it is for others, just as it is easier
for some to perform difficult and valuable physical
or mental tasks than it is for others?
And then you state questions such as these make me happy.
I'm not a philosopher.
What can one say except perhaps, end quote.
And I would add to this, perhaps I would say for sure,
I'm quite sure that it is actually impossible
to really evaluate whether someone is putting in effort
and not, and to some people it comes more naturally
at different things and to others not.
So I would actually be kind of skeptical,
but as I said, I highly appreciate this flexibility
within your approach.
So-
There's actually a very active debate
amongst the collective that manages the,
actually one of the two brothers
who are the most active managers of the website.
Jason raised that on the discussion forum
and said that he thinks that there's a discussion
about whether we should stop using the word effort
in this regard.
Yeah, but it's not an easy issue.
It's not an easy issue.
And it is one that people care tremendously about.
And it's also one where you don't,
it's also one where, I mean, when we're starting
to talk about opportunity costs and social costs,
and whether a planning mechanism will do this or that,
well, I mean, there it requires some expertise.
This isn't any subject that anybody feels
requires any expertise they don't have,
which I always appreciate a subject where everybody thinks
that they are equally equipped to argue and debate,
and their view is just as valid as anybody else.
I think it's lucky when we have a subject
where everybody thinks that way about it.
And I think this is one of those subjects.
Everybody has a very firm opinion
about what they think is fair and not fair
in terms of economic compensation.
Interesting.
One question that I have in the back of my mind
all of the time when you're talking about
like the ways in which these workers councils
are organized internally,
how you might achieve self-management and so on and so forth
is the question of scaling.
So how big can these councils actually become
in order to stay true to these principles
that you would like to see being enacted
within these worker councils?
Because people who have experiences
with self-organized structures,
they might know that this is very much difficult.
It's very, very difficult to achieve
like organizations of scale
that are actually really true to principles
that Perikan tries to promote.
So how do you think about this question of scale?
The simple answer is we're agnostic on that subject.
But that doesn't mean,
there seem to be some things
that clearly the smaller the workers council,
the easier it is for people,
for everybody to participate in all aspects.
So you can ask yourself,
is there an optimal size
just in terms of how would
participatory democratic decision-making procedures
function best?
Obviously from a technology production side,
there's also issues about scale.
And here there's a useful difference.
I mean, economists talk about true economies of scale,
which can be distinguished
from financial economies of scale.
So in a capitalist economy,
there are frequently advantages of being larger,
like being an oligopoly or a monopoly even.
Not necessarily because the technology dictates it.
So we wouldn't want workers councils
to become large for what in capitalism
would be financial economies of scale reasons.
But in terms of social costs
and lowest social cost of production,
there are true economies of scale
where probably the efficient size
for a workers council producing steel
is different from the efficient size
for a workers council that's a haircut salon.
So when I said we're agnostic,
we just, we recognize all that.
And we don't think, I mean,
so suppose you have a workers council
where true economies of scale are significant.
And so we're really talking about an enterprise
that makes sense that has a couple of thousand members.
Well, then you clearly would have to sort of,
you're going to have different divisions.
I mean, something that large is going to have different,
I mean, in a steel mill, there was the blast furnace,
there's the open hearth furnace,
there's the warehouses,
there's the sheet metal cutting places.
So there's all these sort of divisions.
And in a large enterprise,
you would want to have sort of sub worker councils,
for the different divisions.
There's a whole bunch of decisions in the blast furnace area
that really don't affect the rest of the plant that much.
But it seems like that, I mean, so that is our approach.
That would be the sensible way to approach that.
The only thing that should not come into play
are in capitalist economies,
financial economies of scale,
sometimes give you extra market power advantages.
And that's why a firm will get that big.
And certainly, and we don't think that any workers council,
Mondragon set up operations in China.
And the Chinese operation was not self-managed
by Chinese workers at the Mondragon place in China.
So that's for both, that you can't have.
So you're not, I mean,
a lot of the world's large corporations are now global.
And so we're not talking about that at all.
None of these worker councils
are operating outside of the country.
In general, so there would not be any-
Well, they can export, they can import.
I mean, there's a chapter in the last,
in democratic economic planning
that addresses the sort of new practical issue.
There was a point in time when socialists thought that
when socialism finally came to power any place,
the idea was gonna be so obviously wonderful
that the workers were gonna revolt every place
and we were gonna have socialism everywhere.
Even Lenin thought there were gonna be revolutions
in Germany and Europe,
and that they weren't gonna have an isolated Soviet Union.
And Trotskyists for a long time argued
that you really can't have socialism in one country.
Well, it's apparent now
that if we can't have socialism in one country at a time,
we're never gonna have it,
because at this point in the 20th century,
it's very clear to me that it's highly unlikely
that we aren't gonna have,
who knows what country it's going to be,
but countries are gonna try and become socialist
in a world where there are still huge differences
in levels of economic development
and where a lot of the countries are capitalist countries
that they have to interact with.
And then the question is, how do you interact?
So we finally address that in the most recent book,
we'd never talked about it before,
and sort of proposed how could a socialist,
a country with a socialist economy
take part in international trade
in a way that was beneficial to them,
but didn't violate their fundamental principles
in some way that eroded the sort of moral
and political glue that held their system together.
And we basically said,
the one thing that's ruled out
is direct foreign investment.
You can't allow a capitalist firm coming
and come into a participatory economy
and set up a capitalist,
engage in direct foreign investment,
run as a capitalist firm inside the socialist economy.
And we said, we don't think workers councils
in the socialist economy
can basically do direct foreign investment abroad.
But we do think that there's no reason
that a participatory economy
couldn't trade with the rest of the world,
including trading with capitalist countries
and including taking into account dramatic differences
in levels of economic development
in terms of the terms of trade.
And even international financial investment
is something we think is possible
for a participatory economy to engage in.
And a participatory economy could engage
in international financial investment,
both outgoing and ingoing.
It's a question of how you treat the interest rate.
And with certain partners,
you have to treat the interest rate differently.
But that's not something that wasn't discussed.
I mean, there was a huge discussion
in Cuba used to lecture the Soviet Union
and the Eastern European economies
about the morality of the difference
between being a lesser developed country
and a more developed country.
I mean, Che Guevara was famous for just saying,
well, we assume that your socialist principles
will help you understand
why you should afford favorable terms of trade
towards your brother socialist Cuban economy.
Now, to some extent, the Soviet Union did do that,
but more for geopolitical purposes
than commitments to socialist principles.
But in any case, this isn't something
that hasn't been discussed before.
But I do think that amongst socialist in 2020,
that discussion now has to be,
we now have a new perspective realism
about how socialism will eventually come to the world.
It'll come a little here and a little there.
And there's a long period of time
where you have to have some sensible answers
to how do those countries interact and economic,
how do they engage in economic interactions
with other countries?
You've got to have a more sensible discussion of that
than we've ever had before.
That was our show for today.
Thanks a lot for listening.
If you want to support future histories,
you can do so on Patreon.
For this, visit patreon.com slash future histories,
or you can simply tell a friend that you liked the show
and that he, she, or they might like it as well.
Thanks a lot and hear you in two weeks.