Welcome to Future Histories, my name is Jan Groß and it is my great pleasure to welcome Nick Dyer-Whitherford in today's episode.
Nick is professor at the Faculty of Information and Media Studies at the University of Western Ontario, Canada.
His work as an author include Cyber Marks, Cycles and Circuits of Struggle in High Technology Capitalism from 1999,
or Cyber Proletariat, Global Labour and the Digital Vortex from 2015,
and together with Alte, Mikola Kjosen and James Steinhof, In Human Power, Artificial Intelligence and the Future of Capitalism from 2019.
He was also an early and very important contributor to the revived debate around democratic economic planning,
which features quite prominently in future histories as well, with his 2013 paper Red Plenty Platforms.
And I'm absolutely thrilled and honoured to welcome Nick in today's episode, in which we will talk about his most recent work,
a paper on biocommunism titled Biocommie, Power and Catastrophe.
When recording the interview, I was a bit sick and you might hear it from time to time.
In my voice, I hope it didn't interfere too much with the coherence of my questions, though.
I pre-produced this episode for the summer, which means I'm not able to thank the most recent Patreon supporters and or donors by name.
And so I will take this as a chance to thank you all. Thank you for your interest in future histories.
Doing this is such a joy for me and being able to talk to wonderful people and thinkers like Nick every two weeks is simply such a pleasure
and an important part of my life that I wanted to take the chance to thank you all and, of course, thank all of my guests.
So now, please enjoy today's episode with Nick Dyer-Witherford on biocommunism.
Welcome, Nick.
Thanks for inviting me to the show, Jan. Future histories has been a great source of inspiration for me, sometimes in quite bleak times.
So it's a real pleasure to be on the show today.
Well, it's an absolute pleasure to have you, Nick. Thank you very much.
In your most recent work, you developed the concept of biocommunism, building on a term you introduced around a decade ago.
However, the way you use the term now is different from the way you used it back then.
Before we dive deeper into the different elements of what you propose as biocommunism today, how did you define biocommunism back then?
How do you define it now? And what made you rethink the way in which you define the concept?
Biocommunism is a term that, as far as I know, I was the first to use in a series of essays written in about the mid-2000s on Marx's concept of species being, Guttungswesen,
and about how it might be renovated and applied for the 21st century in the midst of capitalism's deployment of digital technologies, genetic transformations, and the like.
Now, those early papers on this topic, I think, can be characterized as optimistic.
They were informed by a sort of lingering, ultra-globalist sense that another world is possible by Hart and Negri's use of the term biopolitics in empire.
And they're suffused with an ethos of what would later be called accelerationism, the same sort of concepts and attitudes that generated works like Sermichek and Williams,
inventing the future, and Helen Hester's Xenotheminism, and Aaron Bustani's fully automated luxury communism.
So the thought ambiance was that there was a sort of technological momentum to capitalism in these digital and genetic technologies and new forms of energy production that would favor the creation of a post-capitalist communal society.
So then a few things happened, such as the 2008 financial crash, the rise and fall of Occupy, the ascent of the far right.
And amidst all this, I forgot about biocommunism until a couple of years ago, I was contacted out of the blue by a young scholar, a graduate student in Denmark,
who'd encountered another version of biocommunism independently developed in the work of the Polish philosopher Simon Robel.
And Philip asked me what, if anything, I was doing with the idea, and my answer was not much right now.
But his question remained with me like an earworm of what could biocommunism mean now in the 2020s?
So, of course, if one looks around in this context, some pretty disturbing things have been happening in regard to human species being a worldwide pandemic in full swing,
a huge economic slump with globally immiserating consequences, a European war between opposing nuclear armed blocs,
and then the increasingly desperate reports of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, whose warnings about the planetary biosphere are being given a concrete illustration
by daily disaster reports of fire, floods, heat waves, et cetera, across the entire planet.
It's a dire and calamitous scene.
And so my return to biocommunism really is an attempt to find a politics adequate to contemporary species being, but set against this far more somber horizon.
Now, I know we're going to go into some detail into the different components of this iteration of biocommunism,
but perhaps it might be useful just to quickly give your listeners a thumbnail of what I'm pointing at with this term.
I am attempting to hypothesize a new mode of beyond capitalism, collective social reproduction,
which I term biocommunism, and I conceive of as a process of combined social and environmental leveling,
creating a social system that steers itself between double boundaries of ecological sustainability and equalized social development
and does so through processes of collective and democratic social planning.
So this is, biocommunism is a program that fuses the goals of contemporary movements fighting against ecocide and inequality.
It is what one might term a project of ecological equality, equalizing and ecological power.
I attempt to propose a system in which the state form persists as a major hub for marshalling and administration of vital resources
and is hence crucial for the left to occupy, but in which the state is also only one point amidst a wider networks of communal self-organization and mutual aid.
So these two components, what one might term the state apparatus and autonomous or communizing organizations, are in dialogue, cooperation,
and perhaps also creative tension, and it is this entire complex field of organizations that constitutes the governmentality of biocommunism.
In this way, I want to suggest a form of governance that becomes what Marx and Engels termed a process of vast association, a phrase from the manifesto.
Now, I'll acknowledge right from the start that there are some serious limitations to my futuristic depiction.
I jump immediately to issues of governance, and I say very little, if anything, about the actual process of transition and the struggles that might lead to it.
My horizons are inescapably, I think, somewhat bound by my position as an inhabitant of the global Northwest.
I don't, for example, deal with the issue of catastrophe politics in China, and while my paper on this topic has some engagement with the profound predicaments of the global South,
it is mainly through the lens of issues of migration and refuge in the context of global warming.
So there are some acknowledged and serious insufficiencies to the picture that I'm painting, and it is in many ways intended just as yet a further provisional sketch and contribution to the work by many, many hands that is going into addressing this question of beyond capitalism.
But I think you might gather from this thumbnail that I am trying to bridge some long-standing divides, not just between green and red, but also between centralizers and decentralizers, between state socialists and autonomous and anarchists.
So, of course, everyone will be unhappy with the propositions.
I accept that and, again, only emphasize that this is a thought experiment intended as part of a vastly wider process.
You describe biocommunism as a new form of governmentality. You just, sorry, you describe it as a form of governmentality that takes into account the current multiplicity of crisis that form the catastrophic conditions that any alternative will have to work with, and I'm very much interested in the governmentality part of it.
But in order to kind of set the scene for this, could you maybe give us an idea of the multidimensional crisis that we are living in? What are the elements that come together there?
But by all means, now, and I should say this idea of a multidimensional crisis is not mine. In fact, I'm drawing on several other usages.
For example, the term polycrisis, referring to the intersection of economic, epidemiological, and ecological crises, has been popularized by the historian and journalist Adam Tooth in his recent, and I think very good, book on the COVID pandemic shutdown.
Now, Tooth and others who use the term polycrisis tend to regard this sort of compounding state of emergencies as an aberrant departure from the norms of the world market.
But there are other perspectives that can be taken on this, and I recently had the pleasure of listening to Alex Kalinikos' retirement speech on the topic of the new age of catastrophe, in which he argues contra Tooth and other liberals that the present polycrisis should be seen as the culmination or logical outcome of capitalism's economic crisis.
Of capitalism's exploitation of the natural and human world, and I think it is, in fact, Kalinikos from whom I get this phrase, a multidimensional crisis involving biological elements with global warming as exhibit one, but accompanied by other symptoms such as the zoonotic overspill of pandemic unleashed by deforestation and agribusiness.
Economic, with the problems of stagnancy, inequality and financial instability manifested in the great crisis of 2008, remaining unresolved and now acquiring new symptoms and new intensities.
These geopolitical crisis in the struggle for global hegemony between rival blocks with the US and the European Union on one side, China and Russia on the other, with lesser powers jockeying for positioning between, and then political being referred to as the extreme center of globalizing neoliberalism is starting to cave in under pressure by what we might call populist eruptions.
Primarily, but not exclusively from the far right. So my recent iteration of biocommunism is an attempt to conceive the politics that are demanded by this type of complex multidimensional crisis.
Especially if one thinks of the polycrisis as not being a punctual event, but a persistent one that goes on for a while. This really raises the issue of what a communism might look like in that context.
So what I'm trying to do really is to map an archipelago of sites and situations and subjectivities that appear in the midst of intensifying turmoil. Islands of counter power that might be connected in some new collective system.
So this is conceived within a sort of near to mid future horizon unfolding over a decade or so, during which the multidimensional crisis continues, perhaps intensifies.
We have to optimistically assume that abyssal depth such as full scale nuclear war remain unplumbed, because in that case all bets are off.
But we're in a situation in which successful governance is increasingly defined by the sustenance of populations undermounting ecological, economic and geopolitical stress. That's the context for my thinking about biocommunism.
Okay, great. Let's get to the governmentality part, because I'm really very much interested in this one. And there's a strand of future history within future histories that kind of deals with the question of alternative governmentalities.
And I think it's absolutely crucial to address this layer. I think most of the episodes are unfortunately in German, the ones that deal with Alternativen Regierungskünsten.
So I was in general very much excited to see you approach biocommunism from the angle of governmentality. And there's this famous quote by Michel Foucault in which he states that there is no intrinsically socialist governmentality and that it needs to be invented.
And am I right in reading your text as a kind of first attempt in pointing towards such a direction? Do we need to invent new forms of governmentality and is biocommunism an attempt to do so?
Absolutely. Your suggestion is completely spot on. The very remark of Foucault's that you cite was one of the starting points for my thinking about biocommunism.
And I'm also excited to hear about this strand on future histories in regard to Foucault and governmentality. I actually became aware of this a little bit by looking at the prospectus for your forthcoming book, where I see your pieces on this topic.
So as you'll know well, there are many different opinions on mixing Marx and Foucault. Some think that they don't go together at all. But I am with those who consider that Foucault is much better read with Marx than against Marx.
This is what is sometimes called the Italian Foucault, the Foucault of the Italian autonomous Marxists such as Tony Negri and Tiziana Terranova, who conceive of a biopolitics that has a dimension that emerges and fights from below rather than simply being imposed from above.
And I share their opinion that a contemporary Marxism must be a biopolitics that grasp social struggles, not just at the point of production, in the short hand that as the factory, but throughout the entire circuit of capital where production is threaded with circulation and social reproduction.
And indeed across an entire planet factory that exists today, entailing issues of reproduction of nature and the environment as it too is exploited and developed by capital.
Now, where I might depart from some of my autonomous friends is in saying that this Marxist biopolitics must indeed actively be a project of governmentality, of biopower.
And here I think Foucault's concept is very rich because to me it speaks of a concept where governance is not just a question of state apparatus, but something much more diffuse and multilayered.
If we pick up on Deleuze's response to Foucault, we can almost say where governance becomes a question today of rhizomatic structures.
And I would say that one might say that the task of a communist biopolitics is precisely to ensure that such a diffuse and rhizomatic structures of governmentality
become the mechanisms of a power that is not simply imposed from above, but that rises up from below to forge its own communal organization of society.
So you described six elements of biocommunism and these are new disaster relief systems, open borders to migrant fleeing calamity, expropriation of capital from crisis critical industries, rationing of consumption,
mobilization of emergency labor and ecological and economic planning.
So let's go through these elements one by one and start with the first one. Could you describe the new disaster relief system you're thinking of?
Yeah, I quite intentionally chose as a starting point an aspect of contemporary social existence that might seem somewhat peripheral or eccentric in terms of traditional Marxian thinking.
Of course, your Marxian analysis has always powerfully started from the point of production.
I want to suggest that we are in a context today where in some ways it is necessary to start from the point of destruction,
the point at which the violent and damaging effects of capitalism begin to manifest in the many, many catastrophes that are emerging, the floods and fires of global warming, pandemics, wars.
So the apparatus that modern capitalist society has developed to deal with these types of abrupt disruptions of the normal order are known in the professional jargon as vital systems security.
And these measures for the security of vital systems are today part of the administrative toolkit of capitalist societies, often involving very, very complex articulations, both centralized and decentralized agencies,
all geared towards the management of outbreaks of disease or various forms of so-called natural disaster.
Now, this is a system that in many ways reflects the priorities of the social order that developed it.
It's very largely concerned with protection of property as well, and sometimes much more so that of people.
It has a major concern with the preservation of civil order, prevention of outbursts of social protest and disobedience in situations of calamity.
Much of it is actually involved also with preparations for international war.
But this is also paradoxically a set of emergency measures and institutions that has recently been significantly undermined by the very logic of capitalist accumulation
through the effects of neoliberal austerity and its reliance on just-in-time systems.
So, for example, in the current COVID pandemic, we saw a revelation of a deep unpreparedness, certainly in the OECD countries, for what had actually been a long predicted event, a global flu-like pandemic.
And as a result, disaster management was often incompetent, confused and contradictory.
It exposed how threadbare various crucial institutions such as health care systems had become.
The pandemic and other disasters, including storms and floods, also have revealed how uneven, how shaped by discriminations around class and race and gender disaster relief is,
how much it suffers from also from the neglect and lack of communication with the very communities that it is meant to be protecting.
My thesis is that such disasters are going to become even more common and that indeed the test for any post-capitalist system, sort of touchstone for their superiority,
will actually be their capacity to better protect their inhabitants from such catastrophes.
I think that this will involve massive investments in social infrastructures, ranging from hospitals to cooling systems for heatwave afflicted cities, flood control, vaccine manufacturing, even the security of food supplies.
And it will also require not simply the construction of the technical infrastructures for this, but a much higher degree of dialogical communication with affected and endangered populations and communities to arrive at some degree of social consensus around how to handle these very difficult situations.
I think this is a situation in which, in fact, much of this disaster planning will have to continue to draw on the apparatus of the state.
We will indeed need a crisis state, but in a better and more benign form than that that is provided under capital in order to marshal expertise to emergency supplies, resources and equipment.
But also this official apparatus of disaster relief should draw on, support and cooperate with initiatives of mutual aid and community self-organization of the sort that has been long discussed in anarchist and autonomous thinking about,
to quote a phrase from the Out of the Woods Collective, disaster communism, the capacities of people to self-organize in situations of severe social stress.
So, you know, in some ways, I think what is needed is a reworked revival of the traditions of popular mobilization in the face of socio-natural disasters that we saw practiced to some extent in socialist societies such as Cuba.
We did some reading around the quite extraordinary way in which Cubans prepare for recurrent hurricane disasters with a sense that this is an occasion which actually calls for communal mobilization and social solidarity.
And this becomes a part of the entire social orientation towards this kind of danger.
So this is the point in which I choose to start my analysis of bio-communism, as I suggested, heretically departing from initiating it at the point of production, going to the point of destruction.
But of course, one has to remember that the point of production is also the point of destruction.
One has to think, you know, about the Amazon warehouse with its roof torn off in a hurricane.
One has to think of a meatpacking plant with a raging COVID outbreak on the shop floor or social service officers being slowly inundated by the rising waters in coastal areas.
So in fact, what we're really talking about, we could say, is the equivalent of a health and safety crisis in the planet factory, which calls for a comprehensive global health and safety response.
Does that give some sense of what I'm getting out with this attention to disaster relief?
Yes, yes, absolutely. And I just saw that I made a note where you say in the text, as capitalism's own forces of production turn against it.
And this just reminded me of the way you described the destruction that already went into the modes of production when talking about the Amazon warehouse.
But I'm still wondering whether or not this is actually to the benefit of capitalism or not, because I mean, somehow you seem to think that it will turn against it.
And this, of course, would be a nice thing to have.
But still, it kind of reminds me of this question of multidimensional crisis and whether or not this is actually maybe a different mode of disaster capitalism, which kind of benefits of this destruction, this confusion, this mayhem and everything around it.
So I really, really like this idea of a biocommunism that is forged around what you call, in reference to Frazier, formed around a politics of care.
So I really like this idea that we have a different kind of offer in the form of biocommunism, and this offer is a form of politics of care.
But still, I was just wondering whether or not you think that this catastrophe, this destruction, if this is really turning against capitalism or not?
It's an excellent question, Jan, and I do agree with you.
Disaster capitalism, as articulated by Nobu Klein, and indeed even earlier theories of the way in which apparent catastrophe could be turned to a new occasion for accumulation, such as Tony Negri's thesis on the crisis state, are very important to this analysis
and very much in play. That is the logic, shall we say, on the other side of the hill, right?
But I also think we should qualify, just as you have properly qualified, any suggestion in my account that there isn't any sort of automaticity to a progressive outcome to catastrophe.
So I think we have to qualify any assumption that capitalism can itself automatically handle and recuperate disaster.
I think it's by no means clear that capital can always control disaster.
You can get a runaway situation, and indeed we may be in such a runaway situation in which the frantic attempts at improvisation to control the polycrisis that Tuus and others have described seems only to generate fresh problems.
You know, we pass from the pandemic to runaway inflation, et cetera, et cetera.
Now, again, there is no reason per se that this runaway effect will go in a positive direction.
It could be terrible. It could result in outcomes worse than capitalism itself.
If we appeal to socialism or barbarism, we're talking a heads or tails situation.
What I am suggesting with biocommunism is what many others have suggested, the need to think of how resistance and alternative also appear as possibilities, not as certainties, but as projects, even in the middle of disaster.
This is the logic of Out of the Woods, as I've already mentioned, the concept of disaster communism.
One could also speak of it as an activity of what Richard Seymour and his associates term salvage socialism, the attempt at the reconstruction of a beyond capitalism in the midst of what I would characterize as an increasingly
volatile set of intersecting crisis, which may not be fully controllable by anyone at this point.
Yes, absolutely. And the idea that capitalism can always be in the position of controlling disasters actually already idealizing capitalism again, I would say somehow.
So this is a very good point you're making. So let's take a look at the next element of biocommunism, which would be migration and refuge.
What would these elements look like?
So we are evidently in a situation in which millions of displaced people today are on the move around because of the combined and indeed virtually inseparable effects of poverty, ecological devastation, war and oppression.
What Saskia Sassen has spoken of as a loss of habitat is tragically and grossly unfairly concentrated in tropics and equatorial zones where global warming is most severe and the malign legacies of colonialism and imperialism already deeply mark the social order.
So with a double injustice, populations least responsible for carbon emissions are most vulnerable in terms of poverty, frail infrastructures, insufficient public services.
Now, the emergent patterns of migration are in fact very complex. We know that most migrants move today from one country to another adjacent to it.
So very often you have people moving from one relatively poor or disadvantaged country to another, yet further pressing the social systems.
But also these migration flows move towards the rich world across the Mediterranean or to the U.S.-Mexico border and other frontiers.
And this is where migrants face exclusion, detention, deportation, criminalization, abandonment, death.
In this situation, we have seen the emergence of self-organization by migrant communities under slogans such as no one is illegal or the border is closed, but we will cross anyway.
And we've also seen, I think, the emergence of important movements supporting these struggles.
Now, there are complex debates in which I'm not likely going to pretend to expertise between advocates of open borders who advocate relaxing state regulations on migration
and advocates of no frontiers who favor abolishing state sovereignty to core.
This is a difficult and controversial set of debates, but it does seem to me that in a very broad sense, any contemporary socialism or communism does require a de-bordering orientation.
I agree with what Zizek says when he writes that the main lesson to be learned from the current migration crisis is that humankind should get ready to live in more plastic and nomadic ways,
as rapid environmental changes require radical redefinitions of national sovereignty.
And my argument would be that biocommunism should, in fact, actively aim to make this reinvention or de-bordering reinvention in favor of the workers of the world, remembering that migration and nomadism has always been an attribute of proletarianized populations.
And the next element of biocommunism would be the expropriation of capital from crisis critical industries.
You state that in some cases it is vital to expand production and in others it is necessary to shut it down.
When does one apply and when does the other? And how do we get about it? Since it shouldn't be simply about nationalization.
You already mentioned it's not only about the state, but we need a bottom-up autonomous element as well. So it's not only about nationalization.
What are the concrete institutional forms that this could take?
Yeah, OK. So let me try and thread a couple of points together.
In one sense, of course, with the discussion of expropriation of the expropriators, we're back on very classic Marxian ground.
But I think with some new twists, it's probably fair to say that in general, not always, but broadly,
when past generations of Marxists have thought about this, they have thought about the expropriation of capitalist industry as a process,
which will actually release the restrained forces of production, which will allow more.
And to some degree, this remains true and often urgently so.
But with the advent of deepening ecological crisis, sometimes the need to expropriate capital in order to ensure less, in fact,
to stop certain types of production becomes apparent.
And so we can perhaps take two very current instances of social campaigns and struggles to illustrate these two contrary faces to contemporary expropriation,
or at least attempts towards expropriation, because neither of these examples I'm going to give have, of course, been fully successful.
So the first I will take is the no profit from pandemic campaign to attempt to enlarge the availability of anti-COVID vaccines
on a scale sufficient to the global scope of the crisis.
So as we know, companies such as Pfizer and Moderna were successful, albeit with the help of very high levels of state support,
of producing vaccines very quickly in the face of a pandemic.
But as we also well know, the distribution of these vaccines has been massively uneven.
And given their scarcity or unavailability in the global south, quite properly described as a state of vaccine apartheid.
And it is in this context that we saw the emergence of a very eloquent and widely supported campaign to compel the trade organization
to some relaxation of the intellectual property rights of big pharma in order to enable the establishment of drug manufacturing plants where they were most urgently needed.
Now this campaign eventually won some modest success, some minor concessions from the big drug companies.
I'm not pretending for a moment that this is a full project of expropriation.
But the logic, the vector that it points towards shows how, yes, indeed, there are situations in which expropriation is called for
because we need to unleash from the feathers of profit-oriented production goods and services that are desperately needed by people around the world.
The sort of contrary example or example of the need to expropriate in order to restrict production is, of course, the fossil fuel industry
in which climate activists from several directions produced plans for what at the moment we will broadly call nationalizing fossil fuel companies or placing them under public control
precisely in order to enable a swift and orderly close down of this type of activity.
This is very well described, I think, in Holly Jean Buck's book on Net Zero, where she speaks about the need to, quote, end things, right?
And the need to have a process which leads to the ending of things.
And so we could say that the placing of oil and gas companies under forms of democratic public control.
I'm going to emphasize that democratic because many big oil companies are, in fact, state sovereign companies, but which act like private companies just responding to the world market.
But need for those forms of public control becomes indispensable for, in fact, ceasing what shall we call the noxious behaviors of capital which are destroying the biosphere.
Now, here we come to the issue about the forms that this type of democratic and communal control might take.
And it's here, I think, that thinking about movements for forms of global commons, which have been ongoing now for decades and the wealth of intellectual and political activity that has attended this, have been really important
because the term commons has really become a signifier around which have been gathered a wide variety of forms of thought as to how communal ownership might take forms that are more genuinely participatory and democratic.
They're subject to corruption and capture than the highly bureaucratic, top-down forms of national utilities, which are often seen as the archetypal form of nationalized industry.
I mean, sometimes those forms function very well, but sometimes they don't.
And what thinking about commons has done is, I think, add to our repertoire of the different ways in which democratic control of economic resources can be initiated, whether it is through various forms of cooperatives, worker cooperatives, consumer cooperatives,
platform cooperatives, whether it is through various types of open source or peer-to-peer activities, as have been developed by thinkers like Richard Stallman and Michelle Bowens, taking full advantage of the immense capacities of digital networks to create
widely shareable forms of goods and services and innovations, or even through the thought that's been put by some sections of the Green Movement into the creation of trusts of various types of public institutions, which may take various environmental resources
outside of the market, but also place them at, but also standing at some arm's length from direct state administration.
So this, I think, is the immense benefit that has come from thinking around commons.
In my essay on biocommunism, I also say, though, that the reason I approach this topic through the issue of expropriation rather than through commons is that I think some, not all, writing on commons has suffered from a certain weakness in not sufficiently
emphasizing the need to dispossess capital as well as create commons.
And here, I would take some of my own writings, my own earlier writings on commons to task.
I think that we today have a much better understanding of how capital can, in fact, not only quite happily coexist with a lot of commoning initiatives such as workers' cooperatives, but can itself, in fact, very often co-opt what seem like excellent commons initiatives
and long and complex saga of the transformation of the free software movement, the free and open source software, to the situation now where we have Microsoft as a company champion so-called open source innovation, tell us something about this.
So my thought about commons today is, yes, commons are great, they're vital.
We can't really discuss communism without thinking about something like commons.
But it seems to me that we also have to, in the same breath, speak about the decapitation of capital, in fact, in order to create the space in which these very important new forms of commons actually become the predominant and central institutions of society.
Okay, that's very interesting, because it also kind of touches upon the question of the state and maybe a bit about the question, the very difficult question of transition and transformation, because this sounds to me as if at the end you are not ditching this idea of
communism that you invented as a term in a, I think, 2007 paper, but that you would kind of urge for a maybe a radicalized additional movement to communism.
So communism plus the abolition of privatized ownership and production.
So you need both elements in order to then make happen the communism as a widespread type of relationality as well.
Do I get that right?
Communism with teeth, yes.
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay, so now let's get to the next element of biocommunism, which is actually, to me at least, some of the juicy stuff, the question of rationing.
You argue for rationing.
And while I personally think you raise some some good points there, I would nonetheless kind of disagree with the framing.
But before I get to formulate my skepticism, could you elaborate on this idea of rationing as a principle of biocommunist governance?
Yes, yes. So indeed, I understand well.
Rationing is not a topic favored by Marxism or indeed by many forms of leftism.
You know, historically, a certain confidence in expanding forces of production has always steered Belaif away from discussions of scarcity.
But I think it is really apparent that in the current poli-crisis, in fact, rationing repeatedly rears its head either as an immediate response to shortages, be they of oil or gas.
I just read this morning, in fact, Germany is in fact ramping up its plans for rationing of gas because of the disruptions caused by the war.
Or even the indeed rationing of food caused by wartime disruptions and corporate opportunism.
These topics come up. And indeed, in a longer term horizon, you should recognize that many ecological thinkers have always and now increasingly think about forms of carbon rationing as an emergency fallback.
If carbon taxes, carbon trading and other mechanisms, market mechanisms fail to hold global warming, as indeed seems extremely likely.
You know, if one looks at, so one of the few, I think, really comprehensive attempts to comprehensively deal with rationing as a socio-economic mechanism is Stan Cox's book on the topic.
It's an environmentalist account of rationing. And he shows that, first of all, the ration has, under various names, always been basic in many pre-capitalist societies, that socialist societies have used governmental rationing as a means of social equalization.
Again, there's, Qbar is an interesting example in this respect. And within capitalism, non-market rationing, and we should remember that the market is itself a rationing mechanism, but non-market rationing is in fact regularly deployed to allocate necessities such as food, fuel or water when escalating inequalities threaten the social order.
This is, and both sorts of usages are deeply ambivalent. One has situations in contemporary Egypt where a food ration for the poor coexists with markets for the better off, and this really serves to stabilize and uphold vertiginous inequalities, except when the ration is reduced, when it becomes an occasion for food riots.
But there are also other historical moments when comprehensive rationing of food and other supplies has, in crisis situations, not only actually enjoyed broad popular support, but has also modeled wider social equalization.
And the classic instance was Britain's wartime rationing, which one can say was in many ways pre-figurative of the creation of the welfare state, which for all its inadequacies was nonetheless an important reformist initiative.
So my suggestion, and I understand well it's very contestable, is that if one accepts biocommunism as a project with a double orientation towards equality and sustainability, one should at least consider the possibility of the place that rations might place in such a project.
I think one could very easily say that rationing of some specific ecologically damaging goods today, such as airline flights, might be an extremely good measure, rather than allowing a market free-for-all in which the rich continue to fly all over the planet and no one else can afford to do so at all.
One might, depending on how the whole questions of energy transition start to shake out, consider whether in fact broader quotas for energy use, which ensured some degree of equalization,
would both restrain consumption in ways that reduced ecological destruction and act against the huge inequalities in access to material resources that exist.
Also, and I know we'll come back to this, I do want to emphasize that there are two sides to the concept of the ration. Ration is not just limit, but it is guarantee. It's a prohibition, but it's also a promise.
It's security as well as a scarcity. If one allocates a ration, it points to the organization of society around the universal provision of a limited but assured and broadly egalitarian basket of goods.
My suggestion is that in the midst of this multidimensional series of crisis that are rendering markets increasingly chaotic, exacerbating social inequalities horribly, and accelerating ecological devastation,
it may be that the ration will represent for biocommunism a sort of guarantee that may come to seem increasingly attractive. But I do understand well that there are concerns that people have about these ideas, and so I think you should make your important points.
Yeah, and I mean, I think actually at the end, we are not that far apart from each other because specifically this point of rationing as a promise is absolutely brilliant, I think. I would simply argue that it should be framed differently.
I think that this is the most important element I would point towards when criticizing this idea of rationing. So as I said, I'm skeptical about this type of framing, the framing of the problem as one of scarcity at the end.
And one of the reasons for this is that scarcity is basically the home turf of liberalism, so to speak. It feeds on the idea of scarcity, liberalism.
And this fear of scarcity is also tightly coupled to a cultural hierarchization in which a specific idea of economic rationality has already been established as the quote unquote correct relationality in regards to the future.
It is a cultural hierarchy in which some, and this is usually a white Western male, are marked as possessing a rationality that is capable of keeping the given abundance in the world.
And then there are those marked as quote unquote primitives who, through their supposed lack of rational relation to the future and the wastefulness associated with it, bring scarcity into the world.
So this cultural hierarchization is, of course, still very much active today, and it is deeply embedded in our institutional structures, popular narratives, and also self perceptions.
Thus, if one thinks that one can activate this liberal fear of scarcity in order to mobilize, e.g. for a more effective addressing of the climate crisis, one kind of enters a terrain in which a specific set of supposed solutions already by far dominates the field.
And it is a terrain in which one can only lose, I would say, because the way the problem is posed already works against us in this case.
So my argument would be, and the alternative is, as I said, already clearly present in your proposal in the form of the ration as a promise, my argument would be to frame the whole thing differently and not coming from a fear of scarcity but as an offer of another kind of abundance, e.g. as a social kind of abundance, a non-material abundance.
And crucially, also an offer of real existential security, as you just stated with the ration as a promise. And of course, this real security can, by definition, only be non-excluding, so it needs to be universal in order to really be a true security, I would say.
In contrast, it seems to me that framing it as a problem of scarcity is actually kind of counterproductive to the whole cause because, as I said, it pushes the debate into an area in which one can only lose, I would argue.
And also, there is already this very positive narrative element of rationing as a promise, as an existential security that one can put into the forefront.
And so I would basically more or less argue for framing that highlights the strength. And when it comes to the question of rationing, I would say it's easy to include this idea of rationing on a meta level, where we have global caps on different types of, like you mentioned, CO2 and other things as well.
So if you have global caps and then you have a type of democratically planned economy that works within these boundaries, you already have this question of rationing addressed on a more higher scale.
And so it wouldn't be of need to make use of this difficult narrative and idea of rationing on an individual level, I'd say.
You know, I think, except your suggestion as a really important and valuable idea as to how to reframe this part of the argument.
And indeed, I mean, I would say I basically cover my ass on these questions by saying that I put forward this proposal of biocommunism as a catalyst for precisely this type of discussion.
I think that we don't differ very much on this. I'm not perhaps as entirely convinced as you are that the discussion of scarcities is one in which the left is doomed always to lose.
I mean, there are a few counterpoints. I mean, communism is a critique of scarcity. It is a critique of socially created scarcity where one part of the world eats and the other does not.
And as I've argued today, communism is also a project in which we want to make something scarce. We want to make fossil fuel very scarce indeed.
I live just north of a country of which would do much better if it made guns a lot scarcer than they were.
So I'm not perhaps as worried about the way conversations might go on that ground, but I think we both agree that rationing is a discussion that while it could start from scarcity,
certainly goes in other directions towards equality and fairness and towards the rethinking of issues of abundance.
And here I think we have to take Aaron Benaneb's excellent aphorism about the nature of abundance as a social relationship very much to heart.
It's an important concept to work with. But I will certainly think very seriously about the points that you've made.
And it may well be that this part of a bio-communist manifesto might need to be rejigged in the sort of directions that you're suggesting.
And I mean, I guess one of the elements that will be of great importance when it comes to the question of whether or not rationing in the sense that you propose it will be accepted by the many
will be the question of whether or not the decisions that lead up to how rationing will be organized are actually really participatory, are actually really democratic,
and whether or not the people have a sense of being part of this idea in a general sense, I would say.
And I mean, it would be horrible if it comes down to a top-down situation where this idea of rationing is simply pushed through some form of coercion,
because then it would, of course, create very different scenarios than the ones that you proposed and imagined, I would say.
Yes, absolutely. And indeed, I think this point that you make is applicable, not just to rationing, but also to so many other aspects of what we can broadly define as disaster management.
This is really the question of whether it is disaster management or disaster self-organization.
And the next element of biocommunism would be the essential workers.
You write that biocommunism, and I quote you here, biocommunism will not be a post-work utopia, but rather a radical recomposition of labor.
And you introduce the essential worker as a figure that will compose a quote-unquote universal army of labor.
And this is the term you borrow from Frederick Jameson.
Could you explain these terms and concepts and how this universal army of labor would come about without turning into a quote-unquote totalitarian nightmare?
And that's the negative, the dystopian element you already point towards in your text as well.
Yeah, yeah. So I would say that this is perhaps the part of my writing on biocommunism, which is most provocative and perhaps a little bit intentionally.
Because it takes some aim at what I now consider some weaknesses in thinking about the future organization of work, including, once again, my own weaknesses in this regard.
So I think that in attempting to think of beyond capital and the organization of labor or work in that context, there are a couple of fallbacks.
But think as you and I have had, either it is to preserve the idea of the wage in some concept of market socialism, which I think always ultimately actually leads back to capitalism once one preserves the wage form.
Or in order to avoid that recuperation, left futurists like to presuppose a high level of abundance.
And in a sense to avoid a number of difficult questions about work by assuming very high levels of automation.
This is in fact really was the appeal of fully automated luxury communism, which by adopting a sort of high technology intensity presuppositions about the future was able to raise a whole lot of very seriously difficult questions about organizations, incentives.
And so on by envisaging what is basically a post work situation.
So I would admit that I admired Jameson's essay in which he made this highly inflammatory suggestion of a universal army of labor, precisely because it directly challenges many of the left and the right's chivalrists about work.
And freedom. So just to give our listeners an idea of this, if I haven't read Jameson's essay, Jameson envisages a socialist society in which every capable person is required to put in the equivalent of four hours of work a day.
This can be calculated on a daily or weekly or yearly basis and assume a lot of flexibility on how it's actually divided up, but to basically devote half of a working day to some socially useful project.
And he calls this a universal army of labor, a term which is, of course, especially combustible because of the use of the military terminology.
So I thought that this was when I first encountered this, I thought this was a very bold step that Jameson had taken and not one that could be dismissed out of hand.
But I have been especially reminded of it in some of the discussions about the effects of climate change on work.
And in particular, I thought of it when I read a review by Cory Doctorow criticizing Bastani's concept of fully automated luxury communism.
And Doctorow writes, remediating climate change will involve unimaginably labor-intensive tasks like relocating every coastal city in the world, kilometers inland, building high-speed rail links to replace aviation links, caring for hundreds of millions of traumatized, displaced people, and treating runaway, zoonotic and insect-borne pandemics.
These tasks will absorb more than 100% of any labor freed up by automation.
Every person whose job is obsolete because of automation will have 10 jobs waiting for them for the entire foreseeable future.
And in fact, as one thinks more deeply into this situation, one can expand Doctorow's list of the sort of, shall we say, essential work that will be required by climate change.
Emergency firefighters, mass tree planters, rewilding land, solar panel installers, housing insulators, coders of climate-sensing software, gigafactory workers, and many, many more.
In fact, you know, one probably has to think of a massively belated fulfillment of plans for a million climate jobs or a Green New Deal, which are unfortunately, I think now, all too likely to be instantiated not in forward-looking crisis anticipation, but under the increasingly chaotic conditions of a biospheric deterioration, which capital has been incapable of.
So, my point here is that climate emergency, as well as the other kinds of emergencies that make up the polycrisis, will take a great deal of work.
And in a certain sense, I think one might almost conceive of a situation in which most work becomes emergency work, right?
But society will be largely occupied with the tasks of dealing with this species-hazardous situation.
And I would say that this is the sort of work that is unlikely to be done at all or done well by market logics, where it will be conducted, if at all, driven by profit imperatives or perhaps by public subsidization of massive corporate accumulation in a whole new disaster relief construction complex,
with all the manifold exploitations of labor, which we don't need to detail here because we understand them all too well in terms of precarity, danger, etc.
So, my view is that in this situation, it is much better to see these large tranches of socially necessary labor explicitly and overtly socially organized.
In a context in what counts as socially useful work is subject to democratic decisions on labor that is undertaken on projects that form part of a discussed and debated and socially decided socio-economic plan.
But that in this condition, the social and collective organization of labor be made explicit by a requirement for all who are capable to take a share in this type of labor.
Now, yes, this does summon up nightmares of forced labor battalions, but I am going to argue that it doesn't have to be like that.
I envisage a situation not in which people are drafted to any old task, but rather precisely because there are so many types of essential work that need to be done.
In fact, there is a wide range of choice as to what one does.
Many types of activity that today are not validated as socially necessary labor, particularly of traditionally feminized work in the area of social reproduction are indeed so recognized and validated.
And I think one can also think about a situation in which workers who are engaged as part of the universal army of labor do in fact have very substantial degrees of autonomy over their own working activities,
have the equivalent of unions with rights to strike, organized in ways which entail many different channels for inputs and proposals about the conditions and methods that are applied to their tasks in which people indeed have a say in how their projects are conducted.
Indeed, if one wants to pick up the singularly provocative military terminology that Jameson uses, the universal army of labor, I think one wants to think about that not in terms of the sort of 19th century top-down regimentation,
but more in terms of what are today called mission tactics in which there's an understanding that very broad objectives are set either by military commanders or by planners.
But in fact, those who execute the task have a very, very high degree of autonomy in determining how the tasks are taken and indeed a certain degree of insubordination and deviation from the set plan is intrinsic to the process.
Now, speaking in these terms, I may only have heaped a few on an already combustible topic, but that's my line of thought about it.
But I think I know on this point, too, you have concerns and I'd like to hear you.
Yeah, well, I mean, I guess the obvious question is the question of coercion or not.
I mean, you right now framed it in a way that allows for a more autonomous way of engaging with this work.
But still at the end, if everything boils down to a universal army of labor that is obligatory, then of course the question of coercion comes up.
So in which way are the subjects disciplined into taking part in this universal army of labor?
So this is, of course, the biggest question I have.
But I mean, in addition to that, I would say that the way that you framed it when it comes to the different perspectives within the socialist positions, that there are those that are still sticking to some kind of wage form.
And then there are the others that are already jumping into a world of abundance, that are alternative ways.
And I would point out specifically the developing of communism in the work of Simon Sutter-Lytti and Stefan Meritz.
I'm not sure, actually, if they refer to your 2007 paper as well.
I think they don't. But there's a German book they wrote, which is called Kapitalismus aufheben.
And they sketch a world of communism.
So a generalization of communing and commons as a principle of social organization.
And in which they envision a form of social production and social reproduction, which is based on radical voluntariness.
So this would be a, so to speak, third position in which it's not necessarily tied to an idea of abundance, because that's not what they are proposing.
They are not in the camp of accelerationist leftist techno-utopianism, so to speak.
But they are very much about different forms of relationality that form a different type of understanding when it comes to this form of social reproduction.
And so there would be a different position, I would say.
And it's also really questionable if a form that at the end relies on coercion is really more effective in attaining the goal of, for example, participation within this form of biocommunist economy.
And if not, relying on radical voluntariness would be, at the end, even more effective by not trying to force people into work.
In this case, not through a wage, but through, I don't know which type of coercion you imagine, but some type of coercion seems to be at play, I think.
Yes, yeah. Well, I look forward very much to reading that work on communism and radical voluntarism.
Behind these questions are the concerns that the universal army of labor concept is authoritarian.
I would say no, but it does imply a high level of collective social responsibility.
And I don't really think that communism is a project for hyper-individualists.
Hyper-individualism, we might say, is the subjective, I would say, the sort of subjectivity that is produced by the so-called free market.
I think that the creation of some form of collective society beyond capital does require the creation of some level of social discipline in which there is an expectation that everyone who can contributes in some way to collective well-being.
And I would say that that sort of normative behavior or normative expectation does indeed, in fact, lie behind most of what we know as successful commons undertakings.
I think that we can envisage a world in which the production of that type of subjectivity does not centrally depend on coercion.
It seems to me that intrinsic to the production of this sort of world is, for example, much more direction, I mean direction in the sense of guidance, advice and assistance for people in terms of defining the sort of paths and types of work
that they find than is available to people within capitalist societies.
I think one should really envisage, actually, as a very important part of a future communist society, one where a great deal of care is taken in actually helping people develop and cultivate a sense of what kind of engagement with work people can constructively have.
It would also be a situation in which very careful attention is given to the physical and psychological circumstances, limits and possibilities that different people have for different types of work, in which, as I've already said, more types of activity would be recognized as socially valid forms of work than are under capitalism,
which, as we understand well, vast swathes of labor are, in fact, invisibilized and denied recognition.
And to riff again on, you know, I think here I'm borrowing a little bit from some recent thoughts again by Banana, but we really don't have a very, you know, I mean, ultimately, one does have to deal with the so-called free rider situation, you know, that of people who, for whatever reason,
really do not wish to engage in a cooperative project of work, but we don't really know how that situation would shape up in conditions absent, compulsive from the wage, where everyone's getting access to some form of universal social services or rations,
and in which it's clearly understood that various forms of work are needed for the society and the species to make a passage through a planetary emergency.
Now, obviously, communist society is not one where one leaves anyone, even if they seem incredibly reluctant to work in a state of physical want or social degradation, so everyone gets food, housing, the necessities of life.
Ultimately, I would not be averse to think of a situation in which there may be some trade-off for, shall we say, the voluntary refusal to work in terms, perhaps, of different levels of access to certain facilities and opportunities.
You know, if you've taken your holidays in advance, you know, you don't benefit from the holiday facilities. I think in some ways that's reasonable, that there should be some form of social contract, but more, I think what is really more basic is the creation of new types of subjectivity with a different relation between
self-realization and collective identity, and that has to be the long-term orientation of a bio-communist project, which I definitely do not conceive of as primarily a coercive project.
On the contrary, I see it as one that, in fact, will liberate people from the massive coercions that are exercised through the wage or through its absence.
Yeah, well, I think two points. I guess one would be, again, maybe it's simply about a question of framing, because if you say that a bio-communist society will highly depend on a different form of social responsibility that will then allow people to engage in this type of work without
feeling coerced, at least, then I kind of wonder why is then any element of coercion needed if there is an element of social responsibility within the subjects of bio-communism?
Then you could easily rely on radical forms of voluntariness, because you already have this form of social responsibility, which will lead the people into wanting to engage in socially necessary work.
So this, again, would be an argument for not going down the road of coercion in any way, shape, or form, and then this will actually be a bit more about the question of framing again, because by framing it as a universal army of labor and these connotations of army, again, of course, you will have this sense of top-down hierarchy and authoritarianism within the framing as such.
So this is actually kind of counterproductive if you want to make the point that it will be a form of relationality that is highly depending on a deeper understanding of, let's say, responsibility towards this different social contract.
So this, again, would be a bit critical of the type of framing.
And then the second thing would be, I would be interested in, I mean, you briefly touched upon it when you talked about the free rider problem, but in general, it's below the surface, but it's not made explicit.
What is the image of quote unquote, and these are like massive quote unquote, what is the image of human nature, so to speak, that you rely on?
So I think I mentioned at the start that the point of departure for thinking about biocommunism was a series of reflections on Marx's writings, predominantly early writings, about 40 terms species being,
which is precisely about this issue of what is human nature, right?
And in considering this, discuss various alternative interpretations as to what Marx meant by species being, when he refers to the essential nature of the species, is he talking about some innate set of propensities or attributes?
Or is he, in fact, talking about humans as a species whose nature is to remake their own nature, to constantly reinstantiate a set of capacities and tendencies based on the convergence of a set of social relations
under a particular mode of production? And I think that I favor the latter view that there is, to use what is perhaps an unfortunate term today, but a handy one, an extreme plasticity to human nature.
And that, in fact, what is taken as natural to human transforms with every shift in a mode of production.
So it is in that line that I think of biocommunism.
And it is that particular perspective which, in fact, gives me a reasonable degree of optimism or to think that a beyond capitalist society
would indeed generate types of subjects who have tendencies and inclinations towards forms of behavior which are very much eclipsed or subordinated within capitalism.
Yes, tendencies towards cooperation, solidarity, responsibility, so forth and so on.
You talk of coercion. I don't think that all forms of social discipline are necessarily negative.
I mean, I actually think that there are situations in which, in fact, it is important for people to have certain types of behavior rewarded more than others.
And depending on the manner in which that is done, that can actually be an important and constructive part of shaping various forms of behavior.
I mean, even if one thinks of some very happy activity like playing soccer or something like that, there are rules.
And so I think that one can arrive at a situation in which while one completely outlaws any form of brutalization or degradation,
one can have a structure of rewards, incentives and even penalties, in fact, which become important and ultimately beneficial in terms of constructing people's capacities and tendencies.
And I would just simply say, you know, I mean, I can think of occasions and contexts in my own life in which various forms of discipline, in fact, have been extremely good,
knowing that if I behaved one way, I would get some things and if I behaved another way, I wouldn't.
And so I don't think that the concept of discipline in that sense should be seen as a no-no in a discussion of a progressive society.
In fact, I actually see the complete rejection of concepts of discipline as much more characteristic of a certain kind of liberal hyper individualism.
But I don't need to expand on that point.
I think that there is probably a reasonable middle ground that one can arrive at between issues of volunteerism and the social shaping of subjectivities,
which would be infinitely more benign and kind and constructive than that to which people are subjected under capitalism today.
And again, here the topic comes up how these forms of discipline are being formed and who participates in forming them and how these rules are actually brought about.
So this will be, of course, a huge question.
And let me just return to that point again in regard to this evidently provocative proposal about the universal army of labor.
But we need to put this in a context in which an assumption that I'm making is that the planning of the activities of the universal army of labor
is itself a democratic and socially distributed activity subject to extensive discussion, debate, various levels of collective determination
in ways that have been well discussed in the recent efflorescence of literature about how types of social planning can be conducted.
So I think this is a question that almost any project for a beyond capital society based on collective planning will have to determine.
If there is going to be, if we are going to democratically determine a plan, how then do we democratically determine that plan is actually executed, right?
And so I don't think one can shrink from that too much, right?
Yeah, right. I mean, again, as I stated before, I think most of my disagreement would be at least a huge part of my disagreement would be about the framing,
because whether or not we would have to call it an army with all the connotation that goes along with it is, of course, a different question.
I know, I know. Yes, it may be that I'm too fond of the provocation value of some, but perhaps it served a purpose because we had an interesting conversation.
Yes, of course. And I mean, what you stated in the last part of your answer, of course, builds a very nice bridge to the last element of biocommunism you described, ecological and economic planning.
On this topic, you provide three biocommunist notes, one on ecological limits, one on an alternative to consumerism and then the transmission problem.
Well, while these are quite short notes within the text, I think they all raised important points. So could you please elaborate on these notes on planning?
Yes, surely. And just let me, I think here I should provide a little bit of contextualization for the situation in which I wrote a paper on which our discussion is based.
So there's recently been a huge surge of interest in socialist or communist economic and social planning.
A search, I should say, in which your podcast and your writings and those of your associates are a very, very important contribution.
I wrote a 2013 paper called Red Plenty Planning on contemporary lessons to be learned from Soviet cybernetic planning.
But since that time, the discussion has been advanced by what I regard as far more expert scholars, economists and activists in a multitude of directions.
So there's now a flourishing literature on the sorts of institutions and technologies required for a democratically planned economy.
And many of the people prominently involved in these discussions were at the conference on socialist futures, in which I first tried out this biocommunist idea.
And that conference featured important and lively discussions, as you saw, about issues such as the relation between algorithmic and associational planning, the role of computers versus humans, and many other aspects of this.
So in this paper, rather than recapitulating those discussions, I essentially assumed them.
I let the conference, I admit, do a lot of the heavy lifting in terms of assumptions about some basic elements of planning.
And instead, I just made these three perhaps rather cryptic comments on what I saw as their special relevance to biocommunism.
There's something on it just shortly on each.
I think that today the importance of including ecological data, ecological goals and objectives in any form of economic planning should be absolutely obvious.
Indeed, the idea that I incorporate into the proposal for biocommunism, that planning should take account of two boundaries, as it were, the boundaries of ecological and social sustainability is not a new one by any means.
Many green thinkers have promoted it for well over a decade.
However, in practice, this idea of planning to situate humans' sociality and economic activity between these two boundaries has been largely hijacked by corporate greenwashers, who have chosen to interpret the idea of social sustainability
as the ongoing necessity for economic growth, a.k.a. expanded capital accumulation.
I therefore see biocommunism as a project that would apply that boundary model of planning between the horizons of social and ecological sustainability in a way that, a, sees a very high degree of social equalization of living conditions as a prerequisite for social sustainability.
It has to be a highly egalitarian society, and b, removes the presupposition of growth or of increased material throughputs in human production as an a priori assumption.
That is to say, I see biocommunist planning as a process which should be open to, but not necessarily tied to, concepts such as those of degrowth or of growth of certain economic activities in some zones and decreases in certain spheres of activity and perhaps in certain regions in others.
The important, the critical factor is that that decision is not taken as already a given, but as an issue for social decision, which is made dependent on changes in environmental, technological, and other conditions.
The transmission problem, I think, is also well known. What I mean by this is the tendency in historic and highly top-down planned economies such as that of the former USSR for planners to be given misinformation by producers who feared retribution for failing to make quotas or seeking to hoard resources, consequently corrupting the entire
process of foresight and coordination that should be intrinsic to planning. Alec Nove wrote many years damningly about this information problem.
And that is, in fact, precisely why, in my perspective as a biocommunist, I wanted to emphasize the importance of planning conducted in a context of multifarious organizations with strong worker protections, including protections and indeed encouragements for criticizing, correcting, and proposing alternatives to plans from above.
Back to the mission tactics of a universal army of labor. Until last with the issue of what you term an alternative to consumerism, because I think in some ways this is perhaps the most important.
As you know well, a great deal of market positive criticism of planning hinges on what is known as the calculation problem.
That is to say, the difficulty of predicting millions upon millions of consumer choices involving a vast range of differentiated commodities.
In many ways, this was Friedrich Hayek's line of attack on planning the impossibility, in fact, of any planning process replicating this type of complex decision making.
And it's a strong attack, one that many people have recently put a lot of work into refuting.
However, it is worth bearing in mind that it may not be the self-chosen task of a future communism to recreate a complex consumerist society.
In a talk I gave many years ago, went on a great length about the calculation problem, Jeffrey Kay once remarked to me at the end that to the degree that one can attain some social consensus on the provision of a certain common or universal basket of goods,
and has that accepted as a norm, then the calculation problem starts to become much less difficult.
It starts to recede, as it were, in centrality, and planning can be devoted to more interesting and important ends rather than ensuring the supply of endless varieties of mobile phones, automobiles, deodorants, you name it.
That observation has stuck with me, and I think it may be key to establishing something like biocommunism.
I am very attracted to some of the concepts put forward by green economists, such as George Monbiot, is a concept of what he terms public luxury and private sufficiency.
That of a society in which very large investments are put into the creation of available shared environments and activities, creating rich and ecologically flourishing urban environments, for example,
or large opportunities for many people to have excellent holidays on occasion in your created public facilities.
But where private consumption is at a level that is sufficient, that is comfortable, but where it does not become the primary access within which levels of extravagance
or conspicuous consumption and status seeking and so on are part of it. I think that is very important, and I think that could well be incorporated as something within a biocommunist horizon,
and something which also reconfigures to some degree some of the problems which attend ideas of democratically planning very complex societies. So those were my three notes on those points.
And I mean, you already mentioned it at the beginning of our conversation that you think that the state will play a crucial role within biocommunism. I mean, of course, it's not an unproblematic actor, the state. So could you maybe elaborate a bit on the role of the state within biocommunism?
Yeah, okay. Fair enough. I think in the introduction to my essay, I suggest that biocommunism, in my thinking, could be defined by a triangulation between three other concepts of communism, solar communism, war communism, and disaster communism.
That is to say, it affirms the potential for a new and relatively plenitudinous mode of species reproduction, drawing, for example, on clean, renewable energy, widely socially distributed, as prophesied by Schwarzman and various other people who've written on the concept of biocommunism.
But it also holds that the conditions for this will have to be created in the emergency context that I've already outlined of disaster, rescue, repair, and restoration as a massive operation of salvage from the damage that has been done to the planet by capitalism.
Yes, it accepts that this will require the emergency mobilization of resources, many of which can only at this moment be commanded through the state apparatus.
And here, I follow the argument made by Andres Malm in his return to the concept of war communism as articulated by Lenin in the depth of the crisis of the Bolshevik revolution, and also to the thinking of, I think, very serious socialist scholars of global warming like Christian Parenti and the Bolsheviks.
And so on, who basically argue that it is, in fact, imperative that the state apparatus be mobilized in order to quell global warming.
There is no other route than that.
But I also accept that while indeed the state apparatus is necessary at this moment, even the exertion of that apparatus demands forces well beyond its scope, including the various forms of autonomous organization,
mutual aid, communization that have been postulated by groups such as out of the woods and other anarchist or or communization theorists.
So what I am attempting to propose in bio communism is a situation in which, yes, the state is in play, but it is engaged with these wider social movements.
And that interplay between state and movements, in fact, transforms both of them in a certain sense, in as much as it creates, shall we say, a much more democratically distributed fabric of governance,
in which both various state departments and functions become disaggregated from a totalizing control system.
And conversely, various forms of communal self organization come to play an ever more important part and become, in fact, an absolutely critical set of nodes and channels for the in terms of social decision making.
You know, I again, I know I'm going to set something off off here if I if I say this, but I believe that well known biocommunist scholar Donald Rumsfeld, most as many say, if you have a problem, make it bigger.
Right. And that's really my my view on the governance question.
If you have a if we have a problem with with this with the state form, in fact, the way it should be addressed, not so much with the state is going to wither away, but it should be exploded from within actually by
the expansion and distribution of governance functions through a much wider range of institutions, all of which have their part to play within this process.
To come back to the phrase that I've already used, Mark described as the creation of vast association.
And I would say that is that that would be my my perspective on the state question in biocommunism.
And this kind of nicely leads me to the question of transition.
I mean, you you state explicitly within the paper that this is not about transition and that this is actually a topic that is in general very much important that that but that you do not address within the paper.
But I thought I'll ask anyway. So how do we get to the point where we can explode the state from within?
So do you have any thoughts about transition?
I have a very brief thought or really just a reference on this because obviously this could be another two hours worth of conversation right there and should be.
So I'm simply going to say that my thinking about transition and the struggles along that road has recently been very strongly influenced by Rodrigo Nunes in his what I consider outstanding work, neither vertical nor horizontal towards the theory of political organization.
I think that this is a book that does a great deal to overcome left fetishisms and divisions both about different forms of communist organization and about the relation of different groups engaged in the struggles against capital.
Nunes writes eloquently, I think, about the need to create what he terms and ecology of struggles.
And although I don't normally favor that sort of naturalizing discourse, I think that in this case, he carries it off very well in terms of making the argument for a type of transition movement.
And he is, in fact, thinking very obviously centrally about environmental traditions, but transitions, but also anti-capitalist transitions in which one will have a multiplicity of different forms of organizations.
And in which the critical factor will be to consider the types of reciprocities, independencies and complementarities that can be created between these different modalities of organization rather than looking for, as he puts it, the one weird trick that will be a strike,
the right variety, the occupation, whatever, that will undo capitalism.
Now, I don't want to usurp Rodrigo's voice.
I do want to recommend strongly his work to your listeners.
But actually, one of the things that I love about his book is the use to which he puts a quote from the 1960s poet Diane de Prima.
And the quote is this, no one way works.
It will take all of us shoving up the thing from all sides to bring it down.
And I would add, yes, and there is going to be a lot of shoving.
Well, I mean, again, a very nice bridge to my last question, which would be, if you think about the future, what makes you joyful?
Joy is in the present.
I don't know what the future holds.
You know the saying, I think it's a Polish one, those who look into crystal balls, that is, they will be likely to be fortune tellers, should be prepared to eat ground glass.
But I do truly enjoy the opportunity to converse with you and I hope indirectly with our listeners about how we might together overcome great dangers in order to create a new and more joyful society.
Well, Nick, this has been an absolute pleasure.
Thank you so much for taking the time to be part of future history.
Thank you for giving me this opportunity to present these, again, very nascent thoughts and for nurturing them with the incisive questions and suggestions that you've made.
I truly appreciate it.
Thank you very much, Jim.
That was our show for today.
Thanks a lot for listening.
If you want to support future histories, you can do so on Patreon.
For this, visit patreon.com slash future histories, or you can simply tell a friend that you like the show and that he, she or they might like it as well.