Welcome to Future Histories, my name is Jan Gross and it is my great pleasure to welcome
Sören Mao in today's episode.
Sören is a communist philosopher and author of the brilliant book Mute Compulsion, a Marxist
Theory of the Economic Power of Capital, which I enjoyed reading a lot.
And by the way, it's also available in German under the title Stummerzwang, eine Marxistische
Analyse der ökonomischen Macht im Kapitalismus, published by the great Karl Dietz Verlag.
So go and get it.
More recently, an essay by Sören titled Communism as Freedom has been translated from Danish
in multiple languages actually, so it's available in English as well.
Both of these works, the book as well as the essay, are relevant for the conversation you're
about to hear.
Before we start, I'd like to thank Lukas, Fabian and Wilfried for their kind donations
and welcome Markus, Daniel and Jakob as patrons of Future Histories.
Thank you so much.
And then some quick social media news.
You can now follow Future Histories on Blue Sky as well, so go and follow, I guess.
And since I never mentioned it before on the podcast on air, there's also a Future Histories
newsletter you can subscribe to.
So you might do that as well.
But now please enjoy today's episode with Sören Mao on planning and freedom.
Welcome Sören.
Thank you.
And thank you so much for inviting me.
Sören, I'm absolutely convinced that freedom and security are two crucial pillars that
must be positively occupied when constructing alternative political imaginaries.
So I was extremely happy to see you make such a strong and very clear-minded case for
why communism is freedom.
Could you explain to us why communism is freedom and why security is part of the package as
well?
Well, I think that for me, freedom is kind of like the guiding principle for thinking
about how to organize a communist society.
And maybe the reason for that is that, or it has to do with what I think the problem
with capitalism is.
I wouldn't emphasize, first of all, that it's an unjust system of exploitation or that it's
alienating, for example.
But I would argue that the most important reason why, or the thing that's first of
all wrong with capitalism is that it implies domination, that it's an enemy of freedom,
that capitalism is an economic system that prohibits people from living the life they
want to live.
And that's what I write about in my book, Mute Compulsion, that capitalism is a system
of domination.
So it kind of follows from that critique of capitalism that we should think of an alternative
to capitalism as a way of avoiding domination, as creating a society with the highest possible
degree of freedom.
So that's how I think about what communism should be.
So that's my guiding principle to think of a society with the highest degree of freedom.
So in that sense, I think freedom is the first and most important principle maybe of communism.
And how does this relate to the question of security?
Well, I think security is a condition for exercising freedom that we want to be able
to exercise in a communist society.
So in that sense, it's also a presupposition or it's a fundamental thing about communism
also.
In the sense that only on the basis of existential security and an absence of fear of not being
able to sustain oneself, freedom can develop.
That's kind of the reason I know.
One of the primary aims of a communist society would be to secure unconditional access to
everything that people need to live a good and stable and healthy life.
And just as an additional follow up in terms of the definition of freedom.
So the way that you described it before, it was very much related to an absence of domination.
Are there other aspects of freedom that you would stress when it comes to this huge and
fundamental question of what this actually means?
Freedom?
Yes.
Well, I like the definition of freedom as absence of domination, but I would also and
I think this is maybe just another way of saying that actually that freedom is intrinsically
connected to democracy or is a democratic idea in the sense that human beings are by
nature social beings and human beings are also natural beings, a part of nature and
are dependent on the earth and the earth belongs to no one and therefore to everyone.
And that means in a sense that we are by nature political animals and that the question of
how human beings relate to their conditions of existence is necessarily a political question.
And because of that, I think that freedom is not just a question of the relationship
between the individual and the political community or political institutions.
And that would be like the modern or liberal notion of political freedom, that freedom
is a question of the absence of political institutions from the point of view of the
individual.
Freedom also has to consist in being able to participate in making decisions about
the necessarily common aspects of our lives.
And in that sense, I think freedom is inherently a democratic ideal.
And since you mentioned this logic that you apply when it comes to the question of human
nature or humans relation to nature, I think it would also be maybe a useful aspect to
point out that when it comes to this idea of freedom, as far as I understand your idea
of it, it does not entail a certain naturalized idea of that there was a human subject as
an essence that should be kind of brought into full fruition, so to speak.
At least that's how I understood it, that you are opposed to this notion of a naturalized
kind of free individual that is suppressed by the conditions that surround them.
Yes, that's right.
So one way of putting it would be to say that there is no natural in the sense of an immediately
given way for human beings to relate to their conditions of existence.
It's always a political question.
So it's up to us.
So communism is not an exercise in trying to discover the authentic natural ways for
human beings to relate to their conditions of existence.
But communism means establishing the political conditions for actually making decisions
about how we want to relate to our collective conditions of existence.
And there's no natural way of doing that.
It's always a political decision.
And there's no subject that should be liberated beneath that, right?
Exactly.
Okay.
So we will get to the point where we kind of dive a little bit deeper into the way you
imagine the set up for how communism might bring all of these things about.
But before we do so, I would first like to address a different layer of abstraction,
so to speak, which I believe to be of great importance for the way in which we think
about alternatives.
In your book, Mute Compulsion, you argue that Marx's critique is not aiming to provide
an alternative political economy, but that he instead criticizes the field of political
economy as such and the implicit assumptions and concepts that are baked into it, so to
speak.
So what are the elements and functional logics of the field of political economy that Marx
criticized and what does this critique mean for the way in which we think about alternatives
to capitalism today?
I think that probably the most fundamental gesture in Marx's critique of political economy
is to historicize.
So the problem with the field of political economy is, first of all, it's a historical
way of thinking about capitalism or about the economy.
So I think that's the most important shift of perspective in Marx's critique of political
economy and his critique of capitalism, to view the capitalist economy as a historical
reality, as something that came into being at a certain point in history for certain
historical reasons that we need to uncover and explain.
So another way of saying that is to say that the problem with political economy is its
economism, its tendency to, and that's something that you also find in mainstream economics
today and also, I would say, much political science, the often implicit idea that the
economy is a separated sphere of society governed by its own distinct forms of rationality.
I think Robert Brenner puts it very well, he writes somewhere that historical materialist
accounts of capitalism begin by denying the existence of a transhistorical economic rationality.
So the idea is to politicize the economy, to see the economy as consisting of social
relations, historically specific social relations, and therefore as a political reality, and
that means rejecting the conceptual separation between politics and economics, the political
and the economic.
So that's obviously also important for how we think about alternatives to capitalism,
because that means that there are no transhistorical economic laws, there is no such thing as
transhistorical economic rationality.
It's up to us to decide how the economy should be organized, that means it's up to us to
decide what should be produced and who should produce it and how it should be produced
and who should get the results of that production and so on.
All of these economic processes, all of these economic decisions are always necessarily
political decisions.
So I think that's maybe the most fundamental idea in Marx's critique of political economy.
Okay, let's maybe dig a little deeper into that.
So in your article you write that it's not, when it comes to the question of alternatives,
you write that following from that it's not about providing an alternative economic principle,
but that it's instead, and I quote, you hear about enabling democratic decision making
about how our shared activities and resources should be organized.
And I think you already mentioned some aspects that are kind of related to this question
when it comes to how to avoid, let's say, the mistakes of economists, so to speak.
But I would be interested to take a second look into this.
Would you say that we should kind of ditch economics altogether?
You stated that you need to historicize it, there are no transhistorical laws of economics,
so to speak.
But are there, let's say, some aspects maybe of the theoretical apparatus of political
economy or maybe a bit more narrowly economics that can sensibly be repurposed for a constructive
effort around alternatives, or would you argue that we should kind of ditch the discipline
of economics altogether?
That would be one part of my question and the other one would be, and this is a very
crucial aspect to me, in neoliberalism, the market constitutes also a site for the production
of truth.
So if we argue for overcoming the market in this function as well, I'm asking myself,
what could be the mechanisms, maybe in plural, to fulfill this aspect of societal organization?
Because this is a very, very crucial mechanism, I would say, within the way our societies
are governed today, and I get the sense that simply stating we will do it democratically
then does not kind of answer the questions sufficiently, I would say, because these
things operate on different levels, I would say.
To be honest, I'm not sure I understand why saying we will do that democratically
is not a good answer, because I think that the way the function of the market in capitalism
as one of the functions of the market in a capitalist society is coordinating production,
coordinating decisions of individual producing units about how much to produce and how to
produce things, by what productivity standards and so on.
That's one of the things that price signals does, and that would be replaced by planning.
So we would take, in a communist society, we would make democratic decisions about
what are we going to produce, and we would also be able, for example, to take democratic
decisions about production methods and productivity standards, for example.
So in that sense, I think my answer would simply be that we are going to replace the
market and market mechanisms with democratic decision processes.
And I'm not sure why that's not a good answer.
It's an absolutely great answer in general, I would say, but since I conducted quite
a couple of interviews on democratic planning by now with different people who develop different
models surrounding that, I more and more got the sense that at some point, when it comes
to crucial questions within these models, this is the default answer, which is kind
of serving as a cover-up in many ways.
And it's serving as a cover-up, for example, when it comes to questions of valuation
or evaluation, like measure, what's the way in which we kind of agree to measure, let's
say?
What do we agree on what the basis of our decision-making and evaluation is, so to speak?
So that's one element.
And the other one is that in some of the instances, there's a certain, for me, problematic
fallback to a certain notion of the subject, because then if you go further, you know,
we do it democratically, okay, fine, that's great.
And then what's the basis of this democratic process?
And then you get to the question of the subject.
And then in many instances, you have a kind of weird notion of the underlying subject,
I would say, which is conceptualized as an autonomous, self-activating and self-governing
subject, to quote Pat Devine, who otherwise has a very, very, very great model or idea
of how to approach democratic planning.
But there you get to some kind of, it gets more complicated than just stating, okay,
we do it democratic and then it's fine, I would say, because there are certain questions
that are attached to it that still need to be answered or that might complicate the
whole thing quite a bit, I would say.
But in general, it's of course right to say so.
If we just state it very generally, then yes, absolutely, let's do democratic planning,
of course.
You're right that there are a lot of complicating factors here and it's obviously an extremely
important question you raise about how we evaluate and how we measure and are we going
to measure in hours and labor time, for example?
Some people would say no, I don't really see a problem with doing that.
But it's obviously extremely difficult, I think, to come up with a very clear answer
to how we decide on productivity standards, for example.
So if we democratically decide that we want to produce a certain amount of a certain
product and then we need to know how much time does it take to produce that.
And in order to make that calculation, we need a productivity standard.
And how do we decide on that?
Should it be the producers, for example, the people who are actually producing the product
that should decide that, decide how they want to work?
Or do we want to accept some kind of that they have to do it within certain limits,
that the broader society as such can demand a certain productivity standard from the producers?
But no matter how we answer those questions, I think it always comes back to that the
only legitimate way of doing that in a communist society would be to do some sort of
democratic decision making process.
So that's a difficult question, but it's a question we would have to find some sort
of answer to, because the alternative would be to accept the blind forces of the blind
domination of the market or something like that, or a despotic authority of some sort.
Right, right.
No, no, neither of those, for sure.
But maybe just to get an idea about the first part of the question.
How much of the corpus of political economy and economics specifically can be repurposed
in a sensible way for this constructive effort?
Because I mean, somehow one gets the sense that it's built on rotten ground.
But I mean, it is also there might still be something that can be useful.
So I would be interested in your opinion on that.
I'm not totally sure what to answer to this question.
I'm tempted to say that there's not much of worth keeping in economics, but I think
that a planned economy would require a lot of data gathering, data collecting, collecting
and managing data and also a lot of calculation.
And it might be that there are some aspects of economics that would be useful in order
to do that calculation and handling of data, but I'm not sure.
Okay, so let's kind of leave this very abstract level and get to a bit more concrete levels
of the discussion.
Your article describes some of the basic coordinates of how to organize our societies differently
in communism in order to provide freedom, security and much, much more.
Could you maybe run us through the basic coordinates of how you imagine communism to be organized?
Yes, that's a big question, but I guess the basic idea is that communism requires replacing
the market with planning and to create new political institutions that would enable
us to make democratic decisions about what to do with our common resources and to make
decisions about, economic decisions about what to produce and how to produce it and
where and when and how to distribute the results of that production.
And that's, I think, the basic coordinates, if that's what you mean.
Well, maybe, I mean, there would be the need for some types of institutions, for example.
So could you maybe go into that?
Like what kind of institutions would we need?
How would they need to be different from the institutions we have?
So maybe you could give us a sketch of this institutional setup.
Yes, I think that in order to secure the highest possible degree of freedom and security
and in order to avoid concentration of power as much as possible, it would be useful to
try to make decisions as close as possible to those who are affected by those decisions.
I think that would be an important guiding principle for creating a network of institutions
that would allow us to plan production.
So power should be decentralised as much as possible.
But of course, there are certain decisions that cannot be left to individuals or to
small local groups or something like that, especially here, I'm especially thinking
of decisions regarding use of natural resources.
So we're obviously also going to need some sort of actually a global institution for
making decisions about that.
But so I'm imagining communist political institutions as a network of several layers of
institutions that make decisions and where there's not a clear hierarchy of institutions
in the way that we're used to from the nation state as we know it.
So I think that if we use the word state to talk about what we know as the modern nation
state, then we would have to abolish the state and design and construct new political
institutions.
If we use a broader notion of the state as basically any kind of political institution,
then I would say that we need to come up with a new form of state, a new state power.
But that's not really an answer to your question, is it?
Well, that's totally fine.
If you do not have this sketch of which kinds of institutions specifically would be needed
and which kinds of tasks they would be able and necessary to perform, that's totally
all right.
I think it would be nonetheless good to kind of paint a little bit more of a picture of
how you imagine this general set up to be, because there are some other aspects that
you do define in your text.
You write about communes.
You write about that these communes should be ideally autark, more or less, even though,
as you pointed towards in your last answer as well, even though there is the need for
kind of higher level coordination as well.
But you, at least in the text state, that you think this would be an ideal structure
to have these communes to be more or less autark.
You also write about a certain amount of work that people should perform.
And I'm absolutely curious about getting to know whether or not this implies some form
of compulsion to work, which is kind of implied, but not really made explicit.
So there are other aspects to the way that you imagine this communist society to be
organized that you do have ideas about.
So maybe we could kind of get into those aspects as well.
Yes, yeah, I use the word commune as a way of talking about what would be the basic
institutional unit of communism.
And ideally, every commune would have control over everything that the commune needs in
order to secure a good and stable life for its communards, for the people who live in
that commune. And the reason why I think that's an important principle is that it would
make us less vulnerable to counterrevolutionary attempts to re-erect class society, for
example, or other forms of also forms of concentration of power or corruption, something
like that. If communes are not too dependent upon each other, then they would have
more autonomy. And that means that if if something went wrong in one commune, it wouldn't
necessarily the other communes would have a better basis for struggling against that or
trying to avoid a concentration of power or corruption or counterrevolutionary
movements and so on.
Yet at the same time, you, I think, rightfully stress that there is actually by nature, you
argue, a high level of interdependence.
You know, and I when reading about this autarky aspect of the commune, even though I
understand your argument as well, that it creates some kind of safety backup, so to
speak, when it comes to attacks and stuff like that.
But still, I was kind of a bit irritated about this falling back into this very strong
notion of autonomy, because, as I said, really like the approach of emphasizing the
interdependence. And this interdependence is also highly relevant when it comes to, like
many, many of the aspects that will have to be addressed through each and every commune
as well. You already talked about the question of resource use.
I mean, if we do want to have some kind of meta level coordination when it comes to
this question of resource use, which is kind of necessary if we want to, for example,
address climate change and excessive resource use as it is being performed right now, then
you immediately get into a situation where you will have to have functioning forms of
mediation between these different levels, so to speak.
So and there I would say I would argue this idea of autarky kind of goes against this
grain, because the level in which this interdependence and therefore
interconnection will have to be enacted is so much ingrained in each and every aspect
of, for example, the production process, that it's very hard to imagine both of these
same things at the same time, you know, this high, very high level of autonomy for each
commune and kind of organizational coordination on a meta level when it comes to, for
example, overall resource use, because these things are necessarily intertwined in a very,
very intense way.
So I was kind of struggling to imagine how highly autarky communes working next to each
other, so to speak, but not really together as a default modus operandi, so to speak,
how these autonomous communes would be able to to achieve this higher level coordination.
I think that regarding the question of interdependence, I think that there's a
fundamental difference between human individuals and political communities.
I think humans are necessarily by nature social animals that are highly dependent upon
each other. So the interdependence I speak about is the interdependence between human
individuals, which is which is one of the reasons why, as I tried to explain earlier,
that that's one of the reasons why human freedom must necessarily also consist in
being able to participate in democratic political decision making processes.
But the same point, that point about interdependence is not necessarily true of
political communities, I would say of communities of human beings.
Political communities are not necessarily dependent upon each other to the same degree.
We are dependent on each other in the way that all political communities would live on
the same planet and we would have to share that planet.
And because of that, it would be necessary to have some sort of global regulation of the
use of natural resources, for example, how it could, for example, take the form of
quotas for CO2 quotas or something like that on a global level for each commune.
And then each commune would decide how they would use that or all sorts of different
quotas for the use of natural resources.
And then it would be up to each commune to decide how to use that.
So there is certainly an interdependence there that means that some sort of cooperation
between communes would be necessary.
But I think it would be a good idea to not to have a too high degree of division of labor
between communes, for example, because interdependence and division of labor would
always be a risk, because if one commune is dependent on something that another
commune produces, then a power relationship of domination can easily arise.
So in order to secure freedom and in order to counteract tendencies to inequality
between communes and relationships of domination between communes, it would be important to
maintain a high degree of autonomy, I would say.
Because imagine, for example, that the commune you live in has decided not to produce
medicine, for example, because there's a neighbor commune that produces a lot of
medicine instead.
And there's a division of labor where you and then you exchange or whatever you produce
something else that that other commune needs.
But then if there's something like a counterrevolutionary political force or movement
in that other commune where all of the medicine you need in your commune is produced, then all
of a sudden you would have to accept what they do or accept their demands or subject
yourself to that.
So you would be vulnerable in that sense if the commune you lived in don't have the
resources to produce medicine for themselves, for example.
How big of a commune do you imagine?
So if you talk about communes as the smallest organizational unit, how big are these
communes you think about?
That's a really good question.
And I think that communes could vary very much in size.
I think one thing that's important to note here is that we would have to build
communism on the basis of whatever capitalism has left us with, which means, for example,
that we would have to build communism also in enormous urban areas with 20 million
people, for example.
So I would imagine, for example, that we would break up cities like Tokyo or Shanghai
or New York into several communes.
And one of the problems with an urban commune would be that it would be unable to produce
its own food.
So it would be a good idea, for example, to have communes that would extend from an urban
area into a rural area in order to be able to produce everything the commune needs.
But I imagine that communes in heavily urbanized areas would maybe have up to one or two
million inhabitants or communists.
But I also imagine that in other places, in very desolate areas with very few people,
we could have quite large, in terms of area, large communes with maybe only 50,000
inhabitants or something like that.
And there are so many different reasons why to draw the borders between communes.
It could also be, for example, natural, like the landscape, the landscape could also be
reasons for drawing borders between communes, mountains or rivers or things like that.
So I think that we would, that the communes could very, very much incise from, for example,
maybe from a few thousand people to millions of people.
I think we kind of then circle back to this question of interdependence again, because
I mean, for many things, I mean, if you want to build a computer, you will have to have
minerals, many materials, knowledge, so many things that not every like two or five
thousand people commune will be able to provide, obviously.
So again, we are back to this question of interdependence and kind of impossibility
of total autarky when it comes to many, many things, you know, infrastructural things
like train connections that span, in this case, many communes for sure, because we would
not want to kind of just get to the border of my commune and then have to change into
another form of transportation, so to speak.
So I mean, these are all, of course, questions that kind of pop up in this very atomized
way of thinking about it.
And if that would be a too big a problem, then I guess communes could decide to make
one larger commune, like to fusion, is that the word, into a larger commune.
Or they would maybe just accept that there are certain things that they are unable to
produce. And because in such a situation people would be able to move freely between
communes, then, you know, it would maybe also, we should maybe also think of that as a
situation where there would be many different kinds of communes with many different forms
of life and that maybe some people would prefer, you know, one way of living in a
rural commune where you wouldn't have to work that much, but there would also be certain
things that you wouldn't be able to have there.
But you would always be able to move to another commune if you wanted to do that.
Or the commune could also just, you know, it would be up to each commune to decide
how much to depend on other communes or make agreements with other communes about
exchanging things or whatever.
Okay, maybe let's then dig a little deeper into this, because you just now mentioned
exchange, so let's dig a little deeper into the planning process, because you do sketch
some ideas within your text.
Could you maybe run us through how you imagine a planning mechanism to go about?
Yes, well, I think the first step is that we would have to make decisions about what we're
going to take collective responsibility for producing.
So, decisions about what to produce would have to be taken democratically in our political
institutions in the commune.
And then, and I imagine that that would, could, for example, take the form of different groups
or organizations or that could submit proposals and that there would be some sort of, you
know, public debate about that or, and then maybe several rounds of voting for those
different plans, which would be plans for maybe a couple of years, let's say two years,
for example.
So, every second year we would vote for a new plan and that plan would basically be a
proposal for what to take collective responsibility for producing.
So, what to do with our common resources.
And then through that political process, we would end up with a production plan and that
would then have to be implemented and that could be translated to a certain amount of
working hours, total working hours that would be distributed as a rule evenly among everyone.
So, that's like the way I think about that in very broad terms.
And would there then be a compulsion to work?
We touched upon this, but didn't yet answer it.
That's a good question and I think that I would love to be able to say no and that there would
never be any form of, that in communism everyone would be able to do whatever they want
all the time and that there would be no one forcing you to do anything, but I'm not sure.
I think that's a realistic thing to say.
So, it's a realistic scenario that some people might not live up to their duties all the time
and I think that we would then have to discuss to what degree we would accept that
because I could also imagine that it would also be possible just to calculate with that
in a sense that there's a certain amount of people that wouldn't show up for work or
something like that and maybe we could just accept that, but if it turns out that it has
too many negative consequences in the long run, I think there would probably need to be
some sort of, I'm not sure compulsion to work is the right way to describe it, but
I could imagine, for example, that you could lose certain privileges if you don't take your
share of collective responsibilities. I think that it's really important to, as I said earlier,
to guarantee unconditional access to everything that people need to live a
good, healthy, stable life, so unconditional access to housing and food, medicine,
healthcare and so on, but imagine, for example, that we have collectively decided that everyone
has the right to take a new education every 10 years, for example, then maybe that's a
right that you could lose or imagine that there are waiting lists for certain, especially
attractive housing, something like that, and then maybe if you don't show up for work,
then you will lose your place on the waiting list for a housing or something like that.
So there could be certain things that I'm not sure I would categorize that as or call that
compulsion to work. Does that make sense? Yeah, kind of. I mean, I think for me the thing is that
I would say that you end up with this dilemma, because I can sense that it's a dilemma for you
as well, somehow it feels like it. And I think you end up with this dilemma because of this
separation that you introduced, the separation between the realm of necessity and the realm
of freedom. So maybe let's talk about that, because I think this is the source for why you then come
to a point where you have this situation where you think that you need to discipline or incentivize,
which is kind of a form of disciplining in a different way, so to speak. That's why you end
up with this constellation where you think that you need to discipline people into doing certain
types of work in order to use this remuneration or withholding of remuneration or benefits in
order to steer, so to speak, the way in which things are being organized. So I think this is
the root of it. So maybe let's talk about it. Could you maybe describe these different realms
to us and why you believe this to be a sensible distinction? Well, it's a distinction
that Marx makes, and I refer to Aaron Benenow when I mentioned it in the essay, but I'm not sure
it's the best way to describe actually what I'm trying to describe there. So the idea is that
there are certain needs that we agree politically to take collective responsibility for,
and that's the public production. That would be what the commune decides to produce,
what we decide together to produce in the commune, and to take responsibility for.
So that's what we could call the realm of necessity, if we want to use that notion,
because it's what we agree is necessary labor, necessary production. So it would obviously be,
for example, production of food for everyone, production of medicine and housing and things
like that. But there are a lot of things that would quite obviously be necessary for
the commune to exist, and we would have to take care of that collectively. But then there are all
sorts of products that we would not necessarily regard as a public responsibility to take care of.
Maybe some people would suggest that we should build a piano factory,
because we want to have pianos. But other people might have the opinion that, well,
I would rather work less, because everything we would decide to produce would mean more work
for everyone, because we would distribute work evenly. So everything we add to the list of what
the commune produces would mean more work for everyone, because we would distribute work evenly.
So it would always be a discussion about or a decision about what do we want to
have more, less work, or do we want to have this or that product.
And then we would disagree on that. So maybe some people would vote for a production plan that
would include pianos and accept that everyone would have to work a little bit more, because
we think it's nice to have pianos. And other people would maybe prefer not to work and then
not to have pianos. And then whatever the result would be, the commune would not necessarily
produce everything that people want. So there will be a lot of needs that will not be met,
or a lot of wants that will not be met by the production that is organized by the commune.
And what are we going to do about that? Well, it's obvious, I think, to say that people
would be, if they can, they would be free to produce that in their free time outside of the
work organized by the commune. So that's kind of like the basis for distinguishing between
the realm of necessity and the realm of freedom. The realm of necessity is the
all of the things we agree are necessary to produce together and that we take collective
responsibility for producing. And as a political community and the realm of freedom is whatever we
want to use all of us, all of the rest of our time, whatever we want to use that for. And it's
important here to know that the realm of freedom would be much larger in
counting in hours and we would have more free time.
Yeah. I want to add that I'm not sure that those terms, the realm of necessity and the realm of
freedom are the best way to describe that. And maybe that's what some of what you were
thinking about when you asked me about this, that I just said earlier that organizing
the economy by means of democratic decision making would be the best thing to do with
one society with as high a degree of freedom as possible. So in a sense that is wrong to oppose
that to freedom. Right. Absolutely. I would agree with that with the last statement. That's why
I think it's an unlucky separation because for me when reading the text I always thought,
what? Wait a second. What you're describing as the realm of necessity is the realm of freedom
since it produces freedom as such. And also through this separation of realm of
necessity and realm of freedom, you get into a position where you kind of reproduce
a certain notion of labor, not only work, but labor, meaning that something that I do not want to do,
but have to do. And this has all kinds of consequences in terms of motivation, in terms of
effectiveness and stuff like that. So I would argue that one would need to approach
what you call the realm of necessity also from a perspective through which
what you have to do in order to reproduce is not just a kind of labor you have to do because you
are being forced to, but is also a part of a perspective that sees this work as absolutely,
I wanted to say logic, but that's maybe the wrong word, as a necessary part of reproduction
that is not separated into a kind of alienating thing to do, so to speak,
maybe to be a bit polemic about it, I would say. So I'm kind of against these different splits.
I can definitely see why you're against that. I think maybe it's good to remind ourselves
why Marx uses these words. And I think it's because when he talks about realm of necessity,
I think he's talking about a kind of natural necessity here, the fact that human beings are
forced to work if we want to live. And I think Marx is right in that one of the fundamental
aspects of human beings is, and he says this already in his early writings in the German
Ideologie, that what distinguishes human beings from other animals is that they produce,
that we are forced to transform our surroundings in order to be able to live of them. So
human beings, we have to work in order to live. We have to transform our surroundings in order
to be able to live off those surroundings. And that is a natural necessity. And that's why
he calls it the realm of necessity, right? And then the more productive we can get,
the less time we need to do that, or also depending on the natural conditions of where we live.
If you live in certain areas, certain places on the earth, it would require more work to
to be able to survive than in other places. But the basic fact is that there is a certain
amount of work that is necessary in order to live. And that's a natural necessity. And that's why
Marx calls it the realm of necessity. And in opposition to that, the rest of your time you
can use to do whatever you want. And that's the realm of freedom. So I think maybe the reason why,
or the source of confusion or disagreement here is maybe that we're maybe confusing
a natural necessity and freedom with political necessity and political freedom,
if that makes sense. Yeah, kind of. But also, I think the way that you use the realm of necessity
is not the way that you described it right now. So it's not the Marxian notion of subsistence. So
the basic level of what you have to do in order to reproduce yourself as a physical,
biological object, so to speak. So you use it in a very different way, which is encompassing
much more than just subsistence. And then, and I think this kind of complicates this as well,
you use these words private sector and public sector. So you use public sector for the realm
of necessity and then private sector for the realm of freedom, so to speak. And I mean,
this also adds another layer of confusion in that it kind of runs the danger of sounding as if you
wanted to say that the private sector, in which you also state that there will possibly still be
markets, exchange, et cetera, that this is the realm of freedom. And it quickly sounds
like this liberal talking point where markets are equated with freedom and planning is
basically tyranny and obligation, so to speak, which is definitely not what you wanted to state.
And it is absolutely clear reading the text that this is not what you wanted to say. But
I just think that this terminology, this additional terminology of public sector and
private sector also kind of feeds into the misunderstanding, I would say. Yeah.
Yeah, I think you're right about that. And there's obviously
a risk that, well, because public and private sector are concepts that we also use about
the capitalist economy, then there's a risk of thinking that what I'm describing
there would be something that's similar to how the capitalist economy works, which is
not what I'm trying to do, but not what I'm trying to say there. So I'm open to suggestions
for a better way of making this distinction, because I think it is an important distinction
to make. And so in a communist mode of production, we would make democratic decisions
about what to produce. But what about all the things that we would decide not to produce?
I mean, I could see myself voting for a production plan that would mean that a lot of things that
some people would like to have would not be produced. And what do we say to those people who
would then would like to have those products? I mean, the thing in capitalism is that Marx puts
it somewhere in capital that money is basically a technology for transforming
a social power into the power of the individual, something like that. He says something about
carrying social power in your pocket or something like that. Because what you can do in capitalism
is that if you have money, then you can basically decide what will happen to some of our
collective resources. Because demand on the market is what determines what gets produced,
right? And that power of the individual in capitalism, that money allows you as an
individual to decide what gets produced. You wouldn't have that in a communist society,
because that's the problem with capitalism, that it's people who have money who decide.
So we would replace that with collective democratic decision making. And that would mean
that there would be a lot of things that we would maybe not take collective responsibility
for producing. And what do we do about that? I think it's not a good answer to say, well,
people just have to accept that we're not going to produce pianos or other things that some
people would maybe think would be luxury products. And I think it's better to say that people would
have the possibility of producing that in their free time. And they could also find other people
who would also like pianos and produce pianos together and then make some kind of private
piano producing factory, if that's what they want. I mean, why shouldn't they not be able to
that? Why should we ban that? And of course, that would require some resources, because you need a
lot of things in order to build pianos. And where would you get those resources from? You would
obviously have to get them from the commune. So again, the commune would have to make decisions
about which resources to give to private production. But I think it's important to
acknowledge that if we are going to have a democratically planned economy, there would be a
lot of things that would not get produced, a lot of needs that would not be met by
our collective production. And we would have to find a way of letting people
having those needs met in other ways. So that's a way of saying that there
would be production also outside of what the commune organizes. The production organized
by the commune would not be all production that there is in society. So we need some sort of
distinction there. We need a concept to distinguish between those two forms of production.
Yeah, I mean, there are different questions attached to that. If you say that what you call
the private sector will need to get some forms of resources, I think then you'll quickly get to
the point where one might say, okay, why then not just include this as a need into the collective
process? Why funnel these resources into a market system, so to speak, in order to be able to
produce piano? So we can have mechanisms that allow for the detection of needs that are not yet
met. We can develop mechanisms that are able to provide some form of plus X that might be some
form of luxury goods. So there should be some mechanisms. I absolutely agree with you. There
should be some mechanisms in place that are able to kind of address these extra needs, so to speak.
I'm not quite sure whether this automatically implies that you will have to have a form of
classical market system, you know, with some form of money, some form of value form and all the
things that go along with this, because at least to me it sounded as if what you describe as a
private sector would then probably have all of these things in order to be able to produce
this plus X. And my argument would be there can be creative ways of integrating this absolutely
valid need for the plus X into forms of democratic planning as well. So it's not about a rigid system
that does not have any ability to change, to include, to have realms of freedom within
what we consider the collective mechanism, I would argue. And also just as a note,
it might be interesting for you to take a look at David Leibman's model of multi-level
democratic iterative coordination, because he does have some kind of setup similar to that,
because he imagines a core sector which is run through this mechanism, the MDIC mechanism,
and then he imagines that there will be some form of kind of peripheral sector,
which will have probably some market mechanisms as well, but which might bit by bit also be
integrated over time into the MDIC system. So just as a note. But we do not have that much
time left and I have so many questions left. So I would have to pick and choose. I mean, maybe
before we get to the final question that I ask all of my guests, maybe let's get back to this
very high level of abstraction that you, I think, very brilliantly look at in your book Mute
Compulsion, because there you describe the fact that capitalism, in order to reproduce itself,
it does not only rely on ideology and violence, but also on mute compulsion or what you call
economic power. So I'm quite interested in the question, which kind of alternatives
a communism would have to provide in order to address these different fields that now
guarantee the reproduction of capitalism. So to frame it a bit more clearly, hopefully,
what kinds of mechanisms of reproduction of reproducing itself would communism need to have
in order to produce this stability and yeah, in order to reproduce itself maybe,
because I think we could go one by one through violence, ideology and economic power and ask
ourselves, okay, now this is in capitalism, this is handled through these three powers,
so to speak, but which kinds of powers would communism need to have in order to reproduce
itself? Well, I think that there would not be something similar to violence in communism,
because I mean, capitalism relies on violence, especially the violence of the state.
Without a state that guarantees private property, for example, through the use of violence in the
form of police and military, capitalism would not be possible. So in capitalism we have a
situation where the economic system is dependent upon the constant use of violence or the threat
of violence for reproducing itself. That would not be necessary in a communist society, but
that does not mean that I don't think that there would be any form of violence in
communism. I think there would still be all sorts of aggression between people and we would
have to find a way to take care of that and that would probably mean also that we would have to
accept that the commune would be able to use violence towards individual people in order to
force them to stop doing something like beating someone else, for example.
Private relationships or violence in that way, but that is not the same as violence as an
integrated element in the economic system. There wouldn't be anything similar to that in
communism. Regarding the question of ideology, I think that's very different. Your question
reminds me of a quote by Louis Althusser in his essay about Marxism and Humanism,
which I really like. There's a passage about ideology where he speaks about what is the role
of ideology and would there be any kind of ideology in a communist society, in a classless society?
I think he has a very nice way of putting that, so I'm just going to read that quote
because I just found it. He writes that, and I quote, in a class society ideology is the
relay whereby and the element in which the relation between men and their condition of existence
is settled to the profit of the ruling class. In a classless society ideology is the relay whereby
and the element in which the relation between men and their conditions of existence is lived to the
profit of all men. So I think that ideology is in a sense, ideology is something that will always
exist. The thing is that ideology is, and he's using a broad notion of ideology here because
this implies that ideology is not necessarily always a form of domination. It can also be
a concept that merely describes how
the way we understand ourselves and our surroundings are affected by our social world
and that can also contribute to reproducing social forms that are not domination or
hierarchies or something like that. So in a class society and in capitalism ideology has the
function of reproducing class society, reproducing capitalism, but we could definitely imagine that
in a communist society there would be ideological forms that would
help reproducing a free society and avoid re-erecting class society.
And then there's the question of whether there would be something similar to
economic power in communism. And I think that when I talk about economic power in capitalism
it's always a form of domination. And in that sense the whole point of
abolishing capitalism and building communism is to get rid of domination. But economic power
reveals something about a unique capacity that human beings have to organize.
We can organize our material surroundings in a way that helps to reproduce certain social
relations. In capitalism those social relations are relations of domination. But it's possible to
think about how in a communist society we could organize our material surroundings in a way that
could help reproduce communism. Or we could think about how could we organize our
material conditions of existence in a way that counteracts tendencies towards domination or
concentration of power, for example. That could be, for example, as we talked about, ensuring a high
degree of local autonomy or autonomy in each commune by giving priority to that above,
for example, productivity and division of labor. Because a high degree of division of labor would
maybe mean higher productivity, less working hours for everyone, less work for everyone.
But it could also have the consequence that it would make society more vulnerable to power
concentration. So there would be a trade-off and we would have to make some
sort of decision about that. So in that sense, if we think of economic power in a broader way as
externalizing social relations in our material conditions of existence or material and social
surroundings, then there would be something similar to that. We could think of using that
capacity, that unique capacity of human beings to work for communist ends in communism.
And then, Sören, there's a last question that I ask all of my guests and it is,
if you think about the future, what makes you joyful?
It makes me joyful to imagine how daily life could be under communism,
to imagine, to work much less and also to imagine that we could have a totally different way of
organizing the division of labor, where maybe I wouldn't just have one function or one job
my entire life. Maybe I could have more than one function at the same time. So one day a week I
could do one thing and then another day in the week I could do something else. And I would maybe have
the opportunity to specialize in something new after a couple of years or do that throughout
my life. And then, of course, it makes me joyful to imagine not to never have to be worried about
money and to know that I would have a secure basis of existence, that I would have a place to live
and something to eat and everything that I would need in order to have a good life without
having to worry about how the economy is developing and what will happen in the next crisis
and whether I will lose my job and will I be able to pay my rent and
stuff like that. That makes me very joyful to think about.
Wonderful. Syrin, thank you so much for being part of Future Histories.
Thank you.
That was our show for today. Thanks a lot for listening. If you want to support Future
Histories, you can do so on Patreon. For this, visit patreon.com slash future histories.
Or you can simply tell a friend that you like the show and that he,
she or they might like it as well. Thanks a lot and hear you in two weeks.