In dieser Episode des Podcasts spreche ich mit Aaron Rabinovitz mit meinem schlechten
Englisch über das Phänomen des ganz stupide übersetzt moralischen Glücks.
Eine deutsche Zusammenfassung für alle, die entweder kein Englisch können oder sich mein
Englisch nicht antun wollen, würde es am Ende noch zusätzlich geben.
Wenn ihr diesen Podcast unterstützen wollt oder bei dem Gast vorbeischauen wollt, dann
schaut doch mal in die Beschreibung.
Mit diesen Worten viel Spaß.
Welcome back, everyone.
Today in the 17th Episode of the Podcast, we have a very special guest.
He's the person or entity behind one of my favorite podcasts.
And I think he can introduce himself a bit, if that's okay for you.
Sure.
My name is Aaron Rabinovitz.
I teach at Rutgers University and do Embrace the Void Podcast and the Philosophers in Space
Podcast and generally hang around social medias, trying to get people to argue about
philosophy.
Great.
So today's topic will be moral luck because a lot of the viewers wanted me to talk about
it and that's not really my specialty.
But as far as I'm aware, you have thought quite a bit about the topic.
Am I correct?
Yeah.
I'm certainly obsessed with the topic.
I don't know if I have anything particularly insightful or useful to say about it, but
I can certainly explain why I'm obsessed with it.
Great.
I think that would be even better than just saying something very important.
Fair enough.
Yeah.
No, no, because I think if you're able to motivate some viewers to think about the topic,
I think that will have a more positive outcome than if you just say something that would
finish the whole topic for the viewer.
So just before we really get into the topic, I have to do something that I always do.
I always have a different drink in the show.
It's a really boring drink as always.
Today I have the star drink, orange zero sugar, just so that everyone knows and can
be aware of me annoying them with the sounds of me drinking.
Do you have anything to drink on your end?
So over here it's 11 a.m., so I'm sticking with water at the moment, depending on what
particular podcast I'm recording and what the content is that that can scale up in various
ways towards whiskey.
Okay, great.
So I guess we could just start.
So the first question would be what moral luck is or what moral luck means.
What are we talking about?
Yeah, so moral luck refers to situations where a person is held morally responsible for
something that is beyond their control.
So in contexts where, you know, someone is seen as guilty of a crime and punished for
doing that crime, even though it seems like the fact that they did that crime was beyond
their control in some important way, would be the sort of classic examples of moral
luck.
And the view that I hold is that pretty much all moral judgments are cases of moral luck
because everything is entirely the result of luck.
Everything is just luck all the way down.
And so that raises real problems for someone like me, who also believes that moral judgments
are real and true and apply objectively and that we should care about them.
So how one reconciles those two things, that's that's really tricky dance.
But I think it's good.
Yeah, on that note, I just have a question on your definition of luck.
So what would you define as luck?
Yeah, and so this gets a little tricky to avoid kind of circularities here.
But I think luck refers to things that are beyond our control.
So the sort of textbook examples that we can think of are, you know, if you're playing a
video game or something that has a random number generator in it, right, it rolls a
number that you have no control over.
And that element of luck, you know, shapes the way that the game is played or how how
these kind of games work.
Right. So, you know, other examples of, you know, really cases of really good or really
bad luck. Right.
You happen to be born into a family where you inherit massive amounts of wealth versus
being born into an abusive household, for example.
Right. These are things that I think there's lots of things that we can reasonably say
are beyond people's control.
Those are the things that I think of as, you know, the features of the world that are luck
in relation to me and in relation to other entities.
And then the hard jump is and everything counts as luck.
Right. And like all of the things are things that are beyond your control in an important
sense. OK, so that that actually was one thing that that was quite problematic for me
when I first read about it, because to me it seems like a problem that I also have with
determinism or fatalism, because in a certain way, if you can apply this concept to
absolutely everything, it seems to me very trivial, like the meaning.
It in a certain sense destroys its own meaning.
Its own impact, because.
Right. It cannot not apply.
Well, so there's a tension right between universality and triviality.
Right. Like we have a similar sort of thing in ethics, I think, where, you know,
you want your moral judgments to be your moral premises to be universal.
You want them to apply to everyone in all situations, in all contexts.
And if they don't, that can seem problematic.
But then some folks will argue the flip side of that is you end up with moral principles
that are incredibly trivial in some kind of way.
And then the hard work becomes teasing out if there really is anything that this adds
to the conversation.
Now, here's why I don't think that this is trivial is because I think a lot actually
really does hang on whether or not everything is beyond our control or not.
If it's true that certain things are under our control and certain things aren't, that's
going to have really important implications for how we shape society, how we treat good
people and bad people.
So I don't think that we can say that this is trivial merely in virtue of the fact that
my position is to argue that everything qualifies as luck, because I think that is a
substantive claim that has substantial implications.
That makes sense?
Yeah, it absolutely makes sense.
But I'm wondering if it is really that important, if it would actually, let's say, let's
say you're absolutely correct.
But would it really change anything in the way of how we experience the world, how we
experience moral dilemmas and so on?
I absolutely think so.
I think that there really is a genuine tension, because so here's why the moral luck problem
and Nagle, I think, does a great job explaining this arises because of a natural feature of
morality, which is that we do think that people should only be held morally responsible
for things that are under their control.
That's a natural condition for moral judgments.
Right. If someone took over your body and went on a killing spree with your body, we
wouldn't think that you should be held morally responsible for that killing spree.
So. So I do think it's important and where we see the implications in the real world
would be in things like how we structure our judicial system.
This is the go to example.
Is that like if you think that human beings have a choice and what they did was wrong and
they did it knowing that it was wrong and that they deserve to be punished for that, you
can build a kind of deterrent, sorry, not deterrent, a kind of retributive model for
justice and say, you know, bad people should go to jail because they deserve to be punished.
If you buy my view, right, it becomes much harder to make any sense of the idea that
people deserve to suffer in any kind of way and that if you're going to have a prison
system, which I still think you need in some form, you're going to have to base it on
rehabilitative kinds of principles, restorative kinds of principles, deterrent kinds of
principles rather than a retributive kind of system.
And that'll have implications for how you build that model, how cruel it is, you know,
what what things you allow your prisoners to do during the times that they are in prison,
stuff like that. So I think it definitely has real applied ethics downstream implications.
And on the personal level, a lot hinges.
A lot of us build our sense of I think all of us, whether we try to resist it some, but
like it's a natural feeling to build your sense of self on your accomplishments and
failures, that like these are the things that define you.
And so I think one reason that people are very uncomfortable with this idea that everything
is luck is that they feel like their sense of self slips away.
And it does. And like part of the reality of recognizing moral luck is recognizing that
there is no free will in a robust sense and with it no robust sense of the separate
self that deserves, you know, a bunch of accolades for doing the right thing.
So I think, yeah, it has lots and lots of implications.
So it's great that you mentioned free will, because I was actually wondering if there
really was a difference on the on a systematic argumentative level between the debate
on free will and determinism and moral luck.
Do you think there is any significance?
I mean, I think they're all connected here, right?
I think what we're saying here is determinism is true and it's true for sentient beings
just as much as it's true for non sentient beings.
And as a result, moral luck is pervasive because luck is pervasive and we continue to
make moral judgments.
So this is a fundamental problem and it is a problem because human beings don't have
free will in the robust kind of sense that we want to think that they do, that you're
not you're just not the author of your actions in the way that would be necessary for it
to be true that you did something wrong in a way that was that was radically independent
and so should be punished in a retributive kind of way.
OK, because to me it was kind of confusing, because when you take a look at the
arguments, how determinism works and how moral luck works, they seem to me to work
on two different different levels.
Determinism is trying to argue from the position of the thing in itself.
If you would like to make this distinction and moral luck is more arguing from the first
person perspective, it seems to me, because luck seems to be a rather strange category
when it comes to determinism.
Mhm, well, so I think it's interesting that you bring that up, because the moral luck
paper that you read is in Nagel's book, Mortal Questions, and he sort of views the unifying
problem of that book, of which moral luck is one version of the problem, as an unresolvable
tension between the subjective way of seeing the world, the way of seeing the world from
our inside first person perspective and an objective account of the world.
The world is seen from the view from nowhere.
And basically the problem is, maybe debatably, from our subjective point of view, we can't
help but see ourselves as free.
Actually, I don't fully believe that, but I think Nagel probably did, or he says that
he does at the end of moral luck.
And so some folks are really concerned that there's no livable way to fully deny the
idea of free will, to deny the idea of the independent, subjectively experiencing self,
to reduce it down to the purely objective.
And I think there are ways in which they're correct about that with regard to phenomenal
consciousness, but not with regard to free will.
I think that the reality is, we are just parts of the large, radically interconnected
system of causal events.
Now, I want to also address your point in terms of unpacking a little bit more the features
of moral luck that Nagel puts forward, because you're right that some of them aren't put
in this necessarily strictly determinist way, though I think that they are just sort of
unpacking forms of determinism.
So he lays out four different kinds of luck.
He talks about luck of consequences, luck of how your actions turn out, right?
He talks about luck of circumstances, what situations that you are facing in your life.
He talks about luck of constitution, which I think is the most important one that he
talks about.
And that's the one that really undermines free will in a robust sense.
And then that's the luck of what makes you who you are, what the features that you happen
to have.
And then there's a fourth one, which often gets dropped out because it's probably exhaustively
accounted for by the other ones, which is essentially the luck of antecedent circumstances,
which is to say, you know, every events are the result of prior events.
And so that one is basically just determinism, right?
It's just saying, you know, we are part of the deterministic framework.
But the value of his argument is the unpacking of that in terms of the nature of constitutive
luck and how it erases any room for an independent, freely acting self.
OK, so you already answered the question of different types.
No problem.
I think it's good that there's a dynamic in this discussion.
Do you yourself think that there are any epistemic problems, any serious epistemic
problems with this position?
Well, yes and no, I guess is my answer to that question, right?
I think there are massive epistemic problems whenever you're talking about conscious
sentient beings and what they are experiencing or not experiencing.
I don't. So like, I've been wrestling myself with this question of do I have, you know,
like I can tell you, I believe that I am not a free agent, right?
I do not have free will, but I'm mouthing those words to you.
Do I know that I actually believe that or is there some part of me that still clings
to the idea that I am actually free?
There are some people who will argue that, like, I am committed in every action to
still believing that I am free in some kind of way.
I don't necessarily think that's true from a logical argumentative side.
But there's also the psychological question of, you know, am I still clinging to this
habituated idea that I am a free, separate entity when I go around continuing to
enact behaviors that, you know, are things like praising and blaming other people?
Because I will still go around and say, you know, great job for doing that other thing,
right? I think that I can make a sense, reasonably explain why I'm doing that
without appealing to personal freedom.
But it is a habit that is associated with that.
And so, you know, we are creatures of habit.
That's part of the whole argument here.
So, like, it may just be part of my luck that I will continue to always believe that
I'm free, even when I have solid arguments, I think that I am not.
If that were true, that would be really unfortunate, right?
Because that's like saying you're stuck believing false things that you know are
false, which we hope is not the case.
But that could be the bad luck that a person has.
And I'm not even sure how I prove either to myself or to other people that I genuinely
have adopted this belief.
So, like, that's about as big an epistemic problem as that you can get, right?
You don't even know if you're holding a belief or whether you can prove it to yourself
or anyone. I think that, like, I have reasonably good reasons to think that I have
adopted the no control, no free will view.
I'm not convinced that I have any good way to convey that to anyone else in a convincing
fashion if they don't sort of also buy my no free will view and then sort
of infer that I'm really genuinely believing it.
So that's that's one major problem, right?
I guess, you know, other problems are, of course, I can't prove that none of you are
free and it's not just me that's the freak here.
Right. That's that's another major problem here.
But like, I think the argument is sound.
Like, I think there's there's no way to point to anything that anyone does that
isn't incredibly coded in luck and just luck all the way through.
Would you then agree that you have to presuppose certain positions concerning,
for example, the construction of reality?
How how reality at its base is built some ontological presuppositions for that?
I mean, so I guess it's possible just on the topic of sorry, sorry.
Just on the topic, for example, of of the philosophy of science, for example,
because for me it's just like most deterministic accounts nowadays.
It really sounds like an argument from the point of view of science or something
that is approaching science methodologically.
Well, I think it is. Yeah, I mean, I think it is an argument bolstered by
empirical evidence, but I also think that it's it's an argument that can be done
without appeals to science would be my I mean, like, I think you could give a
philosophical argument that isn't empirical in nature or fundamentally
empirical in nature. Maybe it's a synthetic a priori kind of thing.
But like, I think it's I think it is the case that we have an argument for this
that isn't just assuming certain things about the nature of reality any more
than like any other argument is right.
Like, I think you can have radical skeptical concerns about all our beliefs.
Like, if if the universe turns out to just not be a consistently behaving thing,
then like everything is out the window.
But like, I think we have good reason to think that the universe behaves
according to consistent patterns and that determinism is the view that like
those consistent patterns involve some sorts of stable relations between things
and that once you have that, the problems arise pretty much immediately.
So I don't I don't think that it's presupposing anything that is implausible.
I think it's presupposing things that are essential for the universe as we
experience it being the way that we experience it in a Kantian kind of sense.
OK. So to take a step back for everyone who's who's listening and who's trying
to get into the topic, where should one start to read, for example?
Yeah, so I would start with the Nagel paper.
I think Thomas Nagel's Moral Luck paper is and you can get it.
It's easy to find Google online.
It's short. It's a little it's a little hard language.
It's not the easiest philosophy language ever, but it's also not the hardest
philosophy language either.
And I think that some of his prose are quite eloquent in laying out the problem,
especially like the parts about two thirds of the way through, where he talks
about how when you really take into account constitutive luck and how everything
about you is the result of factors beyond your control and therefore every action
that you engage in is the result of factors beyond your control.
He talks about how this shrinks the space of the self to an extensionless point.
And I think that that's a really beautiful way of describing how the problem works.
So I think the Nagel paper is really good.
And then, you know, there's various kinds of analysis of this, but I don't I don't
think that anyone has really resolved the problem that he lays out in that
particular paper.
So I think you mentioned, right, you went and read the paper before that, which is
the Williams paper, which I think is good, but I don't think goes as far as the
Nagel paper. And then sorry.
Absolutely. I totally agree.
Yeah. And then there's like one or two individuals whose I'm blanking on the
names, but I can get you for the show notes if you want, who've written like
books about luck who take, I think, different views than me generally in terms
of trying to find, trying to find a way to claim that everything isn't the result
of luck rather than biting the bullet the way that I do.
I don't know of anyone who's out there who's really willing to go.
I don't know. I don't know of a lot of people out there who are going as all in
as I am on on this particular side of things.
I'm sure there are people out there who do take a similar view, though.
Okay, great. Yeah, would would be absolutely great if you can could send me
those names.
Okay, so I just have something left.
I found a definition of luck on the topic that I thought was fairly interesting,
and I wanted to hear your opinion on it.
Maybe you have already heard of it, maybe not from, I hope I pronounce this name
correctly, Nicholas Reschers.
Mhm.
And I summarize it like this.
Something is luck when it is the result of an unplanned event or that the result
itself is unexpected, plus the result has a significant evaluative status in
representing a good or bad result.
So in terms of a benefit or a loss.
Yes, there's a couple of features in there.
So let's go back to it one more time, just real slow.
And I just want to take a part.
Something is luck when it is the result of an unplanned event or that the result
itself is unexpected, plus the results.
Let's hold there for one second, right?
So so I don't know if he's going to say that we need all of these features, but
I'm not sure why either I'm not convinced that either of those features is
necessarily essential for luck.
So like, I think that an event that is planned can still be the result of luck
if the planning process is itself tainted by luck in a, in a sufficient kind of way,
or if the mechanism that is then enacted, right?
So if I plan to roll a die, right, the die result is still the result of luck, it
seems like to me.
Yeah, and your decision to roll the die also and so on and so on.
Right.
And predictability seems to also, I think, be a bit of a red herring here in the
sense that, you know, I think there can be incredibly predictable events that are
still the result of factors beyond anyone's control and so fall into the kind
of luck that I have in mind here, right?
I think your yours and my behavior can be predictable and still the result of luck.
So I'm not convinced that that one makes sense either as a necessary condition.
So all right, go ahead, go ahead.
Why don't you do the other half of it?
So yeah, plus the result has a significant evaluative status in
representing a good or bad result.
The result has a significant evaluative status.
I'm not sure exactly what he means there.
I guess I would need like an example to think about what, what he's trying to
get at with that particular.
If something happened, some event took place and either it can be understood as a
benefit or a loss, I think that that would summarize it.
OK, I mean, yeah, I think, oh, I see.
So he's so the criteria that he's putting in there is for it to count as luck.
It has to be like a good thing or a bad thing essentially.
Yeah, and you have to be able to evaluate it.
I think that that is also very important.
Yeah, I mean, I'm not sure that's necessarily true either, right?
So either it's the case that everything is a good thing or a bad thing, in which case
what he's saying is tautologically true, right?
It isn't adding anything to the definition or if there are neutral events out there in
the world, events that are neither good nor bad, I don't see why they would be any
less the result of determinism and therefore any less the result of luck than like it
seems like the sort of account of luck he's giving there is very similar to like an
anthropomorphic kind of like luck as it pertains to my specific desired outcomes
and goals, whereas I think my definition of luck is a much thinner, you know, anything
that is beyond one's control, where that's important because what is beyond one's
control then does have significant implications when we consider morality.
Yeah, OK, I think that those were very good points on this attempt of a definition.
Yeah, I mean, I think it's a hard thing to define and like there's tricky sort of weird
circularity things about that that I have to try to tease out in terms of what I say
when I say, you know, everything is the result of luck because everything is the result
of things beyond our control, where luck means, you know, sort of things beyond our control.
But I do think that it's that's the right way to unpack luck.
And I think Nagel makes a really good case for that as being sort of the right way to
understand this. When we are when we are keeping in the front of our mind, what is
at stake here in terms of judgments of morality and judgments about the nature of the self?
OK. I think we are almost done.
That went faster than I expected.
Oh, that's no problem. If I may, if we have a little bit extra time.
Sure, we have a lot of extra time.
Yeah. Well, there's a there's a way that I try to make this argument to try to make it
compelling for folks who have, you know, who might be sort of skeptical about this,
because usually the response I get is something along the lines of everybody agrees that a
lot of things are the result of luck, but there's still a little part of you inside of you
somewhere that is still making decisions.
And that thing is somehow separate from in the right kinds of ways these endless chains
of luck. And that's where free will still exists.
That's where control still exists.
Right. There's this little person inside at the control panel kind of view.
So I want to try to make a case against that for folks who may be sort of sitting in that
particular place at the moment.
And the way I like to do this is via sort of a Socratic dialogue where I like to ask a
person I'm talking to, to give an example.
I don't know how convinced you are by my arguments at this point, but if you can remember
a time when you weren't convinced by them, if you are, what you would point to as something
in your life that is an action that you would say is beyond it was under your control,
right, that you would say you were you freely chose to do.
OK, so first I want to say that when I presuppose a certain conception of a self, then I absolutely
agree with you.
The way that I understand the self does not have this homunculi that is able to control
anything, but it leaves the possibility for an event that, how do you say, it overcomes the
strict determinism of the real.
But I would have to have to prepare the explanation for that, because it's not that easy.
For me to do this in English just spontaneously.
Sure, I understand.
But if you take this position, then I would absolutely agree with you.
So, but for the sake of my argument, for people who don't agree, is there an action that you
would point to as being the sort of thing that you think should be counted as an argument
against my position or evidence against my position?
OK, I can try to come up with one, but I think that the hypothetical person in this dialogue
could take any action as an example.
So let's say I bought three apples instead of two because I wanted to.
Mhm, yeah, so you're right that I think almost any action can be put forward.
And they usually, I think, actually get chunked into two categories.
The one you gave would be kind of the trivial category, right?
People think that like trivial small actions are independent in some kind of way.
And then the other would be like big momentous actions that they think that they spend a lot
of time deliberating on, for example, would be the other kind where they think that they
have some sort of control over them.
And so the way I push back on these kind of examples is I ask them to apply a kind of
regress to this, a regress of reasons where I ask them to think, you know, why did you
pick the three apples instead of the two apples?
For example, I saw a tweet by Matonia, which motivated me to buy more apples.
Right. So one account could be, you know, I can point to the thing that got me
thinking about having one more apple or something like that, right?
In which case the argument runs, you know, it was luck that you happened to see that
tweet versus not see that tweet, right?
It wasn't under your control in some kind of way.
And so that the the motivating causal force in your behavior was this thing that was
clearly beyond your control.
So that that seems to reduce that down to an example of not freedom in the sense that
I'm talking about in my framework or right.
The other way this sometimes gets answered is, well, nothing caused it, right?
There was absolutely nothing where somebody will try to say there was there was no no
thing that that made me pick three instead of two.
It just happened. Right.
And there it seems like maybe we can call that free.
But I think I think the reality is that's still going to be a determined event.
You may not be able to point to what I wouldn't I wouldn't say that if nothing caused
that it would was really free.
Right. And we certainly wouldn't say it's an example of the kind of will that we have in
mind when we say free will.
Right. We we want our will to be driven by reasons and we don't want to claim that our
will is free merely because it can sometimes act, you know, with no reason whatsoever.
Right. We want to be able to say our will has reasons.
But we chose those reasons and they are us and that we can have, you know, ownership
of those reasons.
So I don't I don't think that kind of, you know, I rose I raised my left hand side of
my right hand is going to be the kind of case that people want to hang their their free
will arguments on.
And I also think that they are pretty clearly still reducible to, you know, causal effects.
Right. If I ask someone, you know, prove to me that you have free will and they raise
their arm and say, you know, I proved it by raising my hand, I would say you you raised
your hand because you wanted some way to prove that I, you know, prove to me that you had
free will. And you in your mind, you were convinced that that would be sufficient evidence.
And so you did that action caused by trying to want to prove to me that you have free
will in that kind of way.
So these regress problems, I think, arise for all of our actions.
Right. The big momentous choices.
You can still ask, you know, what was your reason for doing this big momentous thing?
And they can, you know, if they give the reason, you can then say, well, what about you?
What about your constitutive luck made you such that you made you such that you were
susceptible to that reason and not all the other competing reasons?
Right. Let's say that you you saved someone's life at some point.
Right. Like what what caused you to do that kind of thing would be that you had been
habituated to be the sort of person who would dive into the water and swim and save
someone's life in that particular situation.
You were lucky enough to have the physical capacity to do that physical event in that
moment. All of these things come together to make it the case that you save that
person's life. And it's a good thing.
Right. It's morally good that you saved that person's life.
But ultimately all of the things that contributed to that event were things that
were beyond your control.
Hmm. Yeah, I only have one question for the first answer, because to me it sounds like
the functionalist description of the self, where you have an output and it doesn't
really matter what happened inside.
But you have an you have an input that doesn't really matter what happens inside.
And then you have an output.
So it's this chain of reactions where the internal state.
Yeah, OK, sure.
No, I didn't know if you've heard that from talking about on the show before.
And that was why you were trying to poke at me with this.
And so, yeah, so here's what I'll say about that.
I it is similar to a functionalist account of the self and that they are both objective
accounts of the self rather than subjective.
But on my view, I don't think that this is incompatible with there being a phenomenal
self that exists and is part of these causal frameworks.
So usually when people think of a functionalist account of the self, they think of an
eliminativist account, functionalist account that says there is no, you know, robust
mental properties or something like that.
There is literally just the input output.
My view is sorry.
I just want to ask if you would then say that in your opinion, the phenomenal
consciousness has some form of causal power or if it just is part of the.
OK, yes, I reject epiphenomenalism.
I think I think that mental states or properties have some sort of causal impact.
And that's absolutely great.
We agree on that. Oh, yeah.
Yeah, no, I totally think that's the case.
My view is just the mental properties and states are just as much the result of luck
as the physical properties and states.
And so they are part of the causal chains.
So your beliefs, for example, right?
I think that your beliefs have and play an important role in how you act in your life.
And they are mental states that you possess.
But every belief you have is the result of luck.
Everything that you've come to believe is the result of the luck of your education,
the location that you were in, your dispositions with regard to like how much evidence
you personally feel you need in order to believe a thing or not believe a thing.
So, yeah, I think.
Yeah, I think the functionalist account is not a sufficient account
if it's meant to replace or leave out the phenomenal side of things.
But the phenomenal side of things are not indeterminate.
They are part of the deterministic framework.
OK.
I adopt lots of very weird positions and then try to match them together, I suppose, to put this.
I don't think that it's really a weird position.
I think, actually, that's what a lot of functionalists are lacking.
I mean, it comes with cost is what I mean.
There's always, you know, like sure, but which position position doesn't.
Right, of course, except for trivialism.
Right. We could always be very trivialist about this.
And like, you know, I mean, I mean, do you know the epistemological position of trivialism?
Oh, no. What is that?
It's absolutely great. I love it.
It's that every proposition is true.
Hmm. Interesting.
So you can't really disagree with it because they will agree with you that it's wrong,
but it's still true because it's not true.
Oh, this is the bit from Fiddler on the Roof where it's like, oh, you're right.
You're right. Oh, and you're right.
You're right, too. Yeah, I know that joke.
Yeah, but it's a real position.
Yeah, I mean, real. I mean, I'm a discordian.
I think everything is true in some sense and false in some sense and meaningless in some sense.
And thanks for reminding me to read the Discordia Procipia.
Oh, yes. Right.
And so here's what I mean.
One of the things I will say about like the kind of quietest,
you know, unresolvability side of all of this that like,
you know, I don't think there's a solution here because I don't think that
our sense of self is really reconcilable with the reality as we understand it.
So I think the best thing to do is to try to jettison our sense of self
and replace it with a more sophisticated framework
that keeps front and center in our mind all of these,
however you think is the result of luck, because I don't think it changes our behavior
in terms of things like humility and how we approach others when they've done things wrong.
But it's always going to be an uneasy tension
because it's always going to be tricky to figure out how to
reinforce people in acting in better ways.
Because I like another part of this.
I do absolutely think that we should still change people's behavior
and think that we can change people's behavior.
And so the question is, how do we do that in a way that
isn't too like horrifyingly dystopian, right?
We still have to kind of respect their autonomy in sophisticated ways, even though.
So, you know, one way to read what I'm saying
would be to say that I've rejected the idea that humans have autonomy.
But I don't think that's the case.
I think that you have autonomy in a sense, in the sense of being able to hear
arguments and adopt different beliefs as a result of those arguments.
Now, whether or not you adopt them is the result of luck.
But we should still respect individuals' freedom.
You know, we shouldn't try to brainwash you.
We should try to convince you, is basically what I'm saying, that there are more
or less coercive ways of approaching changing people's behavior.
And the reality of moral luck is not does not give us sort of carte blanche to go around
reprogramming people because we're all programmed to begin with, if that makes sense.
Yeah, absolutely, it does.
I think if it's true, it would be
really good for everyone to adopt you.
I think it's really healthy.
I like this is why this is why I'm not sure if I actually believe it or not.
But I really do think that the more I've internalized this view, the more I'm able
to cope with bad things, the more like,
you know, when certain people do certain things.
Yeah, the more I can forgive.
And it's hard. Again, there's that there's that unrelenting tension of like,
I don't want this to become a view that means that no one has ever held
responsible for anything in any way.
I just think that we have to hold them responsible in the right way.
And with awareness of the factors
that made them engage in that particular kind of behavior.
And also on the on the personal side, that someone should be happy
if they do something that is something that they wanted to achieve.
Yeah, I mean, they take pleasure, right?
Like crazy. You can't resist taking pleasure.
So like take some pleasure in the world.
And like, I don't think that luck undermines that at all, right?
Everything that I find pleasurable, I do as a result of luck, find it pleasurable.
But I still find it pleasurable.
Like, I still love having this conversation with you.
And like, you know, if we're stuck here, you might as well do the things
that are pleasurable up to a point, right?
There's moral obligations that get in the way
and you shouldn't always just do what's pleasurable.
So I think like none of this undermines the complexity
of moral judgments and like all of the competing factors
that go into making good moral decisions.
In fact, I think it just makes it harder.
It makes it more like you have to recognize that like you're going to spend
your whole life wrestling with moral tensions
and it's going to be a matter of luck how well you actually do.
And that that means that I think that you can like let yourself
off the hook a little bit more than some people do.
I think it's you know, I think a lot of ethics come down to correctives
that like if you if you are, you know, if you have the luck
of being the sort of person who lets yourself off the hook too much, do that less.
Right. And if you're the sort of person who, you know,
you know, beats yourself up for weeks on end, this is what this is.
Like why I became an ethicist is because I'm the sort of person who like
just, you know, kills myself over and over when I've done something
even minorly wrong to someone. I just like it makes me crazy.
And so like maybe I've adopted this as a corrective
for letting myself off the hook a little bit more.
They, you know, we always joke that like philosophers
are always always telling you more about themselves
than about the nature of the universe.
So maybe I'm just, you know, confessing to everyone
that I don't have free will and maybe all of you do so.
Yeah, but that wouldn't be really a problem, because in the end, as a solipsist, you.
Right, I'm the only one.
So the rest of you are just figments of my not free imagination.
It would actually be horrible if you would be a solipsist
who thinks that you are the only one who's determined.
I think you just described God.
I think that's pretty much how God works.
OK, great.
I do believe you all are real, though, if it makes you feel any better.
OK, when we when we are already talking about what's real and what not,
I hope you're aware that I have reappropriated your lightning round.
I am, and I approve of this.
All ideas are free for everyone.
And I modified it a bit.
I try I try to have less categories in the end, I had more.
It's hard, right?
Absolutely, especially because I have a big interest in psychoanalysis,
so I can't not ask certain things.
Every subset of the every subset of the psychological mind.
So how that works, at least from the Lacanian perspective.
And I don't know if you've caught this on the show, but I've
I've started adding a question at the beginning that I'm finding to be very useful.
I have, but I will not.
You're not going to ask that. Yeah.
OK, fair enough.
Do you think that it primes them?
I think it's useful, but I don't like doing useful things.
I mean, I think there are tradeoffs in doing it.
I think it changes their answers and maybe you want the answers to be different
or maybe you don't. So I think there's no there's no moral
fact of the matter about how to do the lightning round.
It's just luck.
OK, so I think every viewer is aware of how this works.
Just basically I will ask if something is real or not and.
You will answer whether or not you think it's real or not,
and you will not be able to explain what you mean by that.
And I promise that I've done prep work in this.
I'm shooting from the hip 100 percent.
Would have been hard, because some of them, I guess, you might
not really have thought about before.
Here's hoping.
Is this the first time you have to suffer through this?
It is. This is a novel experience for me.
Absolutely great. I feel really honored.
Yeah, the torture implement is on the other foot.
OK, so let's start.
The first question would be, is the real lightning round
real?
Is the real real?
Yes, real.
So what about the symbolic order?
The sorry, the symbolic symbolic order.
Yeah, I think symbolic orders are real.
And the imaginary.
Yes.
OK, now a classic one, the external world.
Yes, real colors.
Honestly, not real.
OK, phenomenal consciousness, real, the self.
Not real gender.
Not real race.
Not real species.
Said I really I personally struggle with this with this line here, I.
I'm going to go with not real, not real.
OK, morality, real.
More luck, real, pervasive.
Rights, real.
Borders, borders.
Not real.
OK, knowledge, real.
God, gods or similar entities.
Not real society.
Real.
And just to throw your silence.
Real, yeah.
OK, fictional characters.
Pardon me, really doesn't want to say real.
Do I genuinely believe that they are real, though?
Yeah, I do. I think I do.
Yeah, sure, they're real.
Great. Holes.
Holes are real.
Great. Chess.
Chess like the game chess.
Chair. Oh, chairs, excuse me, chairs.
Chairs are sitting.
Yeah, chairs are not real.
OK, desks.
Desks are also not real.
Sandwiches.
Sandwiches are not real, definitely not real.
OK, science.
As far as I can tell, not well, I don't know if I think society is real.
Yeah, I think science is real.
OK, beauty.
I'm just going to be wildly inconsistent and say that it's real,
even though I said colors aren't real earlier, I'm doing it.
OK, that does not have to be necessarily.
I know, I know that it doesn't necessarily be inconsistent,
but my justifications for it are.
Yeah, linear time.
Linear time.
That's a hard one.
Honest, I'll say not real.
OK, the unconscious.
Real.
OK, unicorns.
Unicorns.
Is a subset of fictional characters?
Sure, yeah, real.
Causality.
Not real.
Causality is real.
Nothingness.
Nothingness is real.
Yeah.
Great.
And the last one would be crows.
Crows.
Not real.
Oh, now I'm sad.
Oh, I still like you in a conventional sense.
I'm just talking like ultimately you're not real.
But it's OK, because ultimately I'm not real either.
So like it's not a slight against you, it's we're on the same boat.
But the problem is I'm now twice not real.
So myself not real and me being a crow.
That's very problematic.
But it makes you feel better, like I was just clearly wildly inconsistent
in my assessment, so like no one should take anything I say remotely seriously.
But would being two times not real not be like being real?
Oh, yeah.
Like two negatives canceling each other out?
Yeah, I'd buy that.
It's like horseshoe theory.
You circle all the way back around to being real.
I'm so not real that I'm real again.
Horseshoe theory of ontology.
Retro-real.
OK, great.
That's it.
Thank you for taking the time.
No problem.
Thank you for having me on.
I always love chatting about moral luck and how absurd reality is.
OK.
Man spricht generell über moralisches Glück,
wenn jemand, der handelt, als moralischer Akteur bewertet wird,
obwohl ein signifikanter Teil seines Handelns
von Faktoren außerhalb seines Einflusses beeinflusst oder bewirkt wird.
Dieser Umstand wirft die Frage auf,
inwiefern man jemanden für sein Handeln bewerten kann und sollte.
Je nachdem, wie ernst man das Thema moralisches Glück nimmt,
ist niemand mehr als gut oder schlecht zu bewerten,
da die Person nichts für das Handeln kann.
Diese gesamte Argumentationslinie erinnert an Diskussionen
über freien Willen und Determinismus.
Wie in dieser Diskussion ist auch hier die Position
eines harten moralischen Glücks schwer im eigenen Leben umzusetzen.
Thomas Nagel hat in seinem einflussreichen Artikel über moral luck
vier Arten von moralischem Glück herausgearbeitet.
Erstens, resultierendes Glück.
Über resultierendes Glück spricht man,
wenn alles außer dem Resultat der Handlung gleich ist,
also die Intention, die Vorbereitung und so weiter.
Und dieses Resultat Produkt von Glück ist.
Zum Beispiel, wenn zwei Personen betrunken nach Hause fahren
und einer von beiden bringt dadurch einen Menschen um.
Wir sollten verstehen, dass es sich dabei nur um resultierendes Glück handelt
und beide gleich bewerten.
Zweitens, das den Umständen verschuldete Glück.
Hierüber spricht man, wenn die äußeren Umstände
das moralische Handeln signifikant beeinflussen.
Ein Beispiel dafür sind die Menschen,
die in Deutschland mit den herrschenden Nazis kollaborierten,
es aber, während sie vorher ausgewandert, nicht getan hätten.
Wenn diese Unterscheidung im Verhalten auftauchen würde,
haben wir es mit dem, den Umständen verschuldeten Glück zu tun.
Drittens, konstitutives Glück.
Hierbei geht es darum, mit welchen Eigenschaften und Dispositionen
jemand ins Leben kommt und aufwächst.
Diese Art des moralischen Glücks ist insbesondere
im politischen Kontext äußerst relevant,
da man hierüber aus einem anderen Blickwinkel über Themen
wie Umverteilung, Privilegien usw. diskutieren kann.
Viertens, kausales Glück.
Dabei geht es darum, wie jemand durch vorherige Umstände
Determiniert wurde.
Für weitere Informationen, die tiefer gehen bezüglich dieses Themas
und neue Einsichten und Kritik vorstellen,
kann ich das Buch Moral Luck, editiert von Daniel Stedman, vorschlagen.
Es beinhaltet sowohl die klassischen Essays
als auch neuere zu diesem Thema.
Ich hoffe, die Episode hat euch gefallen.
Wenn ja, dann gebt doch eine Rückmeldung.
Ansonsten wünsche ich euch noch einen schönen Tag.
Tschüss.